<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="AB" n="1">
<head>About These Guidelines</head>

<p>These Guidelines have been developed and are maintained by the Text
Encoding Initiative Consortium (TEI); see <ptr target="#ABTEI"/>.  They
are addressed to anyone who works with any kind of textual resource in
digital form.</p>

<p>They make recommendations about suitable ways of representing those
features of textual resources which need to be identified explicitly
in order to facilitate processing by computer programs.  In
particular, they specify a set of markers (or <term>tags</term>) which
may be inserted in the electronic representation of the text, in order
to mark the text structure and other features of interest.  Many, or
most, computer programs depend on the presence of such explicit
markers for their functionality, since without them a digitized text
appears to be nothing but a sequence of undifferentiated bits.  The
success of the World Wide Web, for example, is partly a consequence of
its use of such markup to indicate such features as headings and lists
on individual pages, and to indicate links between pages. The process
of inserting such explicit markers for implicit textual features is
often called <soCalled>markup</soCalled>, or equivalently within this
work <soCalled>encoding</soCalled>; the term
<soCalled>tagging</soCalled> is also used informally. We use the term
<term>encoding scheme</term> or <term>markup language</term> to denote
the complete set of rules associated with the use of markup in a given
context; we use the term <term>markup vocabulary</term> for the
specific set of markers or named distinctions employed by a given
encoding scheme. Thus, this work both describes the TEI encoding
scheme, and documents the TEI markup vocabulary.</p>

<p>The TEI encoding scheme is of particular usefulness in facilitating
the loss-free interchange of data amongst individuals and research
groups using different programs, computer systems, or application
software. Since they contain an inventory of the features most often
deployed for computer-based text processing, the Guidelines are also
useful as a starting point for those designing new systems and
creating new materials, even where interchange of information is not a
primary objective. </p>

<p>These Guidelines apply to texts in any natural language, of any
date, in any literary genre or text type, without restriction on form
or content.  They treat both continuous materials (<soCalled>running
text</soCalled>) and discontinuous materials such as dictionaries and
linguistic corpora.  Though principally directed to the needs of the
scholarly research community, the Guidelines are not restricted to
esoteric academic applications.  They are also useful for librarians
maintaining and documenting electronic materials, and for publishers
and others creating or distributing electronic texts.  Although they
focus on problems of representing in electronic form texts which
already exist in traditional media, these Guidelines are also
applicable to textual material which is <soCalled>born
digital</soCalled>.  We believe them to be adequate to 
the widest variety of currently existing practices in using
digital textual data, but by no means limited to them.</p>

<p>The rules and recommendations made in these Guidelines are
expressed in terms of what is currently the most widely-used markup
language for digital resources of all kinds: the Extensible Markup
Language (XML), as defined by the World Wide Web Consortium's XML
Recommendation. However, the TEI encoding scheme itself does not
depend on this language; it was originally formulated in terms of SGML
(the ISO Standard Generalized Markup Language), a
predecessor of XML, and
may in future years be re-expressed in other ways as the
field of markup develops and matures. For more information on markup
languages see chapter <ptr target="#SG"/>; for more
information on the associated character encoding issues see chapter
<ptr target="#CH"/>.
</p>

<p>This document provides the authoritative and complete statement of
the requirements and usage of the TEI encoding scheme.  As such,
although it includes numerous small examples, it must be stressed that
this work is intended to be a reference manual rather than a tutorial
guide. </p>

<p>The remainder of this chapter comprises three sections.  The first
gives an overview of the structure and notational conventions used
throughout these Guidelines.  The second enumerates the design principles
underlying the TEI scheme and the application environments in which it
may be found useful.  Finally, the third section gives a brief account
of the origins and development of the Text Encoding Initiative itself.</p>

<div type="div2" xml:id="ABSTRUNC"><head>Structure and Notational
Conventions of this Document</head>

<p>The remaining two sections of the front matter to the Guidelines
provide background tutorial material for those unfamiliar with basic
markup technologies. Following the present introductory section, we
present a detailed introduction to XML itself, intended to cover in a
relatively painless manner as much as the novice user of the TEI
scheme needs to know about markup languages in general and XML in
particular. This is followed by a discussion of the general principles
underlying current practice in the representation of different
languages and writing systems in digital form. This chapter is largely
intended for the user unfamiliar with the Unicode encoding systems,
though the expert may also find its historical overview of
interest.</p>

<p>The body of this edition of the Guidelines proper contains 23
chapters arranged in increasing order of specialist interest. The
first five chapters discuss in depth matters likely to be of
importance to anyone intending to apply the TEI scheme to virtually
any kind of text. The next seven focus on particular kinds of text:
verse, drama, spoken text, dictionaries, and manuscript
materials. The next nine chapters deal with a wide range of topics,
one or more of which are likely to be of interest in specialist
applications of various kinds. The last two chapters deal with the XML
encoding used to represent the TEI scheme itself, and provide
technical information about its implementation. The last chapter also
defines the notion of TEI conformance and its implications for
interchange of materials produced according to these Guidelines.</p>

<p>As noted above, this is a reference work, and is not intended to be
read through from beginning to end. However, the reader wishing to
understand the full potential of the TEI scheme will need a thorough
grasp of the material covered by the first four chapters and the last
two. Beyond that, the reader is recommended to select according to
their specific interests: one of the strengths of the TEI architecture
is its modular nature. </p>

<p>As far as possible, extensive cross referencing is provided
wherever related topics are dealt with; these are particularly
effective in the online version of the Guidelines. In addition, a
series of technical appendixes provide detailed formal definitions for
every element, every class, and every macro discussed in the body of
the work; these are also cross linked as appropriate. Finally, a
detailed bibliography is provided, which identifies the source of many
examples cited in the text as well as documenting works referred to,
and listing other relevant publications.</p>


<p>As an aid to the reader, most chapters of these Guidelines follow
the same basic organization. The chapter begins with an overview of
the subjects treated within it, linked to the following
subsections. Within each section where new elements are described, a
summary table is first given, which provides their names and a brief
description of their intended usage. This is then followed where
appropriate by further discussion of each element, including wherever
possible usage examples taken somewhat eclectically from a variety of
real sources. These examples are not intended to be exhaustive, but
rather to suggest typical ways in which the elements concerned may
usefully be applied. Where appropriate, a link to a statement of the
source for most examples is provided in the online version. Within the
examples, use of whitespace such as newlines or indentation is simply
intended to aid legibility, and is not prescriptive or normative. </p>

<p>Wherever TEI elements or classes are mentioned in the text, they
are linked in the online version to the relevant reference
specification for the element or class concerned. Element names are
always given in the form <gi>name</gi>, where <q>name</q> is the
<term>generic identifier</term> of the element; empty elements such as
<gi>pb</gi> or <gi>anchor</gi> include a closing slash to distinguish
them wherever they are discussed. References to attributes take the
form <att scheme="meta">attname</att>, where <q>attname</q> is the name of the
attribute.  References to classes are also presented as links, for
example <ident type="class">model.divLike</ident> for a model class,
and <ident type="class">att.global</ident> for an attribute class.
</p>

<div xml:id="AB-namecon">
<head>TEI Naming Conventions</head>
<p>These Guidelines use a more or less consistent set of conventions
in the naming of XML elements and classes. This section summarizes
those conventions.</p>
<div>
<head>Element and Attribute Names</head>
<p>An unadorned name such as <q>blort</q> is the
name of a TEI element or attribute. <note place="foot">During
generation of TEI RelaxNG schema fragments, the patterns corresponding
with these TEI names are given a prefix <code>tei</code> to allow them
to co-exist with names from other XML namespace. This prefix is not
visible to the end user, and is not used in TEI documentation. When
generating multi-namespace schemas, however, the user needs to be
aware of them. </note>.</p>
<p>The following conventions apply to the choice of names :
<list>
<item>Elements are given generic identifiers as far as possible
consisting of one or more <term>tokens</term>, by which we mean whole
words or recognisable abbreviations of them, taken from the English
language. </item>
<item>Where an element name contains more than one token, the first
letter of the second
token, and of any subsequent ones, is capitalised, as in for example
<gi>biblStruct</gi>, <gi>listPerson</gi>. This
<soCalled>camelCasing</soCalled> is used also for attribute names and
symbolic values. </item>
<item>Module names also use whole words, for the most part, but are
always all lower case. </item>
<item>The specification for an element or attribute whose name
contains abbreviations generally also includes a <gi>gloss</gi>
element providing the expanded sense of the name.</item>
<item>An element specification may also contain approved translations
for element or attribute names in one or more other languages using
the <gi>altIdent</gi> element; this is not however generally done in
TEI P5.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Whole words are generally preferred for clarity. The following
abbreviations are however commonly used within generic identifiers:
<list>

<label>att</label>
<item>attribute</item>
<label>bibl</label>
<item>bibliographic description or reference in a bibliography</item>
<label>cat</label>
<item>category, especially as used in text classification </item>
<label>char</label>
<item>character, typically a Unicode character</item>
<label>doc</label>
<item>document : this usually refers to the original source document
which is being encoded,</item>
<label>decl</label>
<item>declaration : has a specific sense in the TEI
Header, as discussed in <ptr target="#HD12"/></item>
<label>desc</label>
<item>description : has a specific sense in the TEI Header, as
discussed in <ptr target="#HD12"/> </item>
<label>grp</label>
<item>group. In TEI usage, a group is distinguised from a list in that
the former associates several objects which act as a single entity,
while the latter does not. For example, a <gi>linkGrp</gi> combines
several <gi>link</gi> elements which have certain properties in
common, whereas a <gi>listBibl</gi> simply lists a number of otherwise
unrelated <gi>bibl</gi> elements.</item>
<label>interp</label>
<item>interpretation or analysis</item>
<label>lang</label><item>(natural) language</item>
<label>ms</label><item>manuscript</item>
<label>org</label>
<item>organization, that is, a named group of people or legal entity</item>
<label>rdg</label>
<item>reading or version found in a specific witness</item>
<label>ref</label><item>reference or link</item>
<label>spec</label>
<item>technical specification or definition</item>
<label>stmt</label>
<item>statement : used in a specific sense in the TEI Header,
as discussed in <ptr target="#HD12"/></item>
<label>struct</label>
<item>structured : that is, containing a specific set of
named elements rather than <soCalled>mixed content</soCalled></item>
<label>val</label>
<item>value, for example of a variable or an attribute</item>
<label>wit</label>
<item>witness: that is, a specific document which attests specific
readings in a textual tradition or apparatus</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Some abbreviations are used inconsistently: for example,
<gi>add</gi> is an addition, and <gi>addSpan</gi> is a spanning
addition, but <gi>addName</gi> is an additional name, not the name of
an addition. Such inconsistencies are relatively few in number, and it
is hoped to remove them in subsequent revisions of the Guidelines.</p>
<p>Some elements have very short abbreviated names: these are for the
most part elements which are likely to be used very frequently in a
marked up text, for example <gi>p</gi> (paragraph), <gi>s</gi>
(segment) <gi>hi</gi> (highlighted phrase), <gi>ptr</gi> (pointer),
<gi>div</gi> (division) etc. We do not specifically list such elements
here: as noted above, an expansion of each such abbreviated name is
provided within the documentation using the <gi>gloss</gi> element
.</p>
</div>
</div>
<div>
<head>Class, macro, and datatype names</head>

<p>All named objects other than elements and attributes have one of
the following prefixes, which indicate whether the object is a module,
an attribute class, a model class, a datatype, or a macro: <table>
<row role="label">
<cell>Component</cell>
<cell>Name</cell>
<cell>Example</cell>
</row>
<row><cell>Attribute 
Classes</cell><cell>att.*</cell><cell>att.global</cell></row>
<row><cell>Model 
Classes</cell><cell>model.*</cell><cell>model.biblPart</cell></row>
<row><cell>Macros</cell><cell>macro.*</cell><cell>macro.paraContent</cell></row>
<row><cell>Datatypes</cell><cell>data.*</cell><cell>data.pointer</cell></row>
</table>
</p>
<p>The concepts of model class, attribute class, etc. are defined in
<ptr target="ST"/>.  Here we simply note some conventions about their
naming. </p>

<p>The following rules apply to attribute class names : <list>
<item>Attribute class names take the form <code>att.xxx</code>, where
<code>xxx</code> is typically an adjective, or a series of adjectives
separated by dots, describing a property common to the attributes
which make up the class.</item>
<item>Attributes with the same name are considered to have the same
semantics, whether the attribute is inherited from a class, or locally
defined.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The following rules apply to model class names: <list>
<item>Model classes have names beginning <code>model.</code> followed
by a <term>root name</term>, and zero or more suffixes as described
below.</item>
<item>A root name may be the name of an element, generally the
prototypical parent or sibling for elements which are members of the
class.</item>
<item>The first suffix should be <code>Part</code>, if the class
members are all children of the element named rootname; or
<code>Like</code>, if the class members are all siblings of the
element named <code>rootname</code>. </item>
<item>The rootname <code>global</code> is used to indicate that class
members are permitted anywhere in a TEI document.</item>
<item>Additional suffixes may be added, prefixed by a dot, to
distinguish subclasses, semantic or structural.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>For example, the class of elements which can form part of a
<gi>div</gi> is called <ident>model.divPart</ident>. This class
includes as a subclass the elements which can form part of a
<gi>div</gi> in a spoken text, which is named
<ident>model.divPart.spoken</ident></p>


</div>



<div type="div3" xml:id="ABTEI2"><head>Design Principles</head>
	
<p>Because of its roots in the humanities research community, the TEI
scheme is driven by its original goal of serving the needs of research,
and is therefore committed to providing a maximum of comprehensibility,
flexibility, and extensibility.  More specific design goals of the TEI
have been that the Guidelines should:
<list type="simple">
<item>provide a standard format for data interchange</item>
<item>provide guidance for the encoding of texts in this format</item>
<item>support the encoding of all kinds of features of all
kinds of texts studied by researchers</item>
<item>be application independent</item></list>
This has led to a number of important design decisions, such as:
<list type="simple">
<item>the choice of XML and Unicode</item>
<item>the provision of a large predefined tag set</item>
<item>encodings for different views of text</item>
<item>alternative encodings for the same textual features</item>
<item>mechanisms for user-defined modification of the scheme</item></list>
We discuss some of these goals in more detail below.</p>

<p>The goal of creating a common interchange format which is
application independent requires the definition of a specific markup
syntax as well as the definition of a large set of elements or
concepts.  The syntax of the recommendations made in this document
conforms to the World Wide Web Consortium's XML Recommendation (<ptr target="#XMLREC"/>)
but their definition is as far
as possible independent of any particular schema language. </p>
<p>The goal of providing guidance for text encoding suggests that
recommendations be made as to what textual features should be recorded
in various situations. However, when selecting certain features for
encoding in preference to others, these Guidelines have tended to
prefer generic solutions to specific ones, and to avoid areas where no
consensus exists, while attempting to accommodate as many diverse views
as feasible.  Consequently, the TEI Guidelines make (with relatively
rare exceptions) no suggestions or restrictions as to the relative
importance of textual features.  The philosophy of the Guidelines is
<q>if you want to encode this feature, do it this way</q> — but very
few features are mandatory. In the same spirit, while the Guidelines
very rarely require you to encode any particular feature, they do
require you to be honest about which features you have encoded, that
is, to respect the meanings and usage rules they recommend for
specific elements and attributes proposed. </p>
<p>The requirement to support all kinds of materials likely to be of
interest in research has largely conditioned the development of the
TEI into a very flexible and modular system. The development of other
XML vocabularies or standards is typically motivated by the desire to
create a single fully specified encoding scheme for use in a
well-defined application domain. By contrast, the TEI is intended for
use in a large number of rather ill-defined and often overlapping
domains. It achieves its generality by means of the modular
architecture described in <ptr target="#ST"/> which enables each user
to create a schema appropriate to their needs without compromising the
interoperability of their data.</p>
<p>The Guidelines have been written largely with a focus on text capture
(i.e. the representation in electronic form of an already existing copy
text in another medium) rather than text creation (where no such copy
text exists).  Hence the frequent use of terms like
<soCalled>transcription</soCalled>, <soCalled>original</soCalled>,
<soCalled>copy text</soCalled>, etc.  However, the Guidelines are
equally applicable to text creation. </p>
<p>Concerning text capture the TEI Guidelines do not specify a
particular approach to the problem of fidelity to the source text and
recoverability of the original; such a choice is the responsibility of
the text encoder.  The current version of these Guidelines, however,
provides a more fully elaborated set of tags for markup of rhetorical,
linguistic, and simple typographic characteristics of the text than for
detailed markup of page layout or for fine distinctions among type fonts
or manuscript hands. It should be noted also that, with the present
version of the Guidelines, it is no longer necessarily the case that
an unmediated version of the source text can be recovered from an
encoded text simply by removing the markup.
	</p>
<p>In these Guidelines, no hard and fast distinction is drawn between
<soCalled>objective</soCalled> and <soCalled>subjective</soCalled>
information or between <soCalled>representation</soCalled> and
<soCalled>interpretation</soCalled>.  These distinctions, though
widely made and often useful in narrow, well-defined contexts, are
perhaps best interpreted as distinctions between issues on which there
is a scholarly consensus and issues where no such consensus exists.
Such consensus has been, and no doubt will be, subject to change.  The
TEI Guidelines do not make suggestions or restrictions as to which of
these features should be encoded.  The use of the terms
<term>descriptive</term> and <term>interpretive</term> about different
types of encoding in the Guidelines is not intended to support any
particular view on these theoretical issues. Historically, it reflects
a purely practical division of responsibility amongst the original
working committees (see further <ptr target="#ABTEI"/>).  </p>
<p>In general, the accuracy and the reliability of the encoding and the
appropriateness of the interpretation is for the individual user of the
text to determine.  The Guidelines provide a means of documenting the
encoding in such a way that a user of the text can know the reasoning
behind that encoding, and the general interpretive decisions on which it
is based.  The TEI header may be used to document and justify many
such aspects of the encoding, but the choice of TEI elements for a
particular feature is in itself a statement about the interpretation
reached by the encoder.</p>

<p>In many situations more than one view of a text is needed since no
absolute recommendation to embody one specific view of text can apply
to all texts and all approaches to them.  Within limits, the syntax of
XML ensures that some encodings can be ignored for some purposes.  To
enable encoding multiple views, these Guidelines not only treat a
variety of textual features, but sometimes provide several alternative
encodings for what appear to be identical textual phenomena.  These
Guidelines offer the possibility of encoding many different
views of the text, simultaneously if necessary. Where different views
of the formal structure of a text are required, as opposed to
different annotations on a single structural view, however, the formal
syntax of XML (which requires a single hierarchical view of text
structure) poses some problems; recommendations concerning ways of
overcoming or circumventing that restriction are discussed in chapter
<ptr target="#NH"/>. </p>

<p>In brief, the TEI Guidelines define a general-purpose encoding
scheme which makes it possible to encode different views of text,
possibly intended for different applications, serving the majority of
scholarly purposes of text studies in the humanities.  Because no
predefined encoding scheme can possibly serve all research purposes,
the TEI scheme is designed to facilitate both selection from a wide
range of predefined markup choices, and the addition of new (non-TEI)
markup options. By providing a formally verifiable means of extending
the TEI recommendations, the TEI makes it simple for such
user-identified modifications to be incorporated into future releases
of the Guidelines as they evolve. The underlying mechanisms which
support these aspects of the scheme are introduced in chapter <ptr target="#ST"/>, and detailed discussions of their use provided in
chapter <ptr target="#USE"/>. </p></div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="ABAPP"><head>Intended Use</head>
<p>We envisage three primary functions for these Guidelines:
<list type="simple">
<item>guidance for individual or local practice in text
creation and data capture;</item>
<item>support of data interchange;</item>
<item>support of application-independent local processing.</item></list>
These three functions are so thoroughly interwoven in practice that it
is hardly possible to address any one without addressing the others.
However, the distinction provides a useful framework for discussing the
possible role of the Guidelines in work with electronic texts.</p>
<div type="div4" xml:id="ABAPP1"><head>Use in Text Capture and Text Creation</head>
<p>The description of textual features found in the chapters which
follow should provide a useful checklist from which scholars planning to
create electronic texts should select the subset of features suitable
for their project.  </p>
<p>Problems specific to text creation or text
<soCalled>capture</soCalled> have not been considered explicitly in
this document.  These Guidelines are not concerned with the process by
which a digital text comes into being: it can be typed by hand,
scanned from a printed book or typescript, read from a typesetter's
tape, or acquired from another researcher who may have used another
markup scheme (or no explicit markup at all).</p>
<p>We include here only some general points which are often raised about
markup and the process of data capture.</p>
<p>XML can appear distressingly verbose, particularly when (as in these
Guidelines) the names of tags and attributes are chosen for clarity and
not for brevity.  Editor macros and keyboard shortcuts can allow a
typist to enter frequently used tags with single keystrokes.
It is often possible to transform word-processed or
scanned text automatically.  Markup-aware software can help with
maintaining the hierarchical structure of the document, and display the
document with visual formatting rather than raw tags.</p>
<p>The techniques described in chapter <ptr target="#MD"/>
may be used to develop simpler data capture TEI-conformant schemas,
for example with limited numbers of elements, or with shorter names
for the tags being used most often.  Documents created with such
schemas may then be automatically converted to a more elaborated TEI
form. </p>
</div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="ABAPP2"><head>Use for Interchange</head>

<p>The TEI format may simply be used as an interchange format,
permitting projects to share resources even when their local encoding
schemes differ. If there are <formula>n</formula> different encoding
formats, to provide mappings between each possible pair of formats
requires <formula>n&#x00D7;(n-1)</formula> translations; with an
interchange format, only <formula>2&#x00D7;n</formula> such mappings
are needed. However, for such translations to be carried out without
loss of information, the interchange format chosen must be as
expressive (in a formal sense) as any of the target formats; this is a
further reason for the TEI's provision of both highly abstract or
generic encodings and highly specific ones.</p>
<p>To translate between any pair of encoding schemes implies:
<list type="ordered">
<item>identifying the sets of textual features distinguished
by the two schemes;</item>
<item>determining where the two sets of features correspond;</item>
<item>creating a suitable set of mappings.</item></list> </p>
<p>For example, to translate from encoding scheme X into the TEI
scheme:
<list type="ordered">
<item>Make a list of all the textual features distinguished in
X. </item>
<item>Identify the corresponding feature in the TEI scheme.
There are three possibilities for each feature:
<list type="ordered">
<item>the feature exists in both X and the TEI scheme;</item>
<item>X has a feature which is absent from the TEI scheme;</item>
<item>X has a feature which corresponds with more than one
feature in the TEI scheme.</item></list>
The first case is a trivial renaming.  The second will require an extension to
the TEI scheme, as described in chapter <ptr target="#MD"/>.  The third
is more problematic, but not impossible, provided that a consistent
choice can be made (and documented) amongst the alternatives.  </item>
</list></p>
<p>The ease with which this translation can be defined will of
course depend on the clarity with which scheme X
represents the features it encodes.</p>
<p>Translating from the TEI into scheme X follows the same pattern,
except that if a TEI feature has no equivalent in X, and X cannot be
extended, information must be lost in translation.</p>
<p>The rules defining conformance to the Guidelines are
given in some detail in chapter <ptr target="#CF"/>.
The basic principles informing those rules may be summarized as
follows:
<list type="ordered">
<item>The TEI <term>abstract model</term> (that is, the set of
categorical distinctions which it defines) must be respected. The
correspondence between a tag X and the semantic function assigned to
it by these Guidelines may not be changed; such changes are known
as <term>tag abuse</term> and strongly deprecated.</item>
<item>A TEI document must be expressed as a valid XML-conformant
document which uses the TEI namespace appropriately. If, for example,
the document encodes features not provided by the Guidelines, such
extensions may not be associated with the TEI namespace.  </item>
<item>It must be possible to validate a TEI document against a schema
derived from these Guidelines, possibly with extensions provided in
the recommended manner.</item>
 </list> 

</p></div>


<div type="div4" xml:id="ABAPP3"><head>Use for Local Processing</head>
<p>Machine-readable text can be manipulated in many ways; some users:
<list type="simple">
<item>edit texts (e.g. word processors, syntax-directed
editors) </item>
<item>edit, display, and link texts in hypertext systems</item>
<item>format and print texts using desktop publishing systems,
or batch-oriented formatting programs </item>
<item>load texts into free-text retrieval databases or
conventional databases </item>
<item>unload texts from databases as search results or for
export to other software </item>
<item>search texts for words or phrases </item>
<item>perform content analysis on texts </item>
<item>collate texts for critical editions </item>
<item>scan texts for automatic indexing or similar purposes</item>
<item>parse texts linguistically </item>
<item>analyze texts stylistically </item>
<item>scan verse texts metrically </item>
<item>link text and images </item></list> </p>
<p>These applications cover a wide range of likely uses but are by no
means exhaustive.  The aim has been to make the TEI Guidelines useful
for encoding the same texts for different purposes.  We have avoided
anything which would restrict the use of the text for other
applications.  We have also tried not to omit anything essential to any
single application.</p>
<p>Because the TEI format is expressed using XML, 
almost any modern text processing system is able to process it, and
new TEI-aware software systems are able to build on a solid base
of existing software libraries. </p> </div></div></div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="ABTEI"><head>Historical Background</head>

<p>The Text Encoding Initiative grew out of a planning conference
sponsored by the Association for Computers and the Humanities (ACH) and
funded by the U.S.  National Endowment for the Humanities (NEH), which
was held at Vassar College in November 1987.  At this conference some
thirty representatives of text archives, scholarly societies, and
research projects met to discuss the feasibility of a standard encoding
scheme and to make recommendations for its scope, structure, content,
and drafting.  During the conference, the Association for Computational
Linguistics and the Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing
agreed to join ACH as sponsors of a project to develop the Guidelines.
The outcome of the conference was a set of principles (the
<soCalled>Poughkeepsie Principles</soCalled>, <ptr target="#AB-eg-01"/>), which
determined the further course of the project.</p>
<!--
<list type="ordered">
<item>The guidelines are intended to provide a standard format
for data interchange in humanities research. </item>
<item>The guidelines are also intended to suggest principles
for the encoding of texts in the same format. </item>
<item>The guidelines should
<list type="ordered">
<item>define a recommended syntax for the format, </item>
<item>define a metalanguage for the description of
text-encoding schemes, </item>
<item>describe the new format and representative existing
schemes both in that metalanguage and in prose. </item></list></item>
<item>The guidelines should propose sets of coding conventions
suited for various applications. </item>
<item>The guidelines should include a minimal set of
conventions for encoding new texts in the format. </item>
<item>The guidelines are to be drafted by committees on
<list type="ordered">
<item>text documentation </item>
<item>text representation </item>
<item>text interpretation and analysis </item>
<item>metalanguage definition and description of existing and
proposed schemes, </item></list>
coordinated by a steering committee of representatives of the principal
sponsoring organizations.  </item>
<item>Compatibility with existing standards will be maintained
as far as possible. </item>
<item>A number of large text archives have agreed in principle
to support the guidelines in their function as an interchange
format, and have (since the publication of the prior edition), actually
done so. We continue to encourage funding agencies to support development
of tools to facilitate this interchange. </item>
<item>Conversion of existing machine-readable texts to the new
format involves the translation of their conventions into the
syntax of the new format. No requirements will be made for the
addition of information not already coded in the texts.</item></list>
<p>In the course of the work, some of these goals assumed greater, some
lesser importance; some proved easier, some harder to achieve.  The
document in hand does define a standard form for the interchange of
textual material, and adumbrate principles for the creation of new
electronic texts.  The only metalanguage used, however, is that common to
XML and SGML,
and no formal definitions are given for other encoding schemes.
These Guidelines do define a minimal set of conventions for text
encoding (i.e. those elements classed as recommended or required),
though few researchers will be satisfied to encode <emph>only</emph>
what is required or recommended here, since the set of required and
recommended elements is rather small.  This document does not,
however, define — at least not explicitly — <q>sets of coding
conventions suited for various applications</q>, since consensus on
suitable conventions for different applications proved elusive; this
remains a goal for future work.</p>-->
<!-- <div type="div3" xml:id="ABTEI1"><head>Origin and Development of the TEI</head>-->
<p>The Text Encoding Initiative project began in June 1988 with funding
from the NEH, soon followed by further funding from the Commission of
the European Communities, the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation, and the
Social Science and Humanities Research Council of Canada.  Four working
committees, composed of distinguished scholars and researchers from both
Europe and North America, were named to deal with problems of text
documentation, <!-- (resulting largely in chapter <ptr target="#HD" type="div1"/>),-->
text representation, text analysis and interpretation, <!-- (together
responsible for most of what has become parts II, III, and IV),--> and
metalanguage and syntax issues. <!-- (largely responsible for part
VI)--> Each committee was charged with the task of identifying
<soCalled>significant particularities</soCalled> in a range of texts,
and two editors appointed to harmonise the resulting recommendations. </p>
<p>A first draft version (P1, with the <q>P</q> here and subsequently
standing for <q>Proposal</q>) of the Guidelines was distributed in July
1990 under the title <title>Guidelines for the Encoding and Interchange
of Machine-Readable Texts</title>. <!-- with the TEI document number TEI
P1.  With minor changes and corrections, this version was reprinted as
version 1.1 in November 1990.</p>-->
Extensive public comment and further work on areas not covered in
this version resulted in the drafting of a revised version, TEI P2,
distribution of which began in April 1992.  This version included
substantial amounts of new material, resulting from work carried out by
several specialist working groups, set up in 1990 and 1991 to propose
extensions and revisions to the text of P1.  The overall organization,
both of the draft itself and of the scheme it describes, was entirely
revised and reorganized in response to public comment on the first
draft.</p>
<p>In June 1993 an Advisory Board met to review the current state of
the TEI Guidelines, and recommended the formal publication of the work
done to that time.  That version of the TEI Guidelines, TEI P3,
consolidated the work published as parts of TEI P2, along with some
additional new material and was finally published in May of 1994
without the label <mentioned>draft</mentioned>, thus marking the
conclusion of the initial development work.
</p>
<p>In February of 1998 the World Wide Web Consortium issued a final
Recommendation for the Extensible Markup Language, XML.<note place="bottom">XML was originally developed as a way of publishing on
the World Wide Web richly encoded documents such as those for which
the TEI was designed.  Several TEI participants contributed heavily to
the development of XML, most notably XML's senior co-editor
C. M. Sperberg-McQueen, who served as the North American editor for
the TEI Guidelines from their inception until 1999. </note>
Following the rapid take-up of this new standard metalanguage, it
became evident that the TEI Guidelines (which had been published
originally as an SGML application) needed to be re-expressed in this
new formalism if they were to survive. The TEI editors, with
abundant assistance from others who had developed and used TEI,
developed an update plan, and made tentative decisions on relevant
syntactic issues. </p>

<p>In January of 1999, the University of Virginia and the University
of Bergen formally proposed the creation of an international
membership organization, to be known as the TEI Consortium, which
would maintain, develop, and promote the TEI. Shortly thereafter, two
further institutions with longstanding ties to the TEI (Brown
University and Oxford University) joined them in formulating an
Agreement to Establish a Consortium for the Maintenance of the Text
Encoding Initiative (<ptr target="#AB-eg-02"/>), on which basis the TEI
Consortium was eventually established and incorporated as a
not-for-profit legal entity at the end of the year 2000. The first
members of the new TEI Board took office during January of 2001. </p>
				
<p>The TEI Consortium was established in order to maintain a permanent
home for the TEI as a democratically constituted, academically and
economically independent, self-sustaining, non-profit organization. In
addition, the TEI Consortium was intended to foster a broad-based user
community with sustained involvement in the future development and
widespread use of the TEI Guidelines (<ptr target="#AB-eg-03"/>). </p>

<p>To oversee and manage the revision process in collaboration with
the TEI Editors, the TEI Board formed a Technical Council, with a
membership elected from the TEI user community. The Council met for
the first time in January 2002 at King's College London. Its first
task was to oversee production of an XML version
of the TEI Guidelines, updating P3 to enable users to
work with the emerging XML toolset. This, the P4 version of the Guidelines,
was published in June 2002. It was essentially an XML version of P3,
making no substantive changes to the constraints expressed in the
schemas apart from those necessitated by the shift to XML, and
changing only corrigible errors identified in the prose of the P3
Guidelines. However, given that P3 had by this time been in steady use
since 1994, it was clear that a substantial revision of its content
was necessary, and work began immediately on the P5 version of the
Guidelines. This was planned as a thorough overhaul, involving a
public call for features and new development in a number of important
areas not previously addressed including character encoding, graphics,
manuscript description, biographical and geographical data, and the
encoding language in which the TEI Guidelines themselves are written. </p>

<p>The members of the TEI Council and its associated workgroups are
listed in <ptr target="#FM1"/>. In preparing this edition, they have
been attentive to the requirements and practice of the widest possible
range of TEI users, who are now to be found in many different research
communities across the world, and have been largely instrumental in
transforming the TEI from a grant-supported international research
project into a self-sustaining community-based effort. One effect
of the incorporation of the TEI has been the legal requirement to hold
an annual meeting of the Consortium members; these meetings have
emerged as an invaluable opportunity to sustain and reinforce that
sense of community. </p>
<p>The present
work is therefore the result of a sustained period of consultation,
drafting, and revision, with input from many different
experts. Whatever merits it may have are to be attributed to them; the
Editors accept responsibility only for the errors remaining. </p>


</div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="ABTEI4"><head>Future Developments</head>

<p>The encoding recommended by this document may be used without fear
that future versions of the TEI scheme will be inconsistent with it in
fundamental ways.  The TEI will be sensitive, in revising these
Guidelines, to the possible problems which revision might pose for those
who are already using this version of the Guidelines.  
</p>
<p>With TEI P5, a version numbering system is introduced: the version
number has two parts, a major number and a minor, for example
<val>1.0</val>. The TEI undertakes that no change will be made to the
formal expression of these Guidelines (that is, a TEI schema, as
defined in <ptr target="#CF"/>) such that documents conformant to a
given major numbered release cease to be compatible with a subsequent
release of the same major number. Moreover, as far as possible, new
minor releases will be made only for the purpose of adding new
compatible features, or of correcting errors in existing features.</p>
<p>The Guidelines are currently maintained as an open source project
on the Sourceforge site <ptr target="http://tei.sf.net/"/>, from which released
and development versions may be freely downloaded; notice of errors
detected and enhancements requested may also be submitted at this
site.</p>
</div></div>
