<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="CE"
     n="17"><head>Certainty, Precision, and Responsibility</head>
<p>Encoders of text often find it useful to indicate that some aspects
of the encoded text are problematic or uncertain, and to indicate who is
responsible for various aspects of the markup of the electronic text.
These Guidelines provide several methods of recording uncertainty about the
text or its markup:
<list type="simple">
<item>the <gi>note</gi> element defined in section <ptr target="#CONO"/> may
be used with a value of <val>certainty</val> for its <att>type</att>
attribute.</item>
<item>the <gi>certainty</gi> element defined in this chapter may be used
to record the nature and degree of the uncertainty in a more structured
way.</item>
<item>the <gi>precision</gi> element defined in this chapter may be
used to record the accuracy with which some numerical value (such as a
date or quantity) is provided by some other element or attribute.</item>
<item>the <gi>alt</gi> element defined in the module for
linking and segmentation may be used to provide alternative encodings
for parts of a text, as described in section <ptr target="#SAAT"/>.</item></list>
There are three methods of indicating responsibility for different
aspects of the electronic text:
<list type="simple">
<item>the TEI header records who is responsible for an electronic text
by means of the <gi>respStmt</gi> element and other more specific elements
(<gi>author</gi>, <gi>sponsor</gi>, <gi>funder</gi>, <gi>principal</gi>,
etc.) used within the <gi>titleStmt</gi>, <gi>editionStmt</gi>, and
<gi>revisionDesc</gi> elements.</item>
<item>the <gi>note</gi> element may be used with a value of <val>resp</val>
or <val>responsibility</val> in its <att>type</att> attribute.</item>
<item>the <gi>respons</gi> element defined in this chapter may be used
to record fine-grained structured information about responsibility for
individual tags in the text.</item></list>
No special steps are needed to use the <gi>note</gi> and <gi>respStmt</gi> elements, since they are defined in the core module and header
respectively.  The <gi>alt</gi> element is only available when the
module for linking has been selected, as described in
chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>. To use the <gi>certainty</gi>, <gi>precision</gi> or
<gi>respons</gi> elements, the module for certainty and
responsibility must be selected. 
</p>

<p>These three elements are all members of an attribute class called
<ident type="class">att.scoping</ident> from which they inherit the
following attributes:

<specList>
<specDesc key="att.scoping" atts="target match"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>These attributes enable statements about certainty, precision, or
responsibility to be made with respect to the whole of a document, or
any part or parts of it which can be identified using standard XML
location methods. Several examples are given in the discussion of the
<gi>certainty</gi> element below; the same mechanisms are available
for all three element discussed in this chapter.
</p>
<div type="div2" xml:id="CECERT"><head>Levels of Certainty</head>
<p>Many types of uncertainty may be distinguished.  The
<gi>certainty</gi> element is designed to encode the following sorts:
<list type="simple">
<item>a given tag may or may not correctly apply (e.g. a given word may
be a personal name, or perhaps not)</item>
<item>the precise point at which an element begins or ends is
uncertain</item>
<item>the value given for an attribute is uncertain</item>
<item>the content given for an element is unreliable for any reason.</item></list></p>
<p>The following types of uncertainty are <emph>not</emph> indicated
with the <gi>certainty</gi> element:
<list type="simple">
<item>the numerical precision associated with a number or date (for
this use the <gi>precision</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#CEPREC"/>)
</item>
<item>the content of the document being transcribed is identifiable,
but may be read or understood in different ways
(for this use the transcriptional elements such as <gi>unclear</gi>,
discussed in chapter <ptr target="#PH"/>)</item>
<item>a transcriber, editor, or author wishes to indicate a level of
confidence in a factual assertion made in the text (for this use the
interpretative mechanisms discussed in <ptr target="#AI"/> and <ptr target="#FS"/>)</item>
<!--<item>an author is not sure if the sentence chosen to start a
paragraph is really the one to be  retained in the final version. </item>--></list>
</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="CECENO"><head>Using Notes to Record Uncertainty</head>
<p>The simplest way of recording uncertainty about markup is to attach a
note to the element or location about which one is unsure.  In the
following (invented) paragraph, for example, an encoder might be
uncertain whether to mark <q>Essex</q> as a place name or a personal
name, since both might be plausible in the given context:
<q rend="display">Elizabeth went to Essex. She had always liked Essex.</q>
Using <gi>note</gi>, the uncertainty here may be recorded quite simply:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>Elizabeth</persName> went to <placeName>Essex</placeName>. She had always liked <placeName>Essex</placeName>.<note type="certainty" resp="#MSM">It is not
clear here whether <mentioned>Essex</mentioned>
refers to the place or to the nobleman. -MSM</note></egXML></p>
<p>Using the normal mechanisms, the note may be associated
unambiguously with specific elements of the text, thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>Elizabeth</persName> went to <placeName xml:id="CE-p1a">Essex</placeName>.
She had always liked <placeName xml:id="CE-p1b">Essex</placeName>.<note type="certainty" resp="#MSM" target="#CE-p1a #CE-p1b">It
is not clear here whether <mentioned>Essex</mentioned>
refers to the place or to the nobleman. If the latter,
it should be tagged as a personal name. -<name xml:id="MSM">Michael</name></note></egXML></p>
<p>The advantage of this technique is its relative simplicity. Its
disadvantage is that the nature and degree of uncertainty are not
conveyed in any systematic way and thus are not susceptible to any sort
of automatic processing.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="CECECE"><head>Structured Indications of Uncertainty</head>
<p>To record uncertainty in a more structured way, susceptible of at
least simple automatic processing, the <gi>certainty</gi> element may be
used:
<specList><specDesc key="certainty" atts="locus degree "/></specList></p>
<p>Returning to the example, the <gi>certainty</gi> element may be used to record doubts about
the proper encoding of <q>Essex</q> in several ways of varying
precision.  To record merely that we are not certain that <q>Essex</q>
is in fact a place name, as it is tagged, we use the <att>target</att>
attribute to identify the element in question, and the <att>locus</att>
attribute to indicate which aspect of the markup we are uncertain about
(in this case, whether we have used the correct <q>name</q> for the
element used to mark it):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Elizabeth went to 
<placeName xml:id="CE-pl1">Essex</placeName>.
<!-- ... elsewhere in the document ... -->
<certainty target="#CE-pl1" locus="name"><desc>possibly not a placename</desc></certainty></egXML>
There are no particular constraints as to where the 
<gi>certainty</gi> element is placed in a document; it may be placed adjacent to the target
element, or elsewhere in the same or another document.  Its position
is however significant when the <att>target</att> attribute is not specified
as further discussed below.
</p>
<p>We may wish to record the probability, assessed in some subjective
way, that <q>Essex</q> really is  a place name here. The
<att>degree</att> attribute is used to indicate the degree of
confidence associated with the <gi>certainty</gi> element, expressed as a
number between 0 and 1:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<!-- ... -->
<certainty target="#CE-pl1" locus="name" degree="0.6"/></egXML>
This expresses the point of view that there is a 60 percent chance of <q>Essex</q>
being a place name here, and hence a 40 percent chance of its being a
personal name. We can use two <gi>certainty</gi> elements to indicate the
two probabilities independently. Both elements indicate the same location in the
text, but the second provides an alternative choice of name
identifier (in this case <gi>persName</gi>), which is given as the
value of the <att>assertedValue</att> attribute:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<!-- ... -->
<certainty target="#CE-pl1" locus="name" degree="0.6">
   <desc>probably a placename, but possibly not</desc></certainty>
<certainty target="#CE-pl1" locus="name" degree="0.4" assertedValue="persName">
   <desc>may refer to the Earl of Essex</desc></certainty></egXML></p>

<p>In the simplest case, it is also possible to place the
<gi>certainty</gi> element within the element concerned:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Elizabeth went to 
<placeName>Essex
<certainty locus="name" degree="0.6"/></placeName>.</egXML>
When  no  <att>target</att>  is specified, by default the proposed
certainty applies to its parent element, in this case the
<gi>placeName</gi> element. The <att>match</att> attribute discussed
below may be used to further vary this behaviour.</p>

<div xml:id="CEconcon"><head>Contingent conditions</head>

<p>Finally, we may wish to make our probability estimates contingent
on some condition.  In the passage <q>Elizabeth went to Essex; she had
always liked Essex,</q> for example, we may feel there is a 60 percent chance
that the county is meant, and a 40 percent chance that the earl is meant.  But
the two occurrences of the word are not independent:  there is (we may
feel) no chance at all that the first occurrence refers to the county
and the second
to the earl.  We can express this by using the <att>given</att>
attribute to list the identifiers of <gi>certainty</gi> elements.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Elizabeth went to <placeName xml:id="CE-PL1">Essex</placeName>.
She had always liked <placeName xml:id="CE-PL2">Essex</placeName>.
<!-- ... -->
<!-- 60% chance that P1 is a placename,
     40% chance a personal name. -->
<certainty xml:id="cert-1" target="#CE-PL1" locus="name" degree="0.6">
  <desc>probably a placename, but possibly not"</desc></certainty>
<certainty xml:id="cert-2" target="#CE-PL1" locus="name" assertedValue="persName" degree="0.4">
   <desc>may refer to the Earl of Essex"</desc></certainty>
<!-- 60% chance that P2 is a placename,
     40% chance a personal name.
    100% chance that it agrees with P1. -->
<certainty target="#CE-PL2" locus="name" given="#cert-1" degree="1.0">
   <desc>if CE-PL1 is a placename, CE-PL2 certainly is"</desc></certainty>
<certainty target="#CE-PL2" locus="name" assertedValue="persName" degree="1.0" given="#cert-2">
   <desc>if CE-PL1 is a personal name, then so is CE-PL2</desc></certainty></egXML>
When <att>given</att> conditions are listed, the <gi>certainty</gi>
element is interpreted as claiming a given degree of confidence in a
particular markup given the assertional content of the
<gi>certainty</gi> elements indicated. That is, a conjectural
assertion is being made solely on the assumption that the
interpretation indicated by the element named by the <att>given</att>
attribute is actually correct.</p>

<p>Conditional confidence may be less that 100 percent:  given the sentence
<q>Ernest went to old Saybrook</q>, we may interpret <q>Saybrook</q> as
a personal name or a place name, assigning a 60 percent probability to the
former. If it is a place name, there may be a 50 percent chance that the
place name actually in question is <q>Old Saybrook</q> rather than
<q>Saybrook</q>, while if it is correctly tagged as a personal name, it
is much more likely (say, 90 percent certain) that the name is <q>Saybrook</q>.
Hence there is uncertainty about the correct location for the markup
as well as about which markup to use.  This state of affairs can be expressed using the <gi>certainty</gi> element thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Ernest went to <anchor xml:id="CE-a1"/> old <persName xml:id="CE-p2">Saybrook</persName>.
<certainty xml:id="cert1" target="#CE-p2" locus="name" degree="0.6"/>
<certainty target="#CE-p2" locus="start" given="#cert1" degree="0.9"/>
<certainty xml:id="cert2" target="#CE-p2" locus="name" assertedValue="placeName" degree="0.4"/>
<certainty target="#CE-p2" locus="start" given="#cert2" degree="0.5"/>
<certainty xml:id="cert3" target="#CE-p2" locus="start"
	   assertedValue="#CE-a1" given="#cert1" degree="0.1"/>
<certainty xml:id="cert4" target="#CE-p2" locus="start" assertedValue="#CE-a1" given="#cert2" degree="0.5"/></egXML>

Note the use of the <att>assertedValue</att> on <gi>certainty</gi>
elements <val>cert3</val> and <val>cert4</val> to reference
the <gi>anchor</gi> element placed at the alternative starting
point for the element.</p>

<p>Multiplying the numeric values out, this markup may be interpreted as
assigning specific probabilities to three different ways of
marking up the sentence:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Ernest went to old <persName>Saybrook</persName>.    (0.6 * 0.9, or 0.54)
Ernest went to old <placeName>Saybrook</placeName>.  (0.4 * 0.5, or 0.20)
Ernest went to <placeName>old Saybrook</placeName>.  (0.4 * 0.5, or 0.20)</egXML>
The probabilities do not add up to 1.00 because the markup indicates
that if <q>Saybrook</q> is (part of) a personal name, there is a
10 percent likelihood that the element should start somewhere other than the
place indicated, without however giving an alternative location; there
is thus a 6 percent chance (0.1 × 0.6) that none of the alternatives given is
correct.</p>
</div>
<div><head>Pervasive conditions</head>
<p>We may also wish to indicate confidence in some aspect
of the tagging throughout a document, rather than (as discussed so far) in one
particular instance. The <att>match</att> attribute may be used to
supply a pattern identifying the portion of a document
concerning which certainty is being expressed. The value of the
<att>match</att> attribute is an XPath expression <!--XSLT2 pattern,-->
using the syntax defined in <ptr target="#XSLT2"/>. In the following
example, we wish to indicate a low degree of confidence
that the <gi>persName</gi> elements used throughout the whole document
have been correctly applied:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<certainty locus="name" degree="0.3" match="//persName"/>
</egXML>

No <att>target</att> has been supplied here, and so by default the
<gi>certainty</gi> expressed would therefore apply to the parent
element. However, in this case the XPath supplied as the value for
<att>match</att> returns a set of all the <gi>persName</gi> elements
in the document, independent of the current context. By contrast, in
the following example
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<div><p>.....</p></div>
<div>
<certainty locus="name" degree="0.3" match=".//persName"/>
</div>
</egXML>
only the <gi>persName</gi> elements within the second <gi>div</gi>
element are in question.
Similarly, we may indicate that we have more
confidence in the <gi>persName</gi> tagging within those <gi>div</gi>
attributes which have a <att>type</att> value of <code>checked</code>:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<certainty locus="name" degree="0.7" match="//div[@type='checked']//persName"/>
</egXML>

If an element in a document is matched by more than one match
expression, then the most specific pattern applies. <note place="bottom">Specificity of
pattern matching is defined further in the XSLT2 reference cited above
(see <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xslt20/#conflict"/>)</note> As a
simple case, if both the preceding <gi>certainty</gi> elements were
present in the same document, a <gi>persName</gi> occurring within a
<gi>div type="checked"</gi> element would potentially match both
pattern expressions. However because the second pattern is more
specific than the former, in fact this is the only one that would
apply. If multiple patterns match and have the same priority, then the
first one (in document order) is applied. Only those statements of certainty
which have matched in this sense are available for conditional
application using the <att>given</att> attribute mentioned above.
</p>
<p>When the <att>match</att> attribute is processed, the namespace bindings in
force are those in effect at that point in the document. 
For example, 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<div xmlns:my="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI">
<!-- ... -->
<certainty match=".//my:*" locus="value" degree="0.9"/>
</div>
</egXML>
might be used to indicate a high degree of certainty about the content
of any elements taken the namespace associated with the prefix
<code>my</code>. This namespace prefix must be associated with an
appropriate namespace definition, either on the <gi>certainty</gi>
element itself, or on one of its ancestor elements.</p>
</div>

<div><head>Content uncertainty</head>

<p>Doubts about whether the content of an element is correct may also be expressed
by assigning to <att>locus</att> the value
<mentioned>value</mentioned>.  For example, if the source is
hard to read and so the transcription is uncertain:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I have a <emph xml:id="CE-p3">bun</emph>.
<certainty target="#CE-p3" locus="value" degree="0.5"/></egXML></p>
<p>Degrees of confidence in the proper expansion of abbreviations may
also be expressed, as in the following example:<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">You will want to use
<choice><expan xml:id="CE-e1">Standard
Generalized Markup Language</expan>
<expan xml:id="CE-e40">Some Grandiose Methodology for Losers</expan>
<abbr>SGML</abbr></choice> ...
<!-- ... -->
<certainty target="#CE-e1" locus="value" degree="0.9"/>
<certainty target="#CE-e40" locus="value" degree="0.5"/></egXML></p>
<p>The <att>assertedValue</att> attribute should be used to provide an
alternative value for whatever aspect of the markup is in doubt:  an
alternative name, or the identifier of an alternative starting or
ending point, as already shown, an alternative attribute value, or
alternative element content, as in this example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I have a <emph xml:id="CE-P3">bun</emph>.
<certainty target="#CE-P3" locus="value" assertedValue="gun" degree="0.8"> 
  <desc>a gun makes more sense in a holdup</desc></certainty></egXML>
  Since attribute values have no internal substructure, the
  <att>assertedValue</att> attribute is not generally useful for
  specifying alternative transcriptions;it cannot for example be used
  if the alternative reading contains markup of any kind.  More robust
  methods of handling uncertainties of transcription are the
  <gi>unclear</gi> element and the <gi>app</gi> and <gi>rdg</gi>
  elements described in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>.  The
  <gi>certainty</gi> element allows for indications of uncertainty to
  be structured with at least as much detail and clarity as appears to
  be currently required in most ongoing text projects.</p>
</div>


<div><head>Target or Match?</head>

<p>As noted in <ptr target="#SA"/>, the <att>target</att> attribute
may take any general <val>data.pointer</val> as values and may thus
also contain an XPath expression of arbitrary complexity. Because full
support for XPath is not provided by current processors, it is not
generally recommended TEI practice. There are however some simple
cases in which XPath syntax is to be preferred, notably those in which
the <att>xml:id</att> attribute is used to identify a single element
occurrence. The usage <val>#A</val> (to indicate the element whose
<att>xml:id</att> attribute has the value <val>A</val>) is
syntactically much simpler than the equivalent xpath2 expression
<val>//*[@xml:id='A']</val> and is hence preferred throughout these
guidelines.
</p>
<p>For similar reasons, the <gi>certainty</gi> element may specify
both a <att>target</att> value (expressed as an URI) and a
<att>match</att> value  (expressed as an XPath). The former defines
the context within which the latter is to be evaluated. As previously
noted, if no value is supplied for <att>target</att>, the context
within which the value of <att>match</att> should be evaluated is the
parent element of the <gi>certainty</gi> element itself. </p>

<p>A typical case where it may be convenient to specify both
<att>target</att> and <att>match</att> is that where we wish to
indicate that the value of  an attribute on some specific element  is
uncertain. In this case, the <att>locus</att> attribute
takes the value <val>value</val>. For example, supposing there is only a 50 percent chance that the question was spoken by
participant A:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u xml:id="CE-u1" who="#A">Have you heard the election results?</u>
<certainty target="#CE-u1" match="@who" locus="value"
	   degree="0.5"/></egXML> or, equivalently and without the
need to define a target,
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#A">Have you heard the election results?<certainty match="@who" locus="value"
	   degree="0.5"/></u>
</egXML> 

</p>

<p>The <att>match</att> and <att>target</att> attributes together
provide a powerful mechanism which can be used to indicate precision for a
large number of assertions throughout an encoded document in an
economical way. Some further
examples follow:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<certainty match="//p" locus="location" degree="0.2"/>
</egXML>
This encoding indicates that there is only a 0.2 certainty that the
boundaries of all <gi>p</gi> elements in the document have been correctly
identified.</p>
<p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<certainty target="#a101" match="p" locus="location" degree="0.2"/>
</egXML>
This encoding indicates that there is only a 0.2 certainty that the
boundaries of the <gi>p</gi> elements contained by the element with
<att>xml:id</att> value <val>a101</val> have been correctly
identified.</p>
<p>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<persName resp="#LB">Essex
<certainty match="@resp" locus="value" degree="0.2"/>
</persName></egXML>
This encoding indicates that there is only a 0.2 certainty that the
value for the <att>resp</att> attribute on the given <gi>persName</gi>
element
is correct.</p>
<p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<certainty match="//*/@resp" locus="value" degree="0.2"/>
</egXML>
This encoding indicates that there is only a 0.2 certainty that any
value for the <att>resp</att> attribute is correct, wherever it
appears in the document.</p>

<p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<certainty target="#dd001" match="@resp" locus="value" degree="0.2"/>
</egXML>
This encoding indicates that there is only a 0.2 certainty that the
value for the <att>resp</att> attribute of the element indicated by
the pointer <val>#dd001</val> is correct</p>

<p><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<certainty match="//*[@resp='#LB']" locus="value" degree="0.2"/>
</egXML>
This encoding indicates that there is only a 0.2 certainty that the
content of any element the <att>resp</att> attribute of which has the
value <val>#LB</val> is correct, wherever it
appears in the document.</p>

<p>The <gi>certainty</gi> element and the other TEI mechanisms for
indicating uncertainty provide a range of methods of graduated
complexity.  Simple expressions of uncertainty may be made by using
the <gi>note</gi> element.  This is simple and convenient, and can
accommodate either a discursive and unstructured indication of
uncertainty, or a complex and structured but probably project-specific
expression of uncertainty.  In general, however, unless special steps
are taken, the <gi>note</gi> element does not provide as much
expressive power as the <gi>certainty</gi> element, and in cases where
highly structured certainty information must be given, it is
recommended that the <gi>certainty</gi> element be preferred.</p>
<!--<p>The <gi>certainty</gi> element may be used for simple unqualified
indications of uncertainty, in which case only the <att>locus</att>,
<att>match</att> and
<att>target</att> attributes might be specified.  
In more complex cases, the
other attributes may be used to provide fuller information.  While
these attributes may take any string of characters as value, the recommended
values should be used wherever possible; if they are not appropriate
in a given situation, encoders should provide their own controlled
vocabulary and document it in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> or
<gi>tagUsage</gi> elements of the TEI header.</p>-->
<specGrp>
&precision;
&certainty;
</specGrp>
<specGrpRef target="#DCERESP"/></div>
</div>

</div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="CEPREC"><head>Indications of Precision</head>
<p>As noted above, certainty about the accuracy of an encoding or its
content is not the same thing as the <term>precision</term> with which
a value is specified. In the case of a date or a quantity, for example, we might be
certain that the value given is imprecise, or  uncertain
about whether or not the value given is correct. The latter
possibility would be represented by the <gi>certainty</gi> element
discussed in the previous section; the former by the
<gi>precision</gi> element discussed in this section.</p>
<p>The elements concerning which statements of precision are to be
made are identified using the same <att>target</att> and
<att>match</att> attributes inherited from the
<ident type="class">att.scoping</ident> class discussed in the
previous section and in the same way. Other aspects are provided by
other attributes as further discussed below.
<specList>
<specDesc key="precision" atts="degree stdDeviation"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>In <ptr target="#CONANU"/> several ways of indicating ranges of
values were introduced. For example, if we know that a date falls between
1930 and 1935, without being certain exactly where, this fact may be
encoded using attributes <att>notBefore</att> and
<att>notAfter</att>, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<date notBefore="1930" notAfter="1935">Early in the 1930s</date>...</egXML>
Equally, if we know that every page of a
manuscript has a width of at least 10 cm but no more than 30, we can
use the attributes <att>atLeast</att> and <att>atMost</att>, as in the
following examples:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<width atLeast="10" atMost="30" unit="cm" scope="all"/></egXML>
</p>
<p>Suppose however that the precision with which the value
of such an attribute can be specified is variable. For example,
suppose an event is dated <q>about fifty years after the death of
Augustus</q>. In this case, the precision of one end of the range (the
death of Augustus) is higher than the other, assuming we know when
Augustus died. We can say that the latest possible date is probably 50
years after that, but with less confidence than we can attach to the
earliest possible date. </p>
<p>The <gi>precision</gi> element allows us to indicate the two
attributes concerned and attach different degrees of precision to
them, using the same mechanism as that provided for the
<gi>certainty</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<date xml:id="d001" notBefore="0014" notAfter="0064">About 50
years after the death of Augustus</date>
<precision target="#d001" match="@notAfter" degree="0.3"/>
<precision target="#d001" match="@notBefore" degree="0.9"/>
</egXML></p>
<p>In much the same way, we may wish to indicate different degrees of
precision about the dating of either end of a historical period. For example,
 the elements defined for encoding personal data all bear a similar
 set of attributes to indicate normalized values for earliest or
 latest dates, etc. (see section
 <ptr target="#NDATTSda"/>); the precision of these attribute values
 may be indicated in exactly the same way. For example, 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<residence from="1857-03-01" notAfter="1857-04-30">From the 1st of March to
some time in April of 1857.
<precision match="@notAfter" degree="0.5"/></residence>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>It may also be useful to indicate that the precisions given for 
minimum and maximum quanta differ. For example, to indicate that all
pages measure at least 10 cm wide, and at most <emph>about</emph> 30:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<width xml:id="w00t" atLeast="10" atMost="30" unit="cm" scope="all"/>
<precision target="#w00t" match="@atMost" degree="0.3"/>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>The 
<att>stdDeviation</att> attribute may be used to indicate the
standard deviation for a range of values. The generic <gi>dim</gi>
element introduced in <ptr target="#msdim"/> might be used to record the average
number of characters per line in a typescript. If in addition we wish
to record the standard deviation for the values summarised by that
average, this would require an additional <gi>precision</gi> element,
as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<dim xml:id="dim1"
type="avgLineLength" unit="chars" quantity="62.4"/>
<precision target="#dim1" stdDeviation="4"/>
</egXML>
</p>
</div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="CERESP"><head>Attribution of Responsibility</head>
<p>In general, attribution of responsibility for the transcription and
markup of an electronic text is made by <gi>respStmt</gi> elements
within the header: specifically, within the title statement, the
edition statement(s), and the revision history.</p>
<p>In some cases, however, more detailed element-by-element information
may be desired. For example, an encoder may wish to distinguish between the
individuals responsible for transcribing the content and those
responsible for determining that a given word or phrase constitutes a
proper noun.  Where such fine-grained attribution of responsibility is
required, the <gi>respons</gi> element can be used. 
<specList><specDesc key="respons" atts="locus resp"/></specList></p>
<p>This element allows one or more aspects of the markup to be
attributed to a given individual.  This element inherits the
<att>target</att> and <att>match</att> attributes from the
<ident>att.scoping</ident> class, in the same way as the
<gi>certainty</gi> and <gi>precision</gi> elements. Its 
<att>locus</att> attribute functions in the same way as that on the
<gi>certainty</gi> element (see <ptr target="#CECERT"/>).
</p>
<p>For example,  the following encoding
indicates that RC is responsible for transcribing an
illegible word, and that PMWR is responsible for identifying that word
as a proper noun, i.e. deciding to mark it with the <gi>persName</gi>
element at the location indicated:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Ernest went to old
<persName xml:id="CE-p5" rend="it">Saybrook</persName>.
<!-- ... -->
<respons target="#CE-p5" locus="value" resp="#RC"/>
<respons target="#CE-p5" locus="name location" resp="#PMWR"/>
<list type="encoders">
<item xml:id="PMWR"/>
<item xml:id="RC"/>
</list></egXML></p>
<p>Similarly, in the following example, we indicate that RC is
responsible for proposing the value of the <att>rend</att> attribute:  
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <respons target="#CE-p5" match="@rend" locus="value" resp="#RC"/>
    </egXML>
</p>
<p>Some elements bear specialized <att>resp</att> or <att>agent</att>
attributes, which have specific meanings that vary from element to
element; the <gi>respons</gi> element should be reserved for the general
aspects of responsibility common to all text transcription and
markup, and should not be confused with the more specific attributes on
individual elements.</p>
<specGrp xml:id="DCERESP" n="Responsibility for markup">
&respons;
</specGrp></div>

<div><head>The Certainty Module</head>
<p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following
additional elements:

<moduleSpec xml:id="DCE" ident="certainty"><altIdent type="FPI">Certainty
and Uncertainty</altIdent><desc>Certainty and uncertainty</desc>
<desc xml:lang="fr">Degré de certitude et responsabilité</desc>
<desc xml:lang="zh-TW">確定程度與不確定程度</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Certezza e incertezza</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Certeza e incerteza</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">確信度モジュール</desc></moduleSpec><!--publicID:  -//TEI P5//ELEMENTS Additional Element Set for Certainty and Responsibility//EN-->

The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.

</p>
</div></div>
