<?oxygen RNGSchema="../../../../../RomaResults/divFragments.rnc" type="compact"?>
<div type="div1" xml:id="CF" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <!-- OVERALL NOTES:
  - standardise use of scheme vs schema
  - the phrase 'Valid TEI ODD file' is used but we don't really define
  what  this means in the section about it, nor where in the header
  to point to the ODD.
  - 
  -->
  <head>Conformance</head>

  <p>The notion of <term>TEI Conformance</term> is intended to assist
    in the description of the format and contents of a particular XML
    document instance or set of documents. It may be found useful in
    such situations as: <list>
      <item>agreements for the interchange of documents among
        researchers</item>
      <item> agreements for the deposit of texts in, and distribution
        of texts from, archives</item>
      <item> describing the documents to be produced by or for a given
        project</item>
      <item>defining the classes of documents accepted or rejected by
        a given piece of software</item>
      <item>characterising the extent to which a document may be
        re-used by some other project than that which originated it,
        or integrated with other documents </item>
    </list> It is not intended to provide any other evaluation, for
    example of scholarly merit, intellectual integrity, or value
    for money. A document may be of major intellectual importance and
    yet not be TEI-conformant; a TEI conformant document may be of no
    scholarly value whatsoever.</p>

  <p>In this section we try to define how exactly the term <term>TEI
      Conformance</term> should be used. The terminology defined here
    should be considered normative, in the sense that users and
    implementors of the TEI Guidelines should use the phrases defined
    here in the senses given and with the usages described only. </p>

  <p> A document is <term>TEI-Conformant</term> if it: <list>
      <item> is a well-formed XML document, which can be validated
      against a schema derived from the TEI Guidelines</item>
      <item> conforms to the TEI abstract model </item>
      <item> uses the <term>TEI Namespace</term> correctly </item>
<!--      <item> contains a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element that includes
        elements for at least a title statement and publication
        statement</item>-->
      <item> documents any customizations of the TEI scheme used to
      produce its schema by means of a
        valid <term>TEI ODD file</term></item>

    </list> Each of these criteria is discussed in more detail below. </p>

  <p>In addition, a TEI document is said to follow <term>TEI
      Recommended Practice</term> if: <list>
      <item> it is a <term>TEI-Conformant</term> Document;</item>
      <item> wherever the Guidelines prefer one encoding practice to
        another, the preferred practice is used;</item>
    </list></p>

<p>
  <div type="div3">
    <head> Well-Formed XML and Valid Document</head>
    <p>All <term>TEI-Conformant</term> documents must be well-formed
      XML documents according to the the World Wide Web Consortium
      recommendation of the <title>Extensible Markup Language (XML)
        1.0 (Fourth Edition)</title> or successor editions found at
        <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/"
        >http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/</ref>. Additionally in order for a
      document to be considered <term>TEI-Conformant</term> it must
      validate against a series of constraints expressed as one or
      more Schema files. </p>
  </div>

  <div type="div3">
    <head>Validating Against a TEI-Derived Schema</head>
    <p> All <term>TEI-Conformant</term> documents must validate
      against one or more Schema files that have been derived from the
      published TEI schema modules, combined and documented in the
      manner described in section <ptr target="#MD"/>.</p>
    <p> Although the TEI attempts to support XML DTDs, W3C XML Schema,
      and RELAX NG (both compact and XML formats), it does not mandate
      any particular schema language<note place="foot">Here and
        elsewhere we use the word <mentioned>schema</mentioned> to
        refer to any formal document grammar, irrespective of the
        formalism used to represent it.</note> only that this schema
      should have been generated from a <term>TEI ODD file</term> that
      references the TEI Guidelines. <term>TEI-Conformant</term>
      documents may embed elements from other namespaces and
      standards, as long as their relationship to the TEI has been
      documented in the <term>TEI ODD file</term> from which their
      schema has been generated.</p>
  </div>

  <div type="div3">
    <head>Use of the <term>TEI Namespace</term>
    </head>

    <p>The elements and attributes defined by the TEI Guidelines
      constitute the <term>TEI Namespace</term>, except for a few such
      as the <att>xml:id</att> attribute that are adopted directly
      from the XML specification. In a <term>TEI-Conformant</term>
      document, all unmodified elements and attributes must be in this
      namespace. This namespace is: "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0/".
      While this in no way precludes the embedding of elements from
      other namespaces inside a <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document,
      their relationship to the TEI must be documented in the TEI ODD
      file and the <term>TEI Namespace</term> must not be extended
      with additional elements or attributes. This is discussed
      further in the section below entitled <ptr target="#CFNS"/>.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="div3">
    <head>Conformance to the TEI abstract model</head>
    <p>The <term>TEI Abstract Model</term> is the conceptual schema
      instantiated by the TEI Guidelines which define, both formally
      and informally, a set of abstract concepts such as
      <q>paragraph</q> or <q>heading</q>. It is an important condition
      of TEI conformance that elements defined in the TEI Guidelines
      as having one specific meaning should not be used with another.
      For example, the element <gi>l</gi> is defined in the TEI
      Guidelines as containing a line of verse. A schema in which it
      is redefined to mean a typographic line, or an ordered queue of
      objects of some kind, cannot therefore be TEI conformant,
      whatever its other properties.</p>
    <p>The semantics of elements defined in the TEI Guidelines are
      conveyed in a number of ways, ranging from formally verifiable
      datatypes to informal descriptive prose. In addition, a mapping
      between TEI elements and concepts in other conceptual models may
      be provided by the <gi>equiv</gi> element where this is
      available. </p>
    <p>A schema which shares equivalent concepts to those of the TEI
      conceptual model may be mappable to the TEI schema by means of
      such a mechanism. For example, the concept of paragraph,
      expressed in the TEI scheme by the <gi>p</gi> element is
      probably mappable to the concept expressed in the Docbook scheme
      by the <gi>para</gi> element. Such areas of overlap facilitate
      interoperability, because elements from one namespace may be
      readily integrated to those from another, but do not affect the
      definition of conformance.</p>
    <p>A document is said to follow the <term>TEI Abstract
      Model</term> if it encodes those features specified in the TEI
      Guidelines, and the structural interrelations of this encoding
      agrees with that specified in a valid schema for
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> documents. That is, the abstract
      definition and markup structurally corresponds to that in the
      TEI Guidelines even if the names of elements and attributes
      might not. While it may be relatively easy to transform a
      document following the <term>TEI Abstract Model</term> into a
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document, it is not itself
      conformant.</p>
    <p>A particularly important special case of this kind of mapping
      is provided by ongoing efforts within the library community to
      define metadata interoperability standards. The relationship of
      the TEI Header to such efforts is discussed in <ptr target="#SH"
      /> below.</p>

  </div>

  <div type="div3">
    <head> Including a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element with a title
      statement and publication statement</head>
    <p>It is a long-standing requirement for any
      <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document that it should contain a
        <gi>teiHeader</gi> element. To be more specific a
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document must contain either: <list>
        <item> a single <gi>teiHeader</gi> element followed by a
          single <gi>text</gi> element, in that order; or</item>
        <item> in the case of a corpus or collection, a single overall
            <gi>teiHeader</gi> element followed by a series of
          <gi>TEI</gi> elements each with its own
        <gi>teiHeader</gi></item>
      </list> All <gi>teiHeader</gi> elements in a
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document must include elements
      for: <list type="gloss">
        <label>Title Statement</label>
        <item>This should include the title of the TEI document
          expressed using a <gi>titleStmt</gi> element.</item>
        <label>Publication Statement</label>
        <item>This should include the place and date of publication or
          distribution of the TEI document, expressed using the
            <gi>publicationStmt</gi> element.</item>
        <label>Source Statement</label>
        <item>For a document derived from some previously existing
          document, this must include a bibliographic description of
          that source. For a document not so derived, this must
          include a brief statement that the document has no
          pre-existing source. In either case, this will be expressed
          using the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element. </item>

      </list></p>

  </div>

  <div type="div3">
    <head>A Customization of the TEI Schema must be expressed using a
      Valid <term>TEI ODD File</term></head>
    <p>For any TEI conformant document, there must exist a valid
        <term>TEI ODD file</term> that specifies which modules,
      elements, classes, etc. are in use, and from which a TEI schema
      can be generated to validate the document. The TEI supplies a
      number of predefined <term>TEI Customization exemplar ODD
      files</term> and the schemas already generated from them (see
        <ptr target="#MDlite"/>), but most projects will typically
      need to customize the TEI beyond what these examples provide. It
      is assumed, for example, that most projects will customize the
      TEI scheme by removing those elements that are not needed for
      the texts they are encoding, and by providing further
      constraints on the attribute values and element content models
      the TEI provides. All such customizations must be specified by
      means of a valid <term>TEI ODD</term> file. </p>

    <p>As different sorts of customization have different implications
      for the interchange and interoperability of TEI documents, to
      ease communication the TEI has determined a number of schema
      categories that TEI-Conformant documents usually fall into.
      Although each of these categories of schema can be used to
      validate a TEI-Conformant document, the TEI has additional
      recommendations that help to distinguish between them. These are
      discussed in detail below in the section entitled <ptr
        target="#CFCATSCH"/>. </p>
  </div>

  <div type="div3" xml:id="CFCATSCH">
    <head>Varieties of TEI Conformance</head>
    <p>The definition of TEI conformance permits several different
      kinds of schema of varying interchangeability. We define names
      for some of the chief varieties here: <list type="gloss">
        <label>
          <term>TEI Pure Subset Schema</term>
        </label>
        <item>A <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> is one which is
          identical to or further constrains the tei_all schema. This
          may include: the removal of unused elements, attributes, and
          classes; the provision of attribute value lists; or the
          further constraint of existing datatypes or content models. 
          A <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> only documents elements in
          the TEI namespace.  A document instance that validates against a
            <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> must always also
          validate against the tei_all schema; in the terminology
          introduced in <ptr target="#MDMD"/>, it is the result of
            <term>clean modification</term>. </item>
        <label>
          <term>TEI Renaming Subset Schema</term>
        </label>
        <item>A <term>TEI Renaming Subset schema</term> is one which
          is identical to or further constrains a <term>TEI Pure
            Subset schema</term>, but which can also rename existing
          elements or attributes if and only if an <gi>equiv</gi> element in
          their valid <term>TEI ODD file</term> documents an existing
            <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> equivalent for them.
          None of these changes should conflict with the names of
          existing TEI elements, attributes or classes and to ensure
          this they should be in a user-defined namespace. A document instance that
          validates against a <term>TEI Renaming Subset schema</term>
          must always also validate against the tei_all schema if the
          renamings are reversed or replaced with their documented
          equivalents from the TEI namespace. </item>
        <label>
          <term>TEI Modification Schema</term>
        </label>
        <item> A <term>TEI Modification schema</term> is one which
          modifies a <term>TEI Pure Subset</term> or <term>TEI
            Renaming Subset</term> by: changing existing elements,
          attributes, or classes; adding existing elements or
          attributes to members of existing classes; or changing
          existing datatypes or content models. These changes should
          not add new elements, attributes or classes, and all changes
          should be documented in a <term>TEI ODD file</term>. Any
          elements or attributes to which unclean modifications (see
            <ptr target="#MDMD"/>) have been been made should be
          placed in a user-defined namespace. A document instance that
          validates against a <term>TEI Modification schema</term> is
          not expected to validate against the tei_all schema or
          subsets of this schema. </item>
        <label>
          <term>TEI Extension Schema</term>
        </label>
        <item> A <term>TEI Extension schema</term> is one that extends
          a <term>TEI Pure Subset</term>, <term>TEI Renaming
          Subset</term>, or <term>TEI Modification schema</term> by
          adding new elements, attributes, classes, datatypes or
          content models. All new elements and attributes, which are
          not renamings of current elements and attributes, must be
          added in a separate namespace. The relationship of any
          extensions to the TEI should be documented in a <term>TEI
            ODD file</term>. Additionally any renamings of existing
          TEI elements and attributes should be documented with an
            <gi>equiv</gi> element to an existing <term>TEI Pure
            Subset schema</term> equivalent for them and appear in a
          user-defined namespace. A document
          instance that validates against a <term>TEI Extension
          schema</term> is not expected to validate against the
          tei_all schema. </item>
        <label>
          <term>TEI Supported Extension schema</term>
        </label>
        <item>A <term>TEI Supported Extension schema</term> is a
          special case of the <term>TEI Extension schema</term>, where
          the extension has been created and is (to some degree)
          supported by the TEI. This includes the <term>TEI
            Customization Exemplars</term> detailed above (see <ptr
            target="#MDlite"/>. A document instance that validates
          against a <term>TEI Supported Extension schema</term> is not
          expected to validate against the tei_all schema. </item>
      </list>
    </p>
  </div>



  <div type="div3">
    <head>Non-Conformant Customizations</head>
    <p> In some cases those using the TEI may wish to customize the
      TEI in a non-conformant manner. While producing
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> customizations is always to be
      preferred, it is recognised there are situations where this may
      not be possible or practical. Most of these situations are
      entirely reasonable, and conformance, while desirable, should
      not be confused with quality. </p>
    <p>It is also recognised that data destined to be in a
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document may originate in a
      variety of forms. Data might be captured by keyboarding or other
      processing pipelines into a locally defined data creation
      format. This may itself be a non-conformant format; as may the
      local storage or format used internally for a project because of
      local processing needs. Whenever possible, however, local
      storage in a <term>TEI-Conformant</term> format is recommended
      as this is likely to record more information than the input
      format for a single application or processing need. It is
      possible that there may be entirely different formats at
      different stages in the processes of data creation, local
      storage and processed dissemination. However, even if any of the
      data creation, local storage or processing formats are not
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term>, they may still follow TEI
      recommendations in the selection of textual features to be
      marked up, element names and content models, or additionally the
        <term>TEI Abstract Model</term>.</p>
    
    <p>As noted above, the TEI ODD system may be used to document any
      markup scheme, whether or not it is TEI conformant. We therefore
      use the term <term>TEI-Based Customization</term> to define an
      application of a valid <term>TEI ODD file</term> that defines any
      non-TEI-conformant markup scheme<note place="foot">Such a
        specification, being a TEI ODD, is ipso facto TEI conformant
        of course</note>.        
      A document instance that validates against a
        <term>TEI-Based customization </term> is not expected to
      validate against the tei_all schema or be interoperable with
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> documents. Where such a document
      makes use of elements defined in the TEI abstract model it may
      signal this fact by making use of the TEI namespace for them.      
    </p>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="CFNS">
    <head>Namespaces and <term>TEI Conformance</term></head>
    <p>It is a requirement of <term>TEI Conformance</term> that, in a
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document, all existing TEI
      elements and attributes be in the <term>TEI Namespace</term>:
      "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0/". Moreover,
      <term>TEI-Conformant</term> documents must not extend the
        <term>TEI Namespace</term> with additional elements and
      attributes <!-- except by means of a <term>TEI Renaming Subset
      Schema</term> produced from a <term>TEI ODD file</term> which
      properly documents the renamed elements or attributes through
      the use of the <gi>equiv</gi> element -->. All new elements or attributes
       must appear in a separate namespace, either a user-defined one or if the
      elements are taken from an existing schema, the namespace
      appropriate to that schema. In a <term>TEI Extension
      schema</term> a TEI element may have an attribute not from the
        <term>TEI Namespace</term>, provided that the expanded-name of
      the attribute has a non-null namespace URI. It is an error for
      an element from the <term>TEI Namespace</term> to have
      attributes with expanded-names which have null namespace URIs
      (i.e. attributes with unprefixed names) other than attributes
      defined for the element in the TEI Guidelines. A
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document might have only one
      namespace, that is the <term>TEI Namespace</term>, or it might
      have any number of namespaces whose relationship and point of
      attachment has been documented in a valid <term>TEI ODD file</term>.
      In choosing user-defined namespaces care should be taken to
      avoid conflicts with existing namespaces, while simultaneously
      indicating the nature of the extension being added. </p>
    <p>It is recognised that some processing software may find coping
      with multiple (or any) namespaces difficult, and that as a
      result the local storage or processing format may conflate or
      remove namespaces. While this is regrettable, and will make
      those document instances non-conformant, it highlights one
      reason that any new elements, even in a separate namespace,
      should not have identical names to existing elements.  There are
      many reasons for the TEI's use of namespaces.  These include the avoidance of
      element name collision and the clear signalling of elements the
      TEI has created.  Wherever possible the removal or conflation of namespaces should be avoided.</p>
  </div>


  <div type="div2">
    <head><term>TEI Conformance</term> and <term>TEI ODD Files</term></head>
    <p>As it is a requirement for conformance that any new
      customizations of the TEI schemas should be documented in a
      valid <term>TEI ODD file</term>, it is recommended practice that
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> document instances should indicate
      the URI of a <term>TEI ODD file</term> from which their
      applicable schemas have been generated. When interchanging TEI
      documents with others, providing this ODD file (or making it
      freely accessible on the internet) is recommended practice. In
      many cases users may simply wish to use the schemas derived from
      the <term>TEI Customization Exemplars</term> such as those
      detailed above. In this case they should indicate either in
      prose or via a URI the ODD and/or schema it validates against.
      Where different versions of this schema have been produced, it
      should be assumed that the document instance validates against
      the most recent version of the schema at the date of publication
      recorded in its header. Although the TEI attempts to support XML
      DTDs, W3C XML Schema, and RELAX NG (both compact and XML
      formats), it does not mandate the schema language you should
      use, only that this schema should have been generated through
      the use of a <term>TEI ODD file</term> that references the TEI
      Guidelines. </p>
  </div>


  <div type="div2">
    <head><term>TEI Conformance</term> and Document Interchange</head>
    <p>Although a wide variety of documents are able to be
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term>, it should be stressed that this
      does not in any way imply that interchange or interoperability
      of these documents will be straightforward. While it should be
      mostly unproblematic with documents that validate against a TEI
      Pure Subset or TEI Renaming schema, any form of TEI Modification
      or <term>TEI Extension</term> schema will necessarily be less
      suitable for interchange or interoperable use. For this reason,
      whenever it is possible it is recommended that where a local
      storage format is validated against a <term>TEI
      Modification</term> or <term>TEI Extension</term> schema, the
      possibilities for transforming these to forms which validate
      against a <term>TEI Pure Subset</term> schema should be investigated. Every care should
      be taken to preserve all the intellectual content that resides
      in the incompatible markup, and wherever possible the
      differences between the two should be documented not only in the
      existing valid <term>TEI ODD file</term>, but also in accompanying
      project documentation. One strategy is to move incompatible
      markup into separate files and use stand-off markup to retain
      the information. </p>
  </div>


  <!-- <div type="div2">
    <head><term>TEI Conformance</term> and Funding Bodies</head>
    <p>The TEI is aware that some academic funding bodies view
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term> documents as superior to
      non-conformant TEI documents. It should be stressed to these
      bodies that although TEI-Conformance does imply additional
      documentation (through the <term>TEI ODD file</term>), and some
      very basic format requirements, it should not be confused with a
      marker of quality. It is possible that a non-conformant TEI
      document may be of superior quality, provide more significantly
      detailed documentation, and have been subjected to greater
      academic scrutiny than one which is technically
        <term>TEI-Conformant</term>. While the TEI recommends the
      production of documents which are <term>TEI-Conformant</term>,
      it recognises that the goals such as textual fidelity,
      documentation, and academic rigour are more important. Although
      the TEI encourages these funding bodies to suggest <term>TEI
        Conformance</term>, and in addition <term>TEI Recommended
        Practice</term>, their prime concern should be the overall
      quality of the documents for the funded purpose and their
      potential for re-use.</p>
  </div>

-->

</div>
