<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="DR" n="10"><head>Performance Texts</head>
<p>This module is intended for use when encoding printed dramatic
texts, screen plays or radio scripts, and written transcriptions of any
other form of performance.
</p> 
<p>Section <ptr target="#DRFAB"/> discusses elements such as cast lists,
which can appear only in the front or back matter of printed dramatic
texts. Section <ptr target="#DRBOD"/> discusses the structural
components of performance texts: these include major structural
divisions such as acts and scenes (section <ptr target="#DRDIV"/>);
individual speeches (section <ptr target="#DRSP"/>); groups of
speeches (section <ptr target="#DRSPG"/>); stage directions
(section <ptr target="#DRSTA"/>); and the elements making up individual
speeches (section <ptr target="#DRPAL"/>). Section <ptr target="#DREMB"/>
discusses ways of encoding units which cross the simple hierarchic
structure so far defined, such as embedded songs or masques.
Finally, section <ptr target="#DROTH"/> discusses a small number of
additional elements characteristic of screen plays and radio or
television scripts, as well as some elements for representing
technical stage directions such as lighting or blocking.</p>

<p>The default structure for dramatic texts is similar to that
defined by chapter <ptr target="#DS"/>, as further discussed in
section <ptr target="#DRDIV"/>.</p>

<p>Two element classes are used by this module.
The <ident type="class">model.frontPart.drama</ident> class supplies
specialized elements which can appear only in the front or back matter
of performance texts.  The <ident type="class">model.stageLike</ident>
class supplies a set of elements for stage directions and similar
items such as camera movements, which can occur between or within
speeches. </p>

<specGrpRef target="#DDRFAB"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDRSTA"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDROTH"/>

<div type="div2" xml:id="DRFAB"><head>Front and Back Matter
 </head>
<p>In dramatic texts, as in all TEI-conformant documents, the header
element is followed by a <gi>text</gi> element, which contains optional
front and back matter, and either a <gi>body</gi> or else a
<gi>group</gi> of nested <gi>text</gi> elements.  For more information
on these, see chapter <ptr target="#DS"/>.
 </p>
<p>The <gi>front</gi> and <gi>back</gi> elements are most likely to be
of use when encoding preliminary materials in published performance
texts.  When the module defined by this chapter is included in a
schema, the following additional elements not generally
found in other forms of text become available as part of the front or
back matter:
<specList><specDesc key="performance"/><specDesc key="prologue"/><specDesc key="epilogue"/><specDesc key="set"/><specDesc key="castList"/></specList>
 </p>

<p>Elements for encoding each of these specific kinds of front matter
are discussed in the remainder of this section, in the order given
above.  In addition, the front matter of dramatic texts may include
the same elements as that of any other kind of text, notably title
pages and various kinds of text division, as discussed in section <ptr target="#DSFRONT"/>.  The encoder may choose to ignore the specialized
elements discussed in this section and instead use constructions of
the type <tag>div type="performance"</tag> or <tag>div1
type="set"</tag>.
 </p>

<p>Most other material in the front matter of a performance text will be
marked with the default text structure elements described in chapter
<ptr target="#DS"/>.  For example, the title
page, dedication, other commendatory material, preface, etc., in a
printed text should be encoded using <gi>div</gi> or <gi>div1</gi>
elements, containing headings, paragraphs, and other core tags.
 </p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDRFAB" n="Specialized front and back matter for performance texts">
<specGrpRef target="#DDRSET"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDRPRO"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDRPERF"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDRCAST"/></specGrp>


<div type="div3" xml:id="DRSET"><head>The Set Element</head>
<p>A special form of note describing the setting of a dramatic text
(that is, the time and place of its action) is sometimes found in the
front matter.
<specList><specDesc key="set"/></specList>
Descriptions of the setting may also appear as initial stage directions
in the body of the play, but such descriptions should be marked as stage
directions, not <gi>set</gi>.  The <gi>set</gi> element should be used
only where the description forms part of the front matter, as in the
following examples:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-01"><front>
  <castList>
    <castItem> ... </castItem>
  </castList>
  <set><p>The action of the play is set in Chicago's
       Southside, sometime between World War II and the
       present.</p></set>
</front></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-02"><front>
  <titlePage type="half-title">
    <docTitle><titlePart>Peer Gynt</titlePart></docTitle>
  </titlePage>
  <div type="copyright_page">  </div>
  <div type="Contents">  </div>
  <div type="Introduction">  </div>
  <div type="note">
    <head>Note on the Translation</head> 
    <p> ... </p>
  </div>
  <div type="Dramatis_Personae">
    <head>Characters</head> 
    <castList><castItem> <!-- ... --> </castItem>  </castList>
  </div>
  <set><p>The action, which opens in the beginning of the nineteenth
  century, and ends around the 1860s, takes place partly in
  Gudbrandsdalen, and on the mountains around it, partly on the coast
  of Morocco, in the desert of Sahara, in a madhouse at Cairo, at sea,
  etc.</p></set>
  <performance>	<p>  <!-- .... --> </p> </performance>
</front>
</egXML>
 </p>

<specGrp xml:id="DDRSET" n="The set element">

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/set.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRPRO"><head>Prologues and Epilogues</head>
<p>Many plays in the Western tradition include in their front matter a
prologue, spoken by an actor, generally not in character.  Similar
speeches often also occur at the end of the play, as epilogues.  The
elements <gi>prologue</gi> and <gi>epilogue</gi> are provided for the
encoding of such features within the front or back matter, where
appropriate.
<specList><specDesc key="prologue"/><specDesc key="epilogue"/></specList>
A prologue may be encoded just like a distinct poem, as in the following
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRPRO-eg-6"><front>
  <prologue>
    <head>Prologue, spoken by <name>Mr. Hart</name></head>
    <l>Poets like Cudgel'd Bullys, never do</l>
    <l>At first, or second blow, submit to you;</l>
    <l>But will provoke you still, and ne're have done,</l>
    <l>Till you are weary first, with laying on:</l>
    <l>We patiently you see, give up to you,</l>
    <l>Our Poets, Virgins, nay our Matrons too.</l>
  </prologue>
  <castList>
    <head>The Persons</head>
    <castItem> ... </castItem>
  </castList>
  <set><head>The SCENE</head>
    <p>London</p>
  </set>
</front>
</egXML>
<!-- Wycherley, Country Wife, 1675 -->
 </p>
<p>A prologue or epilogue may also be encoded as a speech, using the
<gi>sp</gi> element described in section <ptr target="#CODR"/>.  This is
particularly appropriate where stage directions, etc., are involved, as
in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRPRO-eg-7"><epilogue>
   <head>Written by <name>Colley Cibber, Esq</name>
    and spoken by <name>Mrs. Cibber</name></head>
   <sp>
      <lg type="stanza">
         <l>Since Fate has robb'd me of the hapless Youth,</l>
         <l>For whom my heart had hoarded up its truth;</l>
         <l>By all the Laws of Love and Honour, now,</l>
         <l>I'm free again to chuse, — and one of you</l>
      </lg>
      <lg type="stanza">
         <l>Suppose I search the sober Gallery; — No,</l>
         <l>There's none but Prentices — &amp; Cuckolds all a row:</l>
         <l>And these, I doubt, are those that make 'em so.</l>
      </lg>
      <stage>Pointing to the Boxes.</stage>
      <lg type="stanza">
         <l>'Tis very well, enjoy the jest:</l>
      </lg>
   </sp>
</epilogue></egXML>
<!-- G. Lillo, The London Merchant  (1731) -->
 </p>
<p>In cases where the prologue or epilogue is clearly a significant part
of the dramatic action, it may be preferable to include it in the body
of a text, rather than in the front or back matter.  In such cases, the
encoder (and theatrical tradition) will determine whether or not to
regard it as a new scene or division, or simply the final speech in the
play.  In the First Folio version of Shakespeare's
<title>Tempest</title>, for example, Prospero's final speech is clearly
marked off as a distinct textual unit by the headings and layout of the
page, and might therefore be encoded as back matter:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#CODR-eg-295"><text>
  <body>
    <div1 type="scene">
      <sp>
        <l part="Y">I'le deliver all,</l>
        <l>And promise you calme Seas, auspicious gales,</l>
        <l>Be free and fare thou well: please you, draw neere.</l>
        <stage>Exeunt omnes.</stage>
      </sp>
    </div1>
  </body>
  <back>
    <epilogue>
      <head>Epilogue, spoken by Prospero.</head>
      <sp>
        <l>Now my Charmes are all ore-throwne,</l>
        <l>And what strength I have's mine owne</l>
        <l>As you from crimes would pardon'd be,</l>
        <l>Let your Indulgence set me free.</l></sp>
      <stage>Exit</stage>
    </epilogue>
    <set>
	  <p>The Scene, an un-inhabited Island.</p>
	</set>
    <castList>
      <head>Names of the Actors.</head>
      <castItem>Alonso, K. of Naples</castItem>
      <castItem>Sebastian, his Brother.</castItem>
      <castItem>Prospero, the right Duke of Millaine.</castItem>
    </castList>
    <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
  </back>
</text></egXML>
<!-- The Tempest, first folio -->
 </p>
<p>In many modern editions, the editors have chosen to regard
Prospero's speech as a part of the preceding scene:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#CODR-eg-295"><sp>
  <speaker>Prospero</speaker>
  <l part="Y">I'll deliver all,</l>
  <l>And promise you calm seas, auspicious gales,</l>
  <l>Be free and fare thou well. <stage type="exit">Exit Ariel</stage>
	Please you, draw near. <stage type="exit">Exeunt all but Prospero</stage>
    <note place="margin">Epilogue</note> </l>
  <l>Now my charms are all o'erthrown,</l>
  <l>And what strength I have's mine own</l>
  <l>As you from crimes would pardoned be,</l>
  <l>Let your indulgence set me free.</l>
</sp>
<stage type="mix">He awaits applause, then exit.</stage></egXML>
<!-- In nearly every example I have looked at, the prologue -->
	<!-- precedes the dramatis personae.   (LB) -->
 </p>

<specGrp xml:id="DDRPRO" n="The prologue and epilogue elements">







<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/prologue.xml"/>












<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/epilogue.xml"/>





</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRPERF"><head>Records of Performances</head>
<p>Performance texts are not only printed in books to be read, they are
also performed.  It is common practice therefore to include within the
front matter of a printed dramatic text some brief account of particular
performances, using the following element:
<specList><specDesc key="performance"/></specList>
The <gi>performance</gi> element may be used to group any and all
information relating to the actual performance of a play or screenplay,
whether it specifies how the play should be performed in general or how
it was performed in practice on some occasion.
 </p>
<p>Performance information may include complex structures such as cast
lists, or paragraphs describing the date and location of a performance,
details about the setting portrayed in the performance and so forth.
(See the discussion of these specialized structures in section <ptr target="#DRFAB"/> above.)  If
information for more than one performance is being recorded, then more
than one <gi>performance</gi> element should be used, wherever possible.
 </p>
<p>Names of persons, places, and dates of particular significance within
the performance record may be explicitly marked using the general
purpose <gi>name</gi>, <tag>rs type="place"</tag> and <gi>date</gi>
elements described in section <ptr target="#CONADA"/>.
No particular elements for such features as stagehouses,
directors, etc., are proposed at this time.
 </p>
<p>For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRPERF-eg-12"><performance>
   <head>Death of a Salesman</head>
   <p>A New Play by Arthur Miller</p>
   <p>Staged by Elia Kazan</p>
   <castList>
      <head>Cast</head>
      <note rend="small type flush left" place="inline">(in order of appearance)</note>
      <castItem>
         <role>Willy Loman</role> 
         <actor>Lee J. Cobb</actor>
      </castItem>
      <castItem>
         <role>Linda</role>       
         <actor>Mildred Dunnock</actor>
      </castItem>
      <castItem>
         <role>Biff</role>        
         <actor>Arthur Kennedy</actor>
      </castItem>
      <castItem>
         <role>Happy</role>       
         <actor>Cameron Mitchell</actor>
      </castItem>
      <!-- ... -->
   </castList>
   <p>The setting and lighting were designed by 
      <name>Jo Mielziner</name>.</p>
   <p>The incidental music was composed by <name>Alex North</name>.</p>
   <p>The costumes were designed by <name>Julia Sze</name>.</p>
   <p>Presented by <name rend="unmarked">Kermit Bloomgarden</name>
    and <name rend="unmarked">Walter Fried</name> at the 
    <rs type="place">Morosco Theatre in New York</rs> on 
    <date when="1949-02-10">February 10, 1949</date>.</p>
</performance></egXML>
<!-- N.B. first two 'p' elements might also be BYLINE?        -->
	<!-- NOTE could be part of title (but is clearly marked by    -->
	<!-- typography as distinct segment ...)                      -->
	<!-- Last series of P elements could be LIST TYPE='SIMPLE'    -->
	<!-- -msm                                                     -->
Or:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRPERF-eg-13" xml:lang="fr"><performance>
   <p>La Machine Infernale a été
    représentée pour la première fois au
    <rs type="place-theatre">théâtre Louis-Jouvet</rs>
    <rs type="place-theatre">(Comédie des
	Champs-élysées)</rs> <date>le 10 avril 1934</date>,
    avec les décors et les costumes de
    <name>Christian Bérard.</name> ... </p>
</performance></egXML>
<!-- La Machine Infernale, Jean Cocteau -->
 </p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDRPERF" n="The performance element">







<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/performance.xml"/>





</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRCAST"><head>Cast Lists</head>
<p>A <term>cast list</term> is a specialized form of list,
conventionally found at the start or end of a play, usually listing all
the speaking and non-speaking roles in the play, often with additional
description (<q>Cataplasma, a maker of Periwigges and Attires</q>) or
the name of an actor or actress (<q>Old Lady Squeamish. Mrs
Rutter</q>).  Cast lists may be encoded with the general purpose
<gi>list</gi> element described in section <ptr target="#COLI"/>, but for
more detailed work the following specialized elements are provided:
<specList><specDesc key="castList"/><specDesc key="castGroup"/><specDesc key="castItem" atts="type"/></specList>
</p><p>A <gi>castItem</gi> element may contain any mixture of elements
taken from the <ident type="class">model.castItemPart</ident> class,
members of which (when this module is included) are:
<specList>
<specDesc key="role"/><specDesc key="roleDesc"/><specDesc key="actor"/></specList>
Cast lists often have an internal structure of their own; it is quite
usual to find, for example, nobility and commoners, or male and female
roles, presented in different groups or sublists.  Roles are also often
grouped together by their function, for example:
<list type="simple">
<item>Sons of Cato:
<list type="simple">
<item>Portius</item>
<item>Marcus</item></list></item></list>
 </p>
<p>A cast list relating to a specific performance may be accompanied by
notes about the time or place of that performance, indicating (for
example) the name of the theatre where the play was first presented, the
name of the producer or director, and so forth.  When the cast list
relates to a specific performance, it should be embedded within a
<gi>performance</gi> element (see section <ptr target="#DRPERF"/>), as in
the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRCAST-eg-16"><performance>
  <p>The first performance in Great Britain of <title>Waiting for
	  Godot</title> was given at the Arts Theatre, London, on 
         <date when="1955-08-03">3rd August 1955</date>. It was directed by
	  <name>Peter Hall</name>, and the décor was by <name>Peter
	  Snow</name>. The cast was as follows:</p>
  <castList>
	<castItem>Estragon: Peter Woodthorpe</castItem>
	<castItem>Vladimir: Paul Daneman</castItem>
	<castItem> ... </castItem>
  </castList>
</performance></egXML>
<!-- S Beckett, W for G, Faber, 1956 -->
 </p>
<p>In this example, the <gi>castItem</gi> elements have no substructure.
If desired, however, their components may be more finely distinguished
using the elements <gi>role</gi>, <gi>roleDesc</gi>, and <gi>actor</gi>.
For example, the second cast item above might be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><castItem>     
  <role xml:id="vlad">Vladimir</role>:
  <actor>Paul Daneman</actor>
</castItem></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The global <att>xml:id</att> attribute may be used to specify a unique
identifier for the <gi>role</gi> element, where it is desired to link
speeches within the text explicitly to the role, using the
<att>who</att> attribute, as further discussed in section <ptr target="#DRSP"/> below.
 </p>
<p>The occasionally lengthy descriptions of a role sometimes found in
written play scripts may be marked using the <gi>roleDesc</gi> element,
as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRCAST-eg-18"><castItem> 
   <role>Tom Thumb the Great</role>
   <roleDesc>a little hero with a great soul, something violent in his
    temper, which is a little abated by his love for Huncamunca</roleDesc>
   <actor>Young Verhuyk</actor>
</castItem></egXML>
<!-- Fielding, Tragedy of Tragedies (1737) -->
For non-speaking or un-named roles, a <gi>castItem</gi> may contain a
<gi>roleDesc</gi> without an accompanying <gi>role</gi>, for example
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><castItem>  
   <roleDesc>Costermonger</roleDesc>
</castItem></egXML>
 </p>
<p>When a list of such minor roles is given together, the
<att>type</att> attribute of the <gi>castItem</gi> should indicate that
it contains more than one role, by taking a value such as <val>list</val>.  The encoder may or may not elect to
encode each separate constituent within such a composite
<gi>castItem</gi>.  Thus, either of the following is acceptable:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><castItem type="list">Constables, Drawer, Turnkey, etc.</castItem>
<castItem type="list">     
   <roleDesc>Constables,</roleDesc>
   <roleDesc>Drawer,</roleDesc>
   <roleDesc>Turnkey,</roleDesc>
  etc.
</castItem></egXML>
 </p>
<p>A group of cast items forming a distinct subdivision of a cast list
may be marked as such by using the special purpose <gi>castGroup</gi>
element.  The <att>rend</att> attribute may be used to indicate
whether this grouping is indicated in the text by layout alone (i.e. the
use of whitespace), by long braces or by some other means.  A
<gi>castGroup</gi> may contain  an optional heading (represented as
usual by a <gi>head</gi> element) followed by a series of
<gi>castItem</gi> elements:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRCAST-eg-21"><castGroup rend="braced">
   <head>friends of Mathias</head>
   <castItem>        
      <role>Walter</role>
      <actor>Mr Frank Hall</actor>
   </castItem>
   <castItem>       
      <role>Hans</role>
      <actor>Mr F.W. Irish</actor>
   </castItem>
</castGroup></egXML>
<!-- Leopold Lewis, The Bells (1871) -->
 </p>
<p>Alternatively, the encoder may prefer to regard the phrase
<q>friends of Mathias</q> as a role description, and encode the above
example as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><castGroup rend="braced">
   <roleDesc>friends of Mathias</roleDesc>
   <castItem>        
      <role>Walter</role>
      <actor>Mr Frank Hall</actor>
   </castItem>
   <castItem>       
      <role>Hans</role>
      <actor>Mr F.W. Irish</actor>
   </castItem>
</castGroup></egXML>
</p>
<p>This version has the advantage that all role descriptions are treated
alike, rather than in some cases being treated as headings. On the
other hand there are also  cases, such as the following, where the
role description does function more like a heading:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRCAST-eg-23"><castList>
   <castGroup>
      <head rend="braced">Mendicants</head>
      <castItem> <role>Aafaa</role>    <actor>Femi Johnson</actor> </castItem>
      <castItem> <role>Blindman</role> <actor>Femi Osofisan</actor> </castItem>
      <castItem> <role>Goyi</role>     <actor>Wale Ogunyemi</actor> </castItem>
      <castItem> <role>Cripple</role>  <actor>Tunji Oyelana</actor> </castItem>
   </castGroup>
   <castItem> <role>Si Bero</role>
              <roleDesc>Sister to Dr Bero</roleDesc>
              <actor>Deolo Adedoyin</actor> </castItem>
   <castGroup>
      <head rend="braced">Two old women</head>
      <castItem> <role>Iya Agba</role> <actor>Nguba Agolia</actor> </castItem>
      <castItem> <role>Iya Mate</role> <actor>Bopo George</actor> </castItem>
   </castGroup>
   <castItem> <role>Dr Bero</role>
              <roleDesc>Specialist</roleDesc>
              <actor>Nat Okoro</actor> </castItem>
   <castItem> <role>Priest</role>      <actor>Gbenga Sonuga</actor> </castItem>
   <castItem> <role>The old man</role>
              <roleDesc>Bero's father</roleDesc>
              <actor>Dapo Adelugba</actor> </castItem>
</castList></egXML>
<!-- Soyinka, Madmen and Specialists, Methuen 1971 -->
 </p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDRCAST" n="The castList element">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/castList.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/castGroup.xml"/> 
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/castItem.xml"/> 
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/role.xml"/> 
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/roleDesc.xml"/> 
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/actor.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DRBOD"><head>The Body of a Performance Text</head>
<p>The body of a performance text may be divided into structural
units, variously called acts, scenes, stasima, entr'actes, etc.  All
such formal divisions should be encoded using an appropriate
text-division element (<gi>div</gi>, <gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi>,
etc.), as further discussed in section <ptr target="#DRDIV"/>.
Whether divided up into such units or not, all performance texts
consist of sequences of speeches (see <ptr target="#DRSP"/>) and stage
directions (see <ptr target="#DRSTA"/>).  In musical performances, it
is also common to identify groups of speeches which act as a single
unit, sometimes called a <term>number</term>; such units typically
float within the structural hierarchy at the same level as speeches
preceding or following them and cannot therefore be treated as 
text-divisions. (see <ptr target="#DRSPG"/>). Speeches will generally
consist of a sequence of <term>chunk</term>-level items: paragraphs,
verse lines, stanzas, or (in case of uncertainty as to whether
something is verse or prose) <gi>ab</gi> elements (see <ptr
target="#DRPAL"/>).</p>
<p>The boundaries of formal units such as verse lines or paragraphs do
not always coincide with speech boundaries.  Units such as songs may be
discontinuous or shared among several speakers.  As described below in
section <ptr target="#DREMB"/>, such fragmentation may be encoded in a
relatively simple fashion using the linkage and aggregation mechanisms
defined in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRDIV"><head>Major Structural Divisions</head>
<p>Large divisions in drama such as acts, scenes, stasima, or entr'actes
are indicated by numbered or unnumbered <gi>div</gi> elements, as
described in section <ptr target="#DSDIV"/>.  The <att>type</att> and
<att>n</att> attributes may be used to define the type of division being
marked, and to provide a name or number for it, as in the following
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRDIV-eg-31"><body>
   <div1 type="scene" n="1">
      <head>Night—Faust's Study (i)</head>
   </div1> 
   <div1 type="scene" n="2">
      <head>Outside the City Gate</head>
   </div1>
</body></egXML>
<!-- Goethe, Faust Part 1. Penguin, 1949 --></p>
<p>Where the largest divisions of a performance text are themselves
subdivided, most obviously in the case of plays traditionally divided
into acts and scenes, further nested text-division elements may be used,
as in this example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRDIV-eg-32"><body>
  <div1 type="act" n="1">
	<head>Act One</head>
	<div2 type="scene" n="1">
	  <stage>Pa Ubu, Ma Ubu</stage>
	  <sp><speaker>Pa Ubu</speaker> <p>Pschitt!</p> </sp>
	</div2>
	<div2 type="scene" n="2">
	  <stage>A room in Pa Ubu's house, where a magnificent
		collation is set out</stage>
	</div2>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="act" n="2">
	<head>Act Two</head>
	<div2 type="scene" n="1">
	  <head>Scene One</head>
	</div2>
	<div2 type="scene" n="2">
	  <head>Scene Two</head>
	</div2>
  </div1>
</body></egXML>
<!-- Jarry, Ubu Plays (trans C. Connolly & S Watson-Taylor, Methuen 1968 --></p>
<p>In the example above, the <gi>div2</gi> element has been used to
represent the <soCalled>French scene</soCalled> convention, (where the
entrance of each new set of characters is marked as a distinct unit in
the text) and the <gi>div1</gi> element to represent the acts into which
the play is divided.  The elements chosen are determined only by the
hierarchic position of these units in the text as a whole.  If the text
had no acts, but only scenes, then the scenes might be represented by
<gi>div1</gi> elements.  Equally, if a play is divided only into
<q>acts</q>, with no smaller subdivisions, then the <gi>div1</gi>
element might be used to represent acts.  The <att>type</att> should be
used, as above, to make explicit the name associated
with a particular category of subdivision.</p>
<p>As an alternative to the use of numbered
divisions, the encoder may represent all subdivisions with the same
element, the unnumbered <gi>div</gi>.  The second
act in the above example would then be represented as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="act" n="2">
   <head>Act Two</head>
   <div type="scene" n="1">
      <head>Scene One</head>
   </div>
   <div type="scene" n="2">
      <head>Scene Two</head>
   </div>
</div></egXML></p>
<p>For further discussion of the use of numbered and unnumbered
divisions, see section <ptr target="#DSDIV"/>.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRSP"><head>Speeches and Speakers</head>
<p>The following elements are used to identify speeches and speakers in
a performance text:
<specList><specDesc key="sp"/><specDesc key="speaker"/></specList></p>
<p>As noted above, the structure of many performance texts may be
analysed as multiply hierarchic:  a scene of a verse play, for example,
may be divided into speeches and, at the same time, into verse lines.
The end of a line may or may not coincide with the end of a speech, and
vice versa.  Other structures, such as songs, may be discontinuous or
split up over several speeches.  For some purposes it will be
appropriate to regard the verse-structure as the fundamental organizing
principle of the text, and for others the speech structure; in some
cases, the choice between the two may be arbitrary.  The discussion in
the remainder of this chapter assumes that it is the speech-based
hierarchy which most prominently determines the structure of performance
texts, but the same mechanisms could be employed to encode a view of a
performance text in which individual speeches were entirely subordinate
to the formal units of prose and verse. For more detailed discussion and
examples of various treatments of this fundamental issue, refer to
chapter <ptr target="#NH"/>.</p>
<p>The <att>who</att> attribute and the <gi>speaker</gi> element are
both used to indicate the speaker or speakers of a speech, but in
rather different ways.  The <gi>speaker</gi> element is used to encode
the word or phrase actually used within the source text to indicate
the speaker: it may contain any string or prefix, and may be thought
of as a highly specialized form of stage direction.  The
<att>who</att> attribute however contains one or more pointer values,
each of which indicates one or more other XML elements documenting the
character to whom the speech is assigned.  Typically, this attribute
might point to a <gi>person</gi> element in the TEI header <ptr
target="#CCAHPA"/>, to a <gi>role</gi> element in the cast list <ptr
target="#DRCAST"/>, or even to some external source such as an online
handbook of dramatic roles. The most usual case is that the pointer
value supplied (prefixed by a sharp sign) corresponds with the value
of an <att>xml:id</att> attribute,
used elsewhere in the document to identify a particular element, as in the following examples:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRSP-eg-34" xml:lang="la"><castList>
   <castItem> <role xml:id="menae">Menaechmus</role> </castItem>
   <castItem> <role xml:id="penic">Peniculus</role> </castItem>
</castList>
<sp who="#menae"> <speaker>Menaechmus</speaker>
   <l>Responde, adulescens, quaeso, quid nomen tibist?</l> </sp>
<sp who="#penic"> <speaker>Peniculus</speaker>
   <l>Etiam derides, quasi nomen non noveris?</l> </sp>
<sp who="#menae"> <speaker>Menaechmus</speaker>
   <l>Non edepol ego te, quot sciam, umquam ante hunc diem</l>
   <l>Vidi neque novi; ...</l> </sp></egXML>
<!-- Plautus, Menaechmi, 498-9  --></p>
<p>If present, a <gi>speaker</gi> element may only appear as the first
part of an <gi>sp</gi> element. The distinction between the
<gi>speaker</gi> element and the <att>who</att> attribute makes it
possible to encode uniformly characters whose names are not indicated in
a uniform fashion throughout the play, or characters who appear in
disguise, as in the following examples:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRSP-eg-35"><castList>
   <castItem><role xml:id="hh">Henry Higgins</role></castItem>
</castList>
<sp who="#hh">
   <speaker>The Notetaker</speaker>
   <p> ... </p>
</sp></egXML>
<!-- GB Shaw, Pygmalion --></p>
<p>If the speaker attributions are completely regular (and may thus be
reconstructed mechanically from the values given for the <att>who</att>
attribute), or are of no interest for the encoder of the text (as might
be the case with editorially supplied attributions in older texts), then
the <gi>speaker</gi> element need not be used; the former example above
then might look like this:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRSP-eg-34" xml:lang="la"><castList>
   <castItem><role xml:id="menaechmus">Menaechmus</role></castItem>
   <castItem><role xml:id="peniculus">Peniculus</role></castItem>
   </castList>
<sp who="#menaechmus"><l>Responde, adulescens, quaeso, quid nomen tibist?</l></sp>
<sp who="#peniculus"><l>Etiam derides, quasi nomen non noveris?</l></sp>
<sp who="#menaechmus"><l>Non edepol ego te, quot sciam, umquam ante hunc diem</l>
              <l>Vidi neque novi; ...</l></sp></egXML>
<!-- Plautus, Menaechmi, 498-9  --></p>
<p>More than one identifier may be listed as value for the <att>who</att>
attribute if the speech is spoken by more than one person, as in the
following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRSP-eg-37"><castList>
   <castItem><role xml:id="nan">Nano</role></castItem>
   <castItem><role xml:id="cas">Castrone</role></castItem>
   </castList><stage>Nano and Castrone sing</stage>
<sp who="#nan #cas">
   <l>Fools, they are the only nation</l>
   <l>Worth men's envy or admiration</l>
</sp></egXML>
<!-- Jonson, Volpone, p.14 --></p>
<p>The <gi>sp</gi> and <gi>speaker</gi> elements are both declared
within the core module (see section <ptr target="#CODV"/>).
	</p></div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="DRSPG"><head>Grouped speeches</head>
<p>This module makes available the following additional element for
handling groups of speeches: <specList><specDesc
key="spGrp"/></specList></p>
<p>The <gi>spGrp</gi> element is intended for cases where
the characters in a performance launch into something which might be
regarded almost as a kind of separate structural division, typically
associated with its own heading or numbering system, but which
<soCalled>floats</soCalled> in the text, at the same hierarchic level
as speeches preceding or following it. Such units are often numbered,
titled, and visually presented as distinct objects within the
text. Here is a typical example from a well-known American musical comedy:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
       corresp="#GerStra"><spGrp type="number" n="3">
<head>By Strauss : performed by Georges Guetary, Gene Kelly, and Oscar
Levant</head>
<sp><speaker>HENRI BAUREL</speaker>
<lg><l>The waltzes of Mittel Europa </l>
<l>They charm you and warm you within </l>
<l>While each day discloses </l>
<l>What Broadway composes </l>
<l>Is emptiness pounding on tin.</l></lg>
</sp>
<sp xml:lang="de">
<speaker>JERRY MULLIGAN: ADAM COOK:</speaker>
<lg><l>Mein Herr! </l>
<l>Mein Herr!</l>
<l>Bitte, bitte!</l>
<l>Denke, danke!</l>
<l>Aufwiedersehen! Aufwiedersehen!</l></lg>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>HENRI BAUREL:</speaker>
<lg><l>How can I be civil </l>
<l>When hearing this drivel? </l>
<l>It's only for night-clubbing souses. </l>
<l>Oh give me the free 'n easy </l>
<l>Waltz that is Viennes-y </l>
<l>And go tell the band</l>
<l>If they want a hand</l>
<l>The waltz must be Strauss's</l></lg>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>ALL</speaker>
<lg><l>Ya ya ya </l>
<l>Give me oom pah pah...</l></lg>
</sp>
<!-- ... -->
</spGrp>
</egXML></p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRSTA"><head>Stage Directions</head>
<p>Both between and within the speeches of a written performance text,
it is normal practice to include a wide variety of descriptive
directions to indicate non-verbal action.  The following elements are
provided to represent these:
<specList>
<specDesc key="stage" atts="type"/>
<specDesc key="move" atts="type where perf"/>
</specList></p>
<p>A satisfactory typology of stage directions is difficult to define.
Certain basic types such as <q>entrance</q>, <q>exit</q>,
<q>setting</q>, <q>delivery</q>, are easily identified.  But the list is
not a closed one, and it is not uncommon to mix types within a single
direction.  No closed set of values for the <att>type</att> attribute is
therefore proposed at the present time, though some suggested values are
indicated in the list below, which also indicates the range of
possibilities.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><stage type="setting">The throne descends.</stage>
<stage type="setting">Music</stage>
<stage type="entrance">Enter Husband as being thrown off his horse.</stage>
<stage type="exit">Exit pursued by a bear.</stage>
<stage type="business">He quickly takes the stone out.</stage>
<stage type="delivery">To Lussurioso.</stage>
<stage type="delivery">Aside.</stage>
<stage type="delivery">Not knowing what to say.</stage>
<stage type="costume">Disguised as Ansaldo.</stage>
<stage type="location">At a window.</stage>
<stage type="novelistic">Having had enough, and embarrassed
     for the family.</stage></egXML></p>
<p>The meaning of the values used for the <att>type</att> attribute on
<gi>stage</gi> elements may be defined within the <gi>tagUsage</gi>
element of the TEI header (described in section <ptr target="#HD57"/>).
For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><tagUsage gi="stage">This element is used for all stage directions,
  editorial or authorial. The type attribute on this element takes
  one or more of the following values:
  <list type="gloss">
	<label>setting</label>
	<item>describes the set</item>
	<label>blocking</label>
	<item>describes movement across stage, position, etc.</item>
	<label>business</label>
	<item>describes movement other than blocking</item>
	<label>delivery</label>
	<item>describes how the line is said</item>
	<label>motivation</label>
	<item>describes character's emotional state or through line</item>
  </list>
</tagUsage></egXML></p>
<p>This approach is purely documentary; in a real project it would generally be more effective  to define the range of
permitted values explicitly within the project's schema specification,
using the techniques described in chapter <ptr target="#MD"/>. For
example, a specification like the following might be used to produce a
schema in which the <att>type</att> attribute of the
<gi>stage</gi> element is permitted to take only the values listed
above:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<schemaSpec ident="myDrama">
<moduleRef key="core"/>
<moduleRef key="tei"/>
<moduleRef key="structure"/>
<moduleRef key="header"/>
<moduleRef key="drama"/>
<elementSpec ident="stage" mode="change">
<attList>
<attDef ident="type" mode="replace">
<valList type="closed">
<valItem ident="setting"><desc>describes the set</desc></valItem>
<valItem ident="blocking"><desc>describes movement across stage, position, etc.</desc></valItem>
<valItem ident="business"><desc>describes movement other than blocking</desc></valItem>
<valItem ident="delivery"><desc>describes how the line is said</desc></valItem>
<valItem ident="motivation"><desc>describes character's emotional state or through line</desc>
</valItem>
</valList>
</attDef></attList></elementSpec></schemaSpec></egXML>
</p>
<p>The <gi>stage</gi> element may appear both between and within
<gi>sp</gi> elements.  It may contain a mixture of phrase level
elements, possibly combined into paragraphs, as in the following
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRSTA-eg-40"><div1 n="1" type="act">
<stage type="setting">
<p>Scene. — A room furnished comfortably and
tastefully but not extravagantly ...
The floor is carpeted and a fire burns in the stove.
It is winter.</p>
<p>A bell rings in the hall; shortly afterwards the
door is heard to open. Enter NORA humming a tune ...</p>
</stage>
<sp><speaker>Nora</speaker>
<p>Hide the Christmas Tree carefully, Helen. Be sure the
children do not see it till this evening, when it is
dressed. <stage type="delivery">To the PORTER taking
out her purse</stage> How much?</p>
</sp>
</div1></egXML>
<!-- Ibsen, A Dolls House tr Sharp, EML, 1910 --></p>
<p>The <gi>stage</gi> element may also be used in non-theatrical
texts, to mark sound effects or musical effects, etc., as further
discussed in section <ptr target="#DROTH"/>.</p>
<p>The <gi>move</gi> element is intended to help overcome the fact that
the stage directions of a printed text may often not provide full
information about either the intended or the actual movement of actors
on stage.  It may be used to keep track of entrances and exits in
detail, so as to know which characters are on stage at which time.  Its
attributes permit a relatively formal specification for movements of
characters, using user-defined codes to identify the characters involved
(the <att>who</att> attribute), the direction of the movement
(<att>type</att> attribute), and optionally which part of the stage is
involved (<att>where</att> attribute).  For stage-historical purposes, a
<att>perf</att> attribute is also provided; this allows the recording of
different <gi>move</gi> elements 
as taken in different performances of the same text.</p>
<p>The <gi>move</gi> element should be located at the position in the
text where the move is presumed to take place.  This will often coincide
with a stage direction, as in the following simple example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-04"><castList>
<castItem><role xml:id="bella">Bellafront</role></castItem></castList>
<stage type="entrance">  
  <move who="#bella" type="enter"/>
  Enter Bellafront mad.</stage></egXML></p>
<p>The <gi>move</gi> element can however appear independently of a stage
direction, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-05"><castList>
<castItem><role xml:id="lm">Lady Macbeth</role></castItem>
<castItem><role xml:id="g1">First Gentleman</role></castItem><!-- ... --></castList>
<sp who="#g1">
   <speaker>Gent.</speaker>
   <p>Neither to you, nor any one; having no witness
to confirm my speech. <move who="#lm" type="enter" where="C"/>
Lo you! here she comes. This is her very guise; and,
upon my life, fast asleep.</p>
</sp></egXML></p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDRSTA" >
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/spGrp.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/move.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRPAL"><head>Speech Contents</head>
<p>The actual speeches of a dramatic text may be composed of running
text, which must be formally organized into paragraphs, in the case of
prose (see section <ptr target="#COPA"/>), verse lines or line groups in
that of verse (see section <ptr target="#CODV"/>), or <gi>seg</gi>
elements, in case of doubt as to whether the material should be treated
as verse or prose.  The following elements, all of which are defined in
the core, are particularly useful when marking units of prose or verse within
speeches:
<specList><specDesc key="p"/><specDesc key="lb" /><specDesc key="l" atts="part"/><specDesc key="lg"/></specList></p>
<p>Like other milestone elements, the element <gi>lb</gi> additionally bears the attribute
<att>ed</att>, from its membership in the class
<ident>att.sourced</ident>:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.sourced" atts="ed"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>As a member of the classes <ident type="class">att.typed</ident>
and <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident>, the
<gi>lg</gi> element
also bears the following attributes:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.typed" atts="type subtype"/>
<specDesc key="att.divLike" atts="org sample part"/></specList></p>

<p>When the <ident type="module">verse</ident> module is included in a
schema,  the elements <gi>l</gi>
and <gi>lg</gi> also gain additional attributes through their
membership of the class <ident type="class">att.metrical</ident>:

<specList><specDesc key="att.metrical" atts="met rhyme"/></specList></p>


<p>In many texts, prose and verse may be inextricably mingled;
particularly in earlier printed texts, prose may be printed as verse or
verse as prose, or it may be impossible to distinguish the two.  In
cases of doubt, an encoder may prefer to tag the dubious material
consistently as verse, to tag it all as prose, to follow the typography
of the source text, or to use the neutral <gi>ab</gi>
element to contain the speech itself.  When this question arises, the
<gi>tagUsage</gi> element in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element of the
header may be used to record explicitly what policy has been adopted.</p>
<p>Even where they can reliably be distinguished, a single speech may frequently
contain a mixture of prose (marked as <gi>p</gi>) and verse (marked as
<gi>l</gi> or—if stanzaic—<gi>lg</gi>).</p>
 
<p>The <att>part</att> attribute of the <gi>l</gi> and <gi>lg</gi>
elements provides one simple way of indicating where the boundaries of a
speech and of a verse line or line group do not coincide.  The encoder
may simply indicate that a line or line group is metrically incomplete by
specifying the value <val>Y</val> or <val>N</val>, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DRPAL-eg-44"><sp><speaker>Face</speaker><l part="N">You most
notorious whelp, you insolent slave</l>
<l part="Y">Dare you do this?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker>Subtle</speaker><l part="Y">Yes faith, yes faith.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker>Face</speaker><l part="Y">Why! Who</l>
<l part="Y">Am I, my mongrel? Who am I?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker>Subtle</speaker><l part="Y">I'll tell you,</l>
<!-- ... -->
</sp></egXML></p>
<p>Alternatively, where the fragments of the line or line group are
consecutive in the text (though possibly interrupted by stage
directions), the values <val>I</val> (initial), <val>M</val> (medial), and <val>F</val> (final)
may be used to indicate how metrical lines are constituted:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><sp><speaker>Face</speaker><l>You most
notorious whelp, you insolent slave</l>
<l part="I">Dare you do this?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker>Subtle</speaker><l part="M">Yes faith, yes faith.</l></sp>
<sp><speaker>Face</speaker><l part="F">Why! Who</l>
<l part="I">Am I, my mongrel? Who am I?</l></sp>
<sp><speaker>Subtle</speaker><l part="F">I'll tell you,</l>
<!-- ... -->
</sp></egXML>
</p>
<p>In dramatic texts, the <gi>lg</gi> or line group element is most
often of use for the encoding of songs and other stanzaic material. Line groups may be fragmented
across speakers in the same way as individual lines, and the same set of
attributes may be used to record this fact. The  element
<gi>spGrp</gi> is provided in order to simplify the situation, very
common in performances, where performance of a single entity, such as
a song, is shared amongst several performers, as in the following
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
       corresp="#DRPAL-eg-46"><spGrp>
<head>Song — Sir Joseph</head>
<sp>
    <l>I am the monarch of the sea,</l>
    <l>The ruler of the Queen's Navee.</l>
    <l>Whose praise Great Britain loudly chants.</l>
</sp>
<sp>
  <speaker>Cousin Hebe</speaker>
    <l>And we are his sisters and his cousins and his aunts!</l>
</sp>
<sp>
  <speaker>Rel.</speaker>
    <l>And we are his sisters and his cousins and his aunts!</l>
</sp>
<!-- ... -->
</spGrp>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>This encoding however does not indicate that the three lines of
Sir Joseph's song and the two lines following it together constitute a
single verse stanza. This can be indicated by using the <att>part</att>
attribute, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
       corresp="#DRPAL-eg-46"><spGrp>
<head>Song — Sir Joseph</head>
<sp><lg part="I">
    <l>I am the monarch of the sea,</l>
    <l>The ruler of the Queen's Navee.</l>
    <l>Whose praise Great Britain loudly chants.</l>
</lg></sp>
<sp>
  <speaker>Cousin Hebe</speaker>
<lg part="M"> <l>And we are his sisters and his cousins and his aunts!</l></lg>
</sp>
<sp>
  <speaker>Rel.</speaker>
<lg part="F">    <l>And we are his sisters and his cousins and his aunts!</l></lg>
</sp>
<!-- ... -->
</spGrp>
</egXML>
</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DREMB"><head>Embedded Structures</head>
<p>Although primarily composed of speeches, performance texts often
contain other structural units such as songs or strophes which are
shared among different speakers.  More generally, complex nested
structures of plays within plays, interpolated masques, or interludes
are far from uncommon.  In more modern material, comparably complex
structural devices such as flashback or nested playback are equally
frequent.  In all kinds of performance material, it may be necessary to
indicate several actions which are happening simultaneously.</p>
<p>A number of different devices are available within the TEI scheme to
support these complexities in the general case.  Texts may be composite
or self-nesting (see section <ptr target="#DSGRP"/>) and multiple
hierarchies may be defined (see chapter <ptr target="#NH"/>).  The TEI
encoding scheme provides a variety of linking mechanisms, which may be
used to indicate temporal alignment and aggregation of fragmented
structures.  In this section we provide a few specific examples of the
application of these techniques to performance texts:
<list type="simple">
<item>the use of the  <gi>floatingText</gi> element</item>
<item>the use of the <att>part</att> attribute on fragmentary
<gi>lg</gi> elements</item>
<item>the use of the <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes on
fragments of embedded structures to join them into a larger whole</item>
<item>the use of the <gi>join</gi> element to define a
<soCalled>virtual element</soCalled> composed of the fragments
indicated</item></list>
</p>
<p>When the whole of a song appears within a single speech, it may
require no special treatment if it is considered to form a part
of the speech: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-07"><sp><speaker>Kelly</speaker>
   <stage>(calmly).</stage>
   <p>Aha, so you've bad minds along with th' love of gain.
      You thry to pin on others th' dirty decorations that
      may be hangin' on your own coats.</p>
   <stage>(He points, one after the other at Conroy, Bull,
          and Flagonson. Lilting)</stage>
    <lg type="song">
         <l>Who were you with last night?</l>
         <l>Who were you with last night?</l>
         <l>Will you tell your missus when you go home</l>
         <l>Who you were with last night?</l>
    </lg></sp>
<sp><speaker>Flagonson</speaker>
   <stage>(in anguished indignation).</stage>
   <p>This is more than a hurt to us: this hits at the
      decency of the whole nation!</p>
</sp></egXML>
If however, the song is to be regarded as forming a distinct item,
perhaps with its own front and back matter, it may be better to regard
it as a floating text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-07"><sp><speaker>Kelly</speaker>
   <stage>(calmly).</stage>
   <p>Aha, so you've bad minds along with ...</p></sp>
   <stage>(He points, one after the other at Conroy, Bull,
          and Flagonson.  Lilting):</stage>
      <floatingText>
	<front>
	  <titlePart>Kelly's Song</titlePart>
	</front>
	<body>
          <l>Who were you with last night?</l>
          <l>Who were you with last night?</l>
          <l>Will you tell your missus when you go home</l>
          <l>Who you were with last night?</l>
        </body>
      </floatingText>
</egXML></p>
<p>When an embedded structure extends across more than one <gi>sp</gi>
element, each of its constituent parts must be regarded as a distinct
fragment; the problem then facing the encoder is to reconstitute the
interrupted whole in some way.</p>
<p>As already noted above, the <gi>spGrp</gi> element may be used to
group together consecutive speeches which are grouped together in some
way, for example constituting a single song. Alternatively the
<att>part</att> attribute, typically used to
indicate that an <gi>l</gi> element contains a partial, not a complete,
verse line, may also be used on the <gi>lg</gi> element,
to indicate that the line group is partial rather than complete, thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-07"><sp><speaker>Kelly</speaker>
   <stage>(wheeling quietly in his semi-dance,
          as he goes out):</stage>
   <lg type="stanza" part="I">
      <l>Goodbye to holy souls left here,</l>
      <l>Goodbye to man an' fairy;</l>
   </lg>
</sp>
<sp><speaker>Widda Machree</speaker>
   <stage>(wheeling quietly in her semi-dance,
          as she goes out):</stage>
   <lg type="stanza" part="F">
      <l>Goodbye to all of Leicester Square,</l>
      <l>An' the long way to Tipperary.</l>
   </lg>
</sp></egXML></p>
<p>When the fragments of a song are separated by other intervening
dialogue, or even when not, they may be linked together with the
<att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes defined in section
<ptr target="#SAAG"/>.
For example, the line groups making up Ophelia's song
might be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#CODR-eg-293"><div1 n="4" type="act">
  <div2 n="5" type="scene">
    <stage>Elsinore. A room in the Castle.</stage>
    <stage type="setting">Enter Ophelia, distracted.</stage>
    <sp> <speaker>Ophelia</speaker>
      <p>Where is the beauteous Majesty of Denmark?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp> <speaker>Queen</speaker>
      <p>How now, Ophelia?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp> <speaker>Ophelia</speaker>
      <stage>Singing</stage>
      <lg next="#Tl2" xml:id="Tl1" type="song" part="Y">
        <l>How should I your true-love know</l>
        <l>From another one?</l>
        <l>By his cockle hat and staff</l>
        <l>And his sandal shoon.</l>
      </lg>
    </sp>
    <sp> <speaker>Queen</speaker>
      <p>Alas, sweet lady, what imports this song?</p>
    </sp>
    <sp> <speaker>Ophelia</speaker>
      <p>Say you? Nay, pray you mark.</p>
      <stage>Sings</stage>
      <lg prev="#Tl1" xml:id="Tl2" type="song" part="Y">
        <l>He is dead and gone, lady,</l>
        <l>He is dead and gone;</l>
        <l>At his head a grass-green turf,</l>
        <l>At his heels a stone.</l>
      </lg>
      <p>O, ho!</p>
    </sp>
  </div2>
</div1></egXML></p>
<p>The <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes are discussed in
section <ptr target="#SAAG"/>: they form part of the module
for alignment and linking; this module must therefore be included in a
schema if they are to be used, as further discussed in section <ptr target="#STIN"/>.</p>
<p>The fragments of Ophelia's song might also be linked together using
the <gi>join</gi> mechanism described in section <ptr target="#SAAG"/>.
The <gi>join</gi> element is specifically intended to encode the fact
that several discontiguous elements of the text together form one
<soCalled>virtual</soCalled> element.  Using this mechanism, the example
might be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><text>
  <body>
    <div1 n="4" type="act">
      <div2 n="5" type="scene">
        <stage type="setting">Elsinore. A room in the Castle.</stage>
        <sp> <speaker>Queen</speaker>
          <p>How now, Ophelia?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp> <speaker>Ophelia</speaker>
          <stage type="delivery">Singing</stage>
          <lg xml:id="TL1" type="song" part="Y">
            <l>How should I your true-love know</l>
            <l>From another one?</l>
            <l>By his cockle hat and staff</l>
            <l>And his sandal shoon.</l>
          </lg>
        </sp>
        <sp> <speaker>Queen</speaker>
          <p>Alas, sweet lady, what imports this song?</p>
        </sp>
        <sp> <speaker>Ophelia</speaker>
          <p>Say you? Nay, pray you mark.</p>
          <stage type="delivery">Sings</stage>
          <lg xml:id="TL2" type="song" part="Y">
            <l>He is dead and gone, lady,</l>
            <l>He is dead and gone;</l>
            <l>At his head a grass-green turf,</l>
            <l>At his heels a stone.</l>
          </lg>
          <p>O, ho!</p>
          <join type="lg" target="#TL1 #TL2"/>
        </sp>
      </div2>
    </div1>
  </body>
</text></egXML>
The location of the <gi>join</gi> element is not significant; here it
has been placed shortly after the conclusion of the song, in order to
have it close to the fragments it unifies.</p>
<p>Like the <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att> attributes, the
<gi>join</gi> element requires the additional module for linking, which
is selected as shown above.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRSIM"><head>Simultaneous Action</head>
<p>In printed or written versions of performance texts, a variety of
techniques may be used to indicate the temporal alignment of speeches or
actions.  Speeches may be printed vertically aligned on the page, or
braced together; stage directions (e.g. <q>Speaking at the same
time</q>) are also often used.  In operatic or musical works in
particular, the need to indicate timing and alignment of individual
parts of a song may lead to very complex layout.</p>
<p>One simple method of indicating the temporal alignment of speeches or
actions is to use the <att>corresp</att> attribute discussed in
section <ptr target="#SACS"/>, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DR-eg-08"><sp> <speaker>Mangan</speaker>
  <stage type="delivery">wildly</stage>
  <p>Look here: I'm going to take off all my clothes.</p>
  <stage type="action">he begins tearing off his coat.</stage>
</sp>
<sp xml:id="dr-s1"> <speaker>Lady Utterword</speaker>
  <p>Mr Mangan!</p>
</sp>
<sp xml:id="dr-s2"> <speaker>Captain Shotover</speaker>
  <p>Whats that?</p>
</sp>
<sp xml:id="dr-s3"> <speaker>Hector</speaker>
  <p>Ha! ha! Do. Do.</p>
</sp>
<sp xml:id="dr-s4"> <speaker>Ellie</speaker>
  <p>Please dont.</p>
</sp>
<stage corresp="#dr-s1 #dr-s2 #dr-s3 #dr-s4" xml:id="dr-d1" rend="braced" type="delivery">in consternation</stage>
<sp> <speaker>Mrs. Hushabye</speaker>
  <stage type="action">catching his arm and stopping him</stage>
  <p>Alfred: for shame! Are you mad?</p>
</sp></egXML></p>
  <!-- martindholmes says: I believe there is a typo above: "dont"
       should be "don't". However, I don't have access to a 1916
       edition to confirm this. No edition I can find has "dont". -->

<!-- I think the correct date should be 1919. The lack of apostrophes
is one of Shaw's quirks, represented faithfully in the standard
Constable edition of 1931, and in reprints of that such as the Penguin
Classics 2000 edition available at Google Books (LB) -->

<p>In the original, the stage direction <q>in consternation</q> is
printed opposite a brace grouping all four speeches, indicating that all
four characters speak at once, and that the stage direction applies to
all of them. Rather than attempting to represent the appearance of the
source, this example encoding represents its presumed meaning: the
<gi>stage</gi> element is placed arbitrarily after the last relevant
speech,  and the four speeches with which it is to be
associated are pointed to by means of the
<att>corresp</att> attribute. This attribute, which is enabled by the
linking module, provides a simple way of indicating the temporal
alignment of speeches or actions in a play. Producing a readable
version of the text which simulates the original printed effect may
however require more complex markup and processing.
</p>
<p>More powerful and more precise mechanisms for temporal alignment are
defined in chapter <ptr target="#TS"/>.  These would be appropriate for
encodings the focus of which is on the actual performance of a text
rather than its structure or formal properties.  The module described
in that chapter includes a large number of other detailed proposals for
the encoding of such features as voice quality, prosody, etc., which
might be relevant to such a treatment of performance texts.
</p></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DROTH"><head>Other Types of Performance Text</head>
<p>Most of the elements and structures identified thus far are derived
from traditional theatrical texts.  Although other performance texts,
such as screenplays or radio scripts, have not been discussed
specifically, they can be encoded using the elements and structures
listed above.  Encoders may however find it convenient to use, as well,
the additional specialized elements discussed in this section.  For
scripts containing very detailed technical information, the
<gi>tech</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#DRTEC"/> may also
be useful.
 </p>
<p>Like other texts, screenplays and television or radio scripts may
be divided into text divisions marked with <gi>div</gi> or
<gi>div1</gi>, etc.  Within units corresponding with the traditional
<q>act</q> and <q>scene</q>, further subdivisions or sequences may be
identified, composed of individual <q>shots</q>, each associated with
a single camera angle and setting.  Shots and sequences should be
encoded using an appropriate text-division element (i.e., a
<gi>div3</gi> element if numbered division elements are in use and the
next largest unit is a <gi>div2</gi>, or a <gi>div</gi> element if
un-numbered divisions are in use) specifying <val>sequence</val> or
<val>shot</val> as the value of the <att>type</att> attribute, as
appropriate.
 </p>
<p>It is normal practice in screenplays and radio scripts to distinguish
directions concerning camera angles, sound effects, etc., from other
forms of stage direction.  Such texts also generally include far more
detailed specifications of what the audience actually sees:
descriptions of actions and background, etc.  Scripts derived from
cinema and television productions may also include texts displayed as
captions superimposed on the action.  All of these may be encoded using
the general purpose <gi>stage</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#DRSTA"/>, and distinguished by means of its <att>type</att>
attribute.  Alternatively, or in addition, the following more specific
elements may be used, where clear distinctions can be made:
<specList><specDesc key="view"/><specDesc key="camera"/><specDesc key="caption"/><specDesc key="sound" atts="type discrete"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>Some examples of the use of these elements follow:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><camera>Angle on Olivia.</camera>
<view>Ryan's wife, standing nervously alone on the sidelines,
biting her lip. She's scared and she shows it.</view></egXML>
 </p>
<p>Where particular words or phrases within a direction are emphasized
(by change of typeface or use of capital letters), an appropriate
phrase-level element may be used to indicate the fact, as in the
following examples, where certain words in the original are given in
small capitals:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><view>George glances at the window--and freezes.
<camera>New angle--shock cut</camera> Out the window
the body of a dead man suddenly slams into
<hi>frame</hi>. He dangles grotesquely,
held up by his coat caught on a protruding bolt.
George gasps. The train <hi>whistle</hi> screams.</view></egXML>
<!-- source? -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><view>Ext. TV control van—Early morning.
The <name>T.V. announcer</name> from the Ryan interview
stands near the Control Van, the lake in b.g.</view>
<sp> <speaker>T.V. Announcer</speaker>
<p>Several years ago, Jack Ryan was a highly
successful hydroplane racer ...</p>
</sp></egXML>
<!-- source? -->
 </p>
<p>All of these elements, like other stage directions, can appear both
within and between speeches.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><sp>
   <speaker>TV Announcer VO</speaker>
   <p>Working with Ryan are his two coworkers—
Strut Bowman, the mechanical engineer—
<view><camera>Angle on Strut</camera>
standing in the tow boat, walkie-talkie in hand,
watching Ryan carefully.</view>
—and Roger Dalton, a rocket
systems analyst, and one of the scientists
from the Jet Propulsion Lab ...</p>
</sp></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DROTH-eg-57"><sp> <speaker>Benjy</speaker>
   <p>Now to business.</p>
</sp>
<sp> <speaker>Ford and Zaphod</speaker>
   <p>To business.</p> </sp>
<sound>Glasses clink.</sound>
<sp> <speaker>Benjy</speaker>
   <p>I beg your pardon?</p> </sp>
<sp> <speaker>Ford</speaker>
   <p>I'm sorry, I thought you were proposing a toast.</p> </sp></egXML>
<!-- Hitch-hikers Guide, p.83 -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DROTH-eg-58"><camera>Zoom in to overlay showing some stock film
  of hansom cabs galloping past.</camera>
<caption>London, 1895.</caption>
<caption>The residence of Mr Oscar Wilde.</caption>
<sound>Suitably classy music starts.</sound>
<view>Mix through to Wilde's drawing room. A crowd of suitably
  dressed folk are engaged in typically brilliant conversation,
  laughing affectedly and drinking champagne.</view>
<sp>
   <speaker>Prince of Wales</speaker>
   <p>My congratulations, Wilde. Your latest play is a great success.</p>
</sp></egXML>
<!-- Monty Pythons Flying Circus, vol 2, p 230 -->
</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DRTEC"><head>Technical Information</head>
<p>Traditional stage scripts may contain additional technical
information about such production-related factors as lighting,
<soCalled>blocking</soCalled> (that is, detailed notes on actors'
movements), or props required at particular points. More technical
information about intended production effects may also appear in
published versions of screenplays or movie scripts. Where these are
presented simply as marginal notes, they may be encoded using the
general-purpose <gi>note</gi> element defined in section <ptr target="#CONO"/>.
Alternatively, they may be formally distinguished from
other stage directions by using the specialized <gi>tech</gi> element:
<specList><specDesc key="tech" atts="type perf"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>Like stage directions, <gi>tech</gi> elements can appear anywhere
within a speech or between speeches.
 </p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDROTH" n="Screenplays and other technical matters">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/view.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/camera.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/sound.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/caption.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/tech.xml"/>
</specGrp>

</div></div>
<div><head>Module for Performance Texts</head>
<p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following
components:

<moduleSpec xml:id="DDR" ident="drama"><altIdent type="FPI">Performance
Texts</altIdent><desc>Performance texts</desc>
<desc xml:lang="fr">Théâtre</desc>
<desc xml:lang="zh-TW">劇本</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Testi per performance</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Textos de actuação</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">舞台芸術モジュール</desc></moduleSpec>

The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>


</div></div>
