<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<div1 xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="chapter" xml:id="DS" n="7"><head>Default Text Structure</head>
<p>This chapter describes the default high-level structure for TEI
documents.  <!-- The majority of the different base modules described
in part II simply embed the framework defined in this chapter while a
few redefine it with some minor modifications.  This chapter is
therefore relevant to every kind of TEI document.  For further details
on the overall structure of the TEI document type definitions, in
particular the use of base and additional modules, see chapter <ptr
target="#ST"/>.--> A full TEI document combines metadata describing
it, represented by a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element, with the document
itself, represented by a <gi>text</gi> element. This basic pair is
represented by a <gi>TEI</gi> element. The <gi>teiHeader</gi> element
is specified by the <ident>header</ident> module, which is fully
described in chapter <ptr target="#HD"/>. The remainder of the present
chapter describes the <gi>text</gi> element and its high-level
constituents. </p>

<p>A variant on this basic form, the <gi>teiCorpus</gi>, is also
defined for the representation of language corpora, or other
collections of encoded texts. A <gi>teiCorpus</gi> consists of one or
more complete <gi>TEI</gi> elements, each combining a
<gi>teiHeader</gi> and a <gi>text</gi>, which itself carries a
<gi>teiHeader</gi>. This permits the encoder to distinguish metadata
applicable to the whole collection of encoded texts, which is
represented by the outermost <gi>teiHeader</gi>, from that applicable
to each of the individual <gi>TEI</gi> elements within the
corpus. Further information about the organization and encoding of
language corpora is given in chapter <ptr target="#CC"/>. </p>

<p>In summary, the following elements are available for the
representation of the outermost structure of a TEI document:
<specList>
<specDesc key="TEI"/>
<specDesc key="teiCorpus"/>
<specDesc key="teiHeader"/>
</specList>
As noted above, the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element is formally declared in
the <ident type="module">header</ident> module (see chapter <ptr
target="#HD"/>). The <gi>TEI</gi> and <gi>teiCorpus</gi>
elements are formally declared as follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DCOTOPELEMENTS" n="TEI2">
&TEI;
&teiCorpus;
</specGrp>
</p>


<p>TEI texts may be regarded either as <term>unitary</term>, that is,
forming an organic whole, or as <term>composite,</term> that is,
consisting of several components which are in some important sense
independent of each other.  The distinction is not always entirely
obvious:  for example a collection of essays might be regarded as a
single item in some circumstances, or as a number of distinct items in
others.  In such borderline cases, the encoder must choose whether to
treat the text as unitary or composite; each may have advantages and
disadvantages in a given situation.
 </p>

<p>Whether unitary or composite, the text is marked with the
<gi>text</gi> tag and may contain front matter, a text body, and back
matter.  In unitary texts, the text body is tagged <gi>body</gi>; in
composite texts, where the text body consists of a series of subordinate
texts or groups, it is tagged <gi>group</gi>.  The overall structure of
any text, unitary or composite, is thus defined by the following
elements:
<specList><specDesc key="text"/><specDesc key="front"/><specDesc key="body"/><specDesc key="group"/><specDesc key="back"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>The overall structure of a unitary text is:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><TEI>
  <teiHeader>  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
    </front>
    <body>
    </body>
    <back>
    </back>
  </text>
 </TEI></egXML></p>
<p>The overall structure of a composite text made up of two unitary
texts is:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><TEI>
  <teiHeader>  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
    </front>
    <group>
      <text>
        <front>
        </front>
        <body>
        </body>
        <back>
        </back>
      </text>
      <text>
        <body>
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>
    <back>
    </back>
  </text>
 </TEI></egXML>
 </p>
<p>Each of these elements is further described in the following
subsections.  <gi>text</gi>, <gi>body</gi>, and <gi>group</gi> are
formally declared as follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DDSTEXT" n="Top-level parts of default structure">
&text;
&body;
&group;
</specGrp>
Elements <gi>front</gi> and <gi>back</gi> are declared separately,
and are further discussed in sections <ptr target="#DSFRONT"/> and
<ptr target="#DSBACK"/>. Textual elements, such as paragraphs, lists
or phrases, which nest within these major structural elements, are
discussed in chapter <ptr target="#CO"/> (for elements common to all
kinds of document) and in part II (for elements specific to a
particular base). The <gi>group</gi> element, used for composite
texts, is further discussed in section <ptr target="#DSGRP"/>.
</p>
<div2 type="section" xml:id="DSDIV"><head>Divisions of the Body</head>

<p>In some texts, the body consists simply of a sequence of low-level
structural items, referred to here as <term>components</term> or
<term>component-level elements</term> (see section <ptr
target="#STEC"/>).  Examples in prose texts include paragraphs or
lists; in dramatic texts, speeches and stage directions; in
dictionaries, dictionary entries.  In other cases sequences of such
elements will be grouped together hierarchically into textual
divisions and subdivisions, such as chapters or sections.  The names
used for these structural subdivisions of texts vary with the genre
and period of the text, or even with the whim of the author, editor,
or publisher. For example, a major subdivision of an epic or of the
Bible is generally called a <soCalled>book</soCalled>, that of a
report is usually called a <soCalled>part</soCalled> or
<soCalled>section</soCalled>, that of a novel a
<soCalled>chapter</soCalled> &#x2014; unless it is an epistolary
novel, in which case it may be called a <soCalled>letter</soCalled>.
Even texts which are not organized as linear prose narratives, or not
as narratives at all, will frequently be subdivided in a similar way:
a drama into <soCalled>acts</soCalled> and
<soCalled>scenes</soCalled>; a reference book into
<soCalled>sections</soCalled>; a diary or day book into
<soCalled>entries</soCalled>; a newspaper into
<soCalled>issues</soCalled> and <soCalled>sections</soCalled>, and so
forth.
 </p>

<p>Because of this variety, these Guidelines propose that all such
textual divisions be regarded as occurrences of the same neutrally named
elements, with an attribute <att>type</att> used to categorize elements
independently of their hierarchic level.  Two alternative styles are
provided for the marking of these neutral divisions:
<term>numbered</term> and <term>un-numbered</term>.  Numbered divisions
are named <gi>div0</gi>, <gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi>, etc., where the
number indicates the depth of this particular division within the
hierarchy, the largest such division being <q>div0</q>, any subdivision
within it being <q>div1</q>, any further sub-sub-division being
<q>div2</q> and so on.  Un-numbered divisions are simply named
<gi>div</gi>, and allowed to nest recursively to indicate their
hierarchic depth.  The two styles may <emph>not</emph> be combined
within a single <gi>front</gi>, <gi>body</gi> or <gi>back</gi> element.
 </p>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSDIV1"><head>Un-numbered Divisions</head>
<p>The following element is used to identify textual subdivisions
in the un-numbered style:
<specList><specDesc key="div"/></specList>
As a member of the class <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident>, this element has the
following additional attribute:
<specList><specDesc key="att.divLike" atts="type"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>Using this style, the body of a text containing two parts, each
composed of two chapters, might be represented as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><body>
  <div type="part" n="1">
    <div type="chapter" n="1">
    </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="2">
    </div>
  </div>
  <div type="part" n="2">
    <div n="1" type="chapter">
    </div>
    <div n="2" type="chapter">
    </div>
  </div>
</body></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>div</gi> element has the following formal definition:
<specGrp xml:id="DDSDIV" n="Un-numbered divisions">
&div;
</specGrp>
</p></div3>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSDIV2"><head>Numbered Divisions</head>
<p>The following elements are used to identify textual subdivisions
in the numbered style:
<specList>
<specDesc key="div0"/>
<specDesc key="div1"/>
<specDesc key="div2"/>
<specDesc key="div3"/>
<specDesc key="div4"/>
<specDesc key="div5"/>
<specDesc key="div6"/>
<specDesc key="div7"/>
</specList>
As members of the class <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident> these elements all bear the
following additional attribute:
<specList><specDesc key="att.divLike" atts="type"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>The largest possible subdivision of the body may be regarded either
as a <gi>div0</gi> or as a <gi>div1</gi> element,<note place="foot">This
convention (corresponding with the idea that a type-set document
may begin either with a <q>level 0</q> or a <q>level 1</q> heading) is
provided for convenience and compatibility with some widely used
formatting systems.</note> and the smallest possible <gi>div7</gi>.
If numbered divisions are in use, a division at any one level (say,
<gi>div3</gi>), may contain only numbered divisions at the next lowest
level (in this case, <gi>div4</gi>).</p>
<p>Using this style, the body of a text containing two parts, each
composed of two chapters, might be represented as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><body>
  <div0 type="Part" n="1">     
    <div1 type="Chapter" n="1">
    </div1>     
    <div1 type="Chapter" n="2">
    </div1>     
  </div0>
  <div0 type="Part" n="2">
    <div1 type="Chapter" n="1">
    </div1>     
    <div1 type="Chapter" n="2">
    </div1> 
  </div0>
</body></egXML>
<!-- Changed example:  the point of the div1/div0             -->
	<!-- alternation in the body is to allow the scheme to        -->
	<!-- handle Chapters at a consistent level with or without    -->
	<!-- surrounding Parts, so the natural way to tag Part and    -->
	<!-- Chapter here is div0 div1, not div1 div2, or at least    -->
	<!-- so it seems to me.  -msm                                 -->
	<!-- tough if you then want sections too (LB) -->
	<!-- Also changed to agree with previous example in N values  -->
	<!-- and comments. -msm                                       -->
 </p>
<p>Formal definitions for these elements are as follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DDSDIVN" n="Numbered divisions">
&div0;
&div1;
&div2;
&div3;
&div4;
&div5;
&div6;
&div7;
</specGrp>
 </p></div3>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSDIV3"><head>Numbered or Un-numbered?</head>
<p>Within the same <gi>front</gi>, <gi>body</gi>, or <gi>back</gi>
element, all hierarchic subdivisions must be marked either using
nested <gi>div</gi> elements, or using the <gi>div0</gi>,
<gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi> tag appropriate at each level; the two
styles may <emph>not</emph> be mixed.
</p>
<p>The choice between numbered and un-numbered divisions will depend to
some extent on the complexity of the material:  un-numbered divisions
allow for an arbitrary depth of nesting, while numbered divisions limit
the depth of the tree which can be constructed.  Where divisions at
different levels should be processed differently (chapters, but not
sections, for example, beginning on new pages), numbered divisions
slightly simplify the task of defining the desired processing for each level.
Some software may find numbered divisions easier to process, as there is
no need to maintain knowledge of the whole document structure in order
to know the level at which a division occurs; such software may however
find it difficult to cope with some other aspects of the TEI scheme.
On the other hand, in a collection of many works it may
prove difficult or impossible to ensure that the same numbered division
always corresponds with the same type of textual feature: a
<soCalled>chapter</soCalled> may be at level 1 in one work and level 3 in another.
 </p>
<p>Whichever style is used, the global <att>n</att> and <att>xml:id</att>
attributes (section <ptr target="#STGA"/>) may be used to provide
reference strings or labels for each division of a text, where
appropriate. Such labels should be provided for each section
which is regarded as significant for referencing purposes (on
reference systems, see further section <ptr target="#CORS"/>).  
</p>
<p>As indicated above, the <att>type</att> attribute is used to
provide a name or description for the division.  Typical values might
be <soCalled>book</soCalled>, <soCalled>chapter</soCalled>, <soCalled>section</soCalled>, <soCalled>part</soCalled>, or (for
verse texts) <soCalled>book</soCalled>, <soCalled>canto</soCalled>, <soCalled>stanza</soCalled>, or (for
dramatic texts) <soCalled>act</soCalled>, <soCalled>scene</soCalled>.  </p>
<p>In previous versions of these Guidelines this attribute had a
declared value of <val>#CURRENT</val>, which in
SGML implies
that if defaulted, the value used will be that most recently specified
on any element of the same kind, scanning the text left to right.
Hence, if un-numbered divisions are used, the appropriate value must
be specified each time a change of level occurs, both <soCalled>down</soCalled> and
<soCalled>up</soCalled> the document hierarchy. This value is not available in XML, and so
the present edition of these Guidelines does not use it.
 </p>
<p>The following extended example uses numbered divisions to indicate
the structure of a novel, and illustrates the use of the attributes
discussed above.  It also uses some elements discussed in section <ptr target="#DSDTB"/>
and the <gi>p</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#COPA"/>.
<!-- a long example but an irresistible one... -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div0 type="book" n="I" xml:id="JA0100">
  <head>Book I.</head>
  <div1 type="chapter" n="1" xml:id="JA0101">
    <head>Of writing lives in general, and particularly of Pamela, with a word
      by the bye of Colley Cibber and others.</head>
    <p>It is a trite but true observation, that examples work more forcibly on
      the mind than precepts:  ... </p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="chapter" n="2" xml:id="JA0102">
    <head>Of Mr. Joseph Andrews, his birth, parentage, education, and great
      endowments; with a word or two concerning ancestors.</head>  
    <p>Mr. Joseph Andrews, the hero of our ensuing history, was esteemed to
      be the only son of Gaffar and Gammar Andrews, and brother to the
      illustrious Pamela, whose virtue is at present so famous ... </p>
  </div1>
  <trailer>The end of the first Book</trailer>
</div0> 
<div0 type="book" n="II" xml:id="JA0200">
  <head>Book II</head>    
  <div1 type="chapter" n="1" xml:id="JA0201">
    <head>Of divisions in authors</head>
    <p>There are certain mysteries or secrets in all trades, from the highest
      to the lowest, from that of <term>prime-ministering</term>, to this of
      <term>authoring</term>, which are seldom discovered unless to members of
      the same calling ... </p>
    <p>I will dismiss this chapter with the following observation: that it
      becomes an author generally to divide a book, as it does a butcher to
      joint his meat, for such assistance is of great help to both the reader
      and the carver. And now having indulged myself a little I will endeavour
      to indulge the curiosity of my reader, who is no doubt impatient to know
      what he will find in the subsequent chapters of this book.</p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="chapter" n="2" xml:id="JA0202">
    <head>A surprising instance of Mr. Adams's short memory, with the
      unfortunate consequences which it brought on Joseph.
    </head>
    <p>Mr. Adams and Joseph were now ready to depart different ways ... </p>
  </div1>
</div0></egXML>
<!--   Fielding, Joseph Andrews (ed Battestin, 1961) -->
	<!-- Again, example changed to use div0, div1 not 1, 2. -msm  -->
 </p></div3>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSDIV3X"><head>Partial and Composite Divisions</head>
<p>In most situations, the textual subdivisions marked by <gi>div</gi>
elements will be both complete and identically organized with
reference to the original source.  For some purposes however, in
particular where dealing with unusually large or unusually small
texts, encoders may find it convenient to present as textual divisions
sequences of text which are incomplete with reference to the original
text, or which are in fact an ad hoc agglomeration of tiny texts.
Moreover, in some kinds of texts it is difficult or impossible to
determine the order in which individual subdivisions should be
combined to form the next higher level of subdivision, as noted
below.
 </p>
<p>To overcome these problems, the following additional attributes are
defined for all elements in the <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident> class:
<specList><specDesc key="att.divLike" atts="org sample part"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>For example, an encoder might choose to transcribe only the first two
thousand words of each chapter from a novel.  In such a case, each
chapter might conveniently be regarded as a partial division, and tagged
with a <gi>div</gi> element in the following form:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div n="xx" sample="initial" part="Y" type="chapter">
  <p> ... </p>
</div></egXML>
where <q>xx</q> represents a number for the chapter.  The
<gi>sampling</gi> element in the TEI Header should also be used to
record the principles underlying the selection of incomplete samples, as
further described in section <ptr target="#HD52"/>.
 </p>
<p>The following example demonstrates how a newspaper column composed of
very short unrelated snippets may be encoded using these attributes:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div1 type="storylist" org="composite">
<head>News in brief</head>
<div2 type="story">
<head>Police deny <soCalled>losing</soCalled> bomb</head>
<p>Scotland Yard yesterday denied claims in the Sunday
Express that anti-terrorist officers trailing an IRA van
loaded with explosives in north London had lost track of
it 10 days ago.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="story">
<head>Hotel blaze</head>
<p>Nearly 200 guests were evacuated before dawn
yesterday after fire broke out at the Scandic
Crown hotel in the Royal Mile, Edinburgh.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="story">
<head>Test match split</head>
<p>Test Match Special next summer will be split
between Radio 5 and Radio 3, after protests this
year that it disrupted Radio 3's music schedule.</p>
</div2>
</div1></egXML> 
<!-- Guardian 21 Dec 1992, p 2 -->
</p>
<p>The <att>org</att> attribute on the <gi>div1</gi> element is used
here to indicate that individual stories in this group, marked here as
<gi>div2</gi>, are really quite independent of each other, although they
are all marked as subdivisions of the whole group.  They can be read in
any order without affecting the sense of the piece; indeed, in some
cases, divisions of this nature are printed in such a way as to make it
impossible to determine the order in which they are intended to be read.
Individual stories can be added or removed without affecting the
existing components.
 </p>
<p>This method of encoding composite texts as composite divisions has
some limitations compared with the more general and powerful mechanisms
discussed in section <ptr target="#DSGRP"/>. However, it may be preferable
in some circumstances, notably where the individual texts are very
small.
 </p></div3></div2>
<div2 type="section" xml:id="DSDTB"><head>Elements Common to All Divisions</head>
<p>The divisions of any kind of text may sometimes begin with a brief
heading or descriptive title, with or without a byline, an epigraph or
brief quotation, or a salutation such as one finds at the start of a
letter.  They may also conclude with a brief trailer, byline, or
signature. Elements which may appear in this way, either at the start
or at the end of a text division proper, are regarded as forming a
class, known as <term>divtop</term> or <term>divbot</term>
respectively.
 </p>
<p>The following special-purpose elements are provided to
mark features which may appear only at the start of a division:
<specList>
<specDesc key="head" atts="type"/>
<specDesc key="epigraph"/>
<specDesc key="argument"/>
<specDesc key="opener"/>
</specList>
For further details of the <gi>head</gi> element, see section <ptr target="#DSHD"/>; 
for <gi>epigraph</gi> and <gi>argument</gi>, see section
<ptr target="#DSAE"/>; for <gi>opener</gi>, see section <ptr target="#DSOC"/>.
 </p>
<p>The following special-purpose elements are provided to mark features
which may appear only at the end of a division:
<specList>
<specDesc key="trailer"/>
<specDesc key="closer"/>
</specList>
For further details of the <gi>trailer</gi> element, see section <ptr target="#DSHD"/>; 
for the <gi>closer</gi> element, section <ptr target="#DSOC"/>.
</p>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSHD"><head>Headings and Trailers</head>
<p>The <gi>head</gi> element is used to identify a heading prefixed to
the start of any textual division, at any level. A given division may
of course contain more than one such element, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div1 n="Etym">
<head>Etymology</head>
<head>(Supplied by a late consumptive usher to a
grammar school)</head>
<p>The pale Usher &#x2014; threadbare in coat, heart,
body and brain; I see him now. He was ever
dusting his old lexicons and grammars, ...</p></div1></egXML>
<!-- H Melville, M.Dick -->
 </p>
<p>Unlike some other markup schemes, the TEI scheme does
<emph>not</emph> require that headings attached to textual subdivisions
at different hierarchic levels have different identifiers. All kinds of
heading are marked identically using the <gi>head</gi> tag; the type or
level of heading intended is implied by the immediate parent of the
<gi>head</gi> element, which may for example be a <gi>div1</gi>,
<gi>div2</gi>, etc., an un-numbered <gi>div</gi>, or a <gi>list</gi>.
 </p>
<p>In certain kinds of text (notably newspapers), there may be a need
to categorize individual headings within the sequence at the start of a
division,  for example as <soCalled>main</soCalled> headings, or <soCalled>detail</soCalled>
headings. Specific elements are provided for certain kinds of
heading-like features, (notably <gi>byline</gi>, <gi>dateline</gi>, and
<gi>salute</gi>; see further section <ptr target="#DSOC"/>),  but the
<att>type</att> attribute must be used to discriminate among other
forms of heading.
 </p>
<p>In the following example, taken from a British newspaper, the lead
story and its associated headlines have been encoded  as a <gi>div</gi>
element, with appropriate <term>divtop</term> elements attached:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="story">
<head rend="large underlined" type="sub">
President pledges safeguards for 2,400 British
troops in Bosnia</head>
<head rend="very large bold" type="main">
Major agrees to enforced no-fly zone</head>
<byline>By George Jones, Political Editor, in Washington</byline>
<p>Greater Western intervention in the conflict in
former Yugoslavia was pledged by President Bush ...</p></div></egXML>
<!-- Daily Telegraph 21 Dec 1992 -->
 </p>
<p>In older writings, the headings or <term>incipits</term> may be
longer than in modern works.
When heading-like material appears in the middle of a text, the encoder
must decide whether or not to treat it as the start of a new division.
If the phrase in question appears to be more closely connected with what
follows than with what precedes it, then it may be regarded as a
heading and tagged as the <gi>head</gi> of a new <gi>div</gi> element.
If it appears to be simply inserted or superimposed &#x2014; as for example
the kind of <soCalled>pull quotes</soCalled> often found in newspapers
or magazines, then the <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>q</gi>, or <gi>cit</gi>
element may be more appropriate.
 </p>
<p>The <gi>trailer</gi> element, which can appear at the end of a
division only, is used to mark any heading-like feature appearing in
this position, as in this example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div1 type="book" n="I"><head>In the name of Christ here begins the
    first book of the ecclesiastical history of Georgius Florentinus,
    known as Gregory, Bishop of Tours.</head>
  <div2><head>Chapter-Headings</head>
    <list>
    </list>
  </div2>
  <div2><head>In the name of Christ here begins Book I of the history.</head>
    <p>Proposing as I do ...</p>
    <p>From the Passion of our Lord until the death of Saint Martin four
      hundred and twelve years passed.</p>
    <trailer>Here ends the first Book, which covers five thousand, five
      hundred and ninety-six years from the beginning of the world down
      to the death of Saint Martin.</trailer>
  </div2>
</div1></egXML>
 </p>
</div3>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSOC"><head>Openers and Closers</head>
<p>In addition to headings of various kinds, divisions sometimes include
more or less formulaic opening or closing passages, typically conveying
such information as the name and address of the person to whom the
division is addressed, the place or time of its production, a salutation
or exhortation to the reader, and so on.  Divisions in epistolary form
are particularly liable to include such features.  
Additional elements for the detailed encoding of personal names, dates,
and places are provided in chapter <ptr target="#ND"/>.
For simple cases, the following elements should be adequate:
<specList>
<specDesc key="byline"/>
<specDesc key="dateline"/>
<specDesc key="salute"/>
<specDesc key="signed"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>byline</gi> and <gi>dateline</gi> elements are used to encode
headings which identify the authorship and provenance of a division.
Although the terminology derives from newspaper usage, there is no
implication that <gi>dateline</gi> or <gi>byline</gi> elements apply
only to newspaper texts.  The following example illustrates use of the
<gi>dateline</gi> and <gi>signed</gi> elements at the end of the
preface to a novel:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="preface">
<head>To Henry Hope.</head>
<p>It is not because this volume was conceived and partly
executed amid the glades and galleries of the Deepdene,
that I have inscribed it with your name. ... I shall find a
reflex to their efforts in your own generous spirit and
enlightened mind.
</p>
<closer>
<signed xml:lang="el">D.</signed>
<dateline>Grosvenor Gate, May-Day, 1844</dateline>
</closer>
</div>
 </egXML>
<!-- B Disraeli, Coningsby (Nelson, nd) -->
 </p>
<p>Where a sequence of such elements appear together, either at the
beginning or end of an element, it may be convenient to group them
together using one of the following elements:
<specList><specDesc key="opener"/>
<specDesc key="closer"/>
</specList>
The following examples demonstrate the use of the <gi>opener</gi> and
<gi>closer</gi> grouping elements:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="narrative" n="6">
  <head>Sixth Narrative</head>
  <head>contributed by Sergeant Cuff</head>
  <div type="fragment" n="6.1">
	<opener>
	  <dateline>
		<name type="place">Dorking, Surrey,</name>
		<date>July 30th, 1849</date>
	  </dateline>
	  <salute>To <name>Franklin Blake, Esq.</name> Sir, &#x2014;</salute>
	</opener>
	<p>I beg to apologize for the delay that has occurred in the
	  production of the Report, with which I engaged to furnish you. 
	  I have waited to make it a complete Report ...</p>
	<closer>
	  <salute>I have the honour to remain, dear sir, your
		obedient servant </salute>
	  <signed> <name>RICHARD CUFF</name> (late sergeant in the
		Detective Force, Scotland Yard, London). </signed>
	</closer>
  </div>
</div></egXML>
<!-- W. Collins, The Moonstone, Penguin, pp 503, 513 -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="letter" n="14">
<head>Letter XIV: Miss Clarissa Harlowe to Miss Howe</head>
<opener> <dateline>Thursday evening, March 2.</dateline> </opener>
<p>On Hannah's depositing my long letter ...</p>
<p>An interruption obliges me to conclude myself 
in some hurry, as well as fright, what I must ever be,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours more than my own,</salute>
<signed>Clarissa Harlowe</signed>
</closer>
</div></egXML>
<!-- S. Richardson 'Clarissa', (Dent, EML, vol 1, p62,64 -->
 </p>
<p>For further discussion of the encoding of names of persons and places
and of dates, see section <ptr target="#CONADA"/> and chapter <ptr target="#ND"/>.
 </p></div3>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSAE"><head>Arguments and Epigraphs</head>
<p>The <gi>argument</gi> element may be used to encode the prefatory
list of topics sometimes found at the start of a chapter or
other division.  It is most conveniently encoded as a list, since this
allows each item to be distinguished, but may also simply be presented
as a paragraph.  The following are thus both equally valid ways of
encoding the same argument:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="chap" n="6">
  <argument>
    <p>Kingston &#x2014; Instructive remarks on early English history
      &#x2014; Instructive observations on carved oak and life in general
      &#x2014; Sad case of Stivvings, junior &#x2014; Musings on antiquity
      &#x2014; I forget that I am steering &#x2014; Interesting result
      &#x2014; Hampton Court Maze &#x2014; Harris as a guide.</p>
  </argument>
  <p>It was a glorious morning, late spring or early summer, as you
    care to take it ...</p>
</div></egXML>
<!-- Jerome, J.K. : Three men in a boat, ch 6 -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="chap" n="6">
  <argument>
    <list type="inline">
      <item>Kingston</item>
      <item>Instructive remarks on early English history</item>
      <item>Instructive observations on carved oak and life in
        general</item>
      <item>Sad case of Stivvings, junior</item>
      <item>Musings on antiquity</item>
      <item>I forget that I am steering</item>
      <item>Interesting result</item>
      <item>Hampton Court Maze</item>
      <item>Harris as a guide.</item>
    </list>
  </argument>
  <p>It was a glorious morning, late spring or early summer, as you
    care to take it ...</p>
</div></egXML>
<!-- Jerome, J.K. : Three men in a boat, ch 6 -->
 </p>
<p>An <term>epigraph</term> is a quotation from some other work
appearing on a title page, or at the start of a division.  It may be
encoded using the special-purpose <gi>epigraph</gi> element.  Its
content will generally be a <gi>q</gi> or <gi>quote</gi> element,
often associated with a bibliographic reference, as in the
following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div n="19" type="chap"><head>Chapter 19</head>
 <epigraph>
 <cit><quote>I pity the man who can travel
     from Dan to Beersheba, and say <q>'Tis all
     barren;</q> and so is all the world to him
     who will not cultivate the fruits it offers.
     </quote>
     <bibl>Sterne: Sentimental Journey.</bibl>
 </cit></epigraph>
<p>To say that Deronda was romantic would be to
 misrepresent him: but under his calm and somewhat
 self-repressed exterior ...</p>
</div></egXML>
<!-- G. Eliot, D. Deronda, (1876) III.1 (Penguin, 1967, p. 245)  -->
 </p>
<p>For discussion of quotations appearing other than as epigraphs refer
to section <ptr target="#COHQQ"/>.
 </p></div3>
<div3 type="subsection" xml:id="DSCO"><head>Content of Textual Divisions</head>
<p>Other than its initial sequence of <term>divtop</term> elements,
and its closing sequence of <term>divbot</term> elements, every
textual division (numbered or un-numbered) consists of a sequence of
ungrouped <term>macro.component</term> elements (see <ptr
target="#STEC"/>).  
The actual elements available will depend on the base
module in use; in all cases, at least the component-level structural
elements defined in the core will be available (paragraphs, lists,
dramatic speeches, verse lines and line groups etc.).  If the drama
base has been selected, then additionally the low level dramatic
structural elements (speeches or stage directions, as defined in
chapter <ptr target="#DR"/>) will be available.  If the dictionary base
is in use, then dictionary entries, related entries, etc. (as defined
in chapter <ptr target="#DI"/>) will also be available; if the module
for transcribed speech is in use, then utterances, pauses, vocals,
kinesics, etc., as defined in chapter <ptr target="#TSBA"/> will be
available; and so on.
 </p>
<p>Where a text contains low level elements from more than one
module<!-- , two
options are available.  The first option, selected by the
<soCalled>mixed</soCalled> base, allows for low level structural
elements from any or all of the selected bases--> these may appear at any point.
<!--The second option, selected by the <soCalled>general</soCalled> base,
allows for low level structural elements from different bases to appear
in different textual divisions of the same text, but requires that any
one division use elements from only one base.  For further information,
refer to section <ptr target="#STCO"/>.-->
 </p>
<p>The elements discussed in this section are formally defined as
follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DDSDIVX" n="Tags for start and end of divisions">
&trailer;
&byline;
&dateline;
&argument;
&epigraph;
&opener;
&closer;
&salute;
&signed;
</specGrp>
</p>
</div3> 
</div2>
<div2 type="section" xml:id="DSGRP"><head>Groups of Texts</head>
<p>The <gi>group</gi> element should be used to represent a collection
of independent texts which is to be regarded as a single unit for
processing or other purposes.  Examples of such composite texts include
anthologies and other collections. The presence of common front matter
referring to the whole collection, possibly in addition to front matter
relating to each individual text, is a good indication that a given text
might usefully be encoded as a <gi>group</gi>, though encoders may
choose to use this structure to represent other kinds of composite
texts as well.
<specList><specDesc key="group"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>For example, the overall structure of a collection of
short stories might be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><TEI>
  <teiHeader>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
      <docTitle><titlePart>
          The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes
        </titlePart></docTitle>
      <docImprint>First published in <title>The Strand</title>
        between July 1891 and December 1892</docImprint>
    </front>
    <group>
      <text>
        <front>
          <head rend="italic">Adventures of Sherlock
            Holmes</head>
          <docTitle><titlePart>Adventure I. &#x2014;</titlePart>
            <titlePart>A Scandal in Bohemia</titlePart></docTitle>
          <byline>By A. Conan Doyle.</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
          <p>To Sherlock Holmes she is always
            <emph>the</emph> woman. ... </p>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text>
        <front>
          <head rend="italic">Adventures of Sherlock Holmes</head>
          <docTitle><titlePart>Adventure II. &#x2014;</titlePart>
            <titlePart>The Red-Headed League</titlePart></docTitle>
          <byline>By A. Conan Doyle.</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
          <p> </p>
        </body>
      </text>
      <text>
        <front>
          <head rend="italic">Adventures of Sherlock Holmes</head>
          <docTitle><titlePart>Adventure XII. &#x2014;</titlePart>
            <titlePart>The Adventure of the Copper Beeches</titlePart>
          </docTitle>
          <byline>By A. Conan Doyle.</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
          <p><q>&#x201C;To the man who loves art for its
            own sake,&amp;cdq;</q> remarked Sherlock Holmes ...
            ... she is now the head of a private school
            at Walsall, where I believe that she has
            met with considerable success.</p>
        </body>
      </text> 
    </group>
  </text>  
</TEI></egXML>
<!-- Original Illustrated Sherlock Holmes (Castle Books, 1989) -->
</p>
<p>A text which is a member of a group may itself contain groups. This
is quite common in collections of verse, but may happen in any kind of
text. As an example, consider the overall structure of a typical
collection, such as the <title>Muses Library</title> edition of
Crashaw's poetry (ed. J.R. Tutin, [ca. 1900]). Following a critical
introduction and table of contents, this work contains the following
major sections:
<list type="simple">
<item><title>Steps to the Temple</title> (a collection of
verse first published in 1648)</item>
<item><title>Carmen deo Nostro</title> (a second collection,
published in 1652)</item>
<item><title>The Delights of the Muses</title> (a third
collection, published in 1648)</item>
<item><title>Posthumous Poems,</title> I (a collection of
fragments all taken from a single manuscript)</item>
<item><title>Posthumous Poems,</title> II (a further collection
of fragments, taken from a different manuscript)</item></list>
 </p>
<p>Each of the three collections published in Crashaw's lifetime has a
reasonable claim to be considered as a text in its own right, and may
therefore be encoded as such. It is rather more arbitrary as to whether
the two posthumous collections should be treated as two groups,
following the practice of the Muses Library edition. An encoder might
elect to combine the two into a single group, or simply to treat each
fragment as an ungrouped unitary text.
 </p>
<p>The Muses Library edition reprints the whole of each of the three
original collections, including their original front matter (title
pages, dedications etc.). These should be encoded using the
<gi>front</gi> element and its constituents (on which see further
section <ptr target="#DSFRONT"/>), while the body of each collection should
be encoded as a single <gi>group</gi> element. Each individual poem
within the collections should be encoded as a distinct <gi>text</gi>
element. The beginning of the whole collection would thus appear as
follows (for further discussion of the use of the elements <gi>div</gi>
and <gi>lg</gi> for textual subdivision of verse, see section <ptr target="#COVE"/>
and chapter <ptr target="#VE"/>):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><text>
  <front>
    <titlePage>
      <docTitle><titlePart>The poems of Richard Crashaw</titlePart></docTitle>
      <byline>Edited by J.R. Tutin</byline>
    </titlePage>    
    <div type="preface"><head>Editor's Note</head>
      <p>A few words are necessary ... </p>
    </div>
  </front>
  <group>
    <text>
      <front>
        <titlePage>
          <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Steps to the Temple, Sacred Poems</titlePart>
          </docTitle>
        </titlePage>
        <div type="address"><head>The Preface to the Reader</head>
          <p>Learned Reader, The Author's friend will not usurp much
            upon thy eye ... </p>
        </div>
      </front>
      <group>
        <text>
          <front>
            <docTitle><titlePart>Sospetto D'Herode</titlePart></docTitle>
          </front>
          <body>
            <div1 type="book" n="Herod I">
              <head>Libro Primo</head>
              <epigraph>
                <l>Casting the times with their strong signs</l>
              </epigraph>
              <lg n="I.1" type="stanza">
                <l>Muse! now the servant of soft loves no more</l>
                <l>Hate is thy theme and Herod whose unblest</l>
                <l>Hand (O, what dares not jealous greatness?) tore</l>
                <l>A thousand sweet babes from their mothers' breast,</l>
                <l>The blooms of martyrdom ...</l>
              </lg> </div1> </body> </text> 
        <text>
          <front><docTitle><titlePart>The Tear</titlePart></docTitle></front>
          <body>
            <lg n="I">
              <l>What bright soft thing is this</l>
              <l>Sweet Mary, thy fair eyes' expense?</l>
            </lg> </body> </text> 
      </group>  
      <back>  </back>
    </text>
    <text> 
      <front>  </front>
      <group>
        <text>  </text>
        <text>  </text>
      </group>
    </text>
    <text> 
      <group>
        <text>  </text>
        <text>  </text>
      </group>
    </text>
  </group>
  <back>  </back>
</text></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>group</gi> element may be used in this way to encode any kind
of collection of which the constituents are regarded by the encoder as
texts in their own right.  Examples include anthologies of verse or
prose by multiple authors, collections, florilegia or commonplace books,
journals, day books, etc.  As a fairly typical example, we consider
<title>The Norton Book of Travel</title>, an anthology edited by Paul
Fussell and published in 1987 by W. W. Norton.  This work comprises
the following major sections:
<list type="ordered">
<item>Front matter (title page, acknowledgments, introductory essay)</item>
<item>The Beginnings</item>
<item>The Eighteenth Century and the Grand Tour</item>
<item>The Heyday</item>
<item>Touristic Tendencies</item>
<item>Post Tourism</item>
<item>Back matter (permissions list, index)</item></list>
Each titled section listed above comprises a group of extracts or
complete texts from writers of a given historical period, preceded by an
introductory essay.  For example, the second group listed above
contains, inter alia, the following:
<list type="ordered">
<item>Prefatory essay</item>
<item>Five letters by Lady Mary Wortley Montagu</item>
<item>An extract from Swift's Gullivers Travels</item>
<item>Two poems by Alexander Pope</item>
<item>Two extracts from Boswell's Journal</item>
<item>A poem by William Blake</item></list>
Each group of writings by a single author is preceded by a brief
biographical notice.  Some of the extracts are quite lengthy, containing
several chapters or other divisions; others are quite short.  As the
above list indicates, the texts included range across all kinds of
material:  verse, prose, journals and letters.
 </p>
<p>The easiest way of encoding such an anthology is to treat each
individual extract as a text in its own right.  A sequence of texts by a
single author, together with the biographical note preceding it, can
then be treated as a single <gi>group</gi> element within the larger
<gi>group</gi> formed by the section.  The sequence of single or
composite texts making up a single section of the work is likewise
treated, together with its prefatory essay, as a single <gi>group</gi>
within the work.  Schematically:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><text> 
  <front>
  </front>
  <group> 
    <group><head>The Beginnings</head>
    </group>
    <group> 
      <text>  </text>
      <group>      
        <text>      </text>
        <text>      </text>
        <text>      </text>
      </group>     
      <text>     
        <front>   </front>
        <body>    </body>
      </text>    
      <group>  
        <text>  </text>
        <text>  </text>
        <text>  </text>
      </group> 
    </group> 
    <group><head>The Heyday</head>
    </group>
  </group> 
  <back>  </back>
</text> </egXML>
 </p>
<p>Note that the editor's introductory essays on each author may be
treated as texts in their own right (as the essays on Lady Mary
Wortley Montagu and Alexander Pope have been treated above), or as
front matter to the embedded text, as the essay on Swift has been.
The treatment in the example is intentionally inconsistent, to allow
comparison of the two approaches. Consistency can be imposed either
by treating the Swift section as a <gi>group</gi> containing one text
by Swift and one by the editor, or by treating the Montagu and Pope
sections as <gi>text</gi> elements containing the editor's essays as
front matter. Marked in the second way, the Pope section of the book
would look like this:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">      <text>     
        <front>   </front>
        <group>
          <text>  </text>
          <text>  </text>
        </group>
      </text>    </egXML>
 </p>
<p>The essays on <q>The Eighteenth Century and the Grand Tour</q> and
other larger sections could also be tagged as <soCalled>front</soCalled>
matter in the same way, by treating the larger sections as <gi>text</gi>
elements rather than <gi>group</gi> elements.
 </p>
<p>Where, as in this case, an anthology contains different kinds of
text (for example, mixtures of prose and drama, or transcribed speech
and dictionary entries, or letters and verse), the elements to be
encoded may well need to be drawn from more than one of the modules
described in part II. <!-- In such a situation, either the mixed or
the general base should be specified, as further described in section <ptr target="#STCO"/>.-->
The elements provided by the core module
described in chapter <ptr target="#CO"/> should however prove adequate
for most simple purposes, where prose, drama, and verse are combined
in a single collection.
 </p>
<p>For anthologies of short extracts such as commonplace books, it may
often be preferable to regard each extract not as a text in its own
right but simply as a quotation or <gi>cit</gi> element. The following
component-level elements may be used to encode quotations of this kind:
<specList><specDesc key="cit"/><specDesc key="quote"/></specList>
For example, the chapter of <soCalled>extracts</soCalled> which appears
in the front matter of Melville's <title>Moby Dick</title> might be
encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div n="2" type="chap">
  <head>Extracts</head>
  <head>(Supplied by a sub-sub-Librarian)</head>
  <p>It will be seen that this mere painstaking burrower and
	grubworm of a poor devil of a Sub-Sub appears to have gone
	through the long Vaticans and street-stalls of the earth,
	picking up whatever random allusions to whales he could
	anyways find ...
	Here ye strike but splintered hearts together – there,
	ye shall strike unsplinterable glasses!</p>
  <p>
	<cit>
	  <quote>And God created great whales.</quote>
	  <bibl>Genesis</bibl>
	</cit>
	<cit>
	  <quote>
		<l>Leviathan maketh a path to shine after him;</l>
		<l>One would think the deep to be hoary.</l>
	  </quote>
	  <bibl>Job</bibl>
	</cit>
	<cit>
	  <quote>By art is created that great Leviathan,
		called a Commonwealth or State — (in Latin,
		<mentioned xml:lang="la">civitas</mentioned>), which
		is but an artificial man.</quote>
	  <bibl>Opening sentence of Hobbes's Leviathan</bibl>
	</cit>
  </p>
</div></egXML>
For more information on the use of the <gi>quote</gi> and <gi>bibl</gi>
elements, see sections <ptr target="#COHQQ"/> and <ptr target="#COBI"/>
respectively.
 </p>
<p>Where one or more whole texts are embedded within other texts,
without necessarily forming a composite, the encoder may also choose to
represent the nested structure directly. The <gi>text</gi> element is
a member of the <ident type="class">model.inter</ident> class, and can
thus appear <!-- itself a <term>macro.component</term> element, and
thus can appear -->
within any division level element in the same way as a paragraph. For
example, texts such as the <title>Decameron</title> or the
<title>Arabian Nights</title> might be regarded as sequences of discrete
texts embedded within another single text, the framing narrative, rather
than as groups of discrete texts in which the fragments of framing
narrative are regarded as front matter.
</p>
<!-- more examples and discussion needed here -->

</div2>
<div2 type="section" xml:id="DSFRONT"><head>Front Matter</head>
<p>By <term>front matter</term> we mean distinct sections of a text
(usually, but not exclusively, a printed one), prefixed to it by way of
introduction or identification as a part of its production. Features
such as title pages or prefaces are clear examples; a less definite
case might be the prologue attached to a play.  The front matter of an
encoded text should not be confused with the TEI header described in
chapter <ptr target="#HD"/>, which serves as a kind of front matter for
the computer file itself, not the text it encodes.
 </p>
<p>An encoder may choose simply to ignore the front matter in a text,
if the original presentation of the work is of no interest, or for
other reasons; alternatively some or all components of the front matter
may be thought worth including with the text as components of the
<gi>front</gi> element.<note place="foot">This decision should be recorded in the
<gi>sampling</gi> element of the header.</note> With the exception of
the title page, (on which see section <ptr target="#DSTITL"/>), front
matter should be encoded using the same elements as the rest of a text.
As with the divisions of the text body, no other specific tags are
proposed here for the various kinds of subdivision which may appear
within front matter:  instead either numbered or un-numbered
<gi>div</gi> elements may be used.  The following suggested
values<note place="foot">As with all lists of <soCalled>suggested
values</soCalled> for attributes, it is recommended that software
written to handle TEI-conformant texts be prepared to recognize and
handle these values when they occur, without limiting the user to the
values in this list.</note>
for the <att>type</att> attribute may be used to distinguish various
kinds of division characteristic of front matter:
<list type="gloss"><label><term>preface</term></label>
<item>A foreword or preface addressed to
    the reader in which the author or publisher explains the
    content, purpose, or origin of the text.</item><label><term>ack</term></label>
<item>A formal declaration of
    acknowledgment by the author in which persons and institutions
    are thanked for their part in the creation of a text.</item><label><term>dedication</term></label>
<item>A formal offering or dedication of
    a text to one or more persons or institutions by the author.</item><label><term>abstract</term></label>
<item>A summary of the content of a text as
    continuous prose.</item><label><term>contents</term></label>
<item>A table of contents, specifying the
    structure of a work and listing its constituents.
    The <gi>list</gi>
    element should be used to mark its structure.</item><label><term>frontispiece</term></label>
<item>A pictorial frontispiece,
    possibly including some text.</item></list>
 </p>
<p>The following extended example demonstrates how various parts of the
front matter of a text may be encoded.  The front part begins with a
title page, which is presented in section <ptr target="#DSTITL"/> below.
This is followed by a dedication and a preface, each of which is encoded
as a distinct <gi>div</gi>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="dedication">
  <p>To my parents, Ida and Max Fish</p>
</div>
<div type="preface"><head>Preface</head>
  <p>The answer this book gives to its title question is <q>there is
      and there isn't</q>.</p>
  <p>Chapters 1&#x2013;12 have been previously published in the
    following journals and collections:
    <list>
      <item>chapters 1 and 3 in <title>New literary History</title></item>
      <item>chapter 10 in <title>Boundary II</title> (1980)</item>
    </list>.
    I am grateful for permission to reprint.</p>
  <signed>S.F.</signed>
</div></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The front matter concludes with another <gi>div</gi> element, shown
in the next example, this time containing a table of contents, which
contains a <gi>list</gi> element (as described in section 
<ptr target="#COLI"/>).  Note the use of the <gi>ptr</gi> element to provide
page-references:  the implication here is that the target identifiers
supplied (P1, P68 etc.) may correspond with identifiers used either for
<gi>div</gi> elements representing chapters of the text, or for
<gi>pb</gi> elements marking page divisions of the text.  (For the
<gi>ptr</gi> element, see <ptr target="#COXR"/>.)  Alternatively,
the literal page numbers present in the source text might be
transcribed, but they are likely to be of little direct use in work with
the electronic text.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="contents">
  <head>Contents</head>
  <list>
	<item>Introduction, or How I stopped Worrying and Learned to Love
	  Interpretation <ptr target="#P1"/></item>
	<item>
	  <list>
		<head>Part One: Literature in the Reader</head>
		<item n="1">Literature in the Reader: Affective Stylistics
		  <ptr target="#P21"/></item>
		<item n="2">What is Stylistics and Why Are They Saying Such
		  Terrible Things About It? <ptr target="#P68"/></item>
	  </list></item></list>
  </div></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The following example uses numbered divisions to mark up the front
matter of a medieval text. (Entity references are used to represent the
characters thorn, yogh, and ampersand)<!--, as discussed in section <ptr target="CHLON"/>.) -->
Note that in this case no title page in the modern
sense occurs; the title is simply given as a heading at the start of the
front matter. Note also the use of the <att>type</att> attribute on the
<gi>div</gi> elements to indicate document elements comparatively
unusual in modern books such as the initial prayer:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><front>
  <div1 type="incipit">
    <p>Here bygynni&amp;th; a book of contemplacyon, &amp;th;e whiche 
      is clepyd <title>&amp;Th;E CLOWDE OF VNKNOWYNG</title>,
      in &amp;th;e whiche a soule is onyd wi&amp;th; GOD.</p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="prayer">
    <head>Here biginne&amp;th; &amp;th;e preyer on &amp;th;e prologe.</head>
    <p>God, unto whom alle hertes ben open, &amp; unto whome alle wille
      speki&amp;th;, &amp; unto whom no priue &amp;th;ing is hid: I beseche
      &amp;th;ee so for to clense &amp;th;e entent of myn hert wi&amp;th; &amp;th;e
      unspekable &amp;yogh;ift of &amp;th;i grace, &amp;th;at I may parfiteliche
      loue &amp;th;ee &amp; wor&amp;th;ilich  preise &amp;th;ee. Amen.</p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="preface">
    <head>Here biginne&amp;th; &amp;th;e prolog.</head> 
    <p>In &amp;th;e name of &amp;th;e Fader &amp; of &amp;th;e Sone &amp;
      of &amp;th;e Holy Goost.</p>
    <p>I charge &amp;th;ee &amp; I beseeche &amp;th;ee, wi&amp;th; as moche
      power &amp; vertewe as &amp;th;e bonde of charite is sufficient
      to suffre, what-so-euer &amp;th;ou be &amp;th;at &amp;th;is book schalt
      haue in possession ...</p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="contents">
    <head>Here biginne&amp;th; a table of &amp;th;e chapitres.</head>
    <list>
      <label>&amp;th;e first chapitre </label>
      <item>Of foure degrees of Cristen mens leuing; &amp; of &amp;th;e
        cours of his cleping &amp;th;at &amp;th;is book was maad vnto.</item>
      <label>&amp;th;e secound chapitre</label>
      <item>A schort stering to meeknes &amp; to &amp;th;e werk of &amp;th;this
        book</item>
      <label>&amp;th;e fiue and seuenti chapitre</label>
      <item>Of somme certein tokenes bi &amp;th;e whiche a man may proue
        whe&amp;th;er he be clepid of God to worche in &amp;th;is werk.</item>
    </list>
    <trailer>&amp; here eende&amp;th; &amp;th;e table of &amp;th;e chapitres.</trailer>
  </div1>
</front></egXML>
<!-- Cloud of Unknowing, ed Phyllis Hodgson, EETS, 1944 -->
 </p></div2>
<div2 type="section" xml:id="DSTITL"><head>Title Pages</head>
<p>Detailed analysis of the title page and other
<term>preliminaries</term> of older printed books and manuscripts is of
major importance in descriptive bibliography and the cataloguing of
printed books; such analysis may require a rather more detailed module
than that proposed here.<note place="foot">Definition of such a module remains
a work item for the TEI; such modules for contemporary printed matter
already exist or are being created within the publishing industry, for
example the Majour (Modular Application for Journals) Project of the
European Workgroup on SGML. See for example <bibl><title>MAJOUR:
Modular Application for Journals: DTD for Article Headers</title>
([n.p.]: EWS, 1991).</bibl></note> The following elements are
therefore proposed as an interim measure; they constitute a useful
descriptive module for the major features of most title pages:
<specList>
<specDesc key="titlePage"/>
<specDesc key="docTitle"/>
<specDesc key="titlePart" atts="type"/>
<specDesc key="argument"/>
<specDesc key="byline"/>
<specDesc key="docAuthor"/>
<specDesc key="epigraph"/>
<specDesc key="imprimatur"/>
<specDesc key="docEdition"/>
<specDesc key="docImprint"/>
<specDesc key="docDate"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>Together with the <gi>figure</gi> element described in chapter
<ptr target="#FT"/>, these elements constitute the element class
<ident type="class">model.titlepagePart</ident>. Any number of elements from this class can
appear grouped together within a <gi>titlePage</gi> element. (The
<gi>figure</gi> element is included so as to enable encoders to
record the presence of printers' ornaments or other illustrative
material found within a title page; its use implies that the TEI
module for figures and tables has been selected, as discussed in
chapter <ptr target="#FT"/>).</p>
<p>The elements listed above, together with the <gi>head</gi> element,
also constitute the element class <ident type="class">model.pLike.front</ident>. The elements
in this class can appear within a <soCalled>minimal</soCalled>
<gi>front</gi> element without any need to group them together and
encode a complete title page.</p>
<p>Encoders wishing to add new elements to either class may do so by
modifying or redefining this parameter entity, as further described in
chapter <ptr target="#MD"/>. Two examples of the use of these elements
follow. First, the title page of the work discussed earlier in this
section:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><front>
  <titlePage>
    <docTitle>
      <titlePart type="main">Is There a Text in This Class?</titlePart>
      <titlePart type="sub">The Authority of Interpretive Communities</titlePart>
    </docTitle>
    <docAuthor>Stanley Fish</docAuthor>
    <docImprint>
	  <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
      <pubPlace>Cambridge, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
      <pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
    </docImprint>
  </titlePage></front></egXML></p>
<p>Second, a characteristically verbose 17th century example. Note the
use of the <gi>lb</gi> tag to mark the line breaks of the original
where necessary:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><titlePage>
  <docTitle>
    <titlePart type="main">THE
      <lb/>Pilgrim's Progress 
      <lb/>FROM
      <lb/>THIS WORLD,
      <lb/>TO
      <lb/>That which is to come:</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="sub">Delivered under the Similitude of a
      <lb/>DREAM</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="desc">Wherein is Discovered,
      <lb/>The manner of his setting out,
      <lb/>His Dangerous Journey; And safe
      <lb/>Arrival at the Desired Countrey.</titlePart>
  </docTitle>
  <epigraph>
    <cit><quote>I have used Similitudes,</quote><bibl>Hos. 12.10</bibl></cit>
  </epigraph>
  <byline>By <docAuthor>John Bunyan</docAuthor>.</byline>
  <imprimatur>Licensed and Entred according to Order.</imprimatur>
  <docImprint>
    <pubPlace>LONDON,</pubPlace>
    Printed for <name>Nath. Ponder</name>
    <lb/>at the <name>Peacock</name> in the <name>Poultrey</name>
    <lb/>near <name>Cornhil</name>, <docDate>1678</docDate>.
  </docImprint></titlePage></egXML></p>
<p>Those elements in the above list which are not defined elsewhere have
the following formal declarations:
<specGrp xml:id="DDSTPAGE" n="Tags for title pages">
&titlePage;
&docTitle;
&titlePart;
&docAuthor;
&imprimatur;
&docEdition;
&docImprint;
&docDate;
</specGrp>
 </p>
<p>Where title pages are encoded, their physical rendition is
often of considerable importance.  One approach to this requirement
would be to use the <gi>seg</gi> tag, described in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>, to segment the typographic content of each part of the
title page, and then use the global <att>rend</att> attribute to specify
its rendition.  Another would be to use a module specialized for the
description of typographic entities such as pages, lines, rules, etc.,
bearing special-purpose attributes to describe line height, leading,
degree of kerning, font, etc. Further discussion of these problems is
provided in chapter <ptr target="#PH"/>.
 </p>
<p>Front matter elements:
<specGrp xml:id="DDSFRONT">
&front;
<specGrpRef target="#DDSTPAGE"/>
</specGrp>
 </p></div2>
<div2 type="section" xml:id="DSBACK"><head>Back Matter</head>
<p>Conventions vary as to which elements are grouped as back matter and
which as front.  For example, some books place the table of contents at
the front, and others at the back.  Even title pages may appear at the
back of a book as well as at the front.  The content model for
<gi>back</gi> and <gi>front</gi> elements are therefore identical.
 </p>
<p>The following suggested values may be used for the <att>type</att>
attribute on all division elements, in order to distinguish various
kinds of division characteristic of back matter:
<list type="gloss"><label><term>appendix</term></label>
<item>An ancillary self-contained section of
a work, often providing additional but in some sense extra-canonical
text.</item><label><term>glossary</term></label>
<item>A list of terms associated with definition texts
(<q>glosses</q>): this should be encoded as a <gi>list type="gloss"</gi>
(see section <ptr target="#COLI"/>).</item><label><term>notes</term></label>
<item>A section in which textual or
other kinds of notes are gathered together.</item><label><term>bibliogr</term></label>
<item>A list of bibliographic citations: this should be encoded
as a <gi>listBibl</gi> (see section <ptr target="#COBI"/>).</item><label><term>index</term></label>
<item>Any form of index to the work.</item><label><term>colophon</term></label>
<item>A statement appearing at the end of a book describing the
conditions of its physical production.</item></list>
 </p>
<p>No additional elements are proposed for the encoding of back matter
at present.  Some characteristic examples follow; first, an index (for
the case in which a printed index is of sufficient interest to merit
transcription):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><back>  
<div type="index">
  <head>Index</head>
  <list type="index">
  <item>Actors, public, paid for the contempt attending
    their profession, <ptr target="#P209"/></item>
  <item>Africa, cause assigned for the barbarous state of
    the interior parts of that continent, <ptr target="#P125"/></item>
  <item>Agriculture
    <list type="indexentry">
    <item>ancient policy of Europe unfavourable to, <ptr target="#P371"/></item>
    <item>artificers necessary to carry it on, <ptr target="#P481"/></item>
    <item>cattle and tillage mutually improve each other, <ptr target="#P325"/></item>
    <item>wealth arising from more solid than that which proceeds
    from commerce <ptr target="#P520"/></item>
    </list></item>
  <item>Alehouses, not the efficient cause of drunkenness, <ptr target="#P461"/></item>
  </list>
</div>
</back></egXML>
<!-- Smith, Wealth of Nations, 1776; index to vol 1 --></p>
<p>Next, a back-matter division in epistolary form:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><back>  
  <div type="letter">
    <head>A letter written to his wife, founde with this booke
      after his death.</head>
    <p>The remembrance of the many wrongs offred thee, and thy
      unreproued vertues, adde greater sorrow to my miserable state,
      than I can utter or thou conceiue. ...
      ... yet trust I in the world to come to find mercie, by the
      merites of my Saiuour to whom I commend thee, and commit
      my soule.</p>
    <signed>Thy repentant husband for his disloyaltie,
      <name>Robert Greene.</name></signed>
    <epigraph xml:lang="la"><p>Faelicem fuisse infaustum</p></epigraph>
    <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
  </div>
</back></egXML>
<!-- Greene, Groatsworth of witte, 1592 --></p>
<p>And finally, a list of corrigenda and addenda with pseudo-epistolary
features:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><back>
  <div type="corrigenda">
    <head>Addenda</head>
    <salute xml:lang="la">M. Scriblerus Lectori</salute>
    <p>Once more, gentle reader I appeal unto thee, from the shameful
      ignorance of the Editor, by whom Our own Specimen of
      <name>Virgil</name> hath been mangled in such miserable manner,
      that scarce without tears can we behold it. At the very
      entrance, Instead of <q xml:lang="gr">prolego/mena</q>, lo! <q xml:lang="gr">prolegw/mena</q> with an Omega! and in the same line
      <q xml:lang="la">consul&#xE2;s</q> with a circumflex! In the next
      page thou findest <q xml:lang="la">leviter perlabere</q>, which his
      ignorance took to be the infinitive mood of <q xml:lang="la">perlabor</q> but ought to be <q xml:lang="la">perlabi</q> ... Wipe away all these monsters,
      Reader, with thy quill.</p>
  </div>
</back></egXML>
<!-- Pope, Dunciad Variorum, 1729 -->
	<!--  end of draft -->
 </p>
<p>The <gi>back</gi> element; since there are no other specialized
back-matter tags, nothing else is defined here.
<specGrp xml:id="DDSBACK">
&back;
</specGrp>
 </p></div2>
<div2 type="section" xml:id="DSSTRUC">
<head>Module for Default Text Structure</head>
<p>The module described by the present chapter has the following
components:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DDS" ident="textstructure">
<altIdent type="FPI">Default Text Structure</altIdent><desc>Default
text structure</desc>
</moduleSpec>
It is organized as follows:
<!--publicID:  -//TEI P5//ELEMENTS Default Text Structure//EN-->
<specGrpRef target="#DDSTEXT"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSDIV"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSDIVN"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSDIVX"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSBACK"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSFRONT"/>
The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>
</div2> 
</div1>
