<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="FT" n="22"><head>Tables, Formulæ, Graphics and Notated Music</head>
<p>Many documents, both historical and contemporary, include not only
text, but also graphics, artwork, and other images.  Although some
types of images can be represented directly with markup, 
it is more common practice to include
such information by using a reference to an 
external entity (typically a URL) encoded in a suitable graphical notation.</p>
<p>In addition to graphic images, documents often contain material
presented in graphical or tabular format. In such materials, details
of layout and presentation may also be of comparatively greater
significance or complexity than they are for running text. Indeed, it
may often be difficult to make a clear distinction between details
relating purely to the rendition of information and those relating to
the information itself.</p>
<p>Documents may also contain mathematical formulæ or
expressions in other formulaic notations, for which no notation is
defined in these Guidelines.</p>
  
  <p>Finally, documents may contain musical notation, embedded in a manner similar to 
    tables, graphs and formulæ.</p>

<p>These areas (graphics, tabular material, and mathematical or other
formulæ, and music) have in common that they have received considerable attention
from many other standards bodies or similar professional groups.  In
part because of this, they may frequently be most conveniently encoded
and processed using some notation not defined by these Guidelines.
For these reasons, and others, we consider tables, formulæ,
graphics and notated music together in this chapter.</p>

<p>As with text markup in general, many incompatible formats have been
proposed for the representation of graphics, formulæ, and tables in
electronic form.  Unfortunately, no single format as effective as XML
in the domain of text has yet emerged for their interchange, to some
extent because of the difficulty of representing the information these
data formats convey independently of the way it is rendered.</p>

<p>The  module defined by this chapter defines special
purpose <soCalled>container</soCalled> elements that can be used to
encapsulate occurrences of such data within a TEI-conformant document in
a portable way.  Specific recommendations for the encoding of tables are
provided in section <ptr target="#FTTAB"/>, recommendations for
  mathematical or other formulæ in section <ptr target="#FTFOR"/>, and for the encoding of
  musical notation in section <ptr target="#FTNM"/>.
Specific recommendations for the encoding of graphic figures may be
found in section <ptr target="#FTGRA"/>.  The rest of the chapter is
devoted to general problems of encoding graphic information.</p>
  
<p>There is at the time of writing no consensus on formats for graphical
images, and such formats vary in many ways.  We therefore provide (in
section <ptr target="#FTGROV"/>) a brief discussion of the ways in which
images may be represented, and (in section <ptr target="#FTGRNO"/>) a list
of formal names for those representations most popular at this time.
Each one includes a very brief description.  These Guidelines recommend
a few particular representations as being the most widely supported and
understood.</p>

<div type="div2" xml:id="FTTAB"><head>Tables</head>
<p>A table is the least <soCalled>graphic</soCalled> of the elements
discussed in this chapter.  Almost any text structure can be presented
as a series of rows and columns:  one might, for example, choose to show
a glossary or other form of list in tabular form, without necessarily
regarding it as a table.  In such cases, the global <att>rend</att>
attribute is an appropriate way of indicating that some element is being
presented in tabular format, for example by using an appropriate
display property in CSS.  When tabular presentation is regarded as
of less intrinsic importance, it is correspondingly simpler to encode
descriptive or functional information about the contents of the table,
for example to identify one cell as containing a name and another as
containing a date, though the two methods may be combined.
 </p>
<p>When, however, particular elements are required to encode the
tabular arrangement itself, then one or other of the various
<soCalled>table schemas</soCalled> now available may be preferable.
The schemas in common use generally view a table as a special text
element, made up of row elements,
themselves composed of cells.<!--note place="bottom">A markup scheme could
equally well define tables as being composed of columns of cells, but
this is rarely if ever done in practice.</note--> Table cells generally appear in
row-major order, with the first row from left to right, then the
second row, and so on. Details of appearance such as column widths,
border lines, and alignment are generally encoded by numerous
attributes. Beyond this, however, such schemas differ greatly. This
section begins by describing a table schema of this kind; a brief
summary of some other widely available table schemas is also provided
in section <ptr target="#FTTAB2"/>.
 </p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FTTAB1"><head>TEI Tables</head>
<p>For encoding tables of low to moderate complexity, these Guidelines
provide the following special purpose elements:
<specList><specDesc key="table" atts="rows cols"/><specDesc key="row"/><specDesc key="cell"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>table</gi> element is defined as a member of the class
<term>model.inter</term>; it may therefore appear both within other components
(such as paragraphs), or between them, provided that the module defined in this chapter has been enabled, as described at the
beginning of this chapter.</p>
<p>It is to a large extent arbitrary whether a table should be regarded
as a series of rows or as a series of columns.  For compatibility with
currently available systems, however, these Guidelines require a
row-by-row description of a table.  It is also possible to describe a
table simply as a series of cells; this may be useful for tabular
material which is not presented as a simple matrix.
 </p>
<p>The attributes <att>rows</att> and <att>cols</att> may be used to
indicate the size of a table, or to indicate that a particular cell or
row of a table spans more than one row or column.  For both tables and cells,
rows and columns are always given in top-to-bottom, left-to-right
order, although formatting properties such as those provided by CSS may
be used to specify that they should be displayed differently.
These Guidelines do not require that the size of a table be specified;
for most formatting and many other applications, it will be necessary to
process the whole table in two passes in any case.
 </p>
<p>Where cells span more than one column or row, the encoder must
determine whether this is a purely presentational effect (in which case
the <att>rend</att> attribute may be more appropriate), whether the part
of the table affected would be better treated as a nested table, or
whether to use the spanning attributes listed above.
 </p>
<p>The <att>role</att> attribute may be used to categorize a single
cell, or set a default for all the cells in a given row.  The present
Guidelines distinguish the roles of <term>label</term> and
<term>data</term> only, but the encoder may define other roles, such as
<q>derived</q>, <q>numeric</q>, etc., as appropriate.
 </p>
<p>These three attributes are provided by the attribute class <ident type="class">att.tableDecoration</ident> of which both <gi>cell</gi>
and <gi>row</gi> are members; see further <ptr target="#STECAT"/>. </p>

<p>The following simple example demonstrates how the data presented as a
labelled list in section <ptr target="#COLI"/> might be represented by an
encoder wishing to preserve its original appearance as a table:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COLI-eg-172"><table rend="boxed" rows="2" cols="2">
   <head rend="it">Report of the conduct and progress
      of Ernest Pontifex.  Upper Vth form — half
      term ending Midsummer 1851</head>
   <row>
      <cell role="label">Classics</cell>
      <cell>Idle listless and unimproving</cell>
   </row>
   <row>
      <cell role="label">Mathematics</cell>
      <cell>ditto</cell>
   </row>
   <row>
      <cell role="label">Divinity</cell>
      <cell>ditto</cell>
   </row>
   <row>
      <cell role="label">Conduct in house</cell>
      <cell>Orderly</cell>
   </row>
   <row>
      <cell role="label">General conduct</cell>
      <cell>Not satisfactory, on
       account of his great unpunctuality and inattention to
       duties</cell>
   </row>
</table></egXML>
<!-- S Butler, Way of all Flesh, -->
 </p>
<p>Note that this encoding makes no attempt to represent the full
significance of the <q>ditto</q> cells above; these might be regarded as
simple links between the cells containing them and that to which they
refer, or as virtual copies of it.  For ways of representing either
interpretation, see chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.
 </p>
<p>The following example demonstrates how a simple statistical table may
be represented using this scheme:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><table rows="4" cols="4">
  <head>Poor Man's Lodgings in Norfolk (Mayhew, 1843)</head>
  <row role="label">
    <cell>  </cell>
    <cell>Dossing Cribs or Lodging Houses</cell>
    <cell>Beds</cell>
    <cell>Needys or Nightly Lodgers</cell> </row>
  <row>
    <cell role="label">Bury St Edmund's</cell>
    <cell>5</cell> <cell>8</cell> <cell>128</cell> </row>
  <row>
    <cell role="label">Thetford</cell>
    <cell>3</cell> <cell>6</cell> <cell>36</cell> </row>
  <row>
    <cell role="label">Attleboro'</cell>
    <cell>3</cell> <cell>5</cell> <cell>20</cell> </row>
  <row>
    <cell role="label">Wymondham</cell>
    <cell>1</cell> <cell>11</cell> <cell>22</cell> </row>
</table></egXML>
 </p>
<p>Note the use of a blank cell in the first row to ensure that the
column labels are correctly aligned with the data.  Again, this encoding
does not explicitly represent the alignment between column and row
labels and the data to which they apply.  Where the primary emphasis of
an encoding is on the semantic content of a table, a more explicit
mechanism for the representation of structured information such as that
provided by the feature structure mechanism described in chapter <ptr target="#FS"/> may be preferred.  Alternatively, the general purpose linkage
and alignment mechanisms described in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/> may also
be applied to individual cells of a table.
 </p>
<p>The content of a table cell need not be simply character data.  It
may also contain any sequence of the phrase-level elements described in
chapter <ptr target="#CO"/>, thus allowing for the encoding of potentially
more useful semantic information, as in the following example, where the
fact that one cell contains a number and the other contains a place name
has been explicitly recorded:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><table>
  <head>US State populations, 1990</head>
  <row><cell> <name>Wyoming</name> </cell>
       <cell> <num>453,588</num> </cell></row>
  <row><cell> <name>Alaska</name> </cell>
       <cell> <num>550,043</num> </cell></row>
  <row><cell> <name>Montana</name> </cell>
       <cell> <num>799,065</num> </cell></row>
  <row><cell> <name>Rhode Island</name> </cell>
       <cell> <num>1,003,464</num> </cell></row>
</table></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The <att>role</att> attribute provides a slightly less verbose
means of conveying the same information:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><table>
  <head>US State populations, 1990</head>
  <row><cell role="statename">Wyoming </cell>
       <cell role="pop">453,588 </cell></row>
  <row><cell role="statename">Alaska </cell>
       <cell role="pop">550,043 </cell></row>
  <row><cell role="statename">Montana </cell>
       <cell role="pop">799,065 </cell></row>
  <row><cell role="statename">Rhode Island</cell>
       <cell role="pop">1,003,464</cell></row>
</table></egXML>
</p>


<p>The use of semantically marked elements within a
<gi>cell</gi> enables the encoder to convey something about the
nature and significance of the information, rather than merely
suggesting how to display it in rows and columns.</p>
  
  <p>The content of table elements is not limited to <gi>head</gi> and <gi>row</gi>.
  Milestone elements such as <gi>cb</gi> and <gi>lb</gi> allow breaks to be signalled
  inside tables; <gi>figure</gi> provides an option for including data which 
  is not amenable to normal row/cell analysis; and other elements such as <gi>epigraph</gi> 
  and <gi>trailer</gi> provide options for including text which is clearly part of the
  table, but outside the actual tabular layout. This example shows the use of <gi>trailer</gi>:
  
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><table>
  <head>The Table of Battallions, reduced out of the grand square of men.</head>
  <row>
    <cell>1</cell>
    <cell>2</cell>
    <cell>3</cell>
    <cell>4</cell>
  </row>
  <!-- ... -->
  <row>
    <cell>841</cell>
    <cell>3</cell>
    <cell>289 289 256</cell>
    <cell>7</cell>
  </row>
  <trailer>The end of the Table of Battallions reduced out of the battels of g. and squares of men: vpon the right side of euery leafe.</trailer>
</table></egXML>
  </p>
  
  
<specGrp xml:id="DFTTAB" n="Tables">







<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/table.xml"/>












<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/row.xml"/>












<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/cell.xml"/>





</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FTTAB2"><head>Other Table Schemas</head>
<p>Many authoring systems include built-in support for their
own or for public table schemas.  These provide an enhanced user
interface and good formatting capabilities, but are often
product-specific, despite their use of a XML markup language.
 </p>
<p>The DTD developed by the Association of American Publishers (AAP)
and standardized in ANSI Z39.59 provided a very simple encoding for
correspondingly simple tables. This has been further developed,
together with the table DTD documented in ISO Technical Report 9537,
and now forms part of ISO 12083. The TEI table model described above
has functionality very similar to that defined by ISO 12083.
 </p>
<p>For more complex tables, the most effective publicly-available DTD
is probably that developed by the US Department of Defense CALS project.
This supports vertical and horizontal spanning and various kinds of text
rotation and justification within cells and is also directly supported
by a number of existing XML software systems.
 </p>
<p>The CALS table model is much too complex to describe fully here; for
historical background  see <ptr target="http://www.hbingham.com/technical/tables/calstbhs.htm"/>;  for
more recent simplifications of it and current implementations see <ptr target="http://www.oasis-open.org/specs/tablemodels.php"/>. As with any
other XML vocabulary, the XML version of the CALS model may readily be
included in a TEI schema, using the techniques described in <ptr target="#MD"/>. 
 </p>
<!--
<p>The apparent complexity of the CALS table DTDled to
simplification efforts, most notably by OASIS in the form of  <title>OASIS
Technical Resolution 9503:1995, Exchange Table Model Document Type
		Definition</title> (<ptr target="http://www.oasis-open.org/specs/a503.htm"/>). An XML
version of this is also defined in <title>OASIS Technical Memorandum TR 9901:1999,
		XML Exchange Table Model DTD</title> (<ptr
		target="http://www.oasis-open.org/specs/tm9901.html"/>). </p>-->

<!--	<p>With the ascent of the Web, the HTML table model (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/struct/tables.html"/>) has become very popular and widespread in use. The
last few years have seen a growing access to information via devices
of varying capabilities, ranging from desktop computers to handheld
mobile phones.  In response to this demand, HTML has been both
reformulated into XML and modularized into a family of modules (see
<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-modularization"/>) with semantically related elements. This
family includes two Table Modules: the Basic Tables Module (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-modularization/xhtml-modularization.html#s_simpletablemodule"/>) and the Tables
Module (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-modularization/xhtml-modularization.html#s_tablemodule"/>). The Tables
Module mimics the functionality of HTML 4 (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/html401/"/>)
tables and is a part of the XHTML 1.1 (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml11"/>)
document type. The Basic Tables Module is a
<soCalled>diluted</soCalled> version of the Tables Module, retaining
only the minimal functionality with the purpose of extending XHTML's
reach onto resource-constrained devices. It is a part of the XHTML
Basic document type (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xhtml-basic"/>).</p>-->
	<p>The XHTML table model (<ptr target="#XHTML"/>) is based on the HTML table model
	(<ptr target="#HTML4"/>). Both models support
	arrangement of arbitrary data into rows and columns of
	cells. Table rows and columns may be grouped to convey
	additional structural information and may be rendered by user
	agents in ways that emphasize this structure. Support for
	incremental rendering of tables and for rendering on
	<soCalled>non-visual</soCalled> user agents <!-- (<ptr
	target="http://www.w3.org/TR/html4/struct/tables.html#non-visual-rendering"/>)-->
	is also available. Special elements and attributes are
	provided to associate metadata with tables. They indicate the
	table's purpose, or are for the benefit of people using speech
	or Braille-based user agents. Tables are not recommended for
	use purely as a means to lay out document content, as this
	leads to many accessibility problems (see further <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/WCAG10-HTML-TECHS/#tables"/>).
	Stylesheets provide a far more effective means of controlling
	layout and other visual characteristics in both HTML and XML
	documents.
</p>
 </div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FTFOR"><head>Formulæ and
Mathematical Expressions</head>
<p>Mathematical and chemical formulæ pose  problems similar to
those posed by tables in that rendition may be of great significance and
hard to disentangle from content.  They also require access to a wide
range of special characters, for most of which standard entity names
already exist in the documented ISO entity sets (see further chapters <ptr target="#CH"/>
 and <ptr target="#WD"/>).
 </p>
<p>Formulæ and tables are also similar in that well-researched and
detailed DTD fragments have already been developed for them
independently of the TEI.  They differ in that (for mathematics at
least) there also exists a richly detailed text-based but non-XML
notation which is very widely used:  this is the TeX system, and the
sets of descriptive macros developed for it such as LaTeX, AMS-TeX,
and AMS-LaTeX.
 </p>
<p>The AAP and ISO standards mentioned in section <ptr target="#FTTAB"/> above both provide DTDs for equations as well as for
tables, which now form part of ISO 12083.  The European Mathematical
Trust, an organization set up specifically to enhance research support
for European mathematicians, has also defined a general purpose
mathematical DTD known as EuroMath (<ptr target="http://www.dcs.fmph.uniba.sk/~emt/"/>), for which it provides
both software and services.
</p>
<p>Most if not all of the functionality provided by these DTDs can now
be found in the OpenMath and MathML XML-based systems briefly
described below.
</p>
<p>As with tables, in all the XML solutions a tension exists between
the need to encode the way a formula is written (its appearance) and the
need to represent its semantics.  If the object of the encoding is
purely to act as an interchange format among different formatting
programs, then there is no need to represent the mathematical meaning of
an expression.  If however the object is to use the encoding as
input to an algebraic manipulation system (such as Mathematica or Maple)
or a database system, clearly simply representing superscripts and subscripts
will be inadequate.
 </p>
<p>The present Guidelines make no attempt to add to the number of
available DTDs for representing formulæ.  Instead, we recommend
that the user make an informed choice from those already available.  The
module described in this chapter makes available only the
following element, which should be used to encode any formula, no matter
what notation is employed:
<specList><specDesc key="formula" atts="notation"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>By default, a <gi>formula</gi> is assumed to
contain character data which is not validated in any way:
 <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><formula notation="TeX">$e=mc^2$</formula></egXML>
The character data must still be well-formed, of course, which means that <mentioned>&lt;</mentioned> and
<mentioned>&amp;</mentioned> must be escaped with entity references or numeric character references, e.g.
 <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><formula notation="TeX">$\matrix{0 &amp;amp; 1\cr&amp;lt;0&amp;amp;&gt;1}$</formula></egXML>
</p>
<p>If desired, the content of the <gi>formula</gi> element may be
redefined to include elements defined by some other module, such as
that of ISO 12083, or to use elements from the more recently defined OpenMath or
MathML schemas.<!--note place="bottom">In this case additional redefinitions
may also be needed to avoid name clashes with existing TEI elements.
For further details see chapter <ptr target="#MD"/>.</note-->
 </p>
<p>When the content of a <gi>formula</gi> element is not expressed in
XML the notation used should be
specified using the <att>notation</att> attribute as above,
and in the following longer example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#FTFOR-eg-10"><p>Achilles runs ten times faster than the tortoise and
gives the animal a headstart of ten meters.  Achilles runs
those ten meters, the tortoise one; Achilles runs that
meter, the tortoise runs a decimeter; Achilles runs that
decimeter, the tortoise runs a centimeter; Achilles runs
that centimeter, the tortoise, a millimeter; Fleet-footed
Achilles, the millimeter, the tortoise, a tenth of a
millimeter, and so on to infinity, without the tortoise ever
being overtaken. . . Such is the customary version.
<!-- ... -->
The problem does not change, as you can see; but I would
like to know the name of the poet who provided it with a
hero and a tortoise.  To those magical competitors and to
the series
<formula notation="TeX">$$
{1 \over 10} +
{1 \over 100} +
{1 \over 1000} +
{1 \over 10,\!000} +
\dots
$$</formula>
the argument owes its fame.</p></egXML>
The <att>notation</att> attribute supplies the name of a
notation (<q>TeX</q>), which is expected to be identified somewhere
in document metadata. </p>
<p>Mathematical Markup Language (MathML)
(<ptr target="#MATHML"/>) is a vocabulary for describing
mathematical notation, capturing both its structure and
content. <!--MathML 1.0, which became a W3C Recommendation on April 7
1998, was the first vocabulary based on XML syntax to reach that
status. It was subsequently revised, as MathML 1.01 (W3C
Recommendation July 7, 1999), and as the current version MathML 2.0,
which became a W3C recommendation on February 21, 2001.</p>
<p>MathML--> It  provides two types of markup: Presentation Markup, which
captures the <hi>notational</hi> structure of an expression and could
be seen as the <soCalled>TeX for the Web</soCalled> and Content
Markup, which captures the <hi>mathematical</hi> structure of an
expression. Most of its content elements correspond with the range of
operators, relations, and named functions typically found at the
high-school level of mathematics. The tortoise example given above
in TeX can be re-expressed in MathML as
 <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"> 
   <mfrac>
      <mrow> <mn>1</mn> </mrow> 
      <mrow> <mn>10</mn> </mrow>
   </mfrac> 
   <mo>+</mo>
   <mfrac>
      <mrow> <mn>1</mn> </mrow>
      <mrow> <mn>100</mn> </mrow>
   </mfrac> 
   <mo>+</mo>
   <mfrac>
      <mrow> <mn>1</mn> </mrow> 
      <mrow> <mn>1000</mn> </mrow>
   </mfrac> 
   <mo>+</mo>
   <mfrac>
      <mrow> <mn>1</mn> </mrow> 
      <mrow> <mn>10000</mn> </mrow>
   </mfrac> 
   <mo>+</mo> 
   <mo>…</mo>
</math></egXML>
</p>
  <p>MathML 2.0 provides support for a <soCalled>Semantic
Math-Web</soCalled>,  XML namespaces, and
other current XML standards, such as XML DOM, OMG IDL, ECMAScript, and
Java. It also provides a modularized version of the MathML DTD so that
MathML fragments <soCalled>embedded</soCalled> in XHTML 1.1 documents
<!-- as data islands --> can be correctly validated.</p>

<p>The OpenMath (<ptr target="http://www.nag.co.uk/projects/OpenMath.html"/>) project is
coordinated by the OpenMath Society (<ptr target="http://www.openmath.org/"/>) and funded by the European
Commission under the Esprit Multimedia Standards Initiative that
commenced in September 1997. It is likely to become a key standard for
communicating semantically rich representations of mathematical
objects both on and off the Web in a platform-independent manner.</p>

<p>The OpenMath Standard (<ptr target="http://www.openmath.org/V2/standard/index.html"/>) consists of
specifications for
<list type="ordered">
<item>OpenMath objects, representing the structure of formulæ (<ptr
target="http://www.openmath.org/standard/om20-2004-06-30/omstd20html-2.xml#cha_obj"/>);</item>

<item>Content Dictionaries, providing semantic context (<ptr target="http://www.openmath.org/standard/om20-2004-06-30/omstd20html-4.xml#cha_cd"/>);</item>
<item>Encodings, both binary (<ptr target="http://www.openmath.org/standard/om20-2004-06-30/omstd20html-3.xml#sec_binary"/>) and
XML (<ptr target="http://www.openmath.org/standard/om20-2004-06-30/omstd20html-3.xml#sec_xml"/>).</item></list></p>

<p>OpenMath and MathML have certain common aspects. They both use
prefix operators, both are XML-based and they both construct their
objects by applying certain rules recursively. Such similarities
facilitate mapping between the two standards. There are also some key
differences between MathML and OpenMath. OpenMath does not provide
support for presentation of mathematical objects and its scope of
semantically-oriented elements is much broader that of MathML, with
the expressive power to cover virtually all areas of computational
mathematics. In fact, a particular set of Content Dictionaries, the
<soCalled>MathML CD Group</soCalled>, covers the same areas of
mathematics as the Content Markup elements of MathML 2.0.</p>
<p>Finally, OMDoc (<ptr target="http://omdoc.org/"/>) is
an extension of the OpenMath standard that supplies markup for
structures such as axioms, theorems, proofs, definitions, texts
(mixing formal content with mathematical text). </p>
<p>In-line versus block placement for an equation can be distinguished
if desired, via the global <att>rend</att> attribute.  The global
<att>n</att> and <att>xml:id</att> attributes may also be used to
label or identify the formula, as in the following 
example:<!--note place="bottom">We do not show here how elements from the
MathML namespace may be included in a TEI document; see further
discussion at .</note-->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>The volume of a
sphere is given by the formula:
<formula xml:id="f12" n="12" rend="inline">
  <math xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML">
   <mi>V</mi>
   <mo>=</mo>
   <mfrac>
      <mrow> <mn>4</mn> </mrow>
      <mrow> <mn>3</mn> </mrow>
   </mfrac>
   <mi>π</mi>
   <msup>
      <mrow> <mi>r</mi> </mrow>
      <mrow> <mn>3</mn> </mrow>
   </msup>
 </math>

</formula>
which is readily calculated.</p>
<p>As we have seen in equation 
<ptr target="#f12"/>, ... </p></egXML>
 </p>

<specGrp xml:id="DFTFOR" n="Formulæ">







<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/formula.xml"/>





</specGrp>
</div>
  
  <div type="div2" xml:id="FTNM">
    <head>Notated music in written text</head>
    
    <p>Music, like many other art forms, is often mentioned, discussed and described in
      writings of various kinds. This applies to both historical and contemporary
      documents, even though methods of notating music have changed considerably in
      western history. In most cases, music notation enters the text flow in a way
      similar to figures, images or graphs. On other occasions, elements of music
      notation are treated as inline characters in running text.</p>
    
    <p><gi>notatedMusic</gi>provides a way to
      signal the presence of music notation in text, but defer to other
      representations, which are not covered by
      the TEI guidelines, to describe the music notation itself. In fact, several 
      commercial, academic and standard bodies
      have developed digital representations of music notation, and given the topic's
      complexity, these representations often focus on different aspects and adopt
      different methodologies. Therefore, <gi>notatedMusic</gi> only defines a container element to encode the occurrence
      of music notation and allows linking to the data format preferred by the
      encoder. (Note: <gi>notatedMusic</gi> is not the same as <gi>musicNotation</gi>, a metadata element, which is used to describe musical notation that appears in a manuscript. See <ptr target="#MS"/>.)</p>
    
    <p>The following elements can be used for encoding music notation in text:
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="notatedMusic"/>
        <specDesc key="ptr"/>
        <specDesc key="desc"/>
        <specDesc key="graphic"/>
        <specDesc key="binaryObject"/>
      </specList>
    </p>
    
    
    <list rend="specList">
      <item>
        <label><gi>notatedMusic</gi></label> groups elements representing or
        containing music notation.</item>
      <item>
        <label><gi>ptr</gi></label> can be used to indicate the location of a
        representation of the music notation.
        <list>
          <item><att>mimeType</att> supplies the MIME type of the data
            format, when available.</item>
        </list>
      </item>
      <item>
        <label><gi>desc</gi></label> can be used to give a prose description of the
        notated music.</item>
      <item>
        <label><gi>graphic</gi></label> can be used to indicate the location of a
        graphical representation of the music notation.</item>
      <item>
        <label><gi>binaryObject</gi></label> provides encoded binary data
        which constitutes another representation of the music notation (e.g. audio).</item>
    </list>
    
    <p>The <gi>notatedMusic</gi> element may contain a
      textual description and pointers to various representations of the music
      notation in different media. An external representation of the notated music is
      specified using the <gi>ptr</gi> element, whose <att>target</att> attribute provides its
      electronically-accessible location.
      The attribute <att>mimeType</att> supplies the MIME type of the data format when
      available.
      For example:</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.xml"/>
</notatedMusic></egXML>
    
    <p>A textual description of the notation can be provided within the <gi>desc</gi> element;
      alternatively, a <gi>label</gi> may be supplied. For example:</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.xml"/>
  <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39</desc>
</notatedMusic></egXML>
    
    <p>It is possible to link to any kind of music notation data format.
      However, when a
      MIME type is not available, it is
      recommended that the format be specified in the description. See the following examples.</p>
    
    <p>MIME type available:</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.xml" mimeType="application/vnd.recordare.musicxml"/>
  <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39. Encoded in MusicXML.</desc>
</notatedMusic></egXML>
    
    <p>MIME type not available:</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.ly"/>
  <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39. Encoded in Lilypond.</desc>
</notatedMusic></egXML>
    
    <p>Application format:</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.mscz" mimeType="application/x-musescore"/>
  <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39. MuseScore Notation Software format.</desc>
</notatedMusic></egXML>
    
    <p>It is possible to specify the location of digital objects representing the
      notated music in other media such as images or audio-visual files. The
      interpretation of the correspondence between the notated music and these digital
      objects is not encoded explicitly. We recommend the use of <gi>graphic</gi> and
      <gi>binaryObject</gi> mainly as a fallback mechanism when the notated music format is not
      displayable by the application using the encoding. The alignment of encoded
      notated music, images carrying the notation, and audio files is a complex matter
      for which we refer the reader to other formats and specifications such as <ref
        target="http://www.interactivemusicnetwork.org/mpeg-ahg/">MPEG-SMR</ref>.</p>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><notatedMusic>
    <ptr target="bar1.xml"/>
    <graphic url="bar1.jpg"/>
    <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39</desc>
  </notatedMusic></egXML>
    
    
    <p>In modern printing, music notation positioned between blocks of text for
      illustrative purposes is usually referred to as a <q>figure</q> or <q>example</q>. In this
      cases, we recommend the inclusion of <gi>notatedMusic</gi> in <gi>figure</gi> 
      in order to encode possible captions and headers. For
      example:</p>
    
    <figure>
      <figDesc>Example from: <bibl>
        <author>Prout, E.</author> (<date when="1899">1899</date>). <title>The
          orchestra.</title>
      </bibl></figDesc>
      <graphic url="Images/prout-ex1.jpg"/>
    </figure>
    
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div n="67">
   <p>
      We now give some examples, from the works of the great masters, 
      of some of the most frequently used bowings.
   </p>
							
   <figure n="Ex. 3">
      <head>SCHUBERT: Symphony in B minor.</head>
      <notatedMusic> 
         <ptr target="example_schubert.xml"/> 
      </notatedMusic> 
   </figure> 
 </div> 
    </egXML>
<specGrp xml:id="DFTNTM">    
    
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/notatedMusic.xml"/>

</specGrp>

  </div>
  
<div type="div2" xml:id="FTGRA"><head>Specific Elements for Graphic Images</head>
<p>The following special purpose elements are used to indicate the presence of graphic images within a document:
<specList>
<specDesc key="figure"/>
<specDesc key="graphic"/>
<specDesc key="binaryObject"/>
<specDesc key="figDesc"/></specList>
</p>

<p>The <gi>graphic</gi> and <gi>binaryObject</gi> elements form part
of the common core module, and are discussed in section <ptr target="#COGR"/>.
</p>
<p>The <gi>figure</gi> element is used to contain images, captions,
and textual descriptions of the pictures.  The images themselves are
specified using the <gi>graphic</gi> element, whose <att>url</att>
attribute provides the location of an image.  For example: <egXML
xml:lang="und"
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><figure><graphic
url="Fig1.pdf"/></figure></egXML></p>

<p>Three kinds of content may be supplied inside a <gi>figure</gi> element: the
element <gi>head</gi> may be used to transcribe (or supply) a
descriptive heading or title for the graphic itself as in this
example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><figure><graphic url="Fig1.pdf"/><head>The View from the
Bridge</head></figure></egXML></p>
<p>Figures are often accompanied not only by a title or heading, but
by a paragraph or so of commentary or caption. One or more <gi>p</gi> or <gi>ab</gi>
elements <!-- following the <gi>head</gi> --> may be used to transcribe any
caption or discussion of the figure in the source:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#FTGRA-eg-16"><figure><graphic url="pullman.png"/>
  <head>Above:</head>
  <p>The drawing room of the Pullman house, the white and gold saloon
    where the magnate delighted in giving receptions for several
    hundred people.</p>
  <figDesc>The figure shows an elaborately decorated room, at least
    twenty-five feet side to side and fifty feet long, with ornate
    mouldings and Corinthian columns on the walls, overstuffed
    armchairs and loveseats arranged in several conversational
    groupings, and two large chandeliers.</figDesc>
</figure></egXML>
<!-- David Lowe, Lost Chicago (Boston:  Houghton Mifflin, 1978), -->
	<!-- p. 30 top.  Ex libris Wendy Plotkin.                     -->
Here, the figure contains a heading <q>Above</q> which is complemented
by a paragraph of description <q>The drawing room ... several hundred
people</q>. Both of these 
are transcribed from the source, while the description is provided by
the encoder, for use by applications which cannot display the graphic
directly. In documents created in electronic form with the needs of
print-handicapped readers in mind, the <gi>figDesc</gi> element may be
provided by the author rather than a subsequent encoder.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><figure><graphic url="Fig1.jpg"/>
  <head>Figure One: The View from the Bridge</head>
  <figDesc>A Whistleresque view showing four
    or five sailing boats in the foreground, and a
    series of buoys strung out between them.</figDesc>
</figure></egXML></p>
<p>Where the graphic itself contains large amounts of text, perhaps
with a complex structure, and perhaps difficult to distinguish from
the graphic, the encoder should choose whether to regard the graphic
as containing the text (in which case, a nested <gi>floatingText</gi>
element may be included within the <gi>figure</gi> element) or to
regard the enclosed text as being a separate division of the
<gi>text</gi> element in which the graphic appears. In this latter
case, an appropriate <gi>div</gi> or <gi>div1</gi> (etc.) element may
be used for the text represented within the graphic, and the
<gi>figure</gi> element embedded within it. The choice will depend to
a large degree on the encoder's understanding of the relationship
between the graphic and the surrounding text.</p>
<p>A figure which is internally divided, or contains sub-figures, may
be encoded with nested <gi>figure</gi> elements, as in the following example.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#FTGRA-eg-18">
  <figure n="6.45">
    <figure n="a">
      <graphic url="./figs/6.45a.png"/>
      <ab type="caption">Parallel</ab>
    </figure>
    <figure n="b">
      <graphic url="./figs/6.45b.png"/>
      <ab type="caption">Perspective</ab>
    </figure>
    <ab type="caption">The two canonical view volumes, for the (a) parallel
    and (b) perspective projections. Note that -z is to the right.</ab>
  </figure>
</egXML>
<!-- Foley, van Dam, Feiner, & Hughes. _Computer Graphics: Principles and Practice_, 2nd ed., p. 259 -->
</p>
<p>Like any other element in the TEI scheme, figures may be given
identifiers so that they can be aligned with other elements, and
linked to or from them, as described in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.
Some common examples are discussed briefly here; full information is
provided in that chapter.</p>
<p>It is often desirable to maintain two versions of an image in an
electronic file: one a low resolution or
<soCalled>thumbnail</soCalled> version which, when selected by the
user, causes the other, high resolution, version to be accessed. In
TEI terms, the thumbnail image acts as a <term>reference</term> to the
other. Supposing that a thumbnail
version of the  figure discussed above is available as <ident type="file">fig1th.png</ident>, we might embed a reference to the
image using the simple <gi>ref</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#COXR"/>: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><ref target="#IM1">Click here
  <graphic url="fig1th.png"/>
  for enlightenment
</ref>
<figure xml:id="IM1"><graphic url="fig1.jpg"/></figure>
</egXML></p>
<p>Another common requirement is to associate part or the whole of an
image with a textual element not necessarily contiguous to it in the
text; this is sometimes known as a <term>callout</term>. When the
module for transcription is included in a schema, specific attributes
for parts of a text and parts (or all) of a digital image are
available; these are discussed in <ptr target="#PHFAX"/>.  In
addition, chapter <ptr target="#SA"/> may be consulted for other
mechanisms available for this purpose. </p>
<p>The following example assumes that we
wish to associate one portion of the image held as <q>fig1</q> with
chapter two of some text, and another portion of it with chapter
three. The application may be thought of as a hypertext browser in
which the user selects from a graphic image which part of a text to
read next, but the mechanism is independent of this particular
application.</p>

<p>The first requirement is some way of identifying and hence pointing
to sub-parts of a graphic image. This may be done by pointing into an
XML graphic representation, for example an SVG file. Thus <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><ptr xml:id="PD1" target="Fig1.svg#object1"/> <ptr xml:id="PD2" target="Fig1.svg#object2"/></egXML></p>

<p>These <gi>ptr</gi> elements identify two areas within the image
<q>Fig1</q> by pointing at elements inside the XML file <ident type="file">Fig1.svg</ident>, which contains the following.

 <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<svg xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" width="8cm" height="3cm" viewBox="2 1 8 3">
 <g id="object1">
  <ellipse style="fill: #ffffff" cx="3.875" cy="3.025" rx="1.175" ry="1.175"/>
 </g>
 <g id="object2">
  <rect style="fill: #a81616" x="7.8" y="1.9" width="2.17581" height="2.24833"/>
</g>
</svg>

</egXML>
</p>
<p>The next requirement is some way of identifying the parts of the
document to which a link is to be made. The most obvious way of doing
this is to use the global <att>xml:id</att> attribute:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div1 type="chapter" xml:id="CHAP1">
  <!-- ... -->
</div1>
<div1 type="chapter" xml:id="CHAP2">
  <!-- ... -->
</div1></egXML></p>
<p>Now, all that is needed to linking these areas to the relevant
chapters is a <gi>linkGrp</gi> element, as described in section <ptr target="#SAPT"/>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><linkGrp type="callout">
  <link target="#CHAP1 #PD1"/>
  <link target="#CHAP2 #PD2"/>
</linkGrp></egXML>
</p>
<p>In this example, the SVG representation of the graphic is stored
externally to the TEI document and linked by means of a pointer. It is
also possible to embed the SVG representation directly within the TEI
by extending the content model of the <gi>figure</gi> element to
permit an element <gi scheme="SVG">svg</gi> from the SVG namespace. Like other
customizations of the TEI scheme, this is carried out using the
techniques documented in section <ptr target="#STIN"/>; further
examples are provided in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.</p>

<!-- should add some way of doing the same thing using zones -->


<specGrp xml:id="DFTGRA" n="Figures">







<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/figure.xml"/>












<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/figDesc.xml"/>





</specGrp></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FTGROV"><head>Overview of Basic Graphics Concepts</head>
<p>The first major distinction in graphic representation is that between
raster graphics and vector graphics.  A <term>raster image</term> is a
list of points, or dots.  Scanners, fax machines and other simple
devices easily produce digital raster images, and such images are
therefore quite common.  A <term>vector image</term>, in contrast, is a
list of geometrical objects, such as lines, circles, arcs, or even
cubes.  These are much more difficult to produce, and so are mainly
encountered as the output of sophisticated systems such as architectural
and engineering CAD programs.</p>
<p>Raster images are difficult to modify because by definition they only
encode single points:  a line, for example, cannot grow or shrink as
such, since it is not identified as such.  Only its component parts are
identified, and only they can be manipulated.  Therefore the resolution
or dot-size of a raster image is important, which is not the case with
vector images.  It is also far more difficult to convert raster images
to vector images than to perform the opposite conversion.  Raster images
generally require more storage space than vector images, and a wide
variety of methods exists for compressing them; the variation in these
methods leads to corresponding variations in representations for storage
and transmission of raster images.</p>
<p>Motion video usually consists of a long series of raster images.
Data compression is even more effective on video than on single raster
images (mainly owing to redundancy which arises from the usual similarity
of adjacent frames).  Notations for representing full-motion video
are hotly debated at this time, and any user of these Guidelines would
do well to obtain up-to-date expert advice before undertaking a project
using them.</p>
<p>The compression methods used with any of these image types may be
<soCalled>lossy</soCalled> or <soCalled>lossless</soCalled>.  Methods
for <term>lossy compression</term> save space by discarding a small
portion of the image's detail, such as fine distinctions of shading.
When decompressed, therefore, such an image will be only a close
approximation of the original.  In contrast, <term>lossless
compression</term> guarantees that the exact uncompressed image will be
reproducible from the compressed form:  only truly redundant information
is removed. In general, therefore, lossless compression does not save
quite so much space as lossy compression, though it does guarantee
fidelity to the original uncompressed image.</p>
<p>Raster images may be characterized by their <term>resolution</term>,
which is the number of dots per inch used to represent the image.
Doubling the resolution will give a more precise image, but also
quadruple the storage requirement (before compression), and affect
processing time for any operations to be performed, such as displaying
an image for a reader. Motion video also has resolution in time:  the
number of frames to be shown per second.  Encoders should consider
carefully what resolution(s) and frame rate(s) to use for particular
applications; these Guidelines express no recommendation in this matter,
save the universal ones of consistency and documentation.</p>
<p>Within any image, it is typical to refer to locations via Cartesian
coordinate axes: values for x, y, and sometimes z and/or time.
However, graphic notations vary in whether coordinates count from
left-to-right and top-to-bottom, or another way. They also vary in
whether coordinates are considered real (inches, millimeters, and so
on), or virtual (dots). These Guidelines do not recommend any of these
methods over another, but all decisions made should be applied
consistently, and documented in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> section of
the TEI header.<note place="bottom">Since no special purpose element is
provided for this purpose by the current version of the Guidelines,
such information should be provided as one or more distinct paragraphs
at the end of the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element described in section
<ptr target="#HD5"/>.</note></p>
<p>Methods of aligning images and text are discussed in <ptr target="#PHFAX"/>.</p>
<p>The chromatic values of  an image may be rendered in many different ways. In monochrome images every displayed point is either black or
white. In <term>gray-scale</term> images, each point is rendered in
some shade of gray, the number of shades varying from system to system.
In true polychrome images, points are rendered in different hues,
again with varying limitations affecting the number of distinct shades
and the means by which they are displayed.</p></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FTGRNO"><head>Graphic Image Formats</head>

<p>As noted above, there exists a wide variety of different graphics
formats, and the following list is in no way exhaustive.  Moreover,
inclusion of any format in this list should not be taken as indicating
endorsement by the TEI of this format or any products associated with
it. Some of the formats listed here are proprietary to a greater or
lesser extent and cannot therefore be regarded as standards in any
meaningful sense. They are however widely used by many different
vendors.</p>

<p>The following formats are widely used at the present time, and likely to
remain supported by more than one vendor's software:
<list type="simple">
<item>BMP:   Microsoft bitmap format</item>
<item>CGM:  Computer Graphics Metafile</item>
<item>GIF:  Graphics Interchange Format</item>
<item>JPEG:  Joint Photographic Expert Group</item>
<item>PBM:  Portable Bit Map</item>
<item>PCX:  IBM PC raster format</item>
<item>PICT:  Macintosh drawing format</item>
<item>PNG:  Portable Network Graphics format</item>
<item>Photo-CD:  Kodak Photo Compact Disk format</item>
<item>QuickTime:  Apple real-time image system</item>
<item>SMIL: Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language format</item>
<item>SVG: Scalable Vector Graphics format</item>
<item>TIFF:  Tagged Image File Format</item>
</list></p>
<p>Brief descriptions of all the above are given below.  Where possible,
current addresses or other contact information are shown for the
originator of each format.  Many formal standards, especially those
promulgated by ISO and many related national organizations (ANSI, DIN,
BSI, and many more), are available from those national organizations.
Addresses may be found in any standard organizational directory for the
country in question.
	</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FTGRAVGF"><head>Vector Graphic Formats</head>
<list type="gloss"><label>CGM:  Computer Graphics Metafile</label>
<item>This  vector graphics format is
specified by an ISO standard, ISO 8632:1987, amended in 1990.
It defines binary, character, and plain-text encodings;
the non-binary forms are safer for blind interchange,
especially over networks.  Documentation on CGM is available from ISO
and from its member national bodies such as AFNOR, ANSI, BSI, DIN, JIS,
etc.  </item>
<label>SVG:  Scalable Vector Graphics format</label>
<item>SVG is a language for describing two-dimensional vector and 
mixed vector or raster graphics in XML.  
It is defined by the Scalable
Vector Graphics (SVG) 1.0 Specification, W3C Recommendation, 04 September 2001, and is
		available at <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/2001/REC-SVG-20010904/"/>.
</item>
<label>PICT:  Macintosh drawing format</label>
<item>This format is universally supported on Macintosh (tm) systems, and
readable by a limited range of software for other systems.
Documentation is available from Apple Computer Company, Cupertino,
California USA.
 </item></list></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FTGRARGF"><head>Raster Graphic Formats</head>
<list type="gloss">
<label>PNG:  Portable Network Graphics format</label>
<item>PNG is a non-proprietary raster format currently widely
available. It provides an
   extensible file format for the lossless, portable, well-compressed
   storage of raster images. Indexed-color,
   grayscale, and truecolor images are supported, plus an optional alpha
   channel.  Sample depths range from 1 to 16 bits.
   It is defined by IETF RFC 2083, March 1997.
</item>
<label>TIFF:  Tagged Image File Format</label>
<item>Currently the most widely supported raster image format,
especially for black and white images, TIFF is also one of the few
formats commonly supported on more than one operating system.  The
drawback to TIFF is that it actually is a wrapper for several formats,
and some TIFF-supporting software does not support all variants.  TIFF
files may use LZW, CCITT Group 4, or PackBits compression methods, or
may use no compression at all.  Also, TIFF files may be monochrome,
greyscale, or polychromatic.  All such options should be specified in prose at
the end of the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> section of the TEI header for any
document including TIFF images.  TIFF is owned by Aldus Corporation.
Documentation on TIFF is available from them at Craigcook Castle,
Craigcook Road, Edinburgh EH4 3UH, Scotland, or 411 First Avenue
South, Seattle, Washington 98104 USA.
</item><label>GIF:  Graphics Interchange Format</label>
<item>Raster images are widely available in this form, which was
created by CompuServe Information Services, but has by now been
implemented for many other systems as well.  Documentation on GIF is
copyright by, and is available from, CompuServe Incorporated, Graphics
Technology Department, 5000 Arlington Center Boulevard, Columbus, Ohio
43220 USA.
</item><label>PBM:  Portable Bit Map</label>
<item>PBM files are easy to process, eschewing all compression in favor
of transparency of file format.  PBM files can, of course, be compressed
by generic file-compression tools for storage and transfer.  Public
domain software exists which will convert many other formats to and from
PBM.  Documentation on PBM is copyright by Jeff Poskanzer, and is available
widely on the Internet.
</item>
<label>PCX:  IBM PC raster format</label>
<item>This format is used by most IBM PC paint programs, and supports
both monochrome and polychromatic images.  Documentation is available from
ZSoft Corporation, Technical Support Department, ATTN: Technical
Reference Manual, 450 Franklin Rd. Suite 100, Marietta, GA 30067 USA.
 </item>
<label>BMP:   Microsoft bitmap format</label>
<item>This format is the standard raster format for computer using
Microsoft Windows (tm) or Presentation Manager (tm).  Documentation
is available from Microsoft Corporation.
 </item>
 </list></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FTGRAMPEG">
<head>Photographic and Motion Video Formats</head>
<list type="gloss"><label>JPEG:  Joint Photographic Experts Group</label>
<item>This standard is sponsored by CCITT and by ISO.  It is ISO/IEC
Draft International Standard 10918-1, and CCITT T.81.  It handles
monochrome and polychromatic images with a variety of compression techniques.
JPEG per se, like CCITT Group IV, must be encapsulated before
transmission; this can be done via TIFF, or via the JPEG File
Interchange Format (JFIF), as commonly done for Internet delivery.
 </item>
<label>QuickTime:  Apple real-time image system</label>
<item>QuickTime is a proprietary method introduced by Apple Computer
Company to synchronize the display of various data.  The data can
include frames of video, sound, lighting control mechanisms, and other
things.  Viewers for QuickTime productions are available for Apple and
other computers.  Further information is available from Apple Computer
Incorporated, 10201 North de Anza Boulevard MS 23AQ, Cupertino,
California 95014 USA.
</item>
<label>Photo-CD:  Kodak Photo Compact Disk format</label>
<item>This format was introduced by Kodak for rasterizing photographs
and storing them on CD-ROMs (about one hundred 35mm file images fit on
one disk), for display on televisions or CD-I systems.  Information on
Photo-CD is available from Kodak Limited, Research and Development,
Headstone Drive, Harrow, Middlesex HA1 4TY, UK.
</item>
<label>SMIL: Synchronized Multimedia Integration Language
    format</label> <item>SMIL is a W3C Recommendation which supports
    the integration of independent multimedia objects into a
    synchronized multimedia presentation. It provides multimedia
    authors with easily-defined basic timing relationships, fine-tuned
    synchronization, spatial layout, direct inclusion of non-text and
    non-image media objects, hyperlink support for time-based media,
    adaptiveness to varying user and system characteristics.  SMIL 1.0
		(<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-smil/"/>) became a
    W3C Recommendation on June 15, 1998, and was further developed
     in
    SMIL 2.0.  SMIL 2.0 adds native support for transitions,
    animation, event-based interaction, extended layout facilities,
    and more sophisticated timing and synchronization primitives to
    the SMIL 1.0 language. It also allows reuse of SMIL syntax and
    semantics in other XML-based languages, in particular those who
    need to represent timing and synchronization.  For example, SMIL
    2.0 components are used for integrating timing into XHTML Document
    Types and into SVG. SMIL 2.0 also provides recommendations for
		Document Types based on SMIL 2.0 Modules (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/smil-modules.html"/>). One
		such Document Type is the SMIL 2.0 Language Profile (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/smil20-profile.html"/>). It
    contains support for all of the major SMIL 2.0 features including
    animation, content control, layout, linking, media object,
    meta-information, structure, timing, and transition effects and is
    designed for Web clients that support direct playback from SMIL
		2.0 markup.  SMIL 2.0 (<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/smil20/"/>) became a W3C
    Recommendation on August 7, 2001, becoming the first vocabulary to
    provide XML Schema support and to have reached such status.
</item>
</list>
<p>As noted above, the reader will encounter many, many other graphics
formats.  
</p></div></div>
<div><head>Module for Tables, Formulæ, Notated Music, and Graphics</head>
<p>The module described in this chapter provides the following features:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DFTFF" ident="figures">
<altIdent type="FPI">Tables, Formulæ, Notated Music, Figures</altIdent>
<desc>Tables, formulæ, notated music, and figures</desc>
<desc xml:lang="fr">Tableaux, formules et graphiques</desc>
<desc xml:lang="zh-TW">表格、方程式與圖表</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Tabelle, formule e figure</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Tabelas, fórmulas, e figuras</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">図表式モジュール</desc></moduleSpec>

The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.

<specGrpRef target="#DFTTAB"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DFTFOR"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DFTNTM"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DFTGRA"/>
</p>
</div>
</div>
