<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="ND" n="20">

<head>Names, Dates, People, and Places</head>

<p>This chapter describes a module which may be used for the encoding
of names and other phrases descriptive of persons, places, or
organizations, in a manner more detailed than that possible using the
elements already provided for these purposes in the Core module. In
section <ptr target="#CONA"/> it was noted that the elements provided
in the core module allow an encoder to specify that a given text
segment is a proper noun, or a <term>referring string</term>, and to
specify the kind of object named or referred to only by supplying a
value for the <att>type</att> attribute.  The elements provided by the
present module allow the encoder to supply a detailed
sub-structure for such referring strings, and to distinguish
explicitly between names of persons, places, and organizations.</p>

<p>This module also provides elements for the representation of
information about the person, place, or organization to which a given
name is understood to refer and to represent the name itself,
independently of its application. In simple terms, where the core
module allows one simply to represent that a given piece of text is a
<term>name</term>, this module allows one further to represent a
<term>personal name</term>, to represent the <term>person</term> being
named, and to represent the <term>canonical name</term> being used.  A
similar range is provided for names of places and organizations. The
main intended applications for this module are in biographical, historical,
or geographical data systems such as gazetteers and biographical
databases, where these are to be integrated with encoded texts.</p>

<p>The chapter begins by discussing attributes common to many of the
elements discussed in the remaining parts of the chapter (<ptr
target="#NDATTS"/>) before discussing specifically the elements
provided for the encoding of component parts of personal names
(section <ptr target="#NDPER"/>), place names (section <ptr
target="#NDPLAC"/>) and organizational names (section <ptr
target="#NDORG"/>).  Elements for encoding personal and organizational
data are discussed in section <ptr target="#NDPERS"/>.  Elements for
the encoding of geographical data are discussed in section <ptr
target="#NDGEOG"/>.  Finally, elements for encoding onomastic data are
discussed in <ptr target="#NDNYM"/>, and the detailed encoding of
dates and times is described in section <ptr target="#NDDATE"/>.</p>



<div xml:id="NDATTS"><head>Attribute Classes Defined by this
Module</head>
<p>Most of the elements made available by this chapter share some
important characteristics which are expressed by their membership in
specific attribute classes. Members of the class <ident type="class">att.naming</ident> have specialized attributes which
support linkage of a naming element with the entity (person, place,
organization) being named; members of the class <ident type="class">att.datable</ident> have specialized attributes which
support a number of ways of  normalizing the date or time of the data
encoded by the element concerned.</p>

<div xml:id="NDATTSnr"><head>Linking Names and their Referents</head>

<p>The class  <ident type="class">att.naming</ident> is a
subclass of the class <ident type="class">att.canonical</ident>, from
which it
inherits the following attributes:
<specList><specDesc key="att.canonical" atts="key ref"/></specList>
As discussed elsewhere, these attributes provide two 
different ways of associating any sort of name with its referent. For
cases where all that is required is to provide some minimal information about
the person name, for example their occupation or status, the
<ident>att.naming</ident> class also provides a simple
<att>role</att> attribute. It also  provides an
additional attribute, which allows the name itself to be associated
with a base or canonical form:
<specList><specDesc key="att.naming" atts="role nymRef"/></specList>

The encoder may use these attributes in combination as appropriate. For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That silly man
<name role="politician" type="person">David Paul Brown</name> has suffered ...</egXML>
The <att>ref</att> attribute should be used wherever it is possible to supply
a direct link such as a URI to indicate the location of canonical
information about the referent. 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That silly man
<name ref="#DPB1" type="person">David Paul Brown</name> has suffered ...</egXML>
This encoding requires that there exist somewhere 
a <gi>person</gi> element with the identifier <code>DPB1</code>, which
will contain canonical information about this particular person,
marked up using the elements discussed in <ptr target="#NDPERS"/>
below. The same element might alternatively be provided by some other document,
of course, which the same attribute could refer to by means of a URI,
as  explained in <ptr target="#SAXP"/>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That silly man
<name ref="http://www.example.com/personography.xml#DPB1" type="person">David Paul Brown</name> has suffered
...</egXML>More than one URI may be supplied if the name refers to
more than one person. For example, assuming the existence of another
<gi>person</gi> element for Mrs Brown, with identifier
<code>EBB1</code>, a reference to <q>the Browns</q> might be encoded
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That wretched pair
<name ref="#DPB1 #EBB1" type="person">the Browns</name> came to dine
...</egXML>
</p>

<p>The <att>key</att> attribute is provided for cases where no such
direct link is required: for example because resolution of the reference is
carried out by some local convention, or because the encoder judges
that no such resolution is necessary. As an example of the first case,
a project might maintain its own local database system
containing canonical information about persons and places, each entry
in which is accessed by means of some system-specific identifier
constructed in a project-specific way from the value supplied for the
<att>key</att> attribute.<note place="bottom">In the module described by
chapter <ptr target="#TD"/> a similar method is used to link element
descriptions to the modules or classes to which they belong, for
example.</note> As an example of the second case, consider the use of
well-established codifications such as country or airport codes, which
it is probably  unnecessary for an encoder to expand further:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
I never fly from <name key="LHR" type="place">Heathrow Airport</name>
to <name key="FR" type="place">France</name></egXML>
</p>

<p>However, as explained in <ptr target="#CONARS"/>, interchange is 
improved by use of tag URIs in <att>ref</att> instead of <att>key</att>.
</p>

<p>The <att>nymRef</att> attribute has a more specialized use, where
it is the name itself which is of interest rather than the person,
place, or organization being named. See section <ptr target="#NDNYM"/>
for further discussion.</p>

<p>Some members of the <ident type="class">att.naming</ident> class
are also members of the <ident type="class">att.responsibility</ident>
class, from which they inherit the following attributes:
<specList><specDesc key="att.responsibility" atts="resp cert"/></specList>
This enables an encoder to record the agency responsible for a given
assertion (for example, the name) and the confidence placed in that
assertion by the encoder.



Examples are given below.</p>
<!-- or maybe they should be here -->
</div>

<div xml:id="NDATTSda"><head>Dating Attributes</head>

<p>Members of the <ident type="class">att.datable</ident> class
share the following attributes:
  <specList>
    <specDesc key="att.datable" atts="period"/>
    <specDesc key="att.datable.w3c" atts="when notBefore notAfter from to"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>The <att>when</att> attribute is used to specify a normalized form
for any temporal expression, independently of how it is represented
in the text, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDORG-eg-34"><date when="1807-06-09">June 9th</date> The
period is approaching which will terminate my present
copartnership. On the <date when="1808-01-01">1st Jany.</date> next,
it expires by its own limitation.</egXML>
</p>
<p>The <att>period</att> attribute provides a convenient way of
associating an event or date with a named period. Its value is a
pointer which should indicate some other element where the period
concerned is more precisely defined. A convenient location for such
definitions is the <gi>taxonomy</gi> element in the <gi>classDecl</gi>
(classification declaration) in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of a TEI
Header. A <gi>taxonomy</gi> may contain simply a bibliographic
reference to an external definition for it. More usefully, it may also
contain a series of <gi>category</gi> elements, each with an
identifier and a description. The identifier can then be used as the
target for a <att>period</att> attribute. For example, a taxonomy of named periods might be defined as
follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<taxonomy xml:id="greekperiods">
<category xml:id="tyranny">
<catDesc>Before 510 BC</catDesc></category>
<category xml:id="classical">
<catDesc>Between 510 and 323 BC</catDesc></category>
          <category xml:id="hellenistic">
            <catDesc>
              <ref target="http://www.wikipedia.com/wiki/Hellenistic"
                >Hellenistic</ref>. Commonly treated as 
	      <date notBefore="-0323" notAfter="-0031">from 
	      the death of Alexander to the Roman conquest.</date>
            </catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="roman">
            <catDesc>
              <ref target="http://www.wikipedia.com/wiki/Roman_Empire"
              >Roman</ref>
            </catDesc>
          </category>
          <category xml:id="christian">
            <catDesc> The Christian period technically starts at the
	    birth of Jesus, but in
	    practice is considered to date from the conversion of Constantine
	    in <date when="0312">312 AD</date>. </catDesc>
          </category>
        </taxonomy>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>With these definitions in place, any datable event may be
associated with a specific period:
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="und">
<placeName period="#christian">Stauropolis</placeName></egXML></p>
<p>The other dating attributes provided by this class support a wide
range of methods of specifying temporal information in a normalized
form. Some simple examples follow:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<birth when="1857-03-15">15 March 1857.</birth> 
</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<birth notBefore="1857-03-01" notAfter="1857-04-30">Some time 
in March or April of 1857.</birth> 
</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<residence from="1857-03-01" to="1857-04-30">In March and April of 1857.</residence> 
</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<residence from="1857-03-01" notAfter="1857-04-30">From the 1st of March to
some time in April of 1857.</residence>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>Normalization of date and time values permits the efficient
processing of data (for example, to determine whether one event
precedes or follows another). These examples all use the W3C standard
format for representation of dates and times. Further examples, and
discussion of some alternative approaches to normalization are given
in section <ptr target="#NDDATEISO"/> below. </p>
<!-- need reference to something on date normalization issues here -->
</div>

</div>

<div xml:id="NDNA"><head>Names</head>

<div type="div2" xml:id="NDPER"><head>Personal Names</head>

<p>The core <gi>rs</gi> and <gi>name</gi> elements can distinguish
names in a text but are insufficiently powerful to mark their internal
components or structure. To conduct nominal record linkage or even to
create an alphabetically sorted list of personal names, it is
important to distinguish between a family name, a forename and an
honorary title. Similarly, when confronted with a string
such as <q>John, by the grace of God, king of England, lord of
Ireland, duke of Normandy and Aquitaine, and count of Anjou</q>, the
analyst will often wish to distinguish amongst the various constituent
elements present, since they  provide additional information
about the status, occupation, or residence of the person to whom
the name belongs.  The following elements are provided for these and
related purposes:
<specList><specDesc key="persName"/><specDesc key="surname"/><specDesc key="forename"/><specDesc key="roleName"/><specDesc key="addName"/><specDesc key="nameLink"/><specDesc key="genName"/></specList>
</p>

<p>In addition to the <ident type="class">att.naming</ident>
attributes mentioned above, all of the above elements are members of
the class <ident type="class">att.personal</ident>, and thus share the
following attributes: <specList><specDesc key="att.personal"
atts="full sort"/></specList>
</p>
<p>The <gi>persName</gi> element may be used in preference to the
general <gi>name</gi> element irrespective of whether or not the
components of the personal name are also to be marked. <!--Its
<att>key</att> attribute can be used to provide a linkage between the
name and the person named, in exactly the same way as  on
the <gi>rs</gi> and <gi>name</gi> elements (see section <ptr
target="#CONA"/>).  The tag -->The element <gi>persName</gi> is synonymous with the
element <tag>name type="person"</tag>, except that its <att>type</att>
attribute allows for further subcategorization of the personal name
itself, for example as a <val>married</val>, <val>maiden</val>, <val>pen</val>,
<val>pseudo</val>, or <val>religious</val> name.  Consequently the following
examples are equivalent: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That silly man
<rs ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:DPB1" type="person">David Paul Brown</rs> has suffered the 
furniture of his office to be seized 
the third time for rent.</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That silly man
<rs ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:DPB1" type="person">
  <name>David Paul Brown</name>
</rs> has suffered ...</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That silly man
<name ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:DPB1" type="person">David Paul Brown</name> has suffered ...</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">That silly man
<persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:DPB1">David Paul Brown</persName> has suffered ...</egXML>
</p>
<p>The <gi>persName</gi> element is more powerful than the
<gi>rs</gi> and <gi>name</gi> elements because distinctive name
components occurring within it can be marked as such.
</p>
<p>Many cultures distinguish between a family or inherited
<term>surname</term> and additional personal names, often known as
<term>given names</term>.  These should be tagged using the
<gi>surname</gi> and <gi>forename</gi> elements respectively and may
occur in any order:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>  
   <surname>Roosevelt</surname>,
   <forename>Franklin</forename>
   <forename>Delano</forename>
</persName>
<persName>  
   <forename>Franklin</forename>
   <forename>Delano</forename>
   <surname>Roosevelt</surname>
</persName></egXML>
</p>
<p>The <att>type</att> attribute may be used with both
<gi>forename</gi> and <gi>surname</gi> elements to provide further
culture- or project-specific detail about the name component, for
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName> 
   <forename type="first">Franklin</forename>
   <forename type="middle">Delano</forename>
   <surname>Roosevelt</surname>
</persName>
<persName> 
   <forename type="given">Margaret</forename>
   <forename type="unused">Hilda</forename>
   <surname type="maiden">Roberts</surname>
   <surname type="married">Thatcher</surname>
</persName>
<persName type="religious">Muhammad Ali</persName>
<persName>   
   <forename>Norman</forename>
   <surname type="complex">St John Stevas</surname>
</persName>
</egXML>
Values for the <att>type</att> attribute are not constrained, and may
be chosen as appropriate to the encoding needs of the project. They
may be
used to distinguish different kinds of forename or surname, as well as
to indicate the function a name component fills within the whole. In
this example, we indicate that a surname is toponymic, and also point
to the specific  place name from which it is derived:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<persName>
   <forename>Johan</forename>
  <surname type="toponymic" ref="#dystvold">Dystvold</surname>
 </persName>
<!-- ... -->
<placeName xml:id="dystvold">Dystvold</placeName>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>The value <val>complex</val> was suggested above for the not
uncommon case where the whole of a surname is composed of several
other surname elements. These nested surnames may be individually
tagged as well, together with appropriate type values:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>  
   <forename>Kara</forename>
   <surname type="complex">
    <surname type="paternal">Hattersley</surname>-
    <surname type="maternal">Smith</surname>
   </surname>
</persName></egXML>
</p>
<p>The <att>full</att> attribute may be used to indicate whether a
name is an abbreviation, initials,  or given in full:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName> 
   <forename full="abb">Maggie</forename>
   <surname>Thatcher</surname>
</persName></egXML>

</p>

<p>These elements may be applied as the encoder considers appropriate, including cases where phrases or expressions are used to stand for surnames or forenames, as in the following:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDPER-eg-17"><s><persName>
<forename>Peter</forename> <surname>son of Herbert</surname></persName> gives the king 40 m. for 
having custody of the land and heir of <persName><forename>John</forename> <surname>son of Hugh</surname></persName>...</s></egXML>
</p>

<p>Similarly, patronymics may be treated as forenames, thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDPER-eg-18">... but it remained for
<persName>   
   <forename>Snorri</forename>
   <forename>Sturluson</forename>
</persName>
to combine the two traditions in cyclic form.</egXML>
When a patronymic is used as a surname, however (e.g. by an individual
who otherwise would have no surname, but lives in a culture which
requires surnames), it may be tagged as such:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDPER-eg-18">Even <persName><forename>Finnur</forename>
<surname>Jonsson</surname></persName>
acknowledged the artificiality of the procedure...</egXML>

Alternatively, it may be felt more appropriate to mark a patronymic as a distinct kind of name, neither a forename nor a surname, using the <gi>addName</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDPER-eg-18">
         <persName>
             <forename>Egill</forename>
             <addName type="patronym">Skallagrmsson</addName>
         </persName>
</egXML>
In the following example, the <att>type</att> attribute is used
to distinguish a patronymic from other forenames:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:pn9">  
   <forename sort="2">Sergei</forename>
   <forename sort="3" type="patronym">Mikhailovic</forename>
   <surname sort="1">Uspensky</surname>
</persName></egXML>
</p>


<p>This example also demonstrates the use of the <att>sort</att>
attribute 
common to all members of the <ident type="class">model.persNamePart</ident> class; its effect is to state
the sequence in which <gi>forename</gi> and <gi>surname</gi> elements
should be combined when constructing a sort key for the name.
</p>
<p>Some names include generational or dynastic information, such as
 a number, or phrases such as <q>Junior</q>, or <q>the Elder</q>;
 these qualifications may also be used to distinguish similarly named
 but unrelated people. In either case, the <gi>genName</gi>
element may be used to distinguish such labels from other parts of the name,
as in the following examples:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:HEMA1">  
  <surname>Marques</surname>
  <genName>Junior</genName>,
  <forename>Henrique</forename>
</persName></egXML>
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>  
  <forename>Charles</forename>
  <genName>II</genName>
</persName></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>
  <forename>Rudolf</forename>
  <genName>II</genName>
  <surname type="dynasty">Hapsburg</surname>
</persName></egXML>
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>
  <surname>Smith</surname>
  <genName>Minor</genName>
</persName></egXML>
</p>
<p>It is also often convenient to distinguish phrases (historically
similar to the generational labels mentioned above) used to link parts
of a name together, such as <q>von</q>, <q>of</q>, <q>de</q> etc. It
is often a matter of arbitrary choice whether such components
are regarded as part of the surname or not; the <gi>nameLink</gi>
element is provided as a means of making clear what the correct usage
should be in a given case, as in the following examples:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:DUDO1"> 
   <roleName type="honorific" full="abb">Mme</roleName>
   <nameLink>de la</nameLink>
   <surname>Rochefoucault</surname>
</persName></egXML>
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName>  
   <forename>Walter</forename>
   <surname>de la Mare</surname>
</persName></egXML>
</p>
<p>Finally, the <gi>addName</gi> and <gi>roleName</gi> elements are
used to mark all name components other than those already listed. The
distinction between them is that a <gi>roleName</gi> encloses an
associated name component such as an aristocratic or official title
which exists in some sense independently of its bearer. The
distinction is not always a clear one. As elsewhere, the
<att>type</att> attribute may be used with either element to supply
culture- or application- specific distinctions.  Some typical values
for this attribute for names in the Western European tradition follow:
<list type="gloss"><label><val>nobility</val></label>
<item>An inherited or life-time
 title of nobility such as <mentioned>Lord</mentioned>, <mentioned>Viscount</mentioned>, <mentioned>Baron</mentioned>, etc.</item><label><val>honorific</val></label>
<item>An academic or other honorific prefixed to a name
 e.g. <mentioned>Doctor</mentioned>, <mentioned>Professor</mentioned>, <mentioned>Mrs.</mentioned>, etc.</item><label><val>office</val></label>
<item>Membership of some elected or
 appointed organization such as <mentioned>President</mentioned>, <mentioned>Governor</mentioned>, etc.</item><label><val>military</val></label>
 <item>Military rank such as <mentioned>Colonel</mentioned>.</item><label><val>epithet</val></label>
<item>A traditional descriptive phrase or nick-name such as
<mentioned>The Hammer</mentioned>, <mentioned>The Great</mentioned>,
etc.</item></list> Note, however, that the <term>role</term> a person
has in a given context (such as <mentioned>witness</mentioned>,
<mentioned>defendant</mentioned>, etc. in a legal document) should not
be encoded using the <gi>roleName</gi> element, since this is intended
to mark roles which function as part of a person's name, not the role
of the person bearing the name om general. Information about roles,
occupations, etc. of a person are encoded within the <gi>person</gi>
element discussed below in <ptr target="#NDPERS"/>.</p>
<p>Here are some further examples of the usage of these elements:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:PGK1">
   <roleName type="nobility">Princess</roleName>
   <forename>Grace</forename>
</persName></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:GRMO1" type="pseudo">
   <addName type="honorific">Grandma</addName>
   <surname>Moses</surname>
</persName></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:SLWICL1">
   <roleName type="office">President</roleName>
   <forename>Bill</forename>
   <surname>Clinton</surname>
</persName></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:MOGA1">
   <roleName type="military">Colonel</roleName>
   <surname>Gaddafi</surname>
</persName></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:FRTG1">
   <forename>Frederick</forename>
   <addName type="epithet">the Great</addName>
</persName></egXML>
</p>
<p>A name may have any combination of the above elements:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><persName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:EGBR1">     
   <roleName type="office">Governor</roleName>
   <forename sort="2">Edmund</forename>
   <forename full="init" sort="3">G.</forename>
   <addName type="nick">Jerry</addName>
   <addName type="epithet">Moonbeam</addName>
   <surname sort="1">Brown</surname>
   <genName full="abb">Jr</genName>.
</persName></egXML>
</p>
<p>Although highly flexible, these mechanisms for marking
personal name components will not cater for every personal name, nor
for every processing need.  Where the internal structure of personal
names is highly complex or where name components are
particularly ambiguous, feature structures are recommended as
the most appropriate mechanism to mark and analyze them, as further discussed in chapter <ptr target="#FS"/>.
</p>
</div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="NDORG"><head>Organizational Names</head>
<p>In these Guidelines, we use the term <q>organization</q> for any
named collection of people regarded as a single unit. Typical examples
include institutions such as <soCalled>Harvard
College</soCalled> or <soCalled>the BBC</soCalled> and businesses such as
<soCalled>Apple</soCalled> or <soCalled>Google</soCalled> but also racial or
ethnic groupings or political factions where these are regarded as
forming a single agency such as <soCalled>the Scythians</soCalled> or
<soCalled>the Militant Tendency</soCalled>. Giving a loosely-defined
group of individuals a name often serves a
particular political or social agenda and an analysis of the way such
phrases are constructed and used may therefore be of considerable
importance to the social historian, even where the objective existence
of an <q>organization</q> in this sense is harder to demonstrate than
that of (say) a named person. In the case of businesses or other
formally constituted institutions, the component parts of an
organizational name may help to characterize the organization in terms
of its perceived geographical location, ownership, likely number of
employees, management structure, etc.</p>

<p>Like names of persons or places, organizational names can be marked
up as referring strings or as proper names with the <gi>rs</gi> or
<gi>name</gi> elements respectively.  The element <gi>orgName</gi> is
provided for use where it is desired to distinguish organizational
names more explicitly.  <specList><specDesc key="orgName"/></specList>
This element is a member of the same attribute classes as
<gi>persName</gi>, as discussed above in <ptr target="#NDATTSnr"/>.</p>
<p>The <gi>orgName</gi> element may be used to mark up any form of
organizational name:  
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDORG-eg-34">About a year back, a question of considerable 
interest was agitated in the 
<orgName type="voluntary" ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:PAS1">Pennsyla. Abolition Society</orgName></egXML>

This encoding is equivalent to, but more specific than, either of the
following representations:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">About a year back, a question of considerable 
interest was agitated in the  <rs ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:PAS1" type="org">
<name>Pennsyla. Abolition Society</name></rs>.</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">About a year back, a question of considerable 
interest was agitated in the 
<name ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:PAS1" type="org">Pennsyla. Abolition 
Society</name>.</egXML>
As shown above, like the <gi>rs</gi> and <gi>name</gi> elements, the <gi>orgName</gi>
element has a <att>key</att> attribute with which an external
identifier such as a database key can be assigned to the organization
name, and also a <att>ref</att> attribute which can be used to point
directly to an <gi>org</gi> element containing information about the
organization itself (see further <ptr target="#ND-org"/>).  Its
<att>type</att> attribute should be used to characterize the name
(rather than the organization),
for example as an acronym:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Mr Frost will be able to earn an extra fee from 
<orgName type="acronym">BSkyB</orgName>
rather than the <orgName type="acronym">BBC</orgName>
</egXML>

as a phrase:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDORG-eg-38">
The feeling in <country>Canada</country> is one of 
strong aversion to the <orgName type="phrase">United 
States Government</orgName>, and of
predilection for self-government under 
the <orgName type="phrase">English Crown</orgName></egXML>


<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<orgName>The Justified Ancients of Mu Mu</orgName>
</egXML>

or as a composite of other kinds of name:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<orgName type="partnerNames">
   <surname>Ernst</surname> &amp; <surname>Young</surname>
</orgName></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The components of an organization's name may include place names as
well as personal names:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">A spokesman from 
<orgName type="regional">
  <orgName>IBM</orgName>
  <country>UK</country>
</orgName> said ... 
</egXML>
or role names:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">THE TICKET which you will receive herewith has been formed by
the <orgName>Democratic Whig <name type="role">party</name>
</orgName> after the most careful deliberation,
with a reference to all the great objects of NATIONAL, STATE,
COUNTY and CITY concern, and with a single eye to the <hi>Welfare and Best Interests of the Community</hi>.</egXML>
</p>
<p>As indicated above, organizational names may also be specified hierarchically
particularly where the named organization is itself a department
or a branch of a larger organizational entity.  <q>The
Department of Modern History, Glasgow University</q> is an
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><orgName>  
   <orgName>Department of Modern History</orgName>
   <orgName><name type="city">Glasgow</name>
            <name type="role">University</name>
   </orgName>
</orgName></egXML>
</p>

<p>
<specGrp xml:id="DNDPER" n="Personal and organizational names">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/orgName.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/persName.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/surname.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/forename.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/genName.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/nameLink.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/addName.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/roleName.xml"/></specGrp>
</p></div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="NDPLAC"><head>Place Names</head>
<p>Like other proper nouns or noun phrases used as names, place names
can simply be marked up with the <gi>rs</gi> element, or with the
<gi>name</gi> element.  For cartographers and historical geographers,
however, the component parts of a place name provide important
information about the relation between the name and some spot in space
and time.  They also provide important evidence in historical
linguistics.</p>
<p>These Guidelines distinguish three ways of referring to places.  A
place name (represented using the <gi>placeName</gi> element) may
consist of one or more names for hierarchically-organized
geo-political or administrative units (see section <ptr target="#NDPLGU"/>).  A place named simply in terms of geographical
features such as mountains or rivers is represented using the
<gi>geogName</gi> element (see section <ptr target="#NDPLGF"/>).  Finally, an expression consisting of phrases
expressing spatial or other kinds of relationship between other kinds
of named place may itself be regarded as a way of referring to a
place, and hence as a kind of named place 
(see section <ptr target="#NDPLR"/>).
<specList><specDesc key="placeName"/><specDesc key="geogName"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>As members of the <ident type="class">att.naming</ident> class, all
of these elements bear the attributes <att>key</att>,
<att>ref</att>, and <att>nymRef</att> mentioned above. These attributes
are primarily useful as a means of linking a place name with
information about a specific place. Recommendations for the encoding
of information about a place, as distinct from its name, are provided
in <ptr target="#NDGEOG"/> below.
</p>

<p>Like the <gi>persName</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#NDPER"/>, the <gi>placeName</gi> element may be regarded
simply as an abbreviation for the elements <tag>name
type="place"</tag> or <tag>rs type="place"</tag>. The following
encodings are thus equivalent:<note place="bottom">Strictly, a suitable
value such as <val>figurative</val> should be added to the two place
names which are presented periphrastically in the second version of
this example. This would preserve the distinction indicated by the choice of
<gi>rs</gi> rather than <gi>name</gi> to encode them in the first
version of this
example.</note> <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">After
spending some time in our <rs ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:NY1" type="place">modern <name
ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:BA1" type="place">Babylon</name></rs>, <name ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:NY1"
type="place">New York</name>, I have proceeded to 
the <rs ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:PH1" type="place">City of Brotherly Love</rs>.</egXML>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDPLAC-eg-55">After spending some
time in our <placeName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:NY1">modern 
<placeName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:BA1">Babylon</placeName></placeName>, 
<placeName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:NY1">New
York</placeName>, I have proceeded to the <placeName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:PH1">City of
Brotherly Love</placeName>.</egXML>
</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="NDPLGU"><head>Geo-political Place Names</head>
<p>A place name may contain text with no indication of its internal
  structure: <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><placeName>Rochester,
NY</placeName></egXML> More usually however, a place name of this kind
will be further analysed in terms of its constitutive geo-political or
administrative units. These may be arranged in ascending sequence
according to their size or administrative importance, for example:
<q>Rochester, New York</q>, or as a single such unit, for example
<q>Belgium</q>. These Guidelines provide a hierarchy of generic
element names, each of which may be more exactly specified by means of
a <att>type</att> attribute:
<specList>
<specDesc key="district"/>
<specDesc key="settlement"/>
<specDesc key="region"/>
<specDesc key="country"/>
<specDesc key="bloc"/>
</specList></p>
<p>These elements are all members of the <ident type="class">model.placeNamePart</ident> class, members of which may
be used anywhere that text is permitted, including within each other
as in the following examples: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><placeName>  
  <settlement type="city">Rochester</settlement>,
  <region type="state">New York</region>
</placeName></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><placeName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:LSEA1">  
  <country type="nation">Laos</country>,
  <bloc type="sub-continent">Southeast Asia</bloc>
</placeName></egXML>
<egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><placeName>
<district type="arondissement">6ème</district>
 <settlement type="city">Paris, </settlement>
 <country>France</country>
</placeName>
</egXML>
</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="NDPLGF"><head>Geographic Names</head>
<p>Places may also be named in terms of geographic features such as
mountains, lakes, or rivers, independently of geo-political units.  The
<gi>geogName</gi> is provided to mark up such names, as an alternative
to the <gi>placeName</gi> element discussed above. 
For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><geogName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:MIRI1" type="river">Mississippi River</geogName></egXML>
</p>
<p>In addition to the usual phrase level elements, the <gi>geogName</gi>
element may contain the following specialized element:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="geogFeat"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>Where the <gi>geogFeat</gi> element is used to characterize the kind of
geographic feature being named, the <gi>name</gi> element will generally
also be used to mark the associated proper noun or noun phrase:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><geogName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:MIRI1" type="river">    
   <name>Mississippi</name>
   <geogFeat>River</geogFeat> </geogName></egXML> A more complex
   example, showing a variety of practices, follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">The isolated ridge
   separates two great corridors which run from <name ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:GLCO1" type="place">Glencoe</name> into
<geogName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:GLET1" type="glen">
   <geogFeat>Glen</geogFeat>
   <name>Etive</name>
</geogName>, the
<geogName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:LAGA1" type="hill">  
   <geogFeat xml:lang="gd">Lairig</geogFeat> 
   <name>Gartain</name>
</geogName> and the
<geogName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:LAEI1" type="hill">  
   <geogFeat xml:lang="gd">Lairig</geogFeat> 
   <name>Eilde</name>
</geogName></egXML></p>
<p>The Gaelic word <mentioned>lairig</mentioned> may be glossed as
<gloss>sloping hill face</gloss>. The most efficient way of including
this information in the above encoding would be to create a separate
<gi>nym</gi> element for this component of the name and then point to
it using the <att>nymRef</att> attribute, as further discussed in <ptr target="#NDNYM"/>. 
</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="NDPLR"><head>Relative Place Names</head>

<p>All the place name specifications so far discussed are <term rend="noindex">absolute</term>, in the sense that they define only one
place.  A place may however be specified in terms of its relationship
to another place, for example <q>10 miles northeast of Paris</q> or
<q>near the top of Mount Sinai</q>. These <term>relative place
names</term> will contain a place name which acts as a referent
(e.g. <q>Paris</q> and <q>Mount Sinai</q>). They will also contain a
word or phrase indicating the position of the place being named in
relation to the referent (e.g. <q>the top of</q>, <q>north of</q>). A
distance, possibly only vaguely specified, between the referent place
and the place being indicated may also be present (e.g. <q>10
miles</q>, <q>near</q>).</p>
<p>Relative place names may be encoded using the following elements in
combination with either a <gi>placeName</gi> or a <gi>geogName</gi>
element.
<specList><specDesc key="offset"/><specDesc key="measure"/></specList>
Some examples of relative place names are:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><placeName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:NRPA1"> 
   <offset>near the top of</offset>
   <geogName>     
      <geogFeat>Mount</geogFeat>
      <name>Sinai</name>
   </geogName>
</placeName></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><placeName>  
   <measure>20 km</measure>
   <offset>north of</offset>
   <settlement type="city">Paris</settlement>
</placeName></egXML> 
If desired, the distance specified may be
normalized using the <att>unit</att> and <att>quantity</att>
attributes of <gi>measure</gi>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><placeName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:Duncan">
  <measure unit="km" quantity="17.7">11 miles</measure>
  <offset>Northwest of</offset>
  <settlement type="city">Providence</settlement>, <region type="state">RI</region>
</placeName></egXML>
</p>
<p>The internal structure of place names is like that of personal
names—complex and subject to an enormous amount of variation across
time and different cultures. The recommendations in this section
should however be adequate for a majority of users and applications;
they may be extended using the mechanisms described in chapter <ptr target="#MD"/> to add new elements to the existing classes. When the
focus of interest is on the name components themselves, as in place
name studies for example, the elements discussed in <ptr target="#NDNYM"/> may also be of use. Alternatively, the meaning
structure itself may be represented using feature structures (<ptr target="#FS"/>).</p>
<p>
<specGrp xml:id="DNDPLAC" n="Names for places">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/placeName.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/bloc.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/country.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/region.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/district.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/settlement.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/offset.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/geogName.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/geogFeat.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</p>
</div>

</div>
</div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="NDPERS">
<head>Biographical and Prosopographical Data</head>
<p>This module defines a number of special purpose elements which can
be used to markup biographical, historical, and prosopographical
data. We envisage three basic types of users and uses for these
elements.  The first is the person interested in creating or
converting an existing set of biographical records, for example of the
type found in a Dictionary of National Biography.  The second is the
person hoping to create or convert a database-like collection of
information about a group of people, possibly but not necessarily the
people referenced in a marked-up collection of documents or a
text-corpus.  The third type would be those interested in the creation
or conversion of biographical or CV-like structured texts for use
in such applications as Human Resource management.</p>

<p>To cater for this diversity, these Guidelines propose a flexible
approach, in which encoders may choose for themselves the degree of
prescription appropriate to their needs.  If one were interested, for
example, in converting existing DNB-type records, and wanted to
 preserve the text as is, the <gi>person</gi> element (see <ptr target="#NDPERSE"/>) could simply
contain the text of an article, placed within <gi>p</gi> elements,
possibly using elements such as <gi>name</gi> or <gi>date</gi> to mark
up features of that text.  For a more structured entry, however, one
would extract the data and place information contained by the text,
and encode it directly using the more specific elements described in
this section.</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="NDPERSbp">
<head>Basic Principles</head>
<p>Information about people, places, and organizations, of whatever type, essentially comprises a
series of statements or assertions relating to:
<list type="simple">
<item>characteristics or <term>traits</term> which do not, by
and large, change over time</item>
<item>characteristics or <term>states</term> which hold true only at a
specific time</item>
<item><term>events</term> or incidents which may lead to a change of state or, less
frequently, trait.</item></list>
</p>

<p><soCalled>Characteristics</soCalled> or <soCalled>traits</soCalled>
are typically independent of an individual's volition or action and
can be either physical, such as sex or hair and eye colour, or
cultural, such as ethnicity, caste, or faith.  The distinction is not
entirely straightforward, however: while sex is fairly obviously a
physical trait, gender should rather be regarded as culturally
determined, and the division of mankind into different
<soCalled>races</soCalled>, proposed by early (white European)
anthropologists on the basis of physical characteristics such as skin
colour, hair type and skull measurements, is by many modern cultural
anthropologists now considered to be more a social or mental construct
than an objective biological fact.  Furthermore, while some
characteristics will obviously change over time, hair colour for
example, none, in principle—not even sex—is immutable.</p>

<p><soCalled>States</soCalled> include, for example, marital status,
place of residence and position or occupation.  Such states have a
definite duration, that is, they have a beginning and an end and are typically
a consequence of the individual's own action or that of others.</p>

<p>By <soCalled>changes in state</soCalled> are meant the events
in a person's life such as birth, marriage, or appointment to office;
such events will normally be associated with a specific date or a
fairly narrow date-range.  Changes in states can also cause or be caused
by changes in characteristics. Any statement or assertion on any of
these aspects of a person's life will be based on some source, possibly
multiple sources, possibly contradictory.  Taking all this into account
it follows that each such statement or assertion needs to be able to be
documented, put into a time frame and be relatable to other statements
or assertions of the same or any of the other types.</p>

<p>The elements defined by the module described in this chapter may,
for the most part, all be regarded as specializations of one or other
of the above three classes. Generic elements for state, trait, and
event are also defined:
<specList>
<specDesc key="state"/>
<specDesc key="trait"/>
<specDesc key="event" atts="where"/>
<specDesc key="listEvent"/>
  <!-- PB, 19-04-2012
    <specDesc key="listState"/>
    -->
</specList>
</p>

</div>
 <div type="div3" xml:id="NDPERSE">
<head>The Person Element</head>
<p>Information about a person, as distinct from references to a
person, for example by name, is grouped together within a
<gi>person</gi> element. Information about a group of people regarded
as a single entity (for example <soCalled>the audience</soCalled> of a
performance) may be encoded using the <gi>personGrp</gi> element. Note
however that information about a group of people with a distinct
identity (for example a named theatrical troupe) should be recorded
using the <gi>org</gi> element described in section <ptr target="#ND-org"/> below. </p>
<p>These elements may appear only within a <gi>listPerson</gi>
element, which groups such descriptions together, and optionally also
describes relationships amongst the people listed.
<specList>
<specDesc key="listPerson"/>
<specDesc key="listRelation"/>
</specList>
</p>

<p>One or more <gi>listPerson</gi> elements may be supplied within the
<gi>particDesc</gi> (participant description) element in the
<gi>profileDesc</gi> element of a TEI Header (see <ptr
target="#HD4"/>).  Like other forms of list, however, the
<gi>listPerson</gi> can also appear within the body of a text when the
module defined by this chapter is included in a schema.</p>

<p>The <att>type</att> attribute may be used to distinguish lists of
people of different kinds where this is considered convenient:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><profileDesc>
<particDesc>
<listPerson type="historical">
  <person xml:id="ART1"><persName>Arthur</persName></person>
  <person xml:id="BERT1"><persName>Bertrand</persName></person>
  <!-- ... -->
</listPerson>
<listPerson type="mythological">
  <person xml:id="ART2"><persName>Arthur</persName></person>
  <person xml:id="BERT2"><persName>Bertrand</persName></person>
  <!-- ... -->
</listPerson>
</particDesc>
</profileDesc></egXML>
</p>

<p>The <gi>person</gi> element carries several  attributes.
First, as a member of <ident type="class">att.editLike</ident>, which
is a subclass of the <ident type="class">att.responsible</ident>
class, it carries the usual attributes for providing
details about the information  
recorded for that person itself, such as its reliability or source: <specList>
<specDesc key="att.responsibility" atts="cert resp"/>
<specDesc key="att.editLike" atts="evidence source"/>
</specList>
In addition, a small number of very commonly used personal properties
may be recorded using attributes specific to <gi>person</gi> and
<gi>personGrp</gi> :  <specList><specDesc key="person"
atts="role sex age"/>
<specDesc key="personGrp"/>
</specList></p>

<p>These attributes are intended for use where only a small amount of
data is to be encoded in a more or less normalized form, possibly for
many person elements, for example when encoding basic facts about
respondents to a questionnaire. When however a more detailed encoding
is required for all kinds of information about a person, for
example in a historical gazeteer, then it will be more appropriate to
use the elements <gi>age</gi>, <gi>sex</gi> and others described
elsewhere in this chapter.</p>

<p>Note that the <att>age</att> attribute is not intended to record
the person's age expressed in years, months, or other temporal
unit. Rather it is intended to record into which age bracket, for the
purposes of some analysis, the person falls. A simple (perhaps too
simple to be useful) binary classification of age brackets would be
<val>child</val> and <val>adult</val>. The actual age brackets useful
to various projects are likely to be varied and idiosyncratic, and thus
these Guidelines make no particular recommendation as to possible
values. Instead, individual projects are recommended to define
the values they use in their own customization file, using a
declaration like the following:
<egXML xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
	<elementSpec ident="person" module="namesdates" mode="change">
	  <attList>
	    <attDef mode="replace" ident="age">
	      <datatype>
		<rng:ref name="data.enumerated"/>
	      </datatype>
	      <valList type="closed">
		<valItem ident="child">
		  <desc>less than 18 years of age</desc>
		</valItem>
		<valItem ident="adult">
		  <desc>18 to 65 years of age</desc>
		</valItem>
		<valItem ident="retired">
		  <desc>over 65 years of age</desc>
		</valItem>
	      </valList>
	    </attDef>
	  </attList>
	</elementSpec>
</egXML>
The above declaration, were it properly placed in a customization
file, establishes that the <att>age</att> attribute of <gi>person</gi>
has only three possible values, <val>child</val>, <val>adult</val>,
and <val>retired</val>. For more information on customization see <ptr
target="#MD"/>.</p>

<p>The <gi>person</gi> element may contain many sub-elements, each
specifying a different property of the person being described.  The
remainder of this section describes these more specific elements. For
convenience, these elements are grouped into three classes, corresponding with
the tripartite division outlined above: one for traits, one for states
and one for events.  Each class  contains both 
specific elements for  common types of biographical
information, and a generic element for other, user-defined, types
of information.</p> 
<p>All the elements in these three classes belong to the attribute
class <ident type="class">att.datable</ident>, which provides the
following attributes:
<specList><specDesc key="att.datable.w3c" atts="when notBefore notAfter from to"/></specList>
as discussed in <ptr target="#NDATTS"/> above. </p>

   <div type="div4" xml:id="NDPERSEpc">
<head>Personal Characteristics</head>
 <p>The <ident type="class">model.persStateLike</ident> class contains elements
describing physical or socially-constructed characteristics, traits, or states
of a person. Members of the class comprise the following specific
elements:
<!-- MDH: commented out langKnown, as it's not actually in the class, and 
      added state and trait. See http://purl.org/TEI/BUGS/3492947
      and discussion on Council list 2012-02-24. -->
<specList>
<specDesc key="faith"/>
<specDesc key="langKnowledge"/>
<!--<specDesc key="langKnown"/>-->
<specDesc key="nationality"/>
<specDesc key="sex"/>
<specDesc key="age"/>
<specDesc key="socecStatus"/>
  <specDesc key="persName"/>
  <specDesc key="occupation"/>
  <specDesc key="residence"/>
  <specDesc key="affiliation"/>
  <specDesc key="education"/>
  <specDesc key="floruit"/>
  <specDesc key="state"/>
  <specDesc key="trait"/>
</specList>
All, apart from <gi>langKnowledge</gi>, allow  content of ordinary prose containing phrase-level elements.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<socecStatus ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:AB1">Status AB1 in the RG Classification scheme</socecStatus>
</egXML>
<!-- socecstatus has its own @code and @scheme attributes which need
exemplifying here too? -->
</p>
<p>The meanings of concepts such as sex, nationality, or age are
highly culturally-dependent, and the encoder should take particular
care to be explicit about any assumptions underlying their usage of
them. For example, when recording personal age in different cultures,
there may be different assumptions about the point from which age is
reckoned. A statement of the practice adopted in a given encoding may
usefully be provided in the <gi>editorialDecl</gi> element discussed
in <ptr target="#HD53"/>.
</p>

 <p>The <gi>langKnowledge</gi> element contains
either paragraphs or a number of <gi>langKnown</gi> elements; it may
take a <att>tags</att> attribute, which provides one or more standard
codes or <soCalled>tag</soCalled>s for the languages. The
<gi>langKnown</gi> element must have a <att>tag</att> attribute, which
indicates the language with the same kind of <soCalled>language
tag</soCalled>.  These <soCalled>language tags</soCalled> are
discussed in detail in <ptr target="#CHSH"/>.</p> <p>Furthermore, the
<gi>langKnown</gi> element also has a <att>level</att> attribute to
indicate the level of the person's competence in the language. It is
thus possible either to say:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<langKnowledge tags="ff fr wo en"><p>Speaks fluent Fulani, Wolof, and French. Some knowledge of English.</p></langKnowledge>
</egXML>
or
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<langKnowledge>
    <langKnown level="fluent" tag="ff">Fulani</langKnown>
    <langKnown level="fluent" tag="wo">Wolof</langKnown>
    <langKnown level="fluent" tag="fr">French</langKnown>
    <langKnown level="basic" tag="en">English</langKnown>
</langKnowledge>
</egXML>
</p>
 <p>The <gi>sex</gi> element carries a <att>value</att> attribute to
 give the ISO 5218:2004 values (<val>1</val> for male,
 <val>2</val> for female, <val>9</val> for non-applicable, and
 <val>0</val> for unknown).
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<sex value="2">female</sex>
</egXML>
As elsewhere, these coded values may be used as an alternative to or
 normalization of the actual descriptive text contained by the
 element. The previous example might equally well be given as 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<sex value="2"/>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>The generic <gi>trait</gi> and <gi>state</gi> elements are also a member of this class,
<specList>
<specDesc key="trait"/>
<specDesc key="state"/>
</specList>
These element can be used to extend the range of information supplied
about an individual's personal characteristics. Either may contain an
optional <gi>label</gi> element, used to provide a human-readable
specification for the characteristic concerned and a description of
the feature itself supplied within a <gi>desc</gi> element. These may
be followed by or one or more <gi>p</gi> elements supplying more
detailed information about the trait. In either case, these may be
followed by one or more notes or bibliographical references. The
<att>type</att>, <att>ref</att>, and <att>key</att> attributes may be
used to indicate a fuller definition of the combination of feature and
value.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<trait type="ethnicity" key="alb">
    <label>Ethnicity</label>
    <desc>Ethnic Albanian.</desc>
</trait>
</egXML>
</p>
<!-- what does alb point to here? -->
 <!-- AC: I suppose it could point to the defintion of the country for example  -->

<p>These elements are provided as a simple means of extending the set
of descriptive features available in a standardized way.  For example,
there are no predefined elements for such features as eye or hair
colour. If these are to be recorded, they may simply be added as new
types of trait:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<trait type="physical">
   <label>eye colour</label>
   <desc>blue</desc>
</trait>
<trait type="physical">
   <label>hair colour</label>
   <desc>brown</desc>
</trait>
</egXML>
</p>

  <p>If none of the more specialised elements listed above is
  appropriate, then a choice must be made between the two generic
  elements <gi>trait</gi> and <gi>state</gi>. If you wish to
  distinguish between characteristics that are generally perceived to
  be transient and those which are generally considered unchanging,
  use <gi>state</gi> for the former, and <gi>trait</gi> for the
  latter. It may also be helpful to note that that traits are
  typically, but not necessarily, independent of the volition or
  action of the holder. If the distinction between state and trait is
  not considered relevant or useful, use <gi>state</gi>.</p>

<p>The <gi>persName</gi> element is repeatable and can, like all TEI
elements, take the attribute <att>xml:lang</att> to indicate the
language of the content of the element, as well as a
<att>type</att> attribute to indicate the type of name, whether a
nickname, maiden name, alternative form, etc. This is useful in cases
where, for example, a person is known by a Latin name and also by any
number of vernacular names, many or all of which may have claims to
<soCalled>authenticity</soCalled>. In order to ensure uniformity, the
method generally employed in the library world has been to accept the
form found in some authority file, for example that of the American
Library of Congress, as the <soCalled>base</soCalled> or
<soCalled>neutral</soCalled> form. Feelings can run high on this
matter, however, and people are often reluctant to accept as
<soCalled>neutral</soCalled> an overtly foreign form of the name of
their local saint or hero. Within the <gi>person</gi> element any
number of variant forms of a name can be given, with no
prioritisation, and hence less likelihood of offence. The Icelandic
scholar and manuscript collector Árni Magnússon, to give his
name in standard modern Icelandic spelling, is known in Danish as Arne
Magnusson, the form which he himself, as a long term resident of
Denmark, generally used; there is also a Latinised form, Arnas
Magnæus, which he used in his scholarly writings. All three forms
can be given, and in any order:
  <egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<person xml:id="ArnMag">
    <persName xml:lang="is">Árni Magnússon</persName>
    <persName xml:lang="da">Arne Magnusson</persName>
    <persName xml:lang="la">Arnas Magnæus</persName>
</person>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>At the other extreme, a person may be named periphrastically as in
the following example:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <person xml:id="simon_son_of_richard2">
    <persName>Simon, son of Richard</persName>
    <residence><placeName><region>Essex</region></placeName></residence>
    <floruit notBefore="1219" notAfter="1223">1219-1223</floruit>
  </person>
</egXML>
</p>
  
  <p>Alternatively, the generic <gi>name</gi> element may be used for
  all of the naming components in a description. 
  For example, a description of the first living held by the Icelandic
clergyman and poet Jón Oddsson Hjaltalín might be tagged as
follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><state type="office" from="1777-04-07" to="1780-07-12">
    <p>Jón's first living — which he apparently accepted rather  reluctantly — was at 
<name type="place">Háls í Hamarsfirði</name>, <name type="place">Múlasýsla</name>, to which 
he was presented on 7 April 1777. He was ordained the following 
month and spent three years at Háls, but was never happy there, 
due largely to the general penury in which he was forced to live —
a recurrent theme throughout the early part of his life. In June 
of 1780 the bishop recommended that Jón 
should <q xml:lang="da">promoveres til andet bedre kald, end det 
hand hidindtil har havt</q>, and on 12 July it was agreed that 
he should exchange livings with 
<name type="person" ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:ThorJon">sr. Þórður Jónsson</name> at 
<name type="place">Kálfafell á Síðu</name>, 
<name type="place">Skaftafellssýsla</name>.</p>

    <bibl>ÞÍ, Stms I.15, p. 733.</bibl>

    <bibl>ÞÍ, Stms I.17, p. 102.</bibl>

</state>
</egXML>
</p>
  
  <p>Similarly, the  generic <gi>state</gi> or <gi>trait</gi> element
  may be used in preference to the more specific elements listed
  above:
 
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <state type="nationality" notBefore="2002-01-15">
        <label>Nationality</label>
        <desc>American citizen from 15 January 2002.</desc>
      </state>
    </egXML>
    is the same as:
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <nationality notBefore="2002-01-15">American citizen from 15 January 2002.</nationality> 
    </egXML>
    or even:
    <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <nationality notBefore="2002-01-15" key="US"/>
    </egXML>
  </p>
  
</div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="NDPERSEpe">
<head>Personal Events</head>
 <p>The <ident type="class">model.persEventLike</ident> class contains elements
describing specific events in a person's
history, for example birth, marriage, or appointment. These are not
characteristics of an individual, but often cause an individual to
gain such characteristics, or to enter a new state.  Members of this
class comprise the following  elements:
<specList>
<specDesc key="birth"/>
<specDesc key="death"/>
</specList>
Only two specific elements (<gi>birth</gi> and <gi>death</gi>) are
proposed.  The generic element <gi>event</gi> has a similar content
model to that of <gi>state</gi> and <gi>trait</gi>; the chief
difference being that it can include a <gi>placeName</gi> element to
identify the name of the place where the event occurred. It is used 
to describe any event in the life of an individual or organization. </p>

<p>In the following example, we give a brief summary of the wedding of
Jane Burden to the English writer, designer, and socialist William
Morris, encoded as an <gi>event</gi> element embedded within the
<gi>person</gi> element used to record data about Morris, though we
could equally well have embedded the event within the <gi>person</gi>
element for Burden, or have given it as a freestanding <gi>event</gi>
independent of either <gi>person</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<person xml:id="WM">
<!-- ... -->
<event type="marriage" when="1859-04-26">
    <label>Marriage</label>
   <desc><name type="person" ref="#WM">William Morris</name> and <name type="person" ref="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Jane_Burden">Jane Burden</name> were 
married at <name type="place">St Michael's Church, Ship Street, Oxford</name> on
   <date when="1859-04-26">26 April 1859</date>. The wedding was
   conducted by Morris's friend <name type="person" ref="#RWD">R. W. 
Dixon</name> with <name type="person" ref="#CBF">Charles
Faulkner</name> as 
the best man. The bride was given away by her father, 
<name type="person" ref="#RB">Robert Burden</name>. 
According to the account that <name type="person" ref="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edward_Burne-Jones">Burne-Jones</name> 
gave <name type="person" ref="#JWM">Mackail</name> 
<quote>M. said to Dixon beforehand <said>Mind
   you don't call her Mary</said> but he did</quote>. The entry in the
   Register reads: <quote>William Morris, 25, Bachelor Gentleman, 13
   George Street, son of William Morris decd. Gentleman. Jane Burden,
   minor, spinster, 65 Holywell Street, d. of Robert Burden,
   Groom.</quote> The witnesses were Jane's parents and Faulkner. None of
   Morris's family attended the ceremony. Morris presented Jane with a
   plain gold ring bearing the London hallmark for 1858. She gave her
   husband a double-handled antique silver cup.</desc>
    <bibl>J. W. Mackail, <title>The Life of William Morris</title>, 1899.</bibl>
</event>
</person>
<person xml:id="RB">
  <persName>Robert Burden</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="RWD">
  <persName>R.W. Dixon</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="CBF">
  <persName>Charles Faulkner</persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="EBJ">
  <persName>
    <forename>Edward</forename>
    <surname>Burne-Jones</surname>
  </persName>
</person>
<person xml:id="JWM">
  <persName>J.W. Mackail</persName>
</person>
</egXML>
In this example the <att>ref</att> attributes on the various
<gi>name</gi> elements point either to an external source or to a
<gi>person</gi> element within which other information about the
person named may be found. As further
discussed below (<ptr target="#relations"/>), a <gi>relation</gi>
element may then be used to link them in a more meaningful way:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<relation name="spouse" mutual="#WM #JBM"/>
<relation name="friend" mutual="#WM #RWD"/>
<relation name="parent" active="#RB" passive="#JBM"/>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>As mentioned above, all these elements, both the specific and the
generic, are members of the <ident type="class">att.datable</ident> attribute
class, which means they can be limited in terms of time. The
following encoding, for example, demonstrates that the person named
David Jones changed his name in 1966 to David Bowie:
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<person xml:id="DB">
    <persName notAfter="1966">David Jones</persName>
    <persName notBefore="1966">David Bowie</persName>
</person>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>All the generic elements are also members of the <ident
type="class">att.responsibility</ident> and <ident
type="class">att.editLike</ident> classes. These classes make
available the attributes <att>cert</att>, to indicate the degree of
certainty, <att>resp</att>, the agency responsible, and
<att>evidence</att>, the nature of the evidence used. In this way it
is possible, in the case of multiple and conflicting sources, to
provide more than one view of what happened, as in the following
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<event type="birth" resp="#XYZ" cert="high"><p>Born in <name type="place">Brixton</name> on 8 January 1947.</p></event>
<event type="birth" resp="#ABC" cert="low"><p>Born in <name type="place">Berkhamsted</name> on 9 January 1947.</p></event>
</egXML>
</p>
</div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="relations"><head>Personal Relationships</head>

<p>When the module defined by this chapter is included in a schema,
the following two elements may be used to document relationships
amongst the persons, places, or organizations identified:
<specList><specDesc key="listRelation"/><specDesc key="relation" atts="name active mutual passive"/></specList> These elements are both
members of the <ident type="class">att.typed</ident> class, from which
they inherit the <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> attributes in
the usual way. The value specified for either attribute on a
<gi>listRelation</gi> element is implicitly applicable to all of its
child <gi>relation</gi> elements, unless overridden.</p>
<p>A <term>relationship</term>, as defined here, may be any kind of
describable link between specified participants. A participant (in
this sense) might be a person, a place, or an organization. In the
case of persons, therefore, a relationship might be a social
relationship (such as employer/employee), a personal relationship
(such as sibling, spouse, etc.) or something less precise such as
<q>possessing shared knowledge</q>.  A relationship may be
<term>mutual</term>, in that all the participants engage in it on an
equal footing (for example the <q>sibling</q> relationship); or it may
not be if participants are not identical with respect to their role in
the relationship (for example, the <q>employer</q> relationship).  For
non-mutual relationships, only two kinds of role are currently
supported; they are named <term>active</term> and
<term>passive</term>.  These names are chosen to reflect the fact that
non-mutual relations are <term>directed</term>, in the sense that they
are most readily described by a transitive verb, or a verb phrase of
the form <mentioned>is X of</mentioned> or <mentioned>is X to</mentioned>.  The
subject of the verb is classed as <term>active</term>; the direct
object of the verb, or the object of the concluding preposition, as
<term>passive</term>.  Thus parents are <q>active</q> and children
<q>passive</q> in the relationship <q>parent</q> (interpreted as
<mentioned>is parent of</mentioned>); the employer is <q>active</q>, the
employee <q>passive</q>, in the relationship <mentioned>employs</mentioned>.
These relationships can be inverted: parents are <q>passive</q> and
children <q>active</q> in the relationship <mentioned>is child of</mentioned>;
similarly <q>works for</q> inverts the active and passive roles of
<q>employs</q>.</p>
<p>For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><listRelation>
   <relation name="parent" active="#P1 #P2" passive="#P3 #P4"/>
   <relation name="spouse" mutual="#P1 #P2"/>
   <relation type="social" name="employer" active="#P1" passive="#P3 #P4"/>
</listRelation></egXML>
This example defines the relationships amongst a number of people not
further described here; we assume however that each person has been
allocated an identifier such as <val>P1</val>, <val>P2</val>,
etc. which can be linked to using references such as <val>#P1</val>, <val>#P2</val> etc. Then
the above set of <gi>relation</gi> elements describe the following
three relationships amongst the seven people referenced:
<list type="simple">
<item>P1 and P2 are parents of P3 and P4.</item>
<item>P1 and P2 are linked in a mutual relationship called <q>spouse</q>—that is, 
  P2 is the spouse of P1, and P1 is the spouse of P2.</item>
<item>P1 has the social relationship <q>employer</q> with respect to P3
and P4.</item></list></p>
<p>Relationships within places and organizations are further
discussed in the relevant section below. Relationships between for
example organizations and places, or places and persons, may be
handled in exactly the same way. 
<!-- examples plz! -->
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div xml:id="ND-org"> <head>Organizational Data</head>
<p>The <gi>org</gi> and <gi>listOrg</gi> elements are used to store
data about an organization such as its preferred name, its locations,
or key persons within it. 

<specList>
<specDesc key="org"/>
<specDesc key="listOrg"/>
</specList>

These elements are intended to be used in a way analogous to the
<gi>place</gi> and <gi>person</gi> elements discussed elsewhere in
this chapter, that is to provide a unique wrapper element for
information about an entity, distinct from references to that entity
which are typically encoded using a naming element such as <tag>name
type="org"</tag> or <gi>orgName</gi>. The content of a naming element
will represent the way an organization is named in a given context;
the content of an <gi>org</gi> represents the information known to the
encoder about that organization, gathered together in a single place,
and independent of its textual realization.
</p>
<p>An organization is not the same thing as a list or group of people because
it has an identity of its own. That identity may be expressed solely
in the existence of a name (for example <q>The Scythians</q>), but is
likely to consist in the combination of that name with a number of
events, traits, or states which are considered to apply to the
organization itself, rather than any of its members. For example, a
sports team might be defined in terms of its membership (a
<gi>listPerson</gi>), its fixtures (a <gi>listPlace</gi>), its
geographical affiliation (a <gi>placeName</gi>), or any combination of
these. It will also have properties which may be used to categorize it
in some way such as the kind of sport played, whether the team is
amateur or professional, and so on: these are probably best dealt with
by means of the <att>type</att> attribute. However, it is the name of
the sports team alone which identifies it. </p>
<p>The content model for <gi>org</gi> permits any mixture of
generic <gi>state</gi>, <gi>trait</gi>, or <gi>event</gi> elements:
the presence of the <gi>orgName</gi> element
described in <ptr target="#NDORG"/> is however strongly recommended.</p>
<p>In other respects, the <gi>org</gi> element is used in much the
same way as <gi>place</gi> or <gi>person</gi>. An organization may
have different names at different times:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><org><orgName notAfter="1960">The Silver Beetles</orgName>
<orgName from="1960-08">The Beatles</orgName></org></egXML>  
</p>
<p>The names of the people making up an organization can also change
over time, (if they are known at all). For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><org><orgName notAfter="1960">The Silver Beetles</orgName>
<orgName notBefore="1960">The Beatles</orgName>
<state type="membership" from="1960-08" to="1962-05">
<desc><persName>John Lennon</persName>
<persName>Paul McCartney</persName>
<persName>George Harrison</persName>
<persName>Stuart Sutcliffe</persName>
<persName>Pete Best</persName>
</desc></state>
<state type="membership" notBefore="1963">
<desc><persName>John Lennon</persName>
<persName>Paul McCartney</persName>
<persName>George Harrison</persName>
<persName>Ringo Starr</persName>
</desc></state>
</org></egXML>  
</p>
<p>An <gi>org</gi> may contain subordinate <gi>org</gi>s:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><org>
  <orgName>Oxford University Computing Services</orgName>
  <org>
     <orgName>Information and Support Group</orgName>
  </org>
  <org>
     <orgName>Infrastructure Group</orgName>
     <org>
       <orgName>Networking Team</orgName>
     </org>
     <org>
       <orgName>System Development Team</orgName>
     </org>
  </org>
  <org>
     <orgName>Learning Technologies Group</orgName>
  </org>
</org>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>The following example demonstrates the use of the <gi>listOrg</gi>
element to group together a number of <gi>org</gi> elements, each of
which is defined solely by means of an informal description, itself
containing other names. 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<p>The TEI institutional hosts are: <listOrg>
 <org xml:id="bu">
  <orgName>Brown University</orgName>
  <desc>The host contribution is made jointly by the <name
  type="project">Brown University Women Writers Project</name> and the
  <orgName>Brown University Library's Center for Digital
  Initiatives</orgName>.</desc>
 </org>
 <org xml:id="na">
  <orgName>Nancy</orgName>
  <desc>Hosting is provided by a group of institutions located in
  Nancy, France, coordinated by <orgName>Loria</orgName> and also
  including <orgName>ATILF</orgName> and <orgName>INIST</orgName>.</desc>
 </org>
 <org xml:id="ou">
  <orgName>Oxford University</orgName> 
  <desc>Hosting is provided by the <orgName>Research Technologies
  Service</orgName> at <orgName>Oxford University Computing
  Services</orgName>.</desc>
 </org>
 <org xml:id="uv">
  <orgName>University of Virginia</orgName>
  <desc>Virginia's host support comes jointly from the
  <orgName>Institute for Advanced Technology in the
  Humanities</orgName> and the <orgName>University of Virginia
  Library</orgName>.</desc>
 </org>
   <!--  from http://www.tei-c.org/About/hosting.xml-->
    </listOrg>
</p></egXML>
In a more elaborated version of this example, the organizational names
tagged using <gi>orgName</gi> might be linked using the <att>key</att>
or <att>ref</att> attribute to a unique <gi>org</gi> element elsewhere. 


 </p>
        </div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="NDGEOG"><head>Places</head>

<p>In <ptr target="#NDPLAC"/> we discuss various ways of naming places
such as towns, countries, etc. In much the same way as these Guidelines
distinguish between the encoding of names for people and the encoding
of other data about people, so they also distinguish between the
encoding of names for places and the encoding of other data about
places. In this section we present elements which may be used to
record in a structured way data about places of any kind which might
be named or referenced within a text. Such data may be useful as a way
of normalizing or standardizing references to particular places, as
the raw material for a gazetteer or similar reference document
associated with a particular text or set of texts, or in conjunction
with any form of geographical information system.</p>
<p>The following elements are provided for this purpose: <specList>
    <specDesc key="listPlace"/>
    <specDesc key="place"/>
  </specList>
</p>

 <p>The <ident type="class">model.placeStateLike</ident> class
 contains elements describing characteristics of a place which have a
 definite duration, such as its name. Any member of the <ident type="class">model.placeNamePart</ident> may be used for this
 purpose, since a <gi>place</gi> element will usually contain at least
 one, and possibly several, <gi>placeName</gi>-like elements
 indicating the names associated with it, by different people, in
 different languages, or at different times. </p>

<p> For example, the modern city of Lyon in France was in Roman times
known as Lugdunum.  Although the modern and the Roman city are not
physically co-extensive, they have significant areas which overlap,
and we may therefore wish to regard them as the same place, while
supplying both names with an indication of the time period during
which each was current. </p>

<p>A place is defined, however, by its physical location, which does
not typically change over time. Locations may be specified in a number
of ways: as a set of coordinates defining a point or an area on the
surface of the earth, or by providing a description of how the place
may be found, usually in terms of other place names. For example, we
can identify the location of the Canadian city of London, either by
specifying its latitute and longitude, or by specifying that we mean
the city called London located in the province called Ontario within
the country called Canada. </p>
<p>In addition we may wish to supply a brief characterization of the
place identified, for example to state that it is a city, an
administrative area such as a country, or a landmark of some kind such
as a monument or a battlefield. If our typology of places is simple,
the open ended <att>type</att> attribute is the easiest way to
represent it: so we might say <tag>place type="city"</tag>, <tag>place
type="battlefield"</tag> etc. </p>


<p>Within the <gi>place</gi> element, the following elements may be
used to provide more information about specific aspects of the place
in a structured form: <specList>
    <specDesc key="placeName"/>
    <specDesc key="location"/>
  </specList>
</p>
<div xml:id="NDGEOGva"><head>Varieties of Location</head>
<p>A location may be specified in one or more of the following ways:
<list type="ordered">
<item>by supplying a  string representing its coordinates in some
standardized way within a <gi>geo</gi> element, as shown below</item>
<item>by supplying one or more place name component elements
(e.g. <gi>country</gi>, <gi>settlement</gi> etc.)  to place it  within
a geo-political context</item>
<item>by supplying a postal address, e.g. using the <gi>address</gi>
element</item>
<item>by supplying a brief textual description, e.g. using the
<gi>desc</gi> element</item>
<item>by using a non-TEI XML vocabulary such as the Geography Markup
    Language</item>
</list>
We give examples of all of these methods in the remainder of this
  section.</p>

<p>The simplest method of specifying a location is by means of its
geographic coordinates, supplied within the <gi>geo</gi> element. This
may be used to supply any kind of positional information, using one of
the many different geodetic systems available. Such systems vary in
their format, in their scope or coverage, and more fundamentally in
the reference frame (the <soCalled>datum</soCalled>) used for the
coordinate system itself. The default recommended by these Guidelines
is to supply a string containing two real numbers separated by
whitespace, of which the first indicates latitude and the second
longitude according to the 1984 World Geodetic System (WGS84); this is
the system currently used by most GPS applications which TEI users are
likely to encounter.<note place="bottom">See <ptr
target="http://earth-info.nga.mil/GandG/wgs84/index.html"/>. The most
recent revision of this standard is known as the Earth Gravity Model
1996.</note>We might therefore record the information about the place
known as <soCalled>Lyon</soCalled> as follows: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <place xml:id="LYON1" type="city">
      <placeName notBefore="1400">Lyon</placeName>
      <placeName notAfter="0056">Lugdunum</placeName>
      <location><geo>45.769559 4.834843</geo></location>
    </place>
  </egXML>
</p>

  <p>Identifying Lyon by its geo-political status as a settlement
  within a country forming part of a larger political entity, we might
  represent the same <soCalled>place</soCalled> as follows: <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place xml:id="LYON2">
        <placeName notBefore="1400">Lyon</placeName>
        <placeName notAfter="0056">Lugdunum</placeName>
        <location>
        <bloc>EU</bloc>
          <country>France</country>
        </location>
      </place>
    </egXML> Elements such as <gi>bloc</gi> are specialized forms of
    <gi>placeName</gi>, as discussed in <ptr target="#NDPLGU"/>. </p>
<p>We may use the same procedure to represent the location of smaller
places, such as a street or even an individual building:
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place type="building">
        <placeName>Brasserie Georges</placeName>
        <location>
<country key="FR"/>
<settlement type="city">Lyon</settlement>
<district type="arrondissement">IIème</district>
<district type="quartier">Perrache</district>
<placeName type="street">Cours de Verdun</placeName>
        </location>
      </place>
    </egXML>
Note the use of the <att>type</att> attribute to categorize more
precisely both the kind of place concerned (a building) and the kind
of name used to locate it, for example by characterizing the generic
<gi>district</gi> as an <soCalled>arrondissement</soCalled>, or a <soCalled>quartier</soCalled>. </p>

<p>We may also treat imaginary places in the same way: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place type="imaginary">
        <placeName>Atlantis</placeName>
        <location>
<offset>beyond</offset>
<placeName>The Pillars of <persName>Hercules</persName></placeName>
        </location>
      </place>
    </egXML></p>

<p>A <gi>location</gi> sometimes resembles a set of instructions for
finding a place, rather than a name:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place xml:id="MYF">
        <placeName notAfter="1969">Yasgur's Farm</placeName>
        <placeName notBefore="1969">Woodstock Festival Site</placeName>
        <location>
<measure>one mile</measure>
<offset>north west of</offset>
<settlement>Bethel</settlement>
<region>New York</region>
        </location>
      </place>
    </egXML>
  </p>
  <p>The element <gi>address</gi> may also be used to identify a location in terms of its
    postal or other address: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place type="cemetery">
        <placeName>Protestant Cemetery</placeName>
        <placeName type="official" xml:lang="it">Cimitero Acattolico</placeName>
        <location type="geopolitical">
<country>Italy</country>
<settlement>Rome</settlement>
<district>Testaccio</district>
        </location>
        <location type="address">
<address><addrLine>Via Caio Cestio, 6</addrLine><addrLine>00153 Roma</addrLine></address>
        </location>
      </place>
    </egXML> When, as here, the same place is given multiple
    locations, the <att>type</att> attribute should be used to
    characterize the kind of location, as a means of indicating that
    these are alternative ways of identifying the same place, rather
    than that the place is spread across several locations. </p>

<p>The <gi>location</gi> element may thus identify a place to a
greater or lesser degree of precision, using a variety of means: a
name, a set of names, or a set of coordinates. The <gi>geo</gi>
element introduced earlier is by default understood to supply a value
expressed in a specific (and widely used) notation; this may be
modified in two ways. </p>
<p>Firstly,  the content of the <gi>geo</gi> element could be interpreted in
some other way, that is, according to some different geodetic
system. By default, a standard known as the World Geodetic System
(WGS) is employed; the <att>decls</att> attribute can instead point
to a <gi>geoDecl</gi> element defined in the document header, which
describes a different datum.</p>

<p>Secondly, the element <gi>geo</gi> may be redefined to contain
markup from a different XML vocabulary which is specifically designed
to represent this kind of information. This technique is used
throughout the Guidelines where specialized markup is required, for
example to embed mathematical expressions or vector graphics, and is
further described and exemplified in <ptr target="#MDlite"/>. For
geographic information, suitable non-TEI vocabularies include:
<list type="simple">
<item> the OpenGIS Geography Markup Language (GML) being defined by the
OGC<note place="bottom">The OGC is an international voluntary consensus
standards organization whose members maintain the Geography Markup
Language standard. The OGC coordinates with the ISO TC 211 standards
organization to maintain consistency between OGC and ISO standards
work. GML is also an ISO standard (ISO
19136:2007).</note> </item>
<item> the Keyhole Markup Language (KML) used by Google Maps<note place="bottom">See <ptr target="http://code.google.com/apis/kml/documentation/index.html"/></note>
</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>In the following example, we have defined the location of the place
<soCalled>Lyon</soCalled> using GML  and indicated the two names
    associated with it at different times: 
<egXML xmlns:gml="http://www.opengis.net/gml" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible">
<place type="city">
        <placeName notBefore="1400">Lyon</placeName>
        <placeName notAfter="0056">Lugdunum</placeName>
        <location>
<geo>	
<gml:Polygon>
  <gml:exterior>
    <gml:LinearRing> 45.256 -110.45 46.46 -109.48 43.84 -109.86 45.8 -109.2
      45.256 -110.45 </gml:LinearRing>
  </gml:exterior>
</gml:Polygon></geo>
        </location>
      </place></egXML>
  </p>

  <p>A <gi>bibl</gi> element may be used within <gi>location</gi> to
  indicate the source of the location information.</p>
  <!-- example needed -->
</div>
<div xml:id="NDGEOGmp">
  <head>Multiple Places</head>
  <p>A place may contain other places. This containment relation can
  be directly modelled in XML: thus we can say that the towns of
  Vilnius and Kaunas are both in a place called Lithuania (or Lietuva)
  as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="mul">
      <place>
        <country>Lithuania</country>
        <country xml:lang="lt">Lietuva</country>
        <place>
<settlement>Vilnius</settlement>
        </place>
        <place>
<settlement>Kaunas</settlement>
        </place>
      </place>
    </egXML>
  </p>
<p>This does not, of course, imply that Vilnius and Kaunas are the
only places constituting Lithuania; only that they are within it. A
separate <gi>place</gi> element may indicate that it is a part of
Lithuania by supplying a <gi>relation</gi> element, as discussed below
(<ptr target="#place-rel"/>).</p>

<p>As a further example, the islands of Mauritius, Réunion, and
Rodrigues are collectively known as the Mascarene Islands. Grouped
together with Mauritius there are also several smaller offshore
islands, with rather picturesque French names. These offshore islands
do not however constitute an identifiable place as a whole. One way of
representing this is as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place type="islandGroup">
        <placeName>Mascarene Islands</placeName>
        <placeName>Mascarenhas Archipelago</placeName>
        <place type="island">
<placeName>Mauritius</placeName>
<listPlace type="offshoreIslands">
  <place>
    <placeName>La roche qui pleure</placeName>
  </place>
  <place>
    <placeName>Île aux cerfs</placeName>
  </place>
</listPlace>
        </place>
        <place type="island">
<placeName>Rodrigues</placeName>
        </place>
        <place type="island">
<placeName>Réunion</placeName>
        </place>
      </place>
    </egXML>
  </p>
  <p>Here is a more complex example, showing the variety of names
  associated at different times and in different languages with a set
  of hierarchically grouped places—the settlement of Carmarthen
  Castle, within the town of Carmarthen, within the administrative
  county of Carmarthenshire, Wales. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"  xml:lang="mul">
      <place xml:id="wales" type="country">
        <placeName xml:lang="cy">Cymru</placeName>
        <placeName xml:lang="en">Wales</placeName>
        <placeName xml:lang="la">Wallie</placeName>
        <placeName xml:lang="la">Wallia</placeName>
        <placeName xml:lang="fro">Le Waleis</placeName>
        <place xml:id="carmarthenshire" type="region">
<region type="county" xml:lang="en" notBefore="1284">Carmarthenshire</region>
<place xml:id="carmarthen" type="settlement">
  <placeName xml:lang="en">Carmarthen</placeName>
  <placeName xml:lang="la" notBefore="1090" notAfter="1300">Kaermerdin</placeName>
  <placeName xml:lang="cy">Caerfyrddin</placeName>
  <place xml:id="carmarthen_castle" type="castle">
    <settlement>castle of Carmarthen</settlement>
  </place>
</place>
        </place>
      </place>
    </egXML>
  </p>
<p>As noted previously, <gi>country</gi>, <gi>region</gi>, and
<gi>settlement</gi> are all specializations of the generic
<gi>placeName</gi> element; they are not specializations of the
<gi>place</gi> element. If it is desired to distinguish amongst kinds
of <emph>place</emph> this can only be done by means of the
<att>type</att> attribute as in the above example.</p>
  
<p>This use of multiple <gi>place</gi> elements should be
distinguished from the (possibly simpler) case where a number of
places with some property in common are being grouped together for
convenience, for example, in a gazetteer. The <gi>listPlace</gi>
element is provided as a means of grouping places together where there
is no implication that the grouped elements constitute a distinct
place. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place type="county">
        <placeName>Herefordshire</placeName>
        <listPlace type="villages">
<place>
  <placeName>Abbey Dore</placeName>
  <location><geo>51.969604 -2.893146</geo></location>
</place>
<place>
  <placeName>Acton Beauchamp</placeName>
</place>
<!-- etc -->
        </listPlace>
        <listPlace type="towns">
<place>
  <placeName>Hereford</placeName>
</place>
<place>
  <placeName>Leominster</placeName>
</place>
<!-- etc  -->
        </listPlace>
      </place>
    </egXML>
  </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="NDGEOGste">
  <head>States, Traits, and Events</head>

  <p>There are many different kinds of information which it might be
  considered useful to record for a place in addition to its name and
  location, and the categories selected are likely to be very
  project-specific. As with persons therefore these Guidelines make no
  claim to comprehensiveness in this context. Instead, the generic
  <gi>state</gi>, <gi>trait</gi>, and <gi>event</gi> elements defined
  by this module should be used. Each of these may be customized for
  particular needs by means of their <att>type</att> attribute. These
  are complemented by a small number of predefined elements of general
  utility: <specList>
      <specDesc key="population"/>
      <specDesc key="climate"/>
      <specDesc key="terrain"/>
    </specList>
  </p>
  
<p>These are all specializations of the generic <gi>trait</gi>
element. This element may be used for almost any
kind of event in the life of a place; no specialized version of this
element is proposed, nor do we attempt to enumerate the possible
values which might be appropriate for the <att>type</att> attribute on
any of these generic elements. </p>
  <p>Here is an example, showing how the specific and generic elements may be combined:
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place xml:id="IS">
        <placeName xml:lang="en">Iceland</placeName>
        <placeName xml:lang="is">Ísland</placeName>
        <location><geo>65.00 -18.00</geo></location>
        <terrain>
             <desc>Area: 103,000 sq km</desc>
        </terrain>
        <state type="governance" notBefore="1944">
<p>Constitutional republic</p>
        </state>
        <state type="governance" notAfter="1944">
<p>Part of the kingdom of <placeName key="DK">Denmark</placeName></p>
        </state>
        <event type="governance" when="1944-06-17">
	  <desc>Iceland became independent on 17 June 1944.</desc>
        </event>
        <state type="governance" from="1944-06-17">
<p>An independent republic since June 1944</p>
        </state>

      </place>
    </egXML>
  </p>
  
<p>In the following example, the <gi>climate</gi> example is used to
provided a detailed discussion of this particular aspect of the
information available about a particular place:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<place xml:id="greece">
 <placeName>Greece</placeName>
 <climate>
  <desc>Greece's climate is divided into three well defined
  classes:</desc>
  <climate>
   <label>Mediterranean</label>
   <desc>It features mild, wet winters and hot, dry
   summers. Temperatures rarely reach extremes, although snowfalls do
   occur occasionally even in <placeName>Athens</placeName>,
   <placeName>Cyclades</placeName> or <placeName>Crete</placeName>
   during the winter.</desc>
  </climate>
  <climate>
   <label>Alpine</label>
   <desc>It is found primarily in <placeName><offset>Western</offset>
   Greece</placeName> (<placeName>Epirus</placeName>,
   <placeName><offset>Central</offset> Greece</placeName>,
   <placeName>Thessaly</placeName>,
   <placeName><offset>Western</offset> Macedonia</placeName> as well
   as central parts of <placeName>Peloponnesus</placeName> like
   <placeName>Achaea</placeName>, <placeName>Arcadia</placeName> and
   parts of <placeName>Laconia</placeName> where the Alpine range pass
   by)</desc>
  </climate>
  <climate>
   <label>Temperate</label>
   <desc>It is found in <placeName><offset>Central</offset> and
   <offset>Eastern</offset> Macedonia</placeName> as well as in
   <placeName>Thrace</placeName> at places like
   <placeName>Komotini</placeName>, <placeName>Xanthi</placeName> and
   <placeName><offset>northern</offset> Evros</placeName>. It features
   cold, damp winters and hot, dry summers.</desc>
  </climate>
 </climate>
</place>
</egXML>   <!--  adapted from http://greekinfo.wordpress.com/ -->
</p>
<p>As the above example shows,  <gi>state</gi> and <gi>trait</gi>
elements, and others of the same class, can be nested hierarchically
within each other. When this is done, values for the <att>type</att>
attribute are to be understood as cumulatively inherited, as elsewhere
in the TEI scheme (for example on <gi>category</gi> or
<gi>linkGrp</gi>). In the following example, the outermost
<gi>population</gi> element concerns the squirrel population between
the dates given. This is then broken down into red and gray squirrel
populations, and within that into male and female:
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <population type="squirrel" notBefore="1901" notAfter="1902-01-11" resp="#strabo">
        <population type="red" when="1901-01-10">
<population type="female"><desc>12</desc></population>
<population type="male"><desc>15</desc></population>
        </population>
        <population type="gray" when="1902-01-10" cert="high">
<population type="female"><desc>23</desc></population>
<population type="male" cert="low" resp="#biber"><desc>45</desc></population>
        </population>
      </population>
    </egXML> The dating and responsibility attributes here behave
    slightly differently from the <att>type</att> attribute:
    responsibility is not an additive property, and therefore an
    element either states it explicitly, or inherits it from its
    nearest ancestor. Dating is slightly different again, in that a
    child element may specify a date more precisely than its parent,
    as in the example above</p>
 
 <p>Events may also be subdivided into other events. For example, a
 two part meeting might be represented as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <event type="meeting" when="2007-05-29">
	<desc>All day meeting to resolve content models</desc>
        <event type="preamble" notAfter="13:00:00">
	  <desc>first part</desc>
        </event>
        <event type="conclusions" notBefore="13:00:00">
	  <desc>second part</desc>
        </event>
      </event>
    </egXML>
  </p>

<p>An <gi>event</gi> element is usually used to record information
about a place, or a person; for this reason the element usually
appears as content of a <gi>place</gi> or <gi>person</gi>. However, it
is also possible to describe events independently of either a person
or a place. This may be useful in such applications as chronologies,
lists of significant events such as battles, legislation, etc. </p>

<p>The <gi>listEvent</gi> element is a member of the <ident
type="class">model.listLike</ident> class, and may therefore appear
wherever lists are permitted, in the same way as the
<gi>listPerson</gi>, <gi>listPlace</gi> etc. elements described
elsewhere in this chapter.</p>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><listEvent>
<event when="1713" ref="http://eco.canadiana.ca/view/oocihm.9_01832">
<label>Treaty of Utrecht</label>
<desc>France ceded to Great Britain its claims to the <orgName>Hudson's Bay
Company</orgName> territories in <placeName>Rupert's Land</placeName>, 
<placeName>Newfoundland</placeName>, and
<placeName>Acadia</placeName> and  recognized British suzerainty over <orgName
type="tribe">the Iroquois</orgName> but retained its other pre-war
North American possessions, including
<placeName key="PEI">Île-Saint-Jean</placeName> (now <placeName key="PEI">Prince Edward
Island</placeName>)...</desc>
</event>
<event when="1774" key="14-GeoIII-c83">
<label>Quebec Act</label>
<desc>This act of the British Parliament guaranteed free practice of
the Catholic faith and restored use of the French Civil Code for
private matters throughout the Province of Quebec, which had been
expanded in territory following the <ref>Treaty of Paris</ref>.</desc>
</event>
<event when="1778" ref="http://avalon.law.yale.edu/18th_century/del1778.asp">
<label>Treaty of Fort Pitt</label>
<desc>Also known as the <name type="event">Treaty with the
Delawares</name>, this was the first written treaty between the newly
formed <orgName>United States</orgName> and any Native American people, in this
case, the <orgName type="tribe">Lenape</orgName> or Delawares.</desc>
</event>
</listEvent>
</egXML>

</div>
<div xml:id="place-rel"><head>Relations Between Places</head>
  
<p>The <gi>relation</gi> element may also be used to express
relationships of various kinds between places, or between places and
persons, in much the same way as it is used to express relationships
between persons alone. Returning to the Mascarene Islands example
cited above, we might define the island group and its constituents
separately, but indicate the relationship by means of a
<gi>relation</gi> element:
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <listPlace>
        <place xml:id="MASC">
<placeName>Mascarene islands</placeName>
<placeName>Mascarenhas Archipelago</placeName>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="MRU">
<placeName>Mauritius</placeName>
<!-- ... -->
        </place>
        <place xml:id="ROD">
<placeName>Rodrigues</placeName>
        </place>
        <place xml:id="REN">
<placeName>Réunion</placeName>
        </place>
        <relation name="contains" active="#MASC" passive="#ROD #MRU #REN"/>
      </listPlace>
    </egXML>
  </p>
  
<p>This <soCalled>stand-off</soCalled> style of representation has the
advantage that we can now also represent the fact that a place may be
a <q>part of</q> more than one other place; for example, Réunion is
part of France, as well as part of the Mascarenes. If we add a
declaration for France to the list above: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <place type="country" xml:id="FRA">
        <placeName>France</placeName>
      </place>
    </egXML> we can now model this dual allegiance by means of a <gi>relation</gi>
  element: <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <relation name="partOf" active="#REN" passive="#FRA #MASC"/>
    </egXML>
  </p>

<!-- material on oxford colleges to go here -->

<!-- next div3 was originally proposed by MJD workgroup but never
properly elaborated or tested LB 2012-06-15 -->

<!--
<div3 >
<head>Assertions</head>
<p>In order to allow even greater flexibility we intend to propose a new element, tentatively called <gi>assert</gi>,
which may be used for making assertions about characteristics, states
and changes in states and associating these assertions with
bibliographical records, notes and so on. 
<specList>
<specDesc key="assert"/>
</specList>
Using this mechanism allows one for example to date the assertions as distinct from the things
being asserted:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<assert resp="#XYZ" cert="high" notBefore="1999">
    <birth dateValue="1947-01-08">Born in <name type="place">Brixton</name> on 8 January 1947.</birth>
</assert>
<assert resp="#ABC" cert="low" notAfter="1999">
    <birth dateValue="1947-01-09">Born in <name type="place">Berkhamsted</name> on 9 January 1947.</birth>
</assert>
</egXML>
In this example it can be seen that up until 1999 it was believed,
on the authority of ABC, that the individual in question was born in
Berkhamsted on the 9th of January 1947, whereas after 1999 XYZ's
assertion that he had in fact been born in Brixton on the 8th of
January was generally accepted. A bibliographical reference or note can
be added to provide documentation or further explanation.</p>

<p>We also propose a grouping element, <gi>assertGrp</gi> (for <soCalled>assertion group</soCalled>).
<specList>
<specDesc key="assertGrp"/>
</specList>
The <gi>assertGrp</gi> element can serve as a wrapper around several elements, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<assertGrp type="causal">
    <occupation to="2006-06-13">Manuscript scholar</occupation>
    <residence to="2006-06-13">
        <placeName>
            <settlement type="city">Copenhagen</settlement>
            <country>Denmark</country>
        </placeName>
    </residence>
    <persEvent>
        <label>Nervous breakdown</label>
        <date dateValue="2006-06-14">14 June 2006</date>
    </persEvent>
    <occupation from="2006-06-15">Bee-keeper</occupation>
    <residence from="2006-06-15">
        <placeName>
            <settlement type="village">Dobarsko</settlement>
            <country>Bulgaria</country>
        </placeName>
    </residence>
</assertGrp>
</egXML>
In this example an explicit causal link is made between the various
elements, indicating that a specific event has resulted in a change of
occupation and residence.</p>
</div3>
-->
<specGrp xml:id="DCCAHPA" n="Historical data">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/affiliation.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/age.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/birth.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/climate.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/death.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/education.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/event.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/faith.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/floruit.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/geo.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/langKnowledge.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/langKnown.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/listOrg.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/listEvent.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/listPerson.xml"/>


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/listPlace.xml"/>

<!-- PB, 19-04-2012
    &listState;-->

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/location.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/nationality.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/occupation.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/org.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/listRelation.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/relationGrp.xml"/> <!-- we keep it here for backward compatibility -->
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/person.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/personGrp.xml"/>


    


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/place.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/population.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/relation.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/residence.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/sex.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/socecStatus.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/state.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/terrain.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/trait.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
</div>
<div xml:id="NDNYM"><head>Names and Nyms</head>
<p>So far we have discussed ways in which a name or referring string
encountered in running text may be resolved by considering the object
that the name refers to: in the case of a personal name, the name
refers to a person; in the case of a place name, to a place, for
example. The resolution of this reference is effected by means of the
<att>key</att> or <att>ref</att> attributes available to all elements
which are members of the <ident type="class">att.naming</ident> class,
such as <gi>persName</gi> or <gi>placeName</gi> and their more
specialized variants such as <gi>forename</gi> or
<gi>country</gi>. However, <emph>names</emph> can also be regarded as
objects in their own right, irrespective of the objects to which they
are attached, notably in onomastic studies.  From this point of view,
the names <mentioned>John</mentioned> in English, <mentioned>Jean</mentioned> in French, and
<mentioned>Ivan</mentioned> in Russian might all be regarded as existing independently of any
person to which they are attached, and also independently of any
variant forms that might be attested in different sources (such as Jon
or Johnny in English, or Jehan or Jojo in French).  We use the term
<term>nym</term> to refer to the canonical or normalized form of a
name regarded in such a way, and provide the following elements to
encode it:
<specList>
<specDesc key="listNym"/>
<specDesc key="nym"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>Any element which is a member of the <ident type="class">att.naming</ident>
class may use the attribute <att>nymRef</att> to indicate the nym with
which it corresponds.  Thus, given the following <gi>nym</gi> for the
name <mentioned>Antony</mentioned>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listNym>
<nym xml:id="N123">
  <form>Antony</form>
</nym>
<!-- other nym definitions here -->
</listNym></egXML>
an occurrence of this name in running text might be encoded as follows:
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<forename nymRef="#N123">Tony</forename> Blair
</egXML>
Note that this association (between "Tony" and "Antony") has nothing
to do with any individual who might use the name.</p>
<p>The person identified by this particular Tony may however be indicated
independently using the <att>ref</att> attribute, either on the
forename or on the whole name component:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <forename nymRef="#N123" ref="#BLT">Tony</forename>
....
<person xml:id="BLT">
<persName>Tony Blair</persName>
<occupation>politician</occupation>
</person></egXML>
</p>
<p>The <gi>nym</gi> element may be thought of as providing a
specialized kind of  dictionary
entry.  Like a dictionary entry, it may contain any  element from
 the <ident type="class">model.entryPart</ident> class, such as <gi>form</gi>,
<gi>etym</gi>, etc.  For example, we may show that the canonical form
for a given nym has two orthographic variants in this way:
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<nym xml:id="J451">
  <form>
       <orth xml:lang="en-US">Ian</orth>
       <orth xml:lang="en-x-Scots">Iain</orth>
   </form>
</nym>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>Because a schema intending to make use of the <gi>nym</gi> or
<gi>listNym</gi> element must include the <ident type="module">dictionaries</ident> module as well as 
the <ident type="module">namesdates</ident> module, many other
elements are available in addition to <gi>form</gi>.  For example, to provide a more complex etymological decomposition of a name, we
might use the existing <gi>etym</gi> element, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><nym xml:id="XYZ">
<form>Bogomil</form>
<etym>Means <gloss>favoured by God</gloss> from the
<lang>Slavic</lang> elements <mentioned xml:lang="ru">bog</mentioned> 
<gloss>God</gloss> and <mentioned xml:lang="ru">mil</mentioned>
<gloss>favour</gloss></etym>
</nym></egXML>
</p>
<p>Where it is necessary to mark the substructure of nyms, this may be
done by  <gi>seg</gi> elements within the
  <gi>form</gi>:<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<nym xml:id="ABC">
<form>
  <choice>
   <seg type="morph"><seg>Bog</seg><seg>o</seg><seg>mil</seg></seg>
   <seg type="morph"><seg>Bogo</seg><seg>mil</seg></seg>
  </choice>
</form>
</nym></egXML>
<!-- add example to show that Amadeus has same referents -->
The <gi>seg</gi> element used here is provided by the TEI <ident type="module">linking</ident> module, which would therefore also need
to be included in a schema built to validate such markup. Other
possibilities for more detailed linguistic analysis are provided by
elements included in that and the <ident type="module">analysis</ident> (see <ptr target="#AI"/>) or <ident type="module">iso-fs</ident> modules (see <ptr target="#FS"/>).  
</p>
<p>Alternatively, each of the constituents of
<mentioned>Bogomil</mentioned> might be regarded  as a nym in its own
right:
  <egXML  xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <nym xml:id="B1" type="part">
  <form>bog</form>
 </nym>
 <nym xml:id="M1" type="part">
  <form>mil</form>
 </nym>
</egXML>
Within running text, a name can specify all the nyms associated with
it:
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
...<name nymRef="#B1 #M1">Bogomul</name>...
</egXML>
Similarly, within a nym, the attribute <att>parts</att> is used to
indicate its constituent parts, where these have been identified as
distinct nyms:
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<nym xml:id="BM1" parts="#B1 #M1">
  <form>Bogomil</form>
</nym>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>The <gi>nym</gi> element may also combine a number of other
<gi>nym</gi> elements together, where it is intended to show that they
are all regarded as variations on the same root.  Thus the different
forms of the name John,  all being derived from the same root, may be
represented as a hierarchic structure like this:
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><nym xml:id="J45">
  <form xml:lang="la">Iohannes</form>
   <nym xml:id="J450">
     <form xml:lang="en">John</form>
     <nym xml:id="J4501">
       <form>Johnny</form>
     </nym>
     <nym xml:id="J4502">
       <form>Jon</form>
     </nym>
   </nym>
   <nym xml:id="J455">
     <form xml:lang="ru">Ivan</form>
   </nym>
   <nym xml:id="J453">
    <form xml:lang="fr">Jean</form>
   </nym>
</nym></egXML>
</p>
<p>The <gi>nym</gi> element may be used for components of geographical
or organizational names as well. For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<geogName ref="tag:projectname.org,2012:LAEI1" type="hill">  
   <geogFeat xml:lang="gd" nymRef="#LAIRG">Lairig</geogFeat> 
   <name>Eilde</name>
</geogName>
...

<nym xml:id="LAIRG">
  <form xml:lang="gd">lairig</form>
  <def>sloping hill face</def>
</nym>
...

</egXML>
</p>

<p>
<specGrp xml:id="DNDNYM" n="Canonical names">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/nym.xml"/>

<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/listNym.xml"/>
</specGrp>
As noted above, use of these elements implies that both the <ident type="module">dictionaries</ident> and the <ident type="module">namesdates</ident>  modules are included in a
schema.</p>
</div>


<div type="div2" xml:id="NDDATE"><head>Dates and Times</head>
<p>The following elements for the encoding of dates and times were
introduced in section <ptr target="#CONADA"/>:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="date"/>
  <specDesc key="time"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>The current module <ident type="module">namesdates</ident> provides a mechanism for more detailed encoding of relative dates and times. A <term>relative temporal expression</term> describes a date or time with reference to some other (absolute) temporal
expression, and thus may contain an <gi>offset</gi> element in addition to
one or more <gi>date</gi> or <gi>time</gi> elements:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="offset"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>As members of the <ident type="class">att.datable</ident> and <ident type="class">att.duration</ident> classes, which in turn are members of
<ident type="class">att.datable.w3c</ident> and <ident type="class">att.duration.w3c</ident> respectively, the <gi>date</gi>
and <gi>time</gi> elements share the following attributes:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="att.datable.w3c" atts="when"/>
  <specDesc key="att.duration.w3c" atts="dur"/>
</specList>
</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="NDDATER"><head>Relative Dates and Times
 </head>
<p>As noted above, relative dates and times such as <q>in the Two
Hundredth and First Year of the Republic</q>, <q>twenty minutes before
noon</q>, and, more ambiguously, <q>after the lamented death of the
Doctor</q> or <q>an hour after the game</q> have two distinct
components.  As well as the absolute temporal expression or event to
which reference is made (e.g. <q>noon</q>, <q>the game</q>, <q>the
death of the Doctor</q>,  <q>[the foundation of] the Republic</q>), they
also contain a description of the <soCalled>distance</soCalled>
between the time or date which is indicated and the referent
expression (e.g. <q>the Two Hundredth and First Year</q>, <q>twenty
minutes</q>, <q>an hour</q>); and (optionally) an
<soCalled>offset</soCalled> describing the direction of the distance
between the time or date indicated and the referent expression
(e.g. <q>of</q> implying after, <q>before</q>, <q>after</q>).
 </p>
<p>The <soCalled>distance</soCalled> component of a relative temporal
expression may be encoded as a temporal element in its own right using
either <gi>date</gi> or <gi>time</gi>, or with the more generic
<gi>measure</gi> element. A special element, <gi>offset</gi>, is
provided by this module for encoding the <soCalled>offset</soCalled>
component of a relative temporal expression. The absolute temporal
expression contained within the relative expression may be encoded
with a <gi>date</gi> or <gi>time</gi> element; in turn, those elements
may of course be relative, and thus contain <gi>date</gi> or
<gi>time</gi> elements within themselves.  This allows for deeply
nested structures such as <q>the third Sunday after the first Monday
before Lammastide in the fifth year of the King's second marriage
... </q> but so does natural language.</p>
<p>In the following examples, the <att>when</att> and <att>dur</att>
attributes have been used to simplify processing of variant forms of
expression:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><date when="1786-12-11">     
   <date dur="P14D">A fortnight</date>
   <offset>before</offset>
   <date when="1786-12-25" type="holiday">Christmas 1786</date>
</date></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I reached the station <time when="14:15:00">
  <time dur="PT30M0S">precisely half an hour</time>
  <offset>after</offset>
  <time when="13:45:00" type="occasion">the departure of the afternoon train to Boston</time>
</time></egXML></p>
<p>In the following example, a nested <gi>date</gi> element is
used to show that <q>my birthday</q> and the cited date are parts of
the same temporal expression, and hence to disambiguate the phrase
<q>A week before my birthday on 9th December</q>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><date when="--12-02">  
   <date>A week</date>
   <offset>before</offset>
   <date when="--12-09">    
      <date type="occasion">my birthday</date>
      on <date>9th December</date>
   </date>
</date></egXML>
The alternative reading of this phrase could be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><date when="--12-09">  
   <date>A week</date>
   <offset>before</offset>
   <date type="occasion" when="--12-16">my birthday</date>
   on <date>9th December</date>
 </date></egXML>
 </p>
<p>Where more complex or ambiguous expressions are involved, and where
it is desirable to make more explicit the interpretive processes
required, the feature structure notation described in chapter <ptr
target="#FS"/> may be used.  Consider, for example, the following
temporal expression which occurs in the <title>Scottish Temperance
Review</title> of August 1850, referring to the summer holiday known
in Glasgow simply as <q>the Fair</q>: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Not only is the city, <date
ana="#gf50">during the Fair</date>, a horrible nucleus of immorality
and wickedness; it sends our multitudes to pollute and demoralize the
country.</egXML>

</p>
<p>For the definition of the <att>ana</att> attribute, see chapter
<ptr target="#AI"/> (in particular <ptr target="#AIATTS"/>).  It is
used here to link the temporal phrase with an interpretation of it. 
Like most traditional fairs and market days, the
Glasgow Fair was established by local custom and could vary from year
to year.  Consequently, in order to provide such an interpretation, it
is necessary to draw upon additional information which may or may not
be located in the particular text in question.  In this case, it is
necessary at least to know the spatial and temporal context (year and
place) of the fair referred to.  These and other features required for
the analysis of this particular temporal expression may be combined together as one feature
structure of type <val>date-analysis</val>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs xml:id="gf50" type="date-analysis">
   <f name="event"><string>the Fair</string></f>
   <f name="place"><string>Glasgow</string></f>
   <f name="year"><numeric value="1850"/></f>
   <f name="from-value"><string>1850-08-08</string></f>
   <f name="to-value"><string>1850-09-19</string></f>
</fs></egXML>
For further discussion of  feature structure representation see chapter <ptr target="#FS"/>.  </p></div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="NDDATEA"><head>Absolute Dates and Times</head>

<p>The following are examples of absolute temporal expressions.</p>
<p>
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDDATEA-eg-169">The university's view
of American affairs produced a stinging attack by Edmund Burke in the
Commons debate of <date when="1775-10-26">26 October 1775</date></egXML>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#NDDATEA-eg-170"><date when="1993-05-14">Friday, 14 May 1993</date></egXML>

</p>
<p>It may be useful to categorize a temporal expression which is given
in terms of a named event, such as a public holiday, or a
named time such as <q>tea time</q> or <q>matins</q>: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">In New York, <date
type="occasion" when="--01-01">New Year's Day</date> is the quietest of
holidays, <date when="--07-04" type="occasion">Independence Day</date>
the most turbulent.</egXML>
</p>
<!-- Example needs to be re-worked 
<p>These components may be applied to dates using any calendar system
using  subcomponents equivalent to those listed above:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><title>Le Vieux Cordelier:
Journal r&#xE9;dig&#xE9; par Camille Desmoulins</title>,
<date calendar="Revolutionary" value="1794-02-03">   
   Quintidi
   Pluviose
   2e d&#xE9;cade,
   l'an 2 de la R&#xE9;publique Indivisible
</date></egXML> -->
<!-- NB - I removed value= attrs because I do not think -->
	<!-- they were "correct" in the sense that they were    -->
	<!-- non-ISO format and did not normalize; I'm not sure -->
	<!-- what "correct" would be, though; 1794-02-03 was    -->
	<!-- 1794-034 or 1794-W06-1 (per Emacs :-)              -->
	<!-- Date headline from Le Vieux Cordelier of that date -->
	<!-- Thanks to T. Munck for providing the above example -->
 <!-- /p -->
<p>Absolute temporal expressions denoting times which are given
in terms of seconds, minutes, hours, or of well-defined events
(e.g. <q>noon</q>, <q>sunset</q>) may similarly be represented using
the <gi>time</gi> element.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">The train leaves for Boston at
<time type="twentyfourHour" when="13:45:00">13:45</time></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">At <time type="occasion">sunset</time> we walked to the beach.</egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">The train leaves for Boston at
<time xml:lang="en-US" type="descriptive" when="13:45:00-05:00"> a quarter of two
</time></egXML>
 </p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="NDDATEISO"><head>More Expressive Normalizations</head>
    <!-- <?tei winita this needs to be put somewhere intelligent sb ?>-->
<p>The attributes for normalization of dates and times so far
described use a standard format defined by <title>XML Schema Part 2:
Datatypes Second Edition</title>. This format is widely accepted and
has significant software support. It is essentially a profile of ISO
8601 <title>Data elements and interchange formats — Information
interchange — Representation of dates and times</title>. The full ISO
standard provides formats not available in the W3C recommendation, for
example, the capability to refer to a date by its ordinal date or week
date, or to refer to a century. It also provides ways of indicating
duration and range. </p>

<p>When this module is included in a schema, the following additional
attributes are provided:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="att.datable.iso" atts="when-iso notBefore-iso notAfter-iso from-iso to-iso"/>
  <specDesc key="att.duration.iso" atts="dur-iso"/>
</specList>
These attributes may be used in preference to their W3C equivalent
when it is necessary to provide a normalized value in some form not
supported by the W3C attributes. For example,
a century date in the W3C format must be expressed as a range, using
the <att>from</att> together with either the <att>to</att> attribute or the
<att>dur</att> (duration) attribute:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><date from="1301" to="1400">fourteenth century</date>
<date from="1301" dur="P1Y">fourteenth century</date>
</egXML>

With the attribute <att>when-iso</att>, however, it is possible to
express the same normalized value in any of the following ways:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><date when-iso="13">fourteenth century</date>
<date when-iso="1301/1400">fourteenth century</date>
<date when-iso="1301/P1Y">fourteenth century</date>
</egXML>

 </p>

<specGrp>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.orgStateLike.xml"/>    
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.personal.xml"/>    
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.placeLike.xml"/>    
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.datable.iso.xml"/> 
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.duration.iso.xml"/> 
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.temporal.iso.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.duration.iso.xml"/>
    <specGrpRef target="#DNDPER"/>
    <specGrpRef target="#DNDPLAC"/>
    <specGrpRef target="#DCCAHPA"/>
    <specGrpRef target="#DNDNYM"/>
</specGrp>

</div>
</div></div>

<div><head>Module for Names and Dates</head>
<p>The   module described in this chapter makes available the following components:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DND" ident="namesdates">
  <altIdent type="FPI">Names, dates, persons and places</altIdent>
  <desc>Names and dates</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="fr">Noms, dates, personnes et lieux</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="zh-TW">名稱與日期</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Nomi e date</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Nomes e datas</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">名前モジュール</desc></moduleSpec>
The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>
</div>

</div>
