<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="PH" n="18">
<head>Representation of Primary Sources</head>

<p>This chapter defines a module intended for use in the
representation of primary sources, such as manuscripts or other
written materials. Section <ptr target="#PHFAX"/> provides elements
for the encoding of digital facsimiles or images of such materials,
while the remainder of the chapter discusses ways of encoding detailed
transcriptions of such materials. This module may also be useful in
the preparation of critical editions, but the module defined here is
distinct from that defined in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>, and may be
used independently of it. Detailed metadata relating to primary
sources of any kind may be recorded using the elements defined by the
manuscript description module discussed in chapter <ptr
target="#MS"/>, but again the present module may be used independently
if such data is not required.
</p>
<!-- following para may need revision? -->
<!-- p>It should be noted that, as elsewhere in these Guidelines,  this
chapter places more emphasis on the problems of representing the
textual components of a document than on those relating to the
description of the document's physical characteristics such as the
carrier medium or physical construction. These aspects, of particular
importance in codicology and the bibliographic study of incunables,
are touched on in the chapter on Manuscript Description (<ptr target="#MS"/>) and also form the subject of ongoing work in the TEI
Physical Bibliography workgroup.</p-->

<p>Although this chapter discusses manuscript materials more
frequently than other forms of written text, most of the
recommendations presented are equally applicable <foreign>mutatis
mutandis</foreign> to the encoding of printed matter or indeed any
form of written source, including monumental inscriptions. Similarly,
where in the following descriptions terms such as
<soCalled>scribe</soCalled>, <soCalled>author</soCalled>,
<soCalled>editor</soCalled>, <soCalled>annotator</soCalled> or
<soCalled>corrector</soCalled> are used, these may be re-interpreted
in terms more appropriate to the medium being transcribed. In printed
material, for example, the <soCalled>compositor</soCalled> plays a
role analogous to the <soCalled>scribe</soCalled>, while in an
authorial manuscript, the author and the scribe are the same person.
</p>

<div xml:id="PHFAX">

<head>Digital Facsimiles</head>

<p>These Guidelines are mostly concerned with the preparation of
digital texts in which pre-existing sources are transcribed or
otherwise converted into character form, and marked up in
XML. However, it is also very common practice to make a different form
of <soCalled>digital text</soCalled>, which is instead composed of
digital images of the original source, typically one per page, or
other written surface. We call such a resource a <term>digital
facsimile</term>. A digital facsimile may, in the simplest case, just
consist of a collection of images, with some metadata to identify them
and the source materials portrayed. It may sometimes contain a
variety of images of the same source pages, perhaps of different
resolutions, or of different kinds. Such a collection may form part of
any kind of document, for example a commentary of a codicological or
paeleographic nature, where there is a need to align explanatory text
with image data. It may also be complemented by
a transcribed or encoded version of the original source, which may be
linked to the page images. In this section we present elements
designed to support these various possibilities and discuss the
associated mechanisms provided by these Guidelines.</p>


<p>When this module is included in a schema, the class
<ident type="class">att.global</ident> is extended to include two new pointer
attributes,  <att>facs</att> and <att>change</att>:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.global.facs" atts="facs"/>
<specDesc key="att.global.change" atts="change"/>
</specList>
The <att>change</att> attribute is discussed further below in section
<ptr target="#PH-changes"/>. The <att>facs</att> attribute is used to
associate any element in a transcription with an image of the
corresponding part of the source, by means of the usual URI pointing
mechanism. <!-- i.e. URI reference? --> </p>

<p>In the simple case where a digital text is composed of page
images, the <att>facs</att> attribute on the <gi>pb</gi> element may
be used to associate each image with an appropriate point in the text:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible">
<TEI>
<teiHeader> <!--...--></teiHeader>
<text>
  <pb facs="page1.png"/>
    <!-- text contained on page 1 is encoded here -->
  <pb facs="page2.png"/>
    <!-- text contained on page 2 is encoded here -->
</text>
</TEI>  
</egXML>

By convention, this encoding indicates that the image indicated by the
<att>facs</att> attribute represents the whole of the text following
the <gi>pb</gi> (pagebreak) element, up to the next <gi>pb</gi>
element. Any convenient milestone element (see further <ptr
target="#CORS5"/>) could be used in the same way; for example if the
images represent individual columns, the <gi>cb</gi> element might be
used.  Though simple, this method has some drawbacks. It does not
scale well to more complex cases where, for example, the images do not
correspond exactly with transcribed pages, or where the intention is
to align specific marked up elements with detailed images, or parts of
images. The management of information about the images may become more
difficult if references to them are scattered through many files
rather than being concentrated in a single identifiable
location. Nevertheless, this solution may be adequate for many
straightforward <soCalled>digital library</soCalled>
applications. </p>

<p>The recommended approach to encoding facsimiles is instead to use
the <att>facs</att> attribute in conjunction with the elements
<gi>facsimile</gi> or <gi>sourceDoc</gi>, and the elements
<gi>surface</gi>, <gi>surfaceGrp</gi>, and <gi>zone</gi>, which are
also provided by this module. These elements make it possible to
accommodate multiple images of each page, as well as to record
the position and relative size of elements identified any kind of
written surface and to link such elements with digital facsimile
images of them. Typical applications include the provision of full
text search in <soCalled>digital facsimile editions</soCalled>, and
ways of annotating graphics, for example so as to identify individuals
appearing in group portraits and link them to data about the peeople
represented. </p>

<p>The following elements are availble to represent components of a
digital facsimile:
<specList>
<specDesc key="facsimile"/>
<specDesc key="sourceDoc"/>
<specDesc key="surface"/>
<specDesc key="surfaceGrp"/>
<specDesc key="zone" atts="points"/>
</specList>
</p>

<p>Either of the <gi>facsimile</gi> or <gi>sourceDoc</gi> elements
may be used to represent a digital facsimile. Either may appear within a TEI
document along with, or instead of, the <gi>text</gi> element
introduced in section <ptr target="#DS"/>.  The <gi>facsimile</gi>
element is designed for the case where the digital facsimile contains
only images, whereas the <gi>sourceDoc</gi> element is for use in the
case where such images are complemented by a documentary
transcription. In this section, we first discuss the simpler case,
returning to the use of the <gi>sourceDoc</gi> element in section <ptr
target="#PH-transcr"/> below. When this module is selected therefore,
a legal TEI document may thus comprise any of the following :
<list type="simple">
<item>a TEI Header and a text element</item>
<item>a TEI Header and a facsimile element</item>
<item>a TEI Header and a sourceDoc element</item>
<item>a TEI Header, a facsimile element, and a text element</item>
<item>a TEI Header, a sourceDoc element, and a text element</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Like the <gi>text</gi> element, a <gi>facsimile</gi> element may
also contain an optional <gi>front</gi> or <gi>back</gi> element, used
in the same way as described in sections <ptr target="#DSFRONT"/> and
<ptr target="#DSBACK"/>. </p>
  
<p>In the simplest case, a facsimile just contains a series of
<gi>graphic</gi> elements, each of which identifies an image file:

<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<facsimile>
  <graphic url="page1.png"/>
  <graphic url="page2.png"/>
  <graphic url="page3.png"/>
  <graphic url="page4.png"/>
</facsimile>
</egXML>

If desired, the <gi>binaryObject</gi> element described in <ptr
target="#COGR"/> (or any other element from the <ident
type="class">model.graphicLike</ident> class) can be used instead of a
<gi>graphic</gi>.</p>

<p>In this simple case, the four page images are understood to
represent the complete facsimile, and are to be read in the sequence
given. Suppose, however, that the second page of this particular work
is available both as an ordinary photograph and as an infra-red image,
or in two different resolutions. The <gi>surface</gi> element may be
used to group the two image files, since these correspond with the
same area of the work:

  <egXML  xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<facsimile>
  <graphic url="page1.png"/>
  <surface>
   <graphic url="page2-highRes.png"/>
   <graphic url="page2-lowRes.png"/>
  </surface>
  <graphic url="page3.png"/>
  <graphic url="page4.png"/>
</facsimile>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>The <gi>surface</gi> element provides a way of indicating that the
two images of page2 represent the same surface within the source
material. A <term>surface</term> might be one side of a piece of paper
or parchment, a face of a monument, a billboard, a membrane of a
scroll, or indeed any two-dimensional surface, of any size. </p>

<p>The <gi>surfaceGrp</gi> element may be used to indicate that
two (or more) surfaces are associated in some way, for
example because they represent the recto and verso of the same leaf,
as in this example:
  <egXML  xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<facsimile>
<surfaceGrp n="leaf1">
  <surface>
    <graphic url="page1.png"/>
  </surface>
  <surface>
   <graphic url="page2-highRes.png"/>
   <graphic url="page2-lowRes.png"/>
  </surface>
</surfaceGrp>
</facsimile>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>Simply grouping related graphics is not however the main purpose of
the <gi>surface</gi> element: rather it is to help identify the
location and size of the various two-dimensional spaces constituting
the digital facsimile. The actual dimensions of the object represented
are not provided by the <gi>surface</gi> element; instead, the
<gi>surface</gi> element defines an abstract coordinate space which
may be used to address parts of the image. Four attributes supplied by
the <ident type="class">att.coordinated</ident> class are used to
define this space. <!-- A fifth attribute <att>points</att> may be
used to define a polygon of any shape using this coordinate system:-->
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.coordinated" atts="ulx uly lrx lry"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p> By default, the same coordinate space is used for a
<gi>surface</gi> and for all of its child elements.<note
place="bottom">The coordinate space may be thought of as a grid
superimposed on a rectangular space. Rectangular areas of the grid are
defined as four numbers <hi rend="math">a b c d</hi>: the first two
identify the grid point which is at the upper left corner of the
rectangle; the second two give the grid point located at the lower
right corner of the rectangle. The grid point <hi rend="math">a b</hi>
is understood to be the point which is located <hi rend="math">a</hi>
points from the origin along the <hi rend="math">x</hi> (horizontal)
axis, and <hi rend="math">b</hi> points from the origin along the <hi
rend="math">y</hi> (vertical) axis.</note> It may be most convenient
to derive a coordinate space from a digital image of the surface in
question such that each pixel in the image corresponds with a whole
number of units (typically 1) in the coordinate space. In other cases
it may be more convenient to use units such as millimetres.  Neither
practice implies any specific mapping between the co-ordinate system
used and the actual dimensions of the physical object represented.
</p>

<p>A <gi>surface</gi> element can contain one or more <gi>zone</gi>
elements, each of which represents a region or <term>bounding
box</term> defined in terms of the same coordinate space as that of
its parent <gi>surface</gi> element. A zone may be rectangular or
non-rectangular: a rectangular zone is defined by a sequence of four
co-ordinates in the same way as a surface; a non-rectangular zone is
defined using the attribute <att>points</att>, which provides a
sequence of co-ordinates, each of which specifies a point on the
perimeter of the zone.<note place="foot">The <att>points</att> attribute supplies a
<soCalled>points specification</soCalled> in the same form as that
required by the <gi>polyline</gi> or <gi>polygon</gi> elements in the
SVG standard. See <ptr
target="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG/shapes.html#PointsBNF"/>
</note></p>
<p>A zone may be used to define any region of interest, such as a
detail or illustration, or some part of the surface which is to be
aligned with a particular text element, or otherwise distinguished
from the rest of the surface.  A surface establishes a coordinate
system which may be used to address parts or the whole of some digital
representation of a written surface. A zone, by contrast, defines any
arbitrary area of interest within that surface, using the same
coordinate system. It might be bigger or smaller than its parent
surface, or might overlap its boundaries. The only constraint is that
it must be defined using the same coordinate system. </p>

<p>When an image of some kind is supplied within either a zone or a
surface, the implication is that the image represents the whole of the
zone or surface concerned. In the simple case therefore, we might
imagine a surface defining a page, within which there is a graphic
representing the whole of that page, and a number of zones defining
parts of the page, each with its own graphic, each representing a part
of the page. If however one of those graphics actually represents an
area larger than the page (for example to include a binding or the
surface of a desk on which the page rests), then it will be enclosed
by a zone with coordinates larger than those of the parent
surface. </p>


<p>For example, consider the following figure: <figure><head>Relation
between Page, Surface, and Zone</head> <graphic
url="Images/facs-fig2.jpg"/>
<head>Badische Landesbibliothek, 
Manuscript Durlach 1, Fols. 95v-96r </head></figure> This is an image of a two page
spread from a manuscript in the Badische Landesbibliothek,
Karlsruhe. We have no information as to the dimensions of the original
object, but the low resolution image displayed here contains 500
pixels horizontally and 321 pixels vertically. For convenience, we
might map each pixel to one cell of the coordinate space.<note
place="bottom">The coordinate space used here is based on pixels, but
the mapping between pixels and units in the coordinate space need not
be one-to-one; it might be convenient to define a more delicate grid,
to enable us to address much smaller parts of the image. This can be
done simply by supplying appropriate values for the attributes which
define the coordinate space; for example doubling them all would map
each pixel to two grid points in the coordinate space.</note> </p>

<p>We could then define a <gi>surface</gi> element corresponding with
the area of the image which represents the written two page spread in
terms of this coordinate space, simply by counting pixels in the
image.  The left corner of the two page spread appears 50 units from
the left of the image and 20 units from the top, while the bottom
right corner of the spread appears 400 units from the left of the
image, and 280 units from the top. We therefore define the written
surface within this image as follows: <egXML xml:lang="und"
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface ulx="50" uly="20" lrx="400" lry="280">
	<!-- ... -->
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML> To describe the whole image, we will also need to
define a zone of interest which represents an area larger than this
surface. Using the same coordinate system as that defined for the
surface, its coordinates are <val>0,0,500,321</val>. This zone of
interest can be defined by a <gi>zone</gi> element, within which we can
  place the uncropped <gi>graphic</gi>: <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface ulx="50" uly="20" lrx="400" lry="280">
<zone ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="500" lry="321">
<graphic url="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/50/Handschrift.karlsruhe.blb.jpg"/>
</zone></surface>
</facsimile></egXML>
</p>

<p>If desired, the <gi>binaryObject</gi> element described in <ptr target="#COGR"/> (or any other element from the
<ident type="class">model.graphicLike</ident> class) may be used instead of a
<gi>graphic</gi> element.</p>

<p>Since the image in this example is of a two page opening, we will
probably wish to define at least two nested zones, one for each page :

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface ulx="50" uly="20" lrx="400" lry="280">
<zone ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="500" lry="321">
<graphic url="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/5/50/Handschrift.karlsruhe.blb.jpg"/>
</zone>
 <zone ulx="50" uly="20" lrx="210" lry="280">
   <!-- left hand page -->
</zone>
<zone ulx="240" uly="25" lrx="400" lry="280">
  <!-- right hand page -->
</zone>
<zone ulx="90" uly="40" lrx="200" lry="225">
  <!--- written part of left hand page -->
</zone>
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML></p>
<p>As this example shows, in addition to acting as a container for
<gi>graphic</gi> elements, <gi>zone</gi> elements may be used to
identify parts of a surface for any analytical purpose. A zone may
also contain a nested surface, if for example a page has an additional
scrap of paper attached to it, as further discussed in section <ptr
target="#PH-surfzone"/> below.
</p>


<p>In the following extended example, we discuss a hypothetical
digital edition of an early 16th century French work, Charles de
Bovelles' <title>Géometrie Pratique</title>.<note place="bottom">The
image is taken from the collection at <ptr
target="http://ancilla.unice.fr/Illustr.html"/>, and was digitized
from a copy in the Bibliothèque Municipale de Lyon, by whose kind
permission it is included here.</note> In this edition, each page has
been digitized as a separate file: for example, recto page 49 is
stored in a file called <ident type="file">Bovelles-49r.png</ident>.
In the <gi>facsimile</gi> element used to contain the whole set of
pages, we define a <gi>surface</gi> element for this page, which we
situate within a coordinate scale running from 0 to 200 in the x
(horizontal) axis, and 0 to 300 in the y (vertical) axis.  The
<gi>surface</gi> element contains a <gi>graphic</gi> element which
represents the whole of this surface: <egXML xml:lang="und"
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
  <graphic url="Bovelles-49r.png"/>
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML> We can now identify distinct zones within the
page image using the coordinate scale defined for the surface. In
the following figure <ptr target="#facs-fig1"/> we show the upper part of the page, with
boxes indicating four such zones. Each of these will be represented by
a  <gi>zone</gi> element, given within the <gi>surface</gi>
element already defined, and specified in terms of the same
coordinate system. 
<figure xml:id="facs-fig1">
  <head>Zones within a Surface</head>
  <graphic url="Images/facs-fig1.png"/>
</figure>
The following encoding defines each of the four zones identified in
the figure above.
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
<graphic url="Bovelles-49r.png"/>
	<zone ulx="25" uly="25" lrx="180" lry="60"> 
	  <!-- contains the title -->
	</zone>
	<zone ulx="28" uly="75" lrx="175" lry="178"/> 
	<!--  contains the paragraph in italics -->
	<zone ulx="105" uly="76" lrx="175" lry="160"/> 
	<!-- contains the figure -->
	<zone ulx="45" uly="125" lrx="60" lry="130"/>
	<!-- contains the word "pendans" -->
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML> Note that the location of each zone is defined
independently but using the same coordinate system, so that they may
overlap freely. Zones need not nest within each other; moreover, as
noted earlier, a zone may fall outside the area of the surface which
defines its coordinate space.</p>

<p>A non rectangular-zone, for example that containing the word
<mentioned>cloches</mentioned> at bottom left of the page, could also be
defined, using the <att>points</att> attribute : 
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
<graphic url="Bovelles-49r.png"/>
<zone points="4.88147,31.0344 5.46483,30.7339 5.58857,32.2011
		5.85374,32.8022 6.10123,33.4386 5.53554,33.7744 5.11128,33.3679
		4.65166,32.2542"/>
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML>
</p>

<p>In this example a single <gi>graphic</gi> element has been
associated directly with the surface of the page rather than nesting
it within a zone. However, it is also possible to include multiple
<gi>zone</gi> elements which contain a <gi>graphic</gi> element, if
for example a detailed image is available. Since all <gi>zone</gi>
elements use the same coordinate system (that defined by their parent
<gi>surface</gi>), there is no need to demonstrate enclosure of one
zone within another by means of nesting. To continue the current
example, supposing that we have an additional image called
<ident type="file">Bovelles49r-detail.png</ident> containing an additional image
of the figure in the third zone above, we might encode that zone as
follows:
  <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <zone ulx="105" uly="76" lrx="175" lry="160"> 
    <graphic url="Bovelles49r-detail.png"/>
  </zone>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>If, as is often the case, a transcription of the zone identified in
this way is to be included in the encoded TEI document, this may be
done in two ways. If the transcription is regarded as a text in its
own right, organized and structured independently of its physical
realization in the document or documents represented by the facsimile,
then the recommended practice is to use the <gi>text</gi> element to
contain such a structured representation. The <gi>text</gi> element is
a sibling of the <gi>facsimile</gi> and <gi>sourceDoc</gi>
elements. This approach is illustrated in section <ptr
target="#PH-bov"/> below. Alternatively, if the transcription is
intended not to prioritize representation of the final text so much as
the process by which the document came to take its present form, or
the physical disposition of its component parts, it may be preferable
to use a subset of the available elements and to embed them within the
<gi>zone</gi> element, as further described in section <ptr
target="#PHZLAB"/> below.</p>

<div xml:id="PH-bov"><head>Parallel Transcription</head>

<p>Suppose now that we wish to align a transcription of the page discussed 
in the preceding section with particular zones.  We begin by giving each
relevant part of the facsimile an identifier:
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
	<zone xml:id="B49r" ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
		<graphic url="Bovelles-49r.png"/>
	</zone>
	<zone ulx="105" uly="76" lrx="175" lry="160"> 
		<graphic url="Bovelles49r-detail.png"/>
	</zone>
	<zone xml:id="B49rHead" ulx="25" uly="25" lrx="180" lry="60"/> 
	<!-- contains the title -->
	<zone xml:id="B49rPara2" ulx="28" uly="75" lrx="175" lry="178"/> 
	<!-- contains the paragraph in italics -->
	<zone xml:id="B49rFig1" ulx="105" uly="76" lrx="175" lry="160"/> 
	<!-- contains the figure -->
	<zone xml:id="B49rW457" ulx="45" uly="125" lrx="60" lry="130"/>
	<!-- contains the word "pendans" -->
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML> 
The alignment between transcription and image is made, as usual, by
means of the <att>facs</att> attribute:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="fr">
<pb facs="#B49r"/>
<fw>De Geometrie 49</fw>
<head facs="#B49rHead">
DU SON ET ACCORD DES CLOCHES ET <lb/> des alleures des chevaulx,
chariotz &amp; charges, des fontaines:&amp; <lb/> encyclie du monde,
&amp; de la dimension du corps humain.<lb/>
Chapitre septiesme</head>
<div n="1">
<p>Le son &amp; accord des cloches pendans en ung mesme <lb/> axe, est
faict en contraires parties.</p>
<p rend="it" facs="#B49rPara2">LEs cloches ont quasi fi<lb/>gures de rondes
pyra<lb/>mides imperfaictes &amp; <lb/> irregulieres: &amp; leur
accord se <lb/> fait par reigle geometrique. Com<lb/>me si les deux
cloches C &amp; D <lb/> sont <w facs="#B49rW457">pendans</w> à ung
mesme axe <lb/> ou essieu A B: je dis que leur ac<lb/>cord se fera en
co<ex>n</ex>traires parties<lb/> co<ex>m</ex>me voyez icy
figuré. Car qua<ex>n</ex>d <lb/> lune sera en hault, laultre
declinera embas. Aultrement si elles decli<lb/>nent toutes deux
ensembles en une mesme partie, elles seront discord, <lb/> &amp; sera
leur sonnerie mal plaisante à oyr.<figure facs="#B49rFig1"><graphic url="Bovelles49r-detail.png"/> </figure></p>
</div>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>It is also possible to point in the other direction, from a
<gi>surface</gi> or <gi>zone</gi> to the corresponding text. This is
the function of the <att>start</att> attribute, which supplies the
identifier of the element containing at least the start of the
transcribed text found within the surface or zone concerned. Thus,
another way of linking this page with its transcription would be
simply <egXML xml:lang="und"
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface start="#PB49R">
<graphic url="Bovelles-49r.png"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<body>
<div><!-- ... -->
<pb xml:id="PB49R"/>
<fw>De Geometrie 49</fw>
<!-- ... --></div>
</body>
</text>
 </egXML></p>

   
<specGrp xml:id="DPFACS">
&facsimile;
&sourceDoc;
&att.global.facs;
&att.global.change;
&surface;
&surfaceGrp;
&att.coordinated;
&zone;
&model.resourceLike;
</specGrp>

</div>

<div xml:id="PH-transcr"><head>Combining Transcription with Facsimile</head>

<p>A digitized source document may contain nothing more than page
images and a small amount of metadata. It may also contain an encoded
transcription of the pages represented, which may either be
<q>embedded</q> within a <gi>sourceDoc</gi> element, or supplied in
parallel to a <gi>facsimile</gi> as defined above.</p>

</div>

<div xml:id="PHZLAB"><head>Embedded Transcription</head>
<p>An <term>embedded transcription</term> is one in which words
and other written traces are encoded as subcomponents of elements
representing the physical surfaces carrying them rather than
independently of them. </p>
<p>The following elements are available for this purpose:
<specList>
<specDesc key="sourceDoc"/>
<specDesc key="surface"/>
<specDesc key="zone"/>
<!--specDesc key="patch" atts="binder height width flipping"/-->
<specDesc key="line"  />
<specDesc key="seg" />
</specList>
</p>

<p>The elements <gi>surface</gi>, <gi>surfaceGrp</gi>, and
<gi>zone</gi> were introduced above in section <ptr
target="#PHFAX"/>. </p>

<p>Most writing is linear, in the sense that it is composed of
discrete tokens organized physically into groups, typically organized
in a sequence corresponding with the way they are intended to be
read. Depending on the directionality of the writing system used, this
might be any combination of top-down and left to right, or vice
versa. The element <gi>line</gi> may be used to hold a complete group
of such tokens.  Where, however, the lineation is not considered
significant, any group of tokens may be indicated using the
<gi>zone</gi> element. The <gi>seg</gi> element described in section
<ptr target="#SASE"/> may also be used to indicate smaller sequences
of tokens within <gi>zone</gi>, or <gi>line</gi> as appropriate.
</p>

<p>As mentioned above, some or all of the written surfaces being
transcribed may be composed of physically distinct scraps. In the
following example, taken from the Walt Whitman Archive, two pieces of
newsprint have been glued to a piece of blue paper on which a poem is
being drafted:

<figure xml:id="sleeprs" ><graphic url="Images/whitman01.jpg" width="400px"/>
            <head rend="it">Single leaf of notes for a poem, possibly
	    related to the poem eventually titled Sleepers. From the
	    Walt Whitman Archive (Duke 258). </head>
         </figure>  

The two pieces of newsprint might simply be regarded as special kinds
of zone, but they are also  new surfaces, since they might
contain additional written zones themselves (such as the numbers in
this case).  </p>

<p>Using these elements, the Whitman draft above might be encoded as
follows: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#WHITMS2">
<surface>
   <zone>
      <line>Poem</line>
      <line>As in Visions of — at</line>
      <line>night —</line>
      <line>All sorts of fancies running through</line>
      <line>the head</line>
   </zone>
   <zone>
     <surface type="newsprint" attachment="glue" flipping="false">
<zone>Spring has just set in here, and the weather.... a
			   steamer </zone>
         <metamark function="sequence">2</metamark>
     </surface>
   </zone>
   <zone>
     <surface type="newsprint" attachment="glue" flipping="false">
       <zone>"The shores on either side of the Sound are... The In-       </zone>   
			   <metamark function="sequence">3</metamark>
   </surface>
 </zone>
</surface>
</egXML> 
</p>

<p>The <gi>metamark</gi> element used in this example is further
discussed below (<ptr target="#PH-meta"/>)</p>

<p>Note that in this example we have not included any <gi>graphic</gi>
element corresponding with the <gi>zone</gi> or <gi>surface</gi>
elements identified in the transcription. The encoder may choose to
complement a transcription with graphic representations of its source
at whatever level is considered effective, or not at all. Equally, the
encoder may choose to provide only graphics without any transcription,
to provide only a structured (non-embedded) transcription, or to
provide any combination of the three. </p>
<p>This example also lacks any co-ordinate information to specify
either the size of the two newspaper fragments or whereabouts on the
parent <gi>surface</gi> element they are to be found, other than the
reading order implicit in their sequence. Such information could be
added if desired by specifying a coordinate system on the outermost
<gi>surface</gi> element, and then indicating values within that
system for each of the two fragments, as was discussed above. We
discuss this in further detail in section <ptr target="#PH-surfzone"/>
below. </p>
</div>



<div xml:id="PHST"><head>Scope of Transcriptions</head>

<p>When transcribing a primary source, scholars may wish to record
information concerning individual readings of letters, words, or
larger units, whether the object is simply a
<soCalled>neutral</soCalled> transcription or a critical edition.  In
either case they may also wish to include other editorial material,
such as comments on the status or possible origin of particular
readings, corrections, or text supplied to fill lacunae.
</p>

<p>Such elements may also be used for digital transcriptions in which
the object is not to represent a finished text, but rather to
represent the creative process, as evidenced by different
<q>layers</q> or <q>traces</q> of writing in one or more
documents. Transcriptions of this kind are closely focussed on the
physical appearance of specific documents, needing to distinguish the
traces of different writing activities on them, such as additions and
deletions but also other indications of how the writing is to be read,
such as indications of transposition, re-affirmation of writing which
has been deleted, and so on.  Such distinctions are considered of
particular importance when dealing with authorial manuscripts, but are
also relevant in the case of historical sources such as charters or
other legal documents.</p>

<p>In either case, it is customary in transcriptions to register
certain features of the source, such as ornamentation, underlining,
deletion, areas of damage and lacunae. This chapter provides ways of
encoding such information:
<list type="simple">
<item>first, methods of recording editorial or other alterations to
the text, such as expansion of abbreviations, corrections, conjectures,
etc. (section <ptr target="#PHCH"/>)</item>
<item>then, methods of describing important extra-linguistic phenomena
in the source: unusual spaces, lines, page and line breaks, changes of
manuscript hand, etc. (section <ptr target="#PHPH"/>)</item>
<item>finally, a method of recording material such as running heads,
catch-words, and the like (section <ptr target="#PHSK"/>)</item></list></p>


<p>The remainder of this chapter describes a model for encoding such
transcriptions, in which elements such as <gi>mod</gi>, <gi>del</gi>,
etc. are used to mark writing traces and their functions within the
document. Each such element can be assigned to one or more
editorially-defined modification groups, termed a <term>change</term>,
by means of a global <att>change</att> attribute, which references a
definition for the modification group concerned, typically provided within
the TEI Header <gi>creation</gi> element; see further <ptr
target="#PH-changes"/>. The transcription itself may be embedded
within the elements <gi>surface</gi> and <gi>zone</gi> described in
section <ptr target="#PHFAX"/>, or provided in parallel within a
<gi>text</gi> element. Within a <gi>zone</gi>, the transcription may
be organized topographically in terms of lines of writing, using the
<gi>line</gi> element, or in terms of further nested zones, or as a
combination of the two; see further <ptr target="#PHZLAB"/>.
</p>



<p>These recommendations are not intended to meet every
transcriptional circumstance likely to be faced by any scholar.
Rather, they should be regarded as a base which can be elaborated if
necessary by different scholars in different disciplines
</p>
<!-- , with
distinct scholarly domains eventually developing their own document
types.  In time, the feature structure notation developed in chapter
<ptr target="#FS"/>, may also permit scholars to tailor the encoding
of complex transcriptional information in ways not here anticipated.
 We are conscious that a great deal of work remains to done in
these areas, and that the encoder will need to take even more
individual responsibility than usual in applying the recommendations
of this chapter in such contexts, but believe that these
recommendations form a good basis for such future work.-->

<p>As a rule, all elements which may be used in the course of a
transcription of a single witness may also be used in a critical
apparatus, i.e. within the elements proposed in chapter <ptr
target="#TC"/>.  This can generally be achieved by nesting a
particular reading containing tagged elements from a particular
witness within the <gi>rdg</gi> element in an <gi>app</gi> structure.
	</p>
<p>Just as a critical apparatus may contain transcriptional elements
within its record of variant readings in various witnesses, one may
record variant readings in an individual witness by use of the apparatus
mechanisms <gi>app</gi> and <gi>rdg</gi>.  This is discussed in
section <ptr target="#TCTR"/>.
	</p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="PHCH"><head>Altered, Corrected, and Erroneous Texts</head>

<p>In the detailed transcription of any source, it may prove necessary
to record various types of actual or potential alteration of the text:
expansion of abbreviations, correction of the text (either by author,
scribe, or later hand, or by previous or current editors or scholars),
addition, deletion, or substitution of material, and similar matters.
The sections below describe how such phenomena may be encoded using
either elements defined in the core module (defined in chapter <ptr
target="#CO"/>) or specialized elements available only when the module
described in this chapter is available.</p>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCO">
<head>Core elements for Transcriptional Work</head>
<p>In transcribing individual sources 
of any type, encoders may record corrections, normalizations,
expansions of abbreviations, additions, and omissions
using the elements described in section <ptr target="#COED"/>.
Those particularly relevant to this chapter include:
<specList>
<specDesc key="abbr"/>
<specDesc key="add"/>
<specDesc key="choice"/>
<specDesc key="corr"/>
<specDesc key="del"/>
<specDesc key="expan"/>
<specDesc key="gap"/>
<specDesc key="sic"/>
</specList>
	</p>
<p>Several of these elements bear additional attributes for specifying who
is responsible for the  interpretation represented by the markup,
and the certainty associated with it. In addition, some
of them bear an attribute allowing the markup to be categorised by
type and source. 
<specList>
  <specDesc key="att.editLike" atts="evidence source"/>
  <specDesc key="att.responsibility" atts="cert resp"/>
    <specDesc key="att.typed" atts="type subtype"/>
</specList>
The specific aspect of the markup described by these attributes differs
on different elements; for further discussion, see the relevant sections
below, especially section <ptr target="#PHHR"/>.</p>
<p>The following sections describe how the core elements just named may
be used in the transcription of primary source materials. </p></div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHAB"><head>Abbreviation and Expansion</head>

<p>The writing of manuscripts by hand lends itself to the use of
abbreviation to shorten scribal labour. Commonly occurring letters,
groups of letters, words, or even whole phrases, may be represented by
significant marks. This phenomenon of manuscript abbreviation is so
widespread and so various that no taxonomy of it is here attempted.
Instead, methods are shown which allow abbreviations to be encoded using
the core elements mentioned above.</p>
<p>A manuscript abbreviation may be viewed in two ways. One may
transcribe it as a particular sequence of letters or marks upon the
page: thus, a <q>p with a bar through the descender</q>, a
<q>superscript hook</q>, a <q>macron</q>. One may also interpret the
abbreviation in terms of the letter or letters it is seen as standing
for: thus, <q>per</q>, <q>re</q>, <q>n</q>. Both of these views are
supported by these Guidelines. </p>

<p>In many cases the glyph found in the manuscript source also exists
in the Unicode character set: for example the common Latin brevigraph
⁊, standing for <mentioned>et</mentioned> and often known as the
<soCalled>Tironian et</soCalled> can be directly represented in any
XML document as the Unicode character with code point
<val>U+204A</val> (see further <ptr target="#SG-er"/> and <ptr
target="#CHSH"/>). In cases where it does not, these Guidelines
recommend use of the <gi>g</gi> element provided by the <ident
type="module">gaiji</ident> module described in chapter <ptr
target="#WD"/>. This module allows the encoder great flexibility both
in processing and in documenting non-standard characters or glyphs,
including the ability to provide detailed documentation and images for
them.
</p>

<p>These two methods of coding abbreviation may also be combined. An
encoder may record, for any abbreviation, both the sequence of letters
or marks which constitutes it, and its sense, that is, the letter or
letters for which it is believed to stand. For example, in the
following fragment the phrase <mentioned>euery persone</mentioned> is
represented by a sequence of characters which may be transcribed
directly, using the <gi>g</gi> element to indicate the two brevigraphs
it contains as follows: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-BIBL-1">eu<g
ref="#b-er">er</g>y <g ref="#b-per">per</g>sone that loketh after
heuen hath a place in this ladder
<!-- elsewhere -->
<charDecl>
<char xml:id="b-er">
<!-- definition for the er brevigraph -->
</char>
<char xml:id="b-per">
<!-- definition for the per brevigraph -->
</char>
</charDecl></egXML> 
Note that in each case the <gi>g</gi> element may contain a suggested
replacement for the referenced brevigraph; this is purely advisory
however, and may not be appropriate in all cases. The referenced character
definitions may be located elsewhere in this or some other document,
typically forming part of a <gi>charDecl</gi> element, as described in
<ptr target="#D25-20"/>. </p>

<p>The transcriber may also wish to indicate that, because of the
presence of these particular characters, the two words are actually
abbreviations, by using the <gi>abbr</gi> element: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><abbr>eu<g
ref="#b-er">er</g>y</abbr> <abbr><g ref="#b-per">per</g>sone</abbr>
... </egXML> Alternatively, the transcriber may choose silently to
expand these abbreviations, using the <gi>expan</gi> element: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><expan>euery</expan>
<expan>persone</expan> ... </egXML> And, of course, the
<gi>choice</gi> element can be used to show that one encoding is an
alternative for the other: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><choice><abbr>eu<g
ref="#b-er">er</g>y</abbr><expan>euery</expan></choice></egXML>
</p>
<p>When abbreviated forms such as these are expanded, two processes
are carried out: some characters not present in the abbreviation are
added (always), and some characters or glyphs present in the
abbreviation are omitted or replaced (often). For example, when the
abbreviation <mentioned>Dr.</mentioned> is expanded to
<mentioned>Doctor</mentioned>, the dot in the abbreviation is removed,
and the letters <mentioned>octo</mentioned> are added. 
Where detailed markup of abbreviated
words is required, these two aspects may be marked up explicitly,
using the following elements:
<specList>
<specDesc key="ex"/>
<specDesc key="am"/>
</specList>
Using these elements,
a transcriber may indicate the status of the individual letters or signs within both the abbreviation and the
expansion. The <gi>am</gi> element surrounds characters or signs such
as tittles or tildes, used to indicate the presence of an
abbreviation, which are typically removed or replaced by other
characters  in
the expanded form of the abbreviation:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><abbr>eu<am><g ref="#b-er"/></am>y</abbr> <abbr><am><g ref="#b-per"/></am>sone</abbr> ... </egXML>
while the <gi>ex</gi> element may be used to indicate those characters
within the expansion which are not present in the abbreviated
form. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><expan>eu<ex>er</ex>y</expan>
<expan><ex>per</ex>sone</expan> ... </egXML> 
The content of the <gi>abbr</gi> element should usually include the
whole of the abbreviated word, while the <gi>expan</gi> element should
include the whole of its expansion. If this is not considered
necessary, the <gi>am</gi> and <gi>ex</gi> elements may be used within
a <gi>choice</gi> element,
as in this example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">eu<choice><am><g ref="#b-er"/></am><ex>er</ex></choice>y 
<choice><am><g ref="#b-per"/></am><ex>per</ex></choice>sone ... </egXML> 
</p>
<p>As implied in the preceding discussion, making decisions about
which of these various methods of representing abbreviation to use
will form an important part of an encoder's practice. As a rule, the
<gi>abbr</gi> and <gi>am</gi> elements should be preferred where it is wished to
signify that the content of the element is an abbreviation, without
necessarily indicating what the abbreviation may stand for. The
<gi>ex</gi> and <gi>expan</gi> elements should be used where it is wished to signify that
the content of the element is not present in the source but has been
supplied by the transcriber, without necessarily indicating the
abbreviation used in the original. The decision as to which course of
action is appropriate may vary from abbreviation to abbreviation;
there is no requirement that the one system be used throughout a
transcription, although doing so will generally simplify
processing. The choice is likely to be a matter of editorial policy.
If the highest priority is to transcribe the text literatim, while
indicating the presence of abbreviations, the choice will be to use
<gi>abbr</gi> or <gi>am</gi> throughout. If the highest priority is to present a
reading transcription, while indicating that some letters or words are
not actually present in the original, the choice will be to use
<gi>ex</gi> or <gi>expan</gi>
throughout.</p>
<p>Further information may be attached to instances of these elements by
the <gi>note</gi> element, on which see section <ptr target="#CONO"/>, and
by use of the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes. In this
instance from the English <title>Brut</title>,
a note is attached to an editorial expansion of the tail on the final d
of <mentioned>good</mentioned> to <mentioned>goode</mentioned>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-01">For alle the while that I had
good<ex xml:id="exp01">e</ex>
I was welbeloued</egXML>
 <!--  abbr="&#x027d;" -->
Then the note: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><note target="#exp01">The stroke added to the final d could signify the
plural ending (-es, -is, -ys&gt;) but the singular <hi rend="it">goode</hi> was used with the meaning <q>property</q>,
<q>wealth</q>, at this time (v. examples quoted in OED, sb. Good,
C. 7, b, c, d and 8 spec.)</note></egXML> The editor might declare a
degree of certainty for this expansion, based on the OED examples, and
state the responsibility for the expansion: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For alle the while that I had
good<ex resp="#mp" cert="high">e</ex> I was welbeloued</egXML> The
value supplied for the <att>resp</att> attribute should point to the
name of the editor responsible for this and possibly other
interventions; an appropriate element therefore might be a
<gi>respStmt</gi> element in the header like the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<respStmt xml:id="mp">
<resp>Editorial emendations</resp>
<name>Malcom Parkes</name>
</respStmt></egXML>
Observe that the <att>cert</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes are
used with the <gi>ex</gi> element only to indicate
confidence in the content of the element (i.e. the expansion), and
responsibility for suggesting this expansion  respectively. </p>
<p>The <gi>choice</gi> element may be used to indicate that the
proposed expansion is one way of encoding what might equally well be
represented as an abbreviation, represented by the hooked D, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For alle the while that I had
<choice><sic>goo<abbr>&#x0257;</abbr></sic>
<expan resp="#mp" cert="high">good<ex>e</ex></expan></choice>
I was welbeloued</egXML>
If it is desired to express aspects of certainty and responsibility
for some other aspect of the use of these elements, then the
mechanisms discussed in chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> should be
used. See also <ptr target="#PHHR"/> for discussion of the issues of
certainty and responsibility in the context of transcription.</p>

<p>If more than one expansion for the same abbreviation is to be
recorded, multiple notes may be supplied. It may also be appropriate
to use the markup for critical apparatus; an example is given in
section <ptr target="#TCTR"/>.</p>
</div>


<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCC"><head>Correction and Conjecture</head>

<p>The <gi>sic</gi>, <gi>corr</gi>, and <gi>choice</gi> elements,
defined in the <ident type="module">core</ident> module should be used to
indicate passages deemed in need of correction, or actually corrected,
during the  transcription of a source. For
example, in the manuscript of William James's <title>A Pluralistic
Universe</title> as edited by Fredson Bowers (Cambridge: Harvard
University Press, 1977), a sentence first written <q rend="display">One
must have lived longer with this system, to appreciate its
advantages.</q> has been modified by James to begin <q>But One must
...</q>, without the inital capital O having been reduced to
lowercase. This non-standard orthography could be recorded thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">But <sic>One</sic>
must have lived ...</egXML> or corrected: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">But <corr>one</corr> must
have lived ...</egXML> or the two possibilities might be represented
as a choice: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">But
<choice><sic>One</sic><corr>one</corr></choice> must have lived
...</egXML></p>
<p>Similarly, in this example from Albertus Magnus,
both a manuscript error <mentioned>angues</mentioned> and its correction
<mentioned>augens</mentioned> are registered within a  <gi>choice</gi> element:
<egXML xml:lang="la" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-02">Nos autem iam ostendimus quod nutrimentum
et <choice><sic>angues</sic><corr>augens</corr></choice>.</egXML>
</p> 
<p>Note that the <gi>corr</gi> element is used to provide a corrected
form which is <emph>not</emph> present in the source; in the case of a
correction made in the source itself, whether scribal, authorial, or
by some other hand, the <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>,
and <gi>subst</gi> elements described in <ptr target="#PHAD"/> should be
used.</p>
<p>The <gi>sic</gi> element is used to mark passages considered by the
transcriber to be erroneous; in such cases, the <gi>corr</gi> element
indicates the transcriber's correction of them. Where the transcriber
considers that one or more words have been erroneously omitted in the
original source and corrects this omission, the <gi>supplied</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#PHOM"/> should be used in preference to <gi>corr</gi>. Thus,
in the following example, from George Moore's draft of additional materials for
<title>Memoirs of My Dead Life</title>,
the transcriber supplies the word <mentioned>we</mentioned> omitted by the author:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-03">You see that I avoid the word create for we
create nothing <supplied>we</supplied> develope.</egXML>
</p>
<p>As with <gi>expan</gi> and <gi>abbr</gi>, the
choice as to whether to record simply that there is an apparent error,
or simply that a correction has been applied, or to record both
possible readings within a  <gi>choice</gi> element is
left to the encoder. The decision is likely to be a matter of editorial policy,
which might be applied consistently throughout or decided case by case.
If the highest priority is to present an uncorrected transcription while
noting perceived errors in the original, the choice will typically
be to use only <gi>sic</gi> throughout. If the highest priority is to
present a reading transcription, while indicating that perceived errors
in the original have been corrected, the choice will be to use
only <gi>corr</gi> throughout.</p>

<p>Further information may be attached to instances of these elements by
the <gi>note</gi> element and <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes. Instances of these elements may also be classified
according to any convenient typology using the <att>type</att>
attribute. </p>
<p>For example, consider the following encoding of an
emendation in the  Hengwrt manuscript proposed by  E. Talbot
Donaldson: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Telle me also, to what conclusioun
Were membres maad, of generacioun
And of so parfit wis a 
<choice xml:id="corr117"><sic>wight</sic><corr>wright</corr></choice>
ywroght?
<!-- ... -->
<note target="#corr117">This emendation of the Hengwrt copy text,
based on a Latin source and on the reading of three late
and usually unauthoritative manuscripts, was proposed
by E. Talbot Donaldson in <bibl><title>Speculum</title> 40 (1965)
626–33.</bibl></note>
</egXML>
The <gi>note</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#CONO"/> may be
used to give a more detailed discussion of the motivation for or scope
of a correction. If linked by means of a pointer (as in this example)
it may be located anywhere convenient within the transcription;
typically all detailed notes will be collected together in a separate
<gi>div</gi> element in the <gi>back</gi>. Alternatively, the pointer
may be omitted, and the <gi>note</gi> placed immediately adjacent to
the element being annotated. The advantage of the former solution  is
that it permits the same annotation to refer to several corrections,
by supplying more than one pointer in the <att>target</att> attribute
of the <gi>note</gi>, as shown in the example below. </p>
<p>The attribute <att>cert</att> may be used to indicate the
degree of confidence ascribed by the encoder to the proposed
emendation on a broad scale: high, medium, or low. The attribute
<att>resp</att> is used to indicate who is responsible for the
proposed emendation. Its value is a pointer, which will typically
indicate a <gi>respStmt</gi> or <gi>name</gi> element in the header of the transcribed
document, but can point anywhere, for example to some online authority
file. Using these two attributes, the <gi>corr</gi> element
presented above might usefully be enhanced as follows:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<!-- somewhere in the header ... --> 
<name xml:id="ETD">E Talbot Donaldson</name> 
<!-- ... -->
And of so parfit wis a 
<choice><sic>wight</sic><corr resp="#ETD" cert="medium">wright</corr></choice>
ywroght?
</egXML></p>

<p>As remarked above, where the same annotation applies to several
corrections, this may be represented by supplying multiple pointers on
the note. Consider for example such corrections as the following, in
Dudo of S. Quentin. Parkes cites two cases in this manuscript of the
same phenomenon: <egXML xml:lang="la" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-04">quamuis <choice xml:id="sic-1"><sic>mens</sic><corr>iners</corr></choice> que nutu dei
gesta sunt ... unde esset uiriliter <choice xml:id="sic-2"><corr>uegetata</corr><sic>negata</sic></choice></egXML>
which may be described as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><note target="#sic-1 #sic-2">Substitution of a more familiar word which resembles
graphically what the scribe should be copying but which does not make
sense in the context.</note></egXML>
</p>
<p>The <att>target</att> attribute on the <gi>note</gi> element
indicates the <gi>choice</gi> elements which exemplify this kind of
scribal error. This necessitates the addition of an identifier to each
<gi>choice</gi> element. However, if the number of corrections is large
and the number of notes is small, it may well be both more practical
and  more appropriate to
regard the collection of annotations as constituting a typology and
then use the <att>type</att> attribute. Suppose that the note given
above is one of half a dozen possible kinds of corrected phenomena
identified in a given text; others might include, say, <q>repetition
of a word from the preceding line</q>, etc. The <att>type</att>
attribute on the <gi>corr</gi> element can be used to specify an
arbitrary code for the particular kind of correction (or other
editorial intervention) identified within it. This code can be chosen
freely and is not treated as a pointer. 
<egXML xml:lang="la" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">quamuis
<choice><sic>mens</sic><corr type="graphSubs">iners</corr></choice> que nutu dei
gesta sunt ... unde esset uiriliter <choice><corr type="graphSubs">uegetata</corr><sic>negata</sic></choice></egXML>
Note that this encoding might be extended to include a range of
possible corrections:
<egXML xml:lang="la" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">quamuis
<choice><sic>mens</sic><corr type="graphSubs">iners</corr><corr type="reversal">inres</corr></choice> que nutu dei
gesta sunt ...</egXML>
In addition, the conscientious encoder will provide documentation
explaining the circumstances in which particular codes are judged
appropriate. A suitable location for this might be within the
<gi>correction</gi> element of the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of the
header, which might include a <gi>list</gi> such as the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<correction>
<p>The following codes are used to categorise corrections identified
in this transcription:
<list type="gloss">
<label>graphSubs</label>
<item>Substitution of a more familiar word which resembles
graphically what the scribe should be copying but which does not make
sense in the context.</item>
<!-- ... -->
</list></p></correction></egXML>
A <att>subtype</att> attribute may be used in conjunction with the
<att>type</att> for subclassification purposes: the above examples
might thus be represented as <tag>choice type="substitution"
subtype="graphicResemblance"</tag> for example. </p>
<p>For a given project, it may well be desirable to limit the possible
values for the <att>type</att> or <att>subtype</att> attributes automatically. This is easily
done but requires customization of the TEI system using techniques
described in <ptr target="#MD"/>, in particular <ptr target="#MDMDAL"/>, which should be consulted for further information
on this topic.</p>
<p>When making a correction in a source which forms part of a textual
tradition attested by many witnesses, a textual editor will
sometimes use a reading from one witness to correct the reading of the
source text. In the general case, such encoding is best achieved with  the
mechanisms provided by the module for textual criticism described in
chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>. However, for simple cases, the
<att>source</att> attribute of the <gi>corr</gi> attribute may
suffice. In the passage from Chaucer's
<title>Wife of Bath's Tale</title> mentioned above, Parkes proposes to
emend the problematic word <mentioned>wight</mentioned> to
<mentioned>wyf</mentioned> which is the reading found in the Cambridge
manuscript Gg.1. 27. This may be simply represented as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
And of so parfit wis a 
<choice><sic>wight</sic><corr resp="#mp" source="#Gg">wyf</corr></choice>
ywroght?</egXML>
The value of the <att>source</att> attribute here is, like the value
of the <att>resp</att> attribute, a pointer, in this case indicating
the manuscript used as a witness. Elsewhere in the transcribed text, a
list of witnesses used in this text will be given, one of which has an
identifier <code>Gg</code>. Each witness will be represented either by
a <gi>witness</gi> element (see <ptr target="#TCAPLL"/>) or more fully
by a <gi>msDesc</gi> element (see <ptr target="#MS"/>) :
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<msDesc xml:id="Gg">
      <msIdentifier>
        <settlement>Cambridge</settlement>
        <repository>University Library</repository>
        <idno>Gg.1. 27</idno>
      </msIdentifier>
<!-- further description of the manuscript here -->
</msDesc></egXML>
</p>

<p>The <gi>app</gi> element described in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>
provides a more powerful way of representing all three possible
readings in parallel: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">And of so
parfit wis a
<app>
  <rdg wit="#Hg">wight</rdg>
  <rdg wit="#Ln #Ry2 #Ld">wright</rdg>
  <rdg wit="#Gg">wyf</rdg>
</app></egXML></p>
<p>This encoding simply records the three readings found in the
various traditions, and gives (by means of the <att>wit</att>
attribute) an indication of the witnesses supporting each. If the
<att>resp</att> attribute were supplied on the <gi>rdg</gi> element,
it would indicate the person responsible for asserting that the
manuscript indicated has this reading, who is not necessarily the same
as the person responsible for asserting that this reading should
be used to correct the others. Editorial intervention elements such as
<gi>corr</gi> can however be nested within a <gi>rdg</gi> to provide
this additional information:

 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">And of so
parfit wis a
<app>
  <rdg wit="#Hg">wight</rdg>
  <rdg wit="#Ln #Ry2 #Ld"><corr resp="#ETD">wright</corr></rdg>
  <rdg wit="#Gg"><corr resp="#mp">wyf</corr></rdg>
</app></egXML>

This encoding asserts that the reading <mentioned>wyf</mentioned>
found in Gg is regarded as a correction by Parkes. </p>

<p>Like the <att>resp</att> attribute, the <att>cert</att> attribute
may be used with both <gi>corr</gi> and <gi>rdg</gi> elements. When
used on the <gi>rdg</gi> element, these attributes indicate confidence
in and responsibility for identifying the reading within the sources
specified; when used on the <gi>corr</gi> element they indicate
confidence in and responsibility for the use of the reading to correct
the base text. If no other source is indicated (either by the
<att>source</att> attribute, or by the <att>wit</att> attribute of a
parent <gi>rdg</gi>), the reading supplied within a <gi>corr</gi> has
been provided by the person indicated by the <att>resp</att>
attribute.
</p>

<p>If it is desired to express certainty of or responsibility
for some other aspect of the use of these elements, then the
mechanisms discussed in chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> may be found
useful. See also <ptr target="#PHHR"/> for further discussion of the
issues of certainty and responsibility in the context of
transcription.</p></div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHAD"><head>Additions and Deletions</head>

<p>Additions and deletions observed in a source text may be described
using the following elements:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="add"/>
  <specDesc key="addSpan"/>
  <specDesc key="del"/>
  <specDesc key="delSpan"/>
</specList>
Of these, <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> are included in the core
module, while <gi>addSpan</gi> and <gi>delSpan</gi> are available only
when using the module defined in this chapter. These particular elements
are members of the <ident type="class">att.spanning</ident> class,
from which they inherit the following attribute:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.spanning" atts="spanTo"/>
</specList>

</p>

<p>Further characteristics of each addition and deletion, such as the
hand used, its effect (complete or incomplete, for example), or its
position in a sequence of such operations may conveniently be recorded
as attributes of these elements, all of which are members of the
<ident type="class">att.transcriptional</ident> class:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.transcriptional" atts="seq status hand"/>
</specList>
</p>


<p>As described in section <ptr target="#COED"/>, the <gi>add</gi>
element is used to record any manuscript addition observed in the
text, whether it is considered to be authorial or scribal. In the
autograph manuscript of Max Beerbohm's <title>The Golden
Drugget</title>, the author's addition of <mentioned>do
ever</mentioned> may be recorded as follows, with the <att>hand</att>
attribute indicating that the addition was Beerbohm's by referencing a
<gi>handNote</gi> element defined elsewhere in the document (see
further <ptr target="#PHDH"/>): 

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-05">Some things are best at first
sight. Others — and here is one of them — <add hand="#mb">do
ever</add> improve by recognition ....
<handNote xml:id="mb">Max Beerbohm holograph</handNote>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>Similarly, when the <gi>del</gi> element is used to
record manuscript deletions. In the autograph manuscript of D.
H. Lawrence's <title>Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani</title>
the author's deletion of <mentioned>my</mentioned> may be recorded as
follows. In this case, the <att>hand</att> attribute indicating that
the deletion was Lawrence's is complemented by a <att>rend</att>
attribute indicating that the deletion was by strike-through: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-06">For I hate this <del rend="strikethrough" hand="#dhl">my</del> body, which is so dear to me
...
<handNote xml:id="dhl">D H Lawrence holograph</handNote>

</egXML></p>


<p>If deletions are classified systematically, the <att>type</att>
attribute may be useful to indicate the classification; when they are
classified by the manner in which they were effected, or by their
appearance, however, this will lead to a certain arbitrariness in
deciding whether to use the <att>type</att> or the <att>rend</att>
attribute to hold the information. In general, it is recommended that
the <att>rend</att> attribute be used for description of the
appearance or method of deletion, and that the <att>type</att>
attribute be reserved for higher level or more abstract
classifications.</p>

<p>The <att>place</att> attribute is also available to indicate the
location of an addition. For example, consider the following passage
from a draft letter by Robert Graves:
<figure><graphic url="Images/PHgraves2.png" width="500px"/></figure>
At the end of this extract, the writer
inserts the word <q>cant,</q> above the line, with a stroke to
indicate insertion. Assuming that we have previously defined the identifier
<code>RG</code> somewhere:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listPerson>
<person xml:id="RG">
<!-- information about Robert Graves here -->
</person>
</listPerson>
</egXML>,
 this extract might now be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-07">
The O.E.D.  is not a dictionary so much as a corpus of
precedents <del hand="#RG">in the</del>: current, 
obsolete, <add hand="#RG" place="above">cant,</add> 
cataphretic and nonce-words are all included. </egXML>
A little earlier in the same extract, Graves writes <q>for an
abridgement</q> above the line, and then deletes it. This may be
encoded similarly:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-07">
As for 'significant artist.' You quote the  O.E.D <add hand="#RG" place="above"><del>for an abridgement</del></add>in
explanation... </egXML>
Similarly, in the margin, the word <q>Norton</q> has been added and then deleted:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-07">
You quote the <add hand="#RG" place="margin"><del>Norton</del></add>
O.E.D...</egXML>
The word <q>O.E.D.</q> in this first sentence has also clearly been
the result of some  redrafting: it may be that Graves started to write
<q>Oxford</q>, and then changed it; it may be that he inserted other
punctuation marks between the letters before replacing them with the
centre dots used elsewhere to represent this acronym. We do not deal
with these possibilities here, and mention them only to indicate that
any encoding of manuscript material of this complexity will need to
make decisions about what is and is not worth mentioning.
</p>

<!-- line from the typescript of Eliot's
<title>The Waste Land</title> the word
<mentioned>foe</mentioned> is crossed out, and the word
<mentioned>friend</mentioned> is written in the right margin,
together with an insertion mark. <figure>
<graphic url="Images/PHfigEliot-1.png" width="600px"/></figure>
This line might be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-07">
"Oh keep the Dog far hence, that's <del>foe</del> to men, 
<add place="margin">friend</add></egXML>
The deletion and the addition in this example are in the same hand,
presumably Eliot's. Other deletions in the typescript are in different
hands and done in different ways: for example, at the start of the same
passage: <figure><graphic url="Images/PHfigEliot-2.png" width="600px"/></figure>
The first two lines of this passage might be
encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-07">
<l><add place="above">Unreal</add><del rend="overtyped">Terrible</del> City<del resp="#EP">,</del> I have sometimes seen
and see</l>
<l>Under the brown fog of <del resp="#EP" rend="box">your</del> winter
dawn...</l></egXML>
The typescript originally read <q>Terrible City</q>: the first word
was then overtyped with xs to delete it, and the word
<mentioned>Unreal</mentioned> typed above the deletion. Two further
deletions here are attributed to Pound (EP): the comma following
<mentioned>City</mentioned>, and the word <mentioned>your</mentioned>;
the latter deletion being marked by a box drawn around it rather than by
a line through it. </p>
-->


<p>An encoder may also wish to indicate that an addition replaces a
specific deletion, that is to encode a substitution as a single
intervention in the text. This may be achieved by grouping the
addition and deletion together within a <gi>subst</gi> element.
At the end of the passage illustrated above, Graves first writes <q>It is the
expressed...</q>, then deletes <q>It is</q>, and substitutes an
uppercase T at the start of <q>the</q>. 

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-07">
...
are all included. <del hand="#RG">It is</del> 
<subst><add>T</add><del>t</del></subst>he expressed
</egXML>

<!--
"Oh keep the Dog far hence, that's 
<subst><del>foe</del><add place="margin">friend</add></subst> to men, 
</egXML>-->
The use of this element and  of the <att>seq</att> attribute to indicate the
order in which interventions such as deletions are believed to have
occurred are  further discussed in section <ptr target="#PHSU"/> below.
</p>

<p>The <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> elements defined in the core module
suffice only for the description of additions and deletions which fit
within the structure of the text being transcribed, that is, which
each deletion or addition is completely contained by the structural
element (paragraph, line, division) within which it occurs. Where this
is not the case, for example because an individual addition or deletion
involves  several
distinct structural subdivisions, such as poems or prose items, or
otherwise
crosses a structural boundary in the text being encoded, special
treatment is needed. The <gi>addSpan</gi> and
<gi>delSpan</gi> elements are provided by this  module for that
purpose. (For a general discussion of the issue see further <ptr target="#NH"/>).</p>

<p>In this example of the use of <gi>addSpan</gi>, the
insertion by Helgi
Ólafsson  of a gathering containing four neo-Eddic poems into
<title>Lbs 1562 4to</title> is recorded as follows.  
<!-- added clarificatory sentence -->
A <gi>handNote</gi> element is first declared, within the header of the
document, to associate the identifier <val>heol</val> with Helgi. Each
of the added poems is encoded as a distinct <gi>div</gi> element. In
the body of the text, an <gi>addSpan</gi> element is placed to mark
the beginning of the span of added text, and an <gi>anchor</gi> is
used to mark its end.  The <att>hand</att> attribute on the
<gi>addSpan</gi> element ascribes responsibility for the addition to
the manuscript to Helgi, and the <att>spanTo</att> attribute points to
the end of the added text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-08"><handNote xml:id="heol" scribe="HelgiÓlafsson"/>
<!-- ... -->
<body>
<div><!-- text here --></div>
<addSpan n="added gathering" hand="#heol" spanTo="#p025"/>
<div><!-- text of first added poem here --></div>
<div><!-- text of second added poem here --></div>
<div><!-- text of third added poem here --></div>
<div><!-- text of fourth added poem here --></div>
<anchor xml:id="p025"/>
<div><!-- more text here --></div></body>
</egXML></p>
<p>The <gi>delSpan</gi> element is used in the same way. An authorial
manuscript will often contain <!-- For example,
in the Eliot typescript mentioned above, there are --> several occasions
where sequences of whole lines are marked for deletion, either by boxes or by being
struck out. If the encoder is marking up individual verse lines with
the <gi>l</gi> element, such deletions are problematic: deletion of
two consecutive lines should be regarded as a single deletion, but the
<gi>del</gi> element must be properly nested within a single
<gi>l</gi> element. The <gi>delSpan</gi> element solves this problem:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<l>Flowed up the hill and down King William Street,</l>
<delSpan spanTo="#EPdelEnd" resp="#EP" rend="strikethrough"/>
<l>To where Saint Mary Woolnoth kept the time,</l>
<l>With a dead sound on the final stroke of nine.</l>
<anchor xml:id="EPdelEnd"/>
<l>There I saw one I knew, and stopped him, crying "Stetson!</l>...
</egXML>
</p>
<p>It is also often the case that deletions and additions may themselves contain other
deletions and additions. For example, in
 Thomas Moore's autograph of the second version of
<title>Lalla Rookh</title> two lines are marked for omission by vertical
strike-through. Within the first of the two lines, the word
<mentioned>upon</mentioned> has also been struck out, and the word
<mentioned>over</mentioned> has been added: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-09"><l>
   <delSpan rend="verticalStrike" spanTo="#delend01"/>
   Tis moonlight <del>upon</del> <add>over</add> Oman's sky</l>
<l>Her isles of pearl look lovelily<anchor xml:id="delend01"/></l></egXML>
In this case the <gi>anchor</gi> and <gi>delSpan</gi> have been
placed within the structural elements (the <gi>l</gi>s) rather than
between, as in the previous example. This is to indicate that
placement of these empty elements is arbitrary.  </p>
<p>The text deleted must be at least partially legible, in order for
the encoder to be able to transcribe it.  If all of part of it is not legible,
the <gi>gap</gi> element should be used to indicate where text has not
not transcribed, because it could not be. The <gi>unclear</gi> element described in
section <ptr target="#PHDA"/> may be used to indicate areas of
text which cannot be read with confidence. See further section <ptr target="#PHOM"/> and section <ptr target="#PHDA"/>.</p>
</div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHSU"><head>Substitutions</head>

<p>Substitution of one word or phrase for another is perhaps the most
common of all phenomena requiring special treatment in transcription
of primary textual sources.  It may be simply one word overwriting
another, or deletion of one word and its replacement by another
written above it by the same hand at the one time; the deletion and
replacement may be done by different hands at different times; there
may be a long chain of substitutions on the one stretch of text, with
uncertainty as to the order of substitution and as to which of many
possible readings should be preferred.</p>
<p>As we have shown, the simplest method of recording a substitution
is simply to record both the addition and the deletion. However, when
the module defined by this chapter is in use, additional elements are
available to indicate that the encoder believes the addition and the
deletion to be part of the same intervention: a substitution.
   <specList>
      <specDesc key="subst"/>
      <specDesc key="substJoin"/>
</specList>
Using the <gi>subst</gi> element, the example at the end of the last section might
be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l>
   <delSpan rend="verticalStrike" spanTo="#delend02"/>
   Tis moonlight <subst><del>upon</del><add>over</add></subst> Oman's sky</l>
<l>Her isles of pearl look lovelily<anchor xml:id="delend02"/></l></egXML>
Since the purpose of this element is solely to group its child elements
together, the order in which they are presented is not significant. By
convention, however, deletion precedes addition. This may be
overridden by means of the <att>seq</att> attribute, which is of
particular usefulness when a sequence of deletions and additions
occurs.</p>

<p>For example, returning to the example from William James, in a
passage first written out by James as <q>One must have lived longer
with this system, to appreciate its advantages</q>, the word
<mentioned>this</mentioned> is first replaced by <mentioned>such
a</mentioned> and this is then replaced by
<mentioned>a</mentioned>.<note place="bottom">The manuscript contains
several other substitutions, ignored here for the sake of
clarity.</note> This may be encoded as follows, representing the two
changes as a sequence of additions and deletions: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">One must have lived longer
with <subst><del seq="1">this</del> <del seq="2"><add seq="1">such
a</add></del> <add seq="2">a</add></subst> system, to appreciate its
advantages.</egXML> Note the nesting of an <gi>add</gi> element within
a <gi>del</gi> to record text first added, then deleted in the
source. The numbers assigned by the <att>seq</att> attribute may be
used to identify the order in which the various additions and
deletions are believed by the encoder to have been carried out, and
thus provide a simple method of supporting the kind of
<soCalled>genetic</soCalled> textual criticism typified by (for
example) Hans Walter Gabler's work on the reconstruction of the
<soCalled>overlay</soCalled> levels implicit in the manuscripts of James Joyce's
<title>Ulysses</title>.</p>
   
   <p>
      The case of a single substitution or scribal correction that involves non-contiguous addition and deletion can be handled
      by using the <gi>substJoin</gi> element to make an explicit connection between one or more <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi>
      elements. For example, in the following example from Thomas Moore's <title>Lalla Rookh</title>, the metrical structure of
      the verse means that the deleted word and its substitution are in different positions, and so a <gi>subst</gi> element would
      be invalid because of the intervening text:
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         While <del xml:id="change1">pondering</del> thus <add xml:id="change2">she mus'd</add>, 
         her pinions fann'd<substJoin target="#change1 #change2"/>
      </egXML>
   </p>
   
<p>As a more complex example, consider the following passage in one of
the manuscripts of Wilfred Owen's <title>Dulce et decorum
est</title>:
<figure><graphic width="450px" url="Images/PHowen.png"/></figure>
This passage might be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-16">
<l>And towards our distant rest began to trudge,</l>
<l><subst><del>Helping the worst amongst us</del><add>Dragging the
worst amongt us</add></subst>, who'd no boots</l>
<l>But limped on, blood-shod. All went lame;
<subst><del status="shortEnd">half-</del><add>all</add></subst> blind;</l>
<l>Drunk with fatigue ; deaf even to the hoots</l>
<l>Of tired, outstripped <del>fif</del> five-nines that dropped behind.</l></egXML>
In this representation, 
<list type="simple">
<item>the authorial slip (<mentioned>amongt</mentioned> for
<mentioned>amongst</mentioned>) is retained without comment.</item>
<item>the other two authorial corrections are marked as
substitutions, each combining a deletion and an addition.
</item>
<item>the false start <mentioned>fif</mentioned> in the last line is simply marked as
a deletion; </item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The <gi>app</gi> element presented in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>
provides similar facilities, by treating each state 
of the text as a
distinct reading. The <gi>rdg</gi> element has a <att>varSeq</att>
attribute which may be used in the same way as the
<att>seq</att> attribute to indicate the preferred sequence. The James
example above might thus be represented as follows: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">One must have lived longer with
  <app>
    <rdg varSeq="1"><del>this</del></rdg>
    <rdg varSeq="2"><del><add>such a</add></del></rdg>
    <rdg varSeq="3"><add>a</add></rdg>
  </app>
system, to appreciate its advantages.</egXML>
</p></div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCD"><head>Cancellation of Deletions and Other Markings</head>
<p>An author or scribe may mark a word or phrase in some way, and then
on reflection decide to cancel the marking.  For example, text may be
marked for deletion and the deletion then cancelled, thus restoring the
deleted text.  Such cancellation may be indicated by the
<gi>restore</gi> element:
<specList><specDesc key="restore"/></specList></p>
<p>This element bears the same attributes as the other transcriptional
elements. These may be used to supply further information such as
the hand in which the restoration is carried out, the type of
restoration, and the person
responsible for identifying the restoration as such, in the same way as
elsewhere. </p>
<p>Presume that Lawrence decided to restore <mentioned>my</mentioned> to the
phrase of <title>Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani</title> first written
<q>For I hate this my body</q>, with the <mentioned>my</mentioned> first deleted
then restored by writing <q>stet</q> in the margin.  This may be
encoded:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For I hate this
<restore hand="#dhl" type="marginalStetNote"><del>my</del></restore>
body</egXML></p>
<p>Another feature commonly encountered in manuscripts is the use of
circles, lines, or arrows to indicate transposition of material from
one point in the text to another. No specific markup for this
phenomenon is proposed at this time. Such cases are most simply
encoded as additions at the point of insertion and deletions at the
point of encirclement or other marking. </p>
</div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHOM">
<head>Text Omitted from or Supplied in the Transcription</head>
<p>Where text is not transcribed, whether because of damage to the
original, or because it is illegible, or for some other reason such as editorial policy,
the <gi>gap</gi> core element may be used to register the omission;
where such text is transcribed, but the editor wishes to indicate that
they consider it to be superfluous, for example because it is an
inadvertent scribal repetition, the <gi>surplus</gi> element may be
used in preference. Where text not present in the source is supplied (whether
conjecturally or from other witnesses) to fill an apparent gap in the
text,  the <gi>supplied</gi> element may be used. 
<specList><specDesc key="gap" atts="reason hand agent"/>
<specDesc key="surplus" atts="reason"/><specDesc key="supplied" atts="reason"/></specList></p>
<p>By its nature, the <gi>gap</gi> element has no content.  It
marks a point in the text where nothing at all can be read, whether because
of  authorial or scribal erasure, physical damage, or any other form
of  illegibility.  Its attributes allow the encoder to specify the
amount of text which is illegible in this way at this point, using any
convenient units, where
this can be determined.  For example, in
the Beerbohm manuscript of <title>The Golden Drugget</title> cited
above, the author has erased a passage amounting about 10 cm in length
by inking over it completely:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-05">Others <gap reason="cancelled" hand="#mb" quantity="10" unit="cm"/>—and
here is one of them...</egXML></p>
<p>In an autograph letter of Sydney Smith now in the Pierpont Morgan
library three words in the signature are quite illegible:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-10">I am dr Sr yr <gap reason="illegible" quantity="3" unit="word"/>Sydney Smith</egXML>

The degree of precision attempted when measuring the size of a gap
will vary with the purpose of the encoding and the nature of the
material: no particular recommendation is made here.</p>

<p>As noted above, the <gi>gap</gi> element should only be used where
text has not been transcribed. If partially legible text has been
transcribed, one of the elements <gi>damage</gi> and <gi>unclear</gi>
should be used instead (these elements 
are described in section <ptr target="#PHDA"/>); if the text is
legible and has been transcribed, but the editor wishes to indicate
that they regard it is superfluous or redundant, then the element
<gi>surplus</gi> may be used in preference to the core element <gi>sic</gi>
used to indicate text regarded as erroneous. </p>

<p>For example, when encountering the form
<soCalled>dedikararunt</soCalled> on an inscription, the editor may
choose any of the following three possibilities:
<list>
<item>mark this as an erroneous form
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PHegsurp">
<sic>dedikararunt</sic>
</egXML></item>
<item>additionally supply a corrected form
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PHegsurp">
<choice><sic>dedikararunt</sic>
<corr>dedikarunt</corr>
</choice>
</egXML></item>
<item>indicate that the erroneous form contains surplus characters
which the editor wishes to suppress
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PHegsurp">
dedika<surplus>ra</surplus>runt
</egXML></item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The <gi>surplus</gi> element may also be used to mark up
interpolations, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PHegsurp2">
<l n="4">a darmi morte, poi m'avete preso 
<surplus reason="interpolated">a tradimento</surplus></l>
<l n='5'>sì com' l'uccellator prende l'uccello</l>
<gap/>
<l n="43">e lettere dintorno che diriano 
<surplus reason="interpolated">in questa guisa</surplus></l>
<l n="44">Più v'amo, dëa, che non faccio Deo</l>
</egXML>
The words marked as <gi>surplus</gi> here are metrically inconsistent
with the rest and have been marked by the editor as such. </p>

<p>If the source text is completely illegible or missing, an encoder
may sometimes wish to supply new (conjectural) material to replace it.
This conjectural reading is analogous to a correction in that it
contains text provided by the encoder and not attested in the
source. This is not however a correction, since no error is
necessarily present in the original; for that reason a different
element <gi>supplied</gi> should be used.
If another (imaginary) copy of the letter above preserved the
signature as reading <q>I am dear Sir your very humble Servt Sydney
Smith</q>, the text illegible in the autograph might be supplied in
the transcription: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I
am dr Sr yr <supplied reason="illegible" resp="#msm" source="#Ry2">very humble Servt</supplied> Sydney Smith</egXML> Here
the <att>source</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes are used, as
elsewhere, to indicate respectively the sigil of a manuscript from
which the supplied reading has been taken, and the identifier of the
person responsible for deciding to supply the text. If the
<att>source</att> attribute is not supplied, the implication is that
the encoder (or whoever is indicated by the value of the
<att>resp</att> attribute) has supplied the missing reading.  Both
<gi>gap</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> may be used in combination with
<gi>unclear</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, and other elements; for discussion,
see section <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>.</p>
</div></div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="PHPH"><head>Hands and Responsibility</head>
<p>This section discusses in more detail the representation of aspects
of responsibility perceived or to be recorded for the writing of a
primary source. These include points at which one scribe takes over
from another, or at which ink, pen, or other characteristics of the
writing change. A discussion of the usage of the <att>hand</att>,
<att>resp</att>, and <att>cert</att> attributes is also included.
</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHDH"><head>Document Hands</head>

<p>For many text-critical purposes it is important to signal the
person responsible (the <term>hand</term>) for the writing of a whole
document, a stretch of text within a document, or a particular feature
within the document.  A hand, as the name suggests, need not
necessarily be identified with a particular known (or unknown) scribe
or author; it may simply indicate a particular combination of writing
features recognized within one or more documents. The examples given
above of the use of the <att>hand</att> attribute with coding of
additions and deletions illustrate this. </p>

<p>The <gi>handNote</gi> element is used to provide information about
each hand distinguished within the encoded document. 
<specList>
<specDesc key="handNote"/>
</specList>
</p>

<p>A <gi>handNote</gi> element, with an identifier given by its
<att>xml:id</att> attribute, may appear in either of two places in the
TEI Header, depending on which modules are included in a schema. When
the <ident type="module">transcr</ident> module defined by the present
chapter is used, the element <gi>handNotes</gi> is available, within
the <gi>profileDesc</gi> element of the Header, to hold one or more
<gi>handNote</gi> elements. When the <ident type="module">msdescription</ident> module defined in chapter <ptr target="#MS"/> is included, the <gi>handDesc</gi> element described in
<ptr target="#msph2"/> also becomes available as part of a structured
manuscript description. The encoder may choose to place
<gi>handNote</gi> elements identifying individual hands in either
location without affecting their accessibility since the element is
always addressed by means of its <att>xml:id</att> attribute. The
<gi>handDesc</gi> element may be more appropriate when a full
cataloguing of each manuscript is required; the <gi>handNotes</gi>
element if only a brief characterization of each hand is needed.  It
is also possible to use the two elements together if, for example, the
<gi>handDesc</gi> element contains a single summary describing all the
hands discursively, while the <gi>handNotes</gi> element gives
specific details of each. The choice will depend on individual
encoders' priorities.</p>

<p>As shown above, the <att>hand</att> attribute is available on
several elements to indicate the hand in which the content of the
element (usually a deletion or addition) is carried out. The
<gi>handShift</gi> element may also be used within the body of a
transcription to indicate where a change of hand is detected for
whatever reason. 
<specList>
<specDesc key="handShift"/></specList>
</p>
<p>Both <gi>handShift</gi> and <gi>handNote</gi>  are members of the
<ident type="class">att.handFeatures</ident> class, and thus share
the following attributes:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.handFeatures" atts="scribe script scribeRef
				       scriptRef medium scope"/>
</specList>
</p>

<p>A single hand may employ different writing styles and inks within a
document, or may change character.  For example, the writing style
might shift from <q>anglicana</q> to <q>secretary</q>, or the ink from
blue to brown, or the character of the hand may change.  Simple
changes of this kind may be indicated by assigning a new value to the
appropriate attribute within the <gi>handShift</gi> element.  It is
for the encoder to decide whether a change in these properties of the
writing style is so marked as to require treatment as a distinct
hand.</p>
<p>Where such a change is to be identified, the <att>new</att>
attribute is used to indicate the hand applicable to the material
following the <gi>handShift</gi>.  This will ordinarily, but not
necessarily, be the order in which the material was originally
written.</p>

<p> As might be expected, one hand may employ different renditions
within the one writing style, for example medieval scribes often
indicate a structural division by emboldening all the words within a
line.  These should be indicated by use of the <att>rend</att>
attribute on an element, in the same manner as underlining,
emboldening, font shifts, etc. are represented in transcription of a printed text,
rather than by introducing a new <gi>handShift</gi> element.</p>

<p>In the following example there is
a change of ink within the one hand.  This is simply indicated by a new value
for the <att>medium</att> attribute on the <gi>handShift</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-11"><l>When wolde the cat dwelle in his ynne</l>
<handShift medium="greenish-ink"/>
<l>And if the cattes skynne be slyk <handShift medium="black-ink"/> and gaye</l></egXML></p>

<p>In the following example, the encoder has
identified two distinct hands within the document and given them
identifiers <val>h1</val> and <val>h2</val>,  by means of the following
declarations included in the document's TEI Header:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <handNotes>
      <handNote xml:id="h1" script="copperplate" medium="brown-ink">Carefully written with regular descenders</handNote>
      <handNote xml:id="h2" script="print" medium="pencil">Unschooled scrawl</handNote>
    </handNotes>
 </egXML>
</p>
<p>Then the change of hand is indicated in the text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-12"><handShift new="#h1" resp="#das"/>... and that good Order Decency and regular worship
may be once more introduced and Established in this
Parish according to the Rules and Ceremonies of the
Church of England and as under a good Consciencious
and sober Curate there would and ought to be
<handShift new="#h2" resp="#das"/>
and for that purpose the parishioners pray</egXML></p>

<p>When a more precise or nuanced discussion of the writing in a
manuscript is required, the <gi>handNote</gi> and <gi>scriptNote</gi>
elements discussed in <ptr target="#msph2"/> should be used. Either
element may serve as the target for a <gi>handShift</gi>.
</p>

</div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHHR">
<head>Hand, Responsibility, and Certainty Attributes</head>

<p>The <att>hand</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes have similar, but
not identical, meanings.  Observe their distinctive uses in the
following encoding of the William James passage mentioned above in
section <ptr target="#PHCC"/>.  In this example, the <mentioned>But</mentioned>
inserted by James is tagged as an <gi>add</gi>, and the consequent
editorial correction of <mentioned>One</mentioned> to <mentioned>one</mentioned> treated
separately:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><add place="above" resp="#FB" hand="#WJ">But</add>
<choice><sic>One</sic><corr resp="#FB">one</corr></choice> must have
lived ...
<!-- elsewhere -->
<respStmt xml:id="FB">
<resp>editorial changes</resp>
<name>Fredson Bowers</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt xml:id="WJ">
<resp>authorial changes</resp>
<name>William James</name>
</respStmt>
</egXML>
As in this example, <att>hand</att> should be reserved for indicating
the hand of any form of marking—here, addition but also deletion,
correction, annotation, underlining, etc.—within the primary text
being transcribed.  The scribal or authorial responsibility for this
marking may be inferred from the value of the <att>hand</att> attribute.
The value of the <att>hand</att> attribute should be one of the hand
identifiers declared in the document header (see section <ptr target="#PHDH"/>).</p>
<p>The <att>resp</att> attribute, by contrast, 
indicate the person responsible for deciding to apply the element
carrying it to this part of the text, and hence has a slightly
different interpretation.  In the case of the
<gi>add</gi> element, for example, the <att>resp</att> attribute will
indicate  the responsibility for identifying that the addition is
indeed an addition, and also (if the <att>hand</att> attribute is
supplied) to which hand it should be attributed. In this case, 
Bowers is credited with  identifying the hand as that of William
James. In the case of the <gi>corr</gi> element, the <att>resp</att>
attribute indicates who is responsible for supplying the
intellectual content of the correction reported in the transcription:
here, Bowers' correction of <q>One</q> to <q>one</q>. In the case of a
deletion, the <att>resp</att> attribute will similarly indicate who
bears responsibility for identifying or categorising the deletion itself,
while other attributes (<att>hand</att> most obviously) attribute
responsibility for the deletion itself.</p>

<p><!--As these examples show, the field of application of the
<att>resp</att> attributes varies from element to element.  In some
cases, it applies to the content of the element (<gi>corr</gi>, 
<gi>ex</gi>, and <gi>supplied</gi>); in others it applies to the value of a particular
attribute (<gi>sic</gi>, <gi>abbr</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, etc.).  In all-->
In cases where both the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes are
defined for a particular element, the two attributes refer to the same
aspect of the markup.  The one indicates who is intellectually
responsible for some item of information, the other indicates the degree
of confidence in the information.  Thus, for a
correction, the <att>resp</att> attribute signifies the person
responsible for supplying the correction, while the <att>cert</att>
attribute signifies the degree of editorial confidence felt in that
correction.  For the expansion of an abbreviation, the
<att>resp</att> attribute signifies the person responsible for supplying
the expansion and the <att>cert</att> attribute signifies the degree of
editorial confidence felt in the expansion.</p>
<p>This close definition of the use of the <att>resp</att> and
<att>cert</att> attributes with each element is intended to provide for
the most frequent circumstances in which encoders might wish to make
unambiguous statements regarding the responsibility for and certainty of
aspects of their encoding.  The <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes, as so defined, give a convenient mechanism for this.
However, there will be cases where it is desired to state responsibility
for and certainty concerning other aspects of the encoding.  For
example, one may wish in the case of an apparent addition to state the
responsibility for the use of the <gi>add</gi> element, rather than the
responsibility for identifying the hand of the addition.  It may also be
that one editor may make an electronic transcription of another editor's
printed transcription of a manuscript text — here, one will wish to
assign layers of responsibility, so as to allow the reader to determine
exactly what in the final transcription was the
responsibility of each editor.  In these complex cases of divided
editorial responsibility for and certainty concerning the content,
attributes, and application of a particular element, the more general
mechanisms for representing certainty and responsibility described in
chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> should be used.</p>
<!--
<p>The fields of reference of the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes for each element have been chosen to enable what are felt as
the most frequent likely statements an encoder may wish to make
concerning the areas of responsibility and certainty related to that
element.  It is open to each local transcription scheme to vary the use
of the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes on particular
elements where it is felt convenient.  This practice should be
documented in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element in the file header.
Further, it is recommended that before interchange any such local usage
of these attributes be converted to conformancy with the definitions of
the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes given in these
<title>Guidelines</title>.  Use of the <att>resp</att> and
<att>cert</att> in interchange documents in ways not here defined may
lead to unpredictable results.</p>
-->
<p>It should be noted that the certainty and responsibility mechanisms
described in chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> replicate all the functions of the
<att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes on particular elements.
For example, the encoding of Donaldson's conjectured emendation of
<mentioned>wight</mentioned> to <mentioned>wright</mentioned> in line 117 of Chaucer's
<title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> (see <ptr target="#PHCC"/>) may be
encoded as follows using the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes on the <gi>corr</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<choice><sic>wight</sic><corr resp="#ETD" cert="medium">wright</corr></choice></egXML>
Exactly the same information could be conveyed using the certainty
and responsibility mechanisms, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<choice><corr xml:id="c117">wright</corr><sic>wight</sic></choice>
<certainty target="#c117" locus="value" degree="0.7"/>
<respons target="#c117" locus="value" resp="#ETD"/></egXML>
The choice of which mechanism to use is left to the encoder.  In
transcriptions where only such statements of responsibility and
certainty are made as can be accommodated within the <att>resp</att> and
<att>cert</att> attributes of particular elements, it will be economical
to use the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes of those
elements.  Where many statements of responsibility and certainty are
made which cannot be so accommodated, it may be economical to use the
<gi>respons</gi> and <gi>certainty</gi> elements throughout.</p>
<p>The above discussion supposes that in each case an encoder is able to
specify exactly what it is that one wishes to state responsibility for
and certainty about.  Situations may arise when an encoder wishes to
make a statement concerning certainty or responsibility but is unable or
unwilling to specify so precisely the domain of the certainty or
responsibility.  In these cases, the <gi>note</gi> element may be used
with the <att>type</att> attribute set to <q>cert</q> or <q>resp</q>
and the content of the note giving a prose description of the state of
affairs.</p></div></div>

<div><head>Damage and Conjecture</head>
<p>The carrier medium of a primary source may often sustain physical
damage which makes parts of it hard or impossible to read. In this
section we discuss elements which may be used to represent such
situations and give recommendations about how these should be used in
conjunction with the other related elements introduced previously in
this chapter. </p>


<div type="div3" xml:id="PHDA"><head>Damage, Illegibility, and Supplied Text</head>
<p>The <gi>gap</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> elements described above
(section <ptr target="#PHOM"/>) should be used with appropriate
attributes where the degree of damage or illegibility in a text is
such that nothing can be read and the text must be either omitted or
supplied conjecturally or from one or more other sources.  In many
cases, however, despite damage or illegibility, the text may yet be
read with reasonable confidence.  In these cases, the following
elements should be used: <specList>
<specDesc key="damage"/>
<specDesc key="damageSpan"/>
</specList>
As members of the class <ident type="class">att.damaged</ident>, these elements  bear
the following attributes
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.damaged" atts="hand agent degree group"/>
</specList>
The class <ident type="class">att.damaged</ident> is a subclass of the
class <ident type="class">att.dimensions</ident>, itself a subclass of
the class <ident type="class">att.ranging</ident>. Consequently these
elements also therefore bear at least the following attributes:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.dimensions" atts="extent unit quantity"/>
<specDesc key="att.ranging" atts="min max atLeast atMost"/>
</specList>
From the <ident type="class">att.spanning</ident> class,
<gi>damageSpan</gi> inherits  the following additional attribute:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.spanning" atts="spanTo"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>The following examples all refer to the recto of folio 5 of the unique
manuscript of the Elder Edda. Here, the
manuscript of <title>Vóluspá</title> has been damaged
through irregular rubbing so that letters in various places are obscured
and in some cases cannot be read at all.  
</p>
<p>In the first line of this leaf, the transcriber may believe that the
last three letters of <mentioned>daga</mentioned> can be read clearly despite
the damage:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-13" xml:lang="non">um aldr
d<damage>aga</damage> yndisniota</egXML>
</p>
<p>If, as is often the case,  the damage crosses structural divisions, so
that the <gi>damage</gi> element cannot be  nested properly within the containing
<gi>div</gi> elements, the <gi>damageSpan</gi> element may be used, in
the same way as the <gi>delSpan</gi> and <gi>addSpan</gi> elements
discussed in section <ptr target="#PHAD"/>.  
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-13"><p>
<!-- ... -->
  <pb n="5r"/>
  <damageSpan agent="rubbing" extent="whole leaf" spanTo="#damageEnd"/>
</p>
<p> .... </p>
<p> ....
  <pb n="5v" xml:id="damageEnd"/>
</p></egXML>
Note that in this example the <att>spanTo</att> element points to the
next <gi>pb</gi> element rather than to an inserted <gi>anchor</gi>
element, since the whole of the leaf (the text between the two
<gi>pb</gi> elements has sustained damage. For other techniques of handling non-nesting information, see chapter
<ptr target="#NH"/>.</p>
<p>If, as is also likely, the damage affects several disjoint parts of
the text, each such part must be marked with a separate
<gi>damage</gi> or <gi>damageSpan</gi> element. To indicate that each of these is to be
regarded as forming part of the same damaged area, the <att>group</att>
attribute may be used as in the following example. In this (imaginary)
text of Fitzgerald's translation from Omar Khayam, 
water damage has affected an area covering parts of several lines
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l>
The Moving Finger wri<damage agent="water" group="1">es; and</damage> having writ,</l>
<l>Moves <damage agent="water" group="1">on: nor all your</damage> Piety nor Wit</l>
<l><damageSpan agent="water" group="1" spanTo="#washOut"/>Shall lure it back to cancel half a Line,</l>
<l>Nor all your Tears wash <anchor xml:id="washOut"/> out a Word of it</l>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>A more general solution to this problem is provided by the
<gi>join</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#SAAG"/> which may be
used to link together arbitrary elements of any kind in the
transcription. Where, as here, several phenomena of illegibility and conjecture
all result from the one cause, an area of damage to the text — rubbing
at various points — which is not continuous in the text, affecting it
at irregular points, the <gi>join</gi> element may be
used to indicate which tagged features are part of the same physical
phenomenon. </p>

<p>If the damage has been so severe as to render parts of the text
only imperfectly legible, the <gi>unclear</gi> element should be used
to mark the fact. Returning to the Eddic example above, an encoder
less confident in the <mentioned>daga</mentioned> reading, may
indicate this as follows: <egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">um aldr d<unclear reason="damage">aga</unclear> yndisniota</egXML></p>
<p>If it is desired to supply more information about the kind of
damage, it is also possible to nest an <gi>unclear</gi> element within
the <gi>damage</gi> element:
<egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">um aldr d<damage agent="rubbing"><unclear>aga</unclear></damage> yndisniota</egXML></p>
<p>Alternatively, the transcriber may not feel able to read the last
three letters of <mentioned>daga</mentioned> but may wish to supply them by
conjecture. Note the use of the <att>resp</att> attribute to assign
the conjecture to Finnur Jónsson:
<egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-13">um aldr d<supplied reason="rubbing" resp="#msm">aga</supplied> yndisniota</egXML>
The <gi>supplied</gi> element may if desired be enclosed within a
<gi>damage</gi> element:
<egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-13">um aldr d<damage agent="rubbing"><supplied source="#msm">aga</supplied></damage> yndisniota</egXML></p>
<p>Contrast the use of <gi>gap</gi> in the next line, where the
transcriber believes that four letters cannot be read at all because
of the damage:
<egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-13">þar komr inn dimmi dreki fliugandi naþr frann
neþan <gap reason="illegible" agent="rubbing" quantity="4" unit="letter"/></egXML>
As with <gi>supplied</gi>, this <gi>gap</gi> might be enclosed by a
<gi>damage</gi> element.</p>
<p>Where elements are nested in this way, information about agency,
etc. is by default inherited. In the following imaginary example,
there is a smoke-damaged part within which two stretches can be read
with some difficulty, and third stretch which cannot be read at all:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><damage agent="smoke">
   <unclear>and the proof of this is</unclear>
   <gap/>
   <unclear>margin</unclear>
</damage>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>The above examples record imperfect legibility due to damage.  When
imperfect legibility is due to some other reason (typically because the
handwriting is ill-formed), the <gi>unclear</gi> element should be used
without any enclosing <gi>damage</gi> element.  In Robert Southey's
autograph of <title>The Life of Cowper</title> the final six letters
of <mentioned>attention</mentioned> are difficult to read because of the haste
of the writing, though reasonably certain from the context.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-14">and from time to time invited in like manner
his att<unclear>ention</unclear></egXML>
The <att>cert</att> attribute on the <gi>unclear</gi> element may be
used to indicate the level of editorial confidence in the reading
contained within it.</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCOMB"><head>Use of the <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi>, and <gi>supplied</gi> Elements in Combination</head>
<p>The <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi>,
<gi>supplied</gi>, and <gi>del</gi> elements may be closely allied in
their use.  For example, an area of damage in a primary source might
be encoded with any one of the first four of these elements, depending on
how far the damage has affected the readability of the text.
Further, certain of the elements may nest within one another. The
examples given in the last sections illustrate something of how these
elements are to be distinguished in use.  This may be formulated as
follows:
<list type="simple">
<item>where the text has been rendered completely illegible by
deletion or damage and no text is supplied by the editor in place of
what is lost: place an empty <gi>gap</gi> element at the point of
deletion or damage.  Use the <att>reason</att> attribute to state the
cause (damage, deletion, etc.) of the loss of text.</item>
<item>where the text has been rendered completely illegible by
deletion or damage and text is supplied by the editor in place of
what is lost: surround the text supplied at the point of deletion or
damage with the <gi>supplied</gi> element.  Use the <att>reason</att>
attribute to state the cause (damage, deletion, etc.) of the loss of
text leading to the need to supply the text.</item>
<item>where the text has been rendered partly illegible by deletion
or damage so that the text can be read but without perfect
confidence: transcribe the text and surround it with the
<gi>unclear</gi> element.  Use the <att>reason</att> attribute to state
the cause (damage, deletion, etc.) of the uncertainty in transcription
and the <att>cert</att> attribute to indicate the confidence in the
transcription.</item>
<item>where there is deletion or damage but at least some of the text can be read with
perfect confidence: transcribe the text and surround it with the
<gi>del</gi> element (for deletion) or the <gi>damage</gi> element (for
damage).  Use appropriate attribute values to indicate the cause and
type of deletion or damage.  Observe that the <att>degree</att>
attribute on the <gi>damage</gi> element permits the encoding to show
that a letter, word, or phrase is not perfectly preserved, though it
may be read with confidence.</item>
<item>where there is an area of deletion or damage and parts of the
text within that area can be read with perfect confidence, other
parts with less confidence, other parts not at all: in transcription,
surround the whole area  with the <gi>del</gi> element (for deletion; or
the <gi>delSpan</gi> element where it crosses a structural boundary); or
the <gi>damage</gi> element (for damage).  Text within the damaged area
which can be read with perfect confidence needs no further tagging.
Text within the damaged area which cannot be read with perfect
confidence may be surrounded with the <gi>unclear</gi> element.  Places
within the damaged area where the text has been rendered completely
illegible and no text is supplied by the editor may be marked with
the <gi>gap</gi> element. For each element, one may use appropriate
attribute values to indicate the cause and type of deletion or damage
and the certainty of the reading.</item></list></p>
<p>The rules for combinations of the <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi>
elements, and for the interpretation of such combinations, are
similar:
<list type="simple">
<item>if one <gi>add</gi> element (with identifier <ident>ADD1</ident>)
contains another (with identifier <ident>ADD2</ident>), then
the addition <ident>ADD1</ident> was first
made to the text, and later a second addition (<ident>ADD2</ident>) was
made within that added text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">This is the text
<add xml:id="ADD1">with some added
   <add xml:id="ADD2">(interlinear!)</add>
material</add>
as written.</egXML></item>
<item>if one <gi>del</gi> element contains another, and the
<att>seq</att> attribute does not indicate otherwise, it should be
assumed that the inner 
deletion was made before the enclosing one. In the following example,
the word <mentioned>redundant</mentioned> was deleted before a second
second deletion removed the entire passage:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del>This sentence contains
some <del>redundant</del> unnecessary
verbiage.</del></egXML></item>
<item>if a <gi>del</gi> element contains an <gi>add</gi> element, the normal
interpretation will be that an addition was made within a passage
which was later
deleted in its entirety:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del>This sentence was deleted
<add>originally</add> from the text.</del></egXML></item>
<item>if an <gi>add</gi> element contains a <gi>del</gi> element, the
normal interpretation will be that a
deletion was made from  a passage which had earlier been added:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><add>This sentence was added
<del>eventually</del> to the text.</add></egXML></item>
</list></p></div>
</div>
</div>

<div xml:id="alterations">
   <head>Marking up the Writing Process</head>
   <p>Modifications of various kinds (correction, addition, deletion,
   etc.) are frequently found within a single document, and may also
   be inferred when different documents are compared, although it may be
   an open question as to whether inter-document discrepancies <!-- at the
   dossier level --> should be regarded in the same way as intra-document
   alterations. When two witnesses are collated, we may observe that a
   word present in one is missing from the other: this does not necessarily
   imply that the word was added to the first witness, nor that it
   was deleted from the other. 
   </p>

<p>In this section we discuss a number of elements which may be used to 
record traces of the writing process within a document. 
</p>

<div><head>Generic Modification</head>


   
<p>Most, if not all, transcriptional elements imply a certain level of
semantic interpretation. For instance, using the <gi>add</gi> element
to encode a word or phrase that occupies interlinear space involves a
decision that it has been deliberately inserted as an addition rather
than an alternative, and indeed a judgment that it was written after,
rather than before, the other lines. Where it is felt desirable to
keep the recording of <soCalled>what is on the page</soCalled>
entirely separate from <soCalled>what is the editor’s
interpretation</soCalled>, the generic <gi>mod</gi> element may be
preferred.
   
      <specList>
         <specDesc key="mod" />
      </specList>
      
      This element simply indicates any kind of
   modification that has been identified in the document, without
   prejudice as to its function. Occurrences of the <gi>mod</gi>
   element may be categorised by means of their <att>type</att>
   attribute, and visual aspects of their appearance can be described
   by means of the <att>rend</att> attribute, but they provide no
   further interpretation of the function or intention of the passage
   so marked up. The <att>spanTo</att> attribute may be used to indicate the end
   of a modified passage if this extends across the boundaries of some
   other XML element, for example from the middle of one line tagged
   as a <gi>line</gi> to the middle of another <gi>line</gi> some
   distance further on in the document. </p>
<egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line>words words words <mod rend="wavy-underlining" spanTo="#enduw"/>words with wavy underline</line>
&lt;!-- more lines here -->
<line>wavy underlining finishes here<anchor xml:id="enduw"/> more words</line>
</egXML>
<!-- QUERY real example needed -->
<!-- also more discussion of spanTo -->

<p>The distinction between an example such as that above and the simple
use of <gi>hi</gi> to mark the visual salience of the underlining
(apart from  the use of the <att>spanTo</att> attribute) is that
<gi>hi</gi> does not imply that the visual effect being recorded is
understood to represent some kind of modification. 
</p></div>

   <div xml:id="PH-meta"><head>Metamarks</head>

<p>By <term>metamark</term> we mean marks such as numbers, arrows,
crosses, or other symbols introduced by the writer into a document
expressly for the purpose of indicating how the text is to be
read. Such marks thus constitute a kind of markup of the document,
rather than forming part of the text.
 <specList>         
<specDesc key="metamark" atts="function target "/></specList>
</p>      

<p>Unlike marginal notes or other additions to the text, metamarks
are used by the writer to indicate a deliberate alteration of the writing itself,
such as <q>move this passage over there</q>. An addition or annotation
by contrast would typically concern some property of the passage other
than its intended location or status within the text flow.  A metamark
may contain text, or some other graphic which the encoder
wishes to represent, or it may simply consist of arrows, dots, lines
etc. which the encoder simply describes.</p>

<!-- QUERY should it contain <desc> as a child? -->

<p>The <gi>metamark</gi> element carries a <att>function</att>
attribute which specifies the function of the metamark, using values
such as <val>reorder</val>,  <val>flag</val>,  <val>delete</val>,
<val>insert</val> or  <val>used</val>. The passage to
which the metamark applies may be indicated in either of two ways: the
<att>target</att> attribute may be used to point to the element or
elements containing the passage concerned, or the <att>spanTo</att>
element may be used to point to a position in the document at which
the passage concerned finishes. In the latter case, the
<gi>metamark</gi> itself must be supplied at the position in the
document where the passage concerned begins; in the former case it may
be supplied at any convenient point. Both attributes should not be
supplied. </p>
      
<p>The following example is taken from  an
15th century legal book from the city of Göttingen, containing
regulations of everyday life issued by the city council <figure>
<graphic url="Images/ka04_1v-dtl.jpg" width="70%"/>
<head><title>Kundige bok 2</title>, fol 1v. </head>
         </figure>
      </p>
<!-- QUERY : proper reference needed   -->
    
<p>In the second paragraph,  the word <mentioned
xml:lang="lat">lege</mentioned> ("read") was written in the left hand
margin, next to the sentence beginning <q>Ock en schullen
de bruwere...</q>. It is thought to
function as a metamark,  indicating that this sentence forms part of
the regulations. A further sentence was then added, while at some
later stage the text and also the metamark were deleted. We
might encode this as follows: <!-- ka04_1v-dtl.xml --><egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<delSpan spanTo="#endDel" change="#L3"/>
   <metamark function="flag" target="#zone-1" change="#L2">lege</metamark>
   <zone xml:id="zone-1" change="#L1">Ock en schullen de bruwere des hilgen dages nicht over
   setten noch uppe den stillen fridach bruwen.</zone>
   <addSpan spanTo="#endDel" change="#L2"/>
      <zone>Noch nymande over setten, se en sehin denne erst, dat uppe den
         bonen neyn stro noch, huw noch flaß ligghe, by pine eyner
         halven roden, deme bruwere so wol alse dem bruwheren to
         murende.</zone>
   <anchor xml:id="endDel"/>
         </egXML>
      </p>
<p>The <att>change</att> attribute used here to indicate the sequencing
of these various interventions is discussed below, in section <ptr
target="#PH-changes"/>. The elements <gi>addSpan</gi> and
<gi>delSpan</gi> are discussed in section <ptr target="#PHAD"/>. </p>
      
<p>The <gi>metamark</gi> element may also be used to encode the
symbols etc. often found in marked-up proofs such as the following,
taken from the Walt Whitman archive:
         <figure>
<graphic url="Images/whitman-03.jpg" width="400px"/>
<head>http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/</head>
         </figure></p>   <!-- loc.00295 detail -->
<p>In this example, the whole of what was originally the 14th section
of the poem has been marked for deletion, both by horizontal and vertical lines,
and by the metamarks resembling the <q>delta</q> deletion symbol to
left and right of the section. The deletion itself might be encoded 
by using the normal <gi>del</gi> or <gi>delSpan</gi> element, and the
metamarks by the <gi>metamark</gi> element. 
This is quite a different case from that of the next example, in which the
writer does not intend to suppress the content, but only to mark that
it has been copied to another manuscript or reused. </p>
<p>
<figure>
<graphic url="Images/whitman-02.jpg" width="70%"/>
<head>Page from
   http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/20051105_0650.jpg</head>
         </figure> 
</p>   
<p>This page contains internal deletions, additions, and retracings
but these are semantically quite different from the apparent
<soCalled>deletion</soCalled> signalled by the larger of the two
single vertical lines, which shows that the written material has been
transferred or re-used, not deleted. </p>
<egXML
      xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<surface>
   <metamark function="used" rend="line" target="#X2"/>
   <zone xml:id="X2">
      <line>I am that halfgrown <add>angry</add> boy, fallen asleep</line>
      <line>The tears of foolish passion yet undried</line>
      <line>upon my cheeks.</line>
<!-- ... -->
<line>I pass through <add>the</add> travels and <del>fortunes</del> of
<retrace>thirty</retrace></line>
<line>years and become old,</line>
<line>Each in its due order comes and goes,</line>
<line>And thus a message for me comes.</line>
<line>The</line>
   </zone>
<metamark function="used" target="#X2">Entered - Yes</metamark>
</surface>
         </egXML>
<p>In this example, we class as  metamarks both the long vertical line
and the annotation <q>Entered - yes</q>. <!--The first indicates
that all of the writing between its own position and that of the
<gi>anchor</gi> element with identifier <val>X2</val> is marked as
having been used. This metamark takes the form of a cross.  The second
indicates that there is a mark in the form of a wavy line and that its
function is to separate the second writing zone on the surface, which
has identifier <val>z2</val>. --> Both metamarks are assumed to
indicate that the whole of the written zone with identifier
<code>X2</code> is marked as having been used. 
</p>

   </div>

<div><head>Fixation and Clarification</head>

<p>A writer may sometimes rewrite material a second time without
significant change and in the same place. We consider this a distinct
activity from addition as usually defined because no new textual
material results; instead the status of existing material 
is reaffirmed. We may distinguish two variants of this:
<term>fixation</term> where the first version was a tentative draft
which is subsequently reaffirmed, for example by inking it over; and
<term>clarification</term>, where the first version was badly written
and has been rewritten for clarity. The element <gi>retrace</gi> is
provided for both cases; its <att>cause</att> attribute may be used to
distinguish these or other cases.
<specList>
         <specDesc key="retrace" />
      </specList>
</p>
      
<p>In this simple example, taken from the papers of Henrik Ibsen, the
writer wrote the word <mentioned>skuldren</mentioned> hastily, and
then returned to it to make the letter <mentioned>l</mentioned> larger
and clearer: <figure>
<graphic url="Images/skuldren.jpg" width="400px"/>
<head rend="it">Image from a ms of Peer Gynt, Collin 2869, 4°, I.1.1, the
   Royal Library of Copenhagen</head>
         </figure> We might transcribe this word as follows: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line>... Sku<retrace cause="unclear">l</retrace>dren </line>
         </egXML>
</p>

<p>A single rewrite may not be sufficient, and it may be that the
document becomes almost unreadable as a result of repeated
clarification. In the following example, we can distinguish at least
three attempts to write the letters <mentioned>er</mentioned> in the
word <mentioned>bægerklang</mentioned>: <figure>
<graphic url="Images/munch01.jpg" width="400px"/>
<head rend="it">Image from http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms.html </head>
</figure> We might encode this by nesting the <gi>retrace</gi> element as
         follows: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line>ved Bæg<retrace cause="unclear" change="#stage2">
      <retrace cause="unclear" change="#stage1">er</retrace>
   </retrace> ...</line>
         </egXML> The <att>change</att> attribute used here is discussed further below
(<ptr target="#PH-changes"/>). </p>

<p>The <gi>retrace</gi> element is used only for cases where text has
been written multiple times. When metamarks and other markup-like strokes
have been rewritten multiple times, the <gi>redo</gi> element described in
the next section should be used in preference.
</p>   </div>

 <div xml:id="undo">
<head>Fixation, Cancellation, and Reinstatement of Modifications</head>

<p>In a draft version of Goethe’s Faust, a passage was struck through
once in pencil during one revision and then again with ink during a
later revision, supposedly to fixate the deletion.
      <figure>
         <graphic url="Images/faust_redo.jpg" width="90%"/>
         <head rend="it">Fixation of a deletion in Goethe’s Faust</head>
      </figure>
A writer may also indicate that an alteration is itself to be altered:
for example, a struck-through passage may be restored via a dotted
underlining, or the underlining of a passage may be deleted by a wavy
line.</p>

<p>The following elements are provided to represent these situations:
<specList>
<specDesc key="redo" atts="target "/>
<specDesc key="undo" atts="target "/></specList>
</p>

<p>The <gi>redo</gi> element might be used to encode the Faust example above
as follows:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <line><redo xml:id="redo_3" hand="#g_t" target="#mod_1" cause="fix"
   /><mod xml:id="mod_1" rend="strikethrough" spanTo="#anchor_1"
   hand="#g_bl"/>Ihr hagren, triſten, krummgezog<mod rend="strikethrough"
   >nen</mod>ener Nacken</line>
         <line>Wenn ihr nur piepſet iſt die Welt ſchon matt.<anchor xml:id="anchor_1"
/></line>
      </egXML>

<!-- NOTE insert narrative explanation -->

      
<p>The element <gi>restore</gi> (<ptr target="#PHCD"/>) is
provided for the comparatively simple case where a simple deletion is
marked as having been subsequently cancelled. The <gi>undo</gi>
element discussed here is more widely applicable and may be used for
any kind of cancellation. It points to the element or elements which
are being cancelled. These components need not be contiguous, provided
that the cancellation is clearly a single act; each distinct act of
cancellation requires a distinct <gi>undo</gi> element, however. Either
of the attributes <att>target</att> or <att>spanTo</att> may be used to
indicate the passages concerned. </p>

      <p>Consider the following imaginary example : 
<figure>
      <graphic url="Images/undoing1.jpg" width="80%"/>
   </figure>
We hypothesize that the text has gone through three states or changes,
as follows:
<list type="ordered">
<item>This is just some sample text, we need a real example. </item>
<item>This is not a real example.</item>
<item>This is just some text, not a real example.</item>
         </list>
</p>
      
<p>This sequence of events might be encoded as follows:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line>This is <del change="#s2"  rend="overstrike"> 
<undo spanTo="#Xa" rend="dotted" change="#s3"/>just some
<anchor xml:id="Xa"/> sample <undo spanTo="#Xb" rend="dotted" change="#s3"/>text,
<anchor xml:id="Xb"/> we need</del>
<add change="#s2">not</add>
a real example.</line> 
</egXML> 
using two <gi>undo</gi> elements, each with a <att>spanTo</att>
attribute, to delimit the two parts of the deletion which were
reverted at change s3. Note that in this case, since <att>target</att>
is not supplied, it is the effect of the parent element (the
<gi>del</gi>) which is assumed to be undone. </p>

<p>Alternatively, we might more economically use the generic <gi>seg</gi> element within
the <gi>line</gi> to delimit the two sequences whose
deletion is being reverted, and then use the <att>target</att> attribute
on a single <gi>undo</gi> element:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line>This is <del change="#s2"  rend="overstrike"> 
<seg xml:id="X-a">just some</seg>
sample <seg xml:id="X-b">text</seg>,
we need</del>
<add change="#s2">not</add>
a real example.</line> 
<undo target="#X-a #X-b" rend="dotted" change="#s3"/>
</egXML> 


<!-- NOTE maybe add a third example doing this with xpath to pick out
individual tokens. Or one from a real doc -->
</p>
   </div>
 
<div xml:id="transpo"><head>Transpositions</head>
      
<p>A <term>transposition</term> occurs when metamarks are found in a
document indicating that passages should be moved to a different
position. Typically this may be done  using
arrows, asterisks or numbers, or other means. By definition the result
of a transposition is not present in the document, and should not
therefore be encoded, if the intention is to represent the actual
appearance of the document. Instead, the following elements may be used to indicate the
intended reordering:
<specList>
<specDesc key="listTranspose"/>
<specDesc key="transpose"/>
</specList></p>
<p>Consider for example, the
         following extract from an Ibsen manuscript <figure>
<graphic url="Images/ibsen01.jpg" width="400px"/>
<head>Extracted from
   <ref>http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms.html</ref></head>
         </figure>
The underlined numbers 1 and 2 here indicate that, although the word
<mentioned>bör</mentioned> precedes the word
<mentioned>hör</mentioned> in the text, the order of the two words
should be reversed. We may encode this as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line><seg xml:id="ib01">bör</seg><metamark rend="underline"
      function="transposition" target="#ib01" place="above">2.</metamark>
   og <seg xml:id="ib02">hör</seg><metamark rend="underline"
      function="transposition" target="#ib02" place="above"
   >1.</metamark></line>
<listTranspose>
   <transpose>
      <ptr target="#ib02"/>
      <ptr target="#ib01"/>
   </transpose>
</listTranspose>
         </egXML>
      </p>
      
<p>Note the use of the generic <gi>seg</gi> element to identify the
sections of text being transposed. When (as in the following example)
the whole of a line is to be transposed, there is no need to delimit the
sections concerned: <figure>
<graphic url="Images/ibsen04.jpg" width="600px"/>
<head>Extracted from
   <ref>http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms3.html</ref></head>
         </figure>
         <!-- ibsen04.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line xml:id="ib3"><metamark function="transposition"
      place="margin-left">2.)</metamark> thi da er du med Himmelen i
   Pagt; — </line>
<line xml:id="ib4">
   <metamark function="transposition"
	     place="margin-left">1.)</metamark> 
da kan du Folkets Jøkelhjerter tine;</line>
<listTranspose>
   <transpose>
      <ptr target="#ib4"/>
      <ptr target="#ib3"/>
   </transpose>
</listTranspose>
         </egXML> 
When transposition is made, the whole element indicated is understood
to be moved, not just its contents. In the above example, the
metamarks are thus understood to be moved along with the lines to
which they apply. </p>
      
<!-- <p>In case the area to be transposed is overlapping with some other
kind of markup, the generic <gi>milestone</gi> can be used instead of
<gi>seg</gi> or any other existing elements.</p>
-->      

<p>One or more <gi>listTranspose</gi> elements may be supplied either
embedded within the text or in the <gi>profileDesc</gi> of the header,
depending on local preference. Each <gi>listTranspose</gi> can contain
one or more <gi>transpose</gi> elements, each of which defines a
single transposition.</p>
</div>

 <div xml:id="alter">
      <head>Alternative Readings</head>
      <p><figure>
<graphic url="Images/moore04.png" width="400px"/>
<head>Detail from autograph manuscript of the second version of <title>Lalla
Rookh</title>, Pierpont Morgan MA 310</head>
         </figure> 
In this example two alternative readings are provided, but no
preference is indicated. While the author apparently
first composed the line <q>Alone before his native river -</q>, at some
later point, he entertained the possibility of using the word <mentioned>beside</mentioned>
instead of <mentioned>before</mentioned>. The manuscript supplies no
indication of which word Moore favours at this point, although in
fact, in the first printed
edition of <title>Lalla Rookh</title> the word
<mentioned>beside</mentioned> was chosen. </p>
<p>The element <gi>alt</gi> provided by the <ident
type="module">linking</ident> module gives a simple  way of
encoding the state of this manuscript, as  follows: 
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-09">
         <zone>
<line>Alone <seg xml:id="alt1">before</seg>
   <add place="above" xml:id="alt2">beside</add> his
   native river ­—</line>
<alt target="#alt1 #alt2" mode="excl" weights="0 1"/>
         </zone>
      </egXML>
</p><p>The <att>mode</att> attribute here indicates that the two
possible readings indicated by the <att>target</att> attribute are
mutually exclusive. The <att>weights</att> attribute provides the
relative importance or preference to be attached to the two readings;
in this case, we have a very strong preference for the second reading
because this is the one that appears in  the published
version of the poem.  The <gi>alt</gi> element is further discussed in section <ptr
target="#SAAT"/>. </p>
 </div>
<!-- NOTE next section on ice, pending further council discussion -->
<!--   
<div xml:id="subst">
      <head>Substitution</head>
      <p>In the current model for the TEI <gi>subst</gi> element, one or more additions
         and deletions may be combined if they are considered as representing a single
         editorial act, a substitution. Without extension, this model could not
         therefore include cases such as the following example taken from Thomas Moore's
<title>Lalla Rooke</title>
         <figure>
<graphic url="Images/moore01.png" width="400px"/>
         </figure>
</p><p> Here the word <mentioned>pondering</mentioned> is deleted, and the
         phrase <mentioned>she mus'd</mentioned> are added, while the word
<mentioned>thus</mentioned> remains unchanged. It seems appropriate to treat
         all of this as a single substitution. This would require a modification to the
         content model of <gi>subst</gi> so as to permit text along with other members
         of <ident type="class">model.pPart.transcriptional</ident>, so that this
         example could be encoded as follows: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<line>While <subst><del>pondering</del> thus <add>she
   mus'd</add></subst>, her pinions fann'd</line>
         </egXML></p>
   </div>-->

<div xml:id="instant"><head>Instant Corrections</head>
<p>The use of elements such as <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi>
necessarily implies that the modifications they indicate were made at
some time after the original writing. An exception to this is where a
false start or <soCalled>instant</soCalled> correction has been
identified: the author starts to write, and then immediately corrects
what has been written. </p>
<p>The <att>instant</att> attribute defined by this module may be used
on any element which is a member of the <ident
type="class">att.editLike</ident> class to modify this default
assumption.  When the value of <att>instant</att> is set to
<val>true</val>, the addition or deletion is considered to belong to
the same change as its parent element, while <code>false</code> means
some change later than that of its parent.</p>
      <p> An example of false start or instant correction can be seen in the following line:
      <figure corresp="#WHITMS1">
<graphic url="Images/whitman03a.jpg" width="70%"/>
<head>Detail fron <title>[I am a curse]</title>, one of the drafts for
Whitman's <title>Song of Myself</title></head>
         </figure> in which we can detect the following sequence of events: <list
type="ordered">
<item>The letter <val>T</val> is written and then immediately deleted</item>
<item>The word <val>The</val> is written, deleted, and replaced by the word <val>His</val></item>
<item>The added word <val>His</val> is then deleted</item>
<item>The initial letter <val>i</val> of the words <mentioned>iron necklace</mentioned> is overwritten with a
   capital I</item>
         </list> To indicate that the first of these acts must have
	 taken place during the main act of writing, before
         the other deletion and additions, we might encode this revision campaign as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#WHITMS1">
<line><del instant="true">T</del>
   <mod type="subst">
      <del>The</del>
      <add place="above">
         <del rend="overstrike">His</del>
      </add>
   </mod>
   <mod type="subst">
      <del rend="overwritten">i</del>
      <add place="superimposed">I</add>
   </mod>ron necklace</line>
         </egXML>
      </p>
   </div>
</div>

<div xml:id="PH-surfzone"><head>Advanced uses of Surface and Zone</head>

<p>The function of the <gi>surface</gi> element is both to identify a
specific area containing writing and to provide a two dimensional set
of coordinates which can be used to position and dimension sub-parts
of it. Furthermore, surfaces may nest within other surfaces, as in the
case of <q>patches</q> or other written materials attached to the main
writing surface.  In the general case, the position and dimensions of
such nested surfaces will be defined using the same co-ordinate system
as that supplied by the parent <gi>surface</gi> element. It is also
possible, however, that a different coordinate system is required for
such a nested surface, perhaps because it requires a more complex
granularity. We consider both possibilities.</p>

<p>In the earlier examples showing nested examples we did not provide
any coordinate information, for simplicity of presentation. Suppose
however, that we wish to indicate the position and sizes of the
newspaper scraps in figure <ptr target="#sleeprs"/>, relative to the whole 
page. The four attributes <att>ulx</att>, <att>uly</att>,
<att>urx</att> and <att>ury</att> when given on the <gi>surface</gi>
element define the co-ordinate scheme, rather than specifying the
location of that surface; we must therefore introduce an additional
<gi>zone</gi> element, as in the following revised encoding for the
example given in section <ptr target="#PHZLAB"/> above:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="50">
   <zone ulx="1" uly="1" lrx="10" lry="10">
      <line>Poem</line>
      <line>As in Visions of — at</line>
      <line>night —</line>
      <line>All sorts of fancies running through</line>
      <line>the head</line>
   </zone>
   <zone ulx="4" uly="4" lrx="20" lry="20">
   <surface type="newsprint" attachment="glue" flipping="false">
			  <zone>Spring has
      just set in here, and the weather.... a
			   steamer </zone>
         <metamark function="sequence">2</metamark>
   </surface>
</zone>
</surface></egXML>

In this version of the encoding, the inner surface, corresponding with
the first piece of newsprint, inherits locational information from
the <gi>zone</gi> element that contains it. This zone, and the
preceding one, which contains a sequence of <gi>line</gi> elements,
are both positioned in terms of  the coordinates specified on the
outermost <gi>surface</gi> element, which defines a scale running from
0 to 50 in either direction. On that scale, the <gi>line</gi> elements
occupy a rectangle with coordinates (1,1,10,10), while the nested
surface occupies a rectangle with coordinates (4,4,20,20).</p>
<p>Now suppose that we wish to define a finer scale grid for the
newspaper patch, perhaps because we wish to localize zones within it
with greater accuracy. To do this we will need to specify the
position of the nested surface as in the previous example, but also to
define  the new coordinate system. We accomplish this as follows:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="50" lry="50">
   <zone ulx="1" uly="1" lrx="10" lry="10">
      <line>Poem</line>
<!-- ... -->
      <line>the head</line>
   </zone>
   <zone ulx="4" uly="4" lrx="20" lry="20">
   <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="100" lry="100">
     <zone ulx="10" uly="10" lrx="90" lry="95">
       Spring has just set in here, and the weather
       .... a  steamer </zone>
   </surface>
</zone>
</surface></egXML>

As before, the second zone defines the position and size of the
newspaper patch itself in terms of a coordinate system running from
0 to 50 on both X and Y axes. The nested <gi>surface</gi> element
however defines a new scale for all of its components, running from 0
to 100 on both X and Y axes. The position of the nested zone
containing the text <mentioned>Spring ... steamer</mentioned> is now
given in terms of this scale.</p>

<p>All of the examples so far given have involved rectangular zones,
for clarity of exposition. As noted above, the <att>points</att>
attribute may be used to define non rectangular zones as a series of
points. For example, in the last of the Whitman examples discussed in
section <ptr target="#PH-meta"/> above, we might wish to record the
exact shape of the zone containing the metamark
<mentioned>Entered</mentioned>. Since this is not a rectangular zone,
we use the <att>points</att> attribute to indicate the points defining
a polygon which contains it. The values used are expressed in terms of
a coordinate space running from 0 to 229 in the X dimension, and 0 to
160 in the Y dimension. </p>

<egXML
      xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<surface ulx="229" uly="160" lrx="0" lry="0"> 
<graphic url="whitman-02.jpg"/> 
<zone xml:id="entered" 
 points="142.625,122.19 155.024,113.736 178.133,122.754
	 208.569,144.172 198.988,154.881 178.133,139.663"/> 
</surface>
</egXML>

<p>In exactly the same way, we may wish to identify the curved zone 
in the following image containing the word
<mentioned>Northamptonshire</mentioned>:
<figure><graphic url="Images/mould-stone.jpg"/>
<head>Gravestone of Private Mould in the Protestant Cemetery in
Rome</head>
</figure>
This curved zone might be encoded in the following way:

<egXML
      xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <surface xml:id="badge" ulx="14.54" uly="16.14" lrx="0" lry="0">
  <graphic url="stone.jpg"/>
  <zone xml:id="county" points="4.6,6.3 5.25,5.85 6.2,6.6
  8.19222,7.4125 9.89222,6.5875 10.9422,6.1375 11.4422,6.7125
  8.21722,8.3125 6.2,7.65"/>
  </surface>
</egXML>
</p>


</div>



<div><head>Aspects of Layout</head>
<p>Finally in this chapter we present elements which may be used to
capture aspects of the layout of material on a page where this is
considered important.  Methods for recording page breaks, column breaks, and line breaks in the
source are described in section <ptr target="#CORS"/>. A similar
method is provided by this module for the markup of quire or gathering
boundaries, using the element <gi>gb</gi>.  
<specList>
<specDesc key="gb"/>
</specList>
More detailed information about the physical make-up of a source will
usually be summarized by the <gi>physDesc</gi> component of a
<gi>msDesc</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#msph"/>; if it is
desired to structure a
transcription as a sequence of blocks of text corresponding with pages
or quires, the generic <gi>ab</gi> element may be used in preference
to the elements <gi>div</gi> <gi>p</gi> etc. 
</p>

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHSP"><head>Space</head>
<p>The author or scribe may
have left space for a word, or for an initial capital, and for some
reason the word or capital was never supplied and the space left empty.
The presence of significant space in the text being transcribed may
be indicated by the <gi>space</gi> element.  
<specList><specDesc key="space" atts="resp"/></specList>
Note that this element should not be used to mark normal inter-word space or the
like. </p>
<p>In line 694 of Chaucer's <title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> in
the Holkham manuscript the scribe has left a space for a word where
other manuscripts read <mentioned>preestes</mentioned>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">By god if wommen had writen storyes
As <space quantity="7" unit="char"/> han within her oratoryes</egXML>
The <gi>supplied</gi> element discussed in the previous section may be
used to supply the text presumed missing:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">By god if wommen had writen storyes
As <supplied reason="space" resp="#ETD" source="#Hg">preestes</supplied>
han within her oratoryes</egXML>
Here, the fact of the space within the manuscript is indicated by the
value of the <att>reason</att> attribute.  The source of the supplied
text is shown by the value of the <att>source</att> attribute as the
Hengwrt manuscript; the transcriber responsible for supplying the text
is ES.
</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHLN"><head>Lines</head>
<p>The most common form of marking of text in manuscripts is by lines
written under, beside, or through the text.  The lines themselves may be
of various types:  they may be solid, dashed or dotted, doubled or
tripled, wavy or straight, or a combination of these and other
renderings.  The line may be used for emphasis, or to mark a foreign or
technical term, or to signal a quotation or a title, etc.:  the elements
<gi>emph</gi>, <gi>foreign</gi>, <gi>term</gi>, <gi>mentioned</gi>,
<gi>title</gi> may be used for these.  Frequently, a scholar may judge
that a line is used to delete text:  the <gi>del</gi> element is
available to indicate this.  In all these cases, the <att>rend</att>
attribute may be used on these or other elements to indicate that the
text is marked by a line and the style of the line.  Thus, Lawrence's
deletion by strike-through of <mentioned>my</mentioned> in the autograph of
<title>Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani</title> is noted:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For I hate this
<del rend="strikethrough" hand="#dhl">my</del> body,
which is so dear to me</egXML></p>
<p>There will be instances, however, where a scholar wishes only to
register the occurrence of lines in the text, without making any
judgement as to what the lines signify.  In these the <gi>hi</gi>
element may be used, with the <att>rend</att> attribute to mark the
style of line.  In the manuscript of a letter by Robert Browning to
George Moulton-Barrett the
underlining of the phrase <mentioned>had obtained all the letters to Mr Boyd</mentioned>
may be marked-up as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#PH-eg-15">I have once — by declaring I would prosecute
by law — hindered a man's proceedings who
<hi rend="underline">had obtained all the letters
to Mr Boyd</hi></egXML></p>
<p>The above examples presume the common case where a single word or
phrase is marked by a line, with no doubt as to where the marking begins
or ends and with no overlapping of the area of text with other marked
areas of text.  Where there is doubt, the <gi>certainty</gi> element may
be used to record the doubt.  In the Browning example cited above the
underlining actually begins half-way under <mentioned>who</mentioned>, and this
uncertainty could be remarked as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I have once — by declaring I would prosecute
by law — hindered a man's proceedings who
<hi xml:id="cstart1" rend="underline">had obtained all
the letters to Mr Boyd</hi>
<!-- ... -->
<certainty target="#cstart1" locus="start" degree="0.70">
<desc>may begin with previous word</desc>
</certainty></egXML></p>
<p>Where the area of text marked overlaps other areas of text, for
example crossing a structural division, one of the spanning mechanisms
mentioned above must be used; for example where the line is thought to
mark a deletion, the <gi>delSpan</gi> element may be used.  Where it is
desired simply to record the marking of a span of text in circumstances
where it is not possible to surround the text with a <gi>hi</gi>
element, the <gi>span</gi> element may be used with the <att>rend</att>
or <att>type</att> attribute indicating the style of line-marking.</p>
<p>More work needs to be done on clarifying the treatment of other
textual features marked by lines which might so overlap or nest.  For
example, in many Middle English manuscripts (e.g. the Jesus and Digby
verse collections), marginal sidebars may indicate metrical structure:
couplets may be linked in pairs, with the pairs themselves linked
into stanzas. Or, marginal sidebars may indicate emphasis, or may
point out a region of text on which there is some annotation: in many
manuscripts of Chaucer's <title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> lines
655–8 are marked with nesting parentheses against which the scribe
has written <mentioned>nota</mentioned>.</p>
<p>At the lowest level, all such features could be captured by use of
the <gi>note</gi> element, containing a prose description of the
manuscript at this point, enhanced by a link to a visual
representation (or facsimile) of the feature in question.  
It is not yet clear how best to mark up such
phenomena so as to
obtain more usefully structured encodings.  For example,
in the Chaucer example just cited, one may wish to record that the
<mentioned>nota</mentioned> is written in the Hengwrt manuscript in the right
margin against a single large left parenthesis bracketing the four
lines, with two right parentheses in the right margin bracketing two
overlapping pairs of lines:  the first and third, the second and fourth.
The <gi>note</gi> element allows us to record that the scribe wrote
<mentioned>nota</mentioned>, but is not well-adapted to show that the
<mentioned>nota</mentioned> points both at all four lines and at two pairs of
lines within the four lines.  </p></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="PHSK"><head>Headers, Footers, and Similar Matter</head>

<p>Such information as page numbers, signatures, or catchwords may be
recorded in a specialised <gi>fw</gi> element provided for that
purpose. Although the name derives from the term <term>forme
work</term>, used in description of early printed documents (the
<q>forme</q> being the block used to hold movable type), the
<gi>fw</gi> element may be used for such features of any document,
written or printed.  Note that the purpose of this element is to
record page numbers etc. <emph>actually present</emph> in the document
being encoded, not necessarily to provide a complete or accurate
pagination of it. </p>
<p>Information about pagination etc. may also be provided using the <att>n</att> attribute of the
<gi>pb</gi> or <gi>gb</gi> elements, or by other appropriate
<gi>milestone</gi> elements, as further discussed in section <ptr
target="#CORS"/>: since this information is usually provided by the
encoder, it is not subject to the constraint that it should be
present only if textually present in the source being encoded. In
text-critical situations it may be useful to provide both a normalised
version of the pagination and a representation of the catch-word
or numbering, especially when the latter presents a variant reading, or is
significant for compositor identification. 
 <specList><specDesc key="fw"/></specList> 
The <gi>fw</gi> element may
be used to encode any of the unchanging portions of a page forme, such
as:
<list type="simple">
<item>running heads (whether repeated or changing on every page, or
alternating pages)</item>
<item>running footers</item>
<item>page numbers</item>
<item>catch-words</item>
<item>other material repeated from page to page, which falls outside the
stream of the text</item></list>
It should not be used for marginal glosses, annotations, or textual
variants, which should be tagged using <gi>gloss</gi>, <gi>note</gi>, or
the text-critical tags described in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>,
respectively.</p>
<p>For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fw type="head" place="top-centre">Poëms.</fw>
<fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">29</fw>
<fw type="sig" place="bot-centre">E3</fw>
<fw type="catch" place="bot-right">TEMPLE</fw></egXML>
<!-- Donne, Poems 1633, p. 29 -->
	<!-- [Need several examples, all fuller than this one.     -->
	<!-- Take from DOSL materials? -MSM]                          --></p>
</div>



<div xml:id="PH-changes"><head>Changes</head>
<p>A major purpose of genetic editing is the identification of
<soCalled>revision campaigns</soCalled> or, more generally,
<term>changes</term>. An editor may wish to assign a set of
alterations (deletions, additions, substitutions, transpositions,
etc.) or any other act of writing to a particular change, to indicate
both that one or more of such phenomena preceded or followed another
and also to indicate that they are related in some way, for example
that one is a consequence of the other. They might also wish to group
together certain revisions, regardless of when they might have
occurred, based on a variety of other shared characteristics (e.g.,
corrections of factual errors or revisions that incorporate
suggestions made by a given reader).  To document this we need:
<list><item>a system to assign phenomena to a particular change</item>
<item>a way to characterize a change, in itself and in relation to
other changes.</item>
</list></p>
      
<p>The element <gi>creation</gi> (within the TEI Header
profile description) contains  all 
information relating to the genesis or production of a text. It may
contain a <gi>listChange</gi> element which contains
a number of <gi>change</gi> elements, one for each identified change:
<specList>
            <specDesc key="listChange" atts="ordered"/>
            <specDesc key="change"/>
         </specList>
      </p>
      
<p>In the following example taken from the genetic edition of Goethe’s
Faust, the editor has identified four distinct changes:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <profileDesc>
            <creation>
               <listChange ordered="true">
                  <change xml:id="ST-1">First stage, written in ink by a writer</change>
                  <change xml:id="ST-2">Second stage, written in Goethe's hand using pencil</change>
                  <change xml:id="ST-3">Fixation of the revised passages and further revisions by
Goethe using ink</change>
                  <change xml:id="ST-4">Addition of another stanza in a          different hand,
probably at a later stage</change>
               </listChange>
            </creation>
         </profileDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>The <gi>listChange</gi> element carries an attribute
      <att>ordered</att>, which can take the values <code>true</code>
      or <code>false</code> (the default). The attribute specifies
      whether the order of child elements signifies a temporal order
      for the revision campaigns which they document. In the Faust
      example above, the editor has asserted that the four stages
      distinguished are ordered chronologically according to the order
      of the <gi>change</gi> elements. Note that asserting a specific
      order early on, though probably one of the hardest tasks in a
      genetic analysis, can considerably reduce the encoding effort in
      assigning textual alterations to stages during the
      transcription, as we will see below.  For instance deletions can
      only be assigned to a stage that follows the one in which the
      passage being deleted was written down. Hence, having a certain
      order of stages put in place before transcription begins will
      allow the encoder to reduce verbose tagging, where default
      assumptions based on the natural order of actions can be
      made.</p>
      <p>If necessary, <gi>listChange</gi> elements can be nested
      hierarchically. This may be helpful in two cases. Firstly one
      can build up hypotheses about related revisions step-by-step,
      starting with stages of smaller coverage, whose members are
      certainly related, and then in a subsequent pass grouping these
      stages in turn, thereby extending their reach.</p>

      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <profileDesc>
            <creation>
               <listChange>
                  <change xml:id="o">An unrelated change note</change>
                  <listChange xml:id="m">
<change xml:id="m1">Alterations on one manuscript page, certainly
   related</change>
<change xml:id="m2">Alterations on another manuscript page, certainly
   related</change>
                  </listChange>
                  <change xml:id="p">Another unrelated change note</change>
               </listChange>
            </creation>
         </profileDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>A nested <gi>listChange</gi> elements is also useful         to indicate a
            <emph>partial</emph> ordering of revision campaigns.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <listChange ordered="true">
            <change xml:id="ST1">The first stage</change>
            <listChange>
               <!-- We have no information about the order of these changes, except
     that they both followed ST1 and prececeded STX  -->
                  <change xml:id="ST-rev1">A revision of the first stage</change>
               <change xml:id="ST-rev2">Another revision of the first          stage</change>
            </listChange>
            <change xml:id="STX">The last stage</change>
         </listChange>
      </egXML>
      <p>In addition to the possibility of ordering text stages in relation to each other,
            <gi>change</gi> elements may carry a number of attributes from the
            <ident>att.datable</ident> class (<att>period</att>, <att>when</att>,
            <att>notBefore</att>, <att>notAfter</att>, <att>from</att>, and <att>to</att>) which
         allow each stage to be dated as exactly or inexactly as necessary, in the same way as is
         currently possible for the TEI <gi>date</gi> element.</p>
      <!-- Maybe note that absolute dates and relative order can conflict -->
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <profileDesc>
            <creation>
               <date notAfter="1816-07-18"/>
               <listChange ordered="true">
                  <change xml:id="mod1" when="1816-07-16">The first draft of
   <title>Persuasion</title> is completed by the <date>July 16    1816</date>
written after the word <q>Finis</q> at <ref target="#pers-30">page
30</ref>.</change>
                  <change xml:id="mod2" notBefore="1816-07-16">After the <date>16th    of July</date>
Austen starts revision of the two final chapters, by rewriting the end and
adding a new zone (<ref target="#transp-1">pages 32-35</ref>) to be inserted
at <ref target="#insertion-p1">page 19</ref>. This stage is documented by the
deletion of the date (<date>July 16 1816</date>) at <ref target="#pers-30">page
   30</ref>, and the addition of more text and of a new date    (<date>July 18.
   1816</date>) at <ref target="#pers-31">page    31</ref></change>
                  <change notBefore="1816-07-18">Before publication, after <date>July    18th,
   1816</date> chapters 10-11 were broken into three chapters, 10, 11, 12, as
witnessed by the print.</change>
               </listChange>
            </creation>
         </profileDesc>
      </egXML>
      <p>Each <gi>change</gi> element, apart from declaring a distinct
      change in the creation of the document, may also contain
      references to other annotations contained within the
      <gi>teiHeader</gi> or in the document (as shown in the previous
      example). Such references, along with the textual content are
      purely documentary and do not affect the textual stage
      associated with any element thus referred to. The association of
      a textual component with a change is always made explicitly,
      either by using the <att>target</att> attribute on the
      <gi>change</gi> element to point to one or more elements, or
      (preferably) by pointing from the element or elements concerned
      to the <gi>change</gi> element by means of their
      <att>change</att> attribute:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <line change="#firstStage">This is a <mod type="subst" change="#secondStage">
               <del>house</del>
               <add>mouse</add>
            </mod>.</line>
      </egXML>
      <p>This simple example shows the latter of the two options: The
      relevant changes are declared in the header; then textual
      alterations and acts of writing are associated with them. The
      above markup indicates that the whole sentence was realized in
      the first stage, while the substitution of “house” with “mouse”
      happened at the second stage. </p>
      <p>A more complex and complete example:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <profileDesc>
            <creation>
               <listChange ordered="true">
                  <change xml:id="firstStage">First stage, written in ink by a writer</change>
                  <change xml:id="secondStage">Revised by Goethe using pencil</change>
                  <change xml:id="thirdStage">Fixation of the revised passages and further revisions
by Goethe using ink</change>
                  <change xml:id="fourthStage">Addition of another stanza, probably at a later
stage</change>
               </listChange>
            </creation>
         </profileDesc> [...] <div change="#firstStage">
            <l n="11656">
               <subst>
                  <del>Ihr</del>
                  <add>
<retrace change="#thirdStage">
   <seg change="#secondStage">Nun</seg>
</retrace>
                  </add>
               </subst> wanſtige Schuften mit den Feuerbacken</l>
            <l n="11657">Ihr glüht ſo recht vom Höllen Schwefel <subst
                  change="#secondStage
         #thirdStage">
                  <del>ſatt</del>
                  <add>feiſt</add>
               </subst>.</l>
            <l n="11658">
               <delSpan spanTo="#anchor_delSpan_1" change="#thirdStage"/>Ihr hagren,  triſten, krummgezog<subst>
                  <del>nen</del>
                  <add>ener</add>
               </subst> Nacken</l>
            <l>Wenn ihr nur piepſet iſt die Welt ſchon matt.<anchor xml:id="anchor_delSpan_1"/></l>
         </div>
      </egXML>
      <p>Note first that a change, once assigned to an element, is
      inherited by all descendants of that element unless overridden
      by a subsequent assignment. So in the example above the three
      verses are assigned to the first stage initially. The writing of
      <mentioned>Nun</mentioned> (as part of the substitution in the
      first verse) takes place in the second stage and is repeated or
      fixed in the third. Also the substitution in the second verse
      is done repeatedly: initially it takes place in the second
      stage, but is fixated as a whole in the third.</p>
      <p>The interpretation of change assignments for a particular
      text passage is based on a number of implicit assumptions and
      constraints which have the effect of minimizing the amount of
      tagging necessary. The system is also flexible enough to support
      an explicit distinction between acts of writing and textual
      alterations, since either of these can be associated with
      changes described in the encoding. The following example shows
      an encoding in which the same passage is transcribed twice, once
      from a documentary perspective, and once from a textual one
      :</p>
      <!-- faust_2.xml -->
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
         <profileDesc>
            <creation>
               <listChange ordered="true">
                  <change target="#zone_1 #subst_3">First stage, written in ink by a scribe</change>
                  <change
target="#zone_2 #mod_1 #line_1 #line_2 #subst_1 #subst_2
#subst_4 #delSpan_1"
>Revised by Goethe using pencil</change>
                  <change target="#redo_1 #redo_2 #redo_3 #subst_1 #subst_2
#delSpan_1 #add_1"
>Fixation of the revised passages and further revisions by Goethe using
ink</change>
               </listChange>
            </creation>
         </profileDesc> 
<!-- ... -->
<sourceDoc>
            <surface>
               <zone xml:id="zone_1">
                  <line xml:id="line_1">
<handShift new="#g_bl"/>
<retrace hand="#g_t" xml:id="redo_1">Nun</retrace>
                  </line>
                  <line><handShift new="#jo_t"/>Ihr wanſtige Schuften mit den Feuerbacken</line>
                  <line xml:id="line_2">
<handShift new="#g_bl"/>
<retrace hand="#g_t" xml:id="redo_2">feiſt</retrace>
                  </line>
                  <line>Ihr glüht ſo recht vom Höllen Schwefel ſatt.</line> [...]       </zone>
            </surface>
         </sourceDoc>
         <text>
            <body>
               <l n="11656">
                  <subst xml:id="subst_1">
<del>Ihr</del>
<add>Nun</add>
                  </subst> wanſtige Schuften mit den Feuerbacken</l>
               <l n="11657">Ihr glüht ſo recht vom Höllen Schwefel <subst xml:id="subst_2">
<del>ſatt</del>
<add>feiſt</add>
                  </subst>.</l>
            </body>
         </text>
      </egXML>
      <p>The documentary transcription stresses the writing process,
      while the textual transcription emphasizes textual
      alterations. In either case, the change of writing activity
      associated with a particular feature in the transcript is
      explicitly indicated. From the documentary perspective, the
      stage assignments describe the writing process, in that they
      specify which segment has been written when and how often. From
      the textual perspective, the markup concentrates on the order of
      textual alterations and makes no assumptions about the order of
      writing.  In this example, the association is made by pointing
      from the <gi>change</gi> element to all the passages and
      alterations in question in either perspective, which has the
      merit of not confusing the presentation of the interventions
      concerned with writing sequence information, at the price of
      requiring a distinct identifier on each intervention.
      </p>
   </div>



<div type="div2" xml:id="PHTRXX"><head>Other Primary Source Features not Covered in these Guidelines</head>
<p>We repeat the advice given at the beginning of this chapter, that
these recommendations are not intended to meet every transcriptional
circumstance ever likely to be faced by any scholar.  They are intended
rather as a base to enable encoding of the most common phenomena found
in the course of scholarly transcription of primary source materials.
These guidelines particularly do not address the encoding of physical
description of textual witnesses:  the materials of the carrier, the
medium of the inscribing implement, 
the organisation of the carrier materials themselves (as
quiring, collation, etc.), authorial instructions or scribal markup,
etc., except insofaras these are involved in the broader question of
manuscript description, as addressed by the <ident type="module">msdescription</ident> module described in chapter <ptr target="#MS"/>. </p></div>

<div><head>Module for Transcription of Primary Sources</head>

<p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following
components:

<moduleSpec xml:id="DPH" ident="transcr"><altIdent type="FPI">Transcription
of Primary Sources</altIdent><desc>Transcription of primary
sources</desc>
<desc xml:lang="zh-tw">原文轉錄</desc>
<desc xml:lang="fr">Représentation de sources primaires</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Trascrizione di fonti primarie</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Transcrição de fontes primárias</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">転記モジュール</desc></moduleSpec><!--publicID:  -//TEI P5//ELEMENTS Additional Element Set for Transcription of Primary Sources//EN-->

The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTCHD" >
&addSpan;
&damage;
&damageSpan;
&delSpan;
&ex;
&fw;
&gb;
&handNotes;
&handShift;
&am;
&restore;
&space;
&subst;
&substJoin;
&supplied;
&surplus;
&line;
&listChange;
&listTranspose;
&metamark;
&mod;
<!--&patch;-->
&redo;
&retrace;
&transpose;
&undo;
</specGrp>
</div>
</div>
