<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="SH" n="24">
<head>The TEI Header and Other Metadata Standards</head>
<p>Many libraries, text repositories, research sites and related
institutions with collections of TEI documents need to map, or export,
metadata from the TEI header to other metadata formats such as MARC,
Dublin Core (DC), or MODS.  The increasing momentum behind recent
efforts such as the Z39.50 Bath Profile (interoperability) (<ptr
target="http://www.collectionscanada.ca/bath/bp-current.htm"/>) and
the Open Archive Initiative (OAI) (<ptr
target="http://www.openarchives.org/"/>), which facilitate the
automated publishing, harvesting, and aggregation of digital object
metadata, increases the need for such mappings.</p>
<p>This section of the Guidelines outlines practices recommended for
encoders (especially those responsible for the documentation of text)
and catalogers when creating TEI headers that will require mapping to
other schema and specifies the set of recommended elements that should
be included to facilitate such mappings. It also discusses the
relationship between TEI headers elements and MARC fields and between
TEI elements and Dublin Core elements, to facilitate cataloguing of
TEI documents and the loading of TEI header metadata into MARC-based
bibliographic databases, HTML/XHTML <gi scheme="XHTML">meta</gi> tags,
OAI data providers, or other metadata systems.
</p>
<div type="div2" xml:id="SHDEF"><head>Principles for Encoders</head>
<p>The richness and size of the header reflect the diversity of uses
to which electronic texts conforming to these Guidelines will be put.
As described in section <ptr target="#HD7"/>, the TEI header allows for
the provision of a very large amount of information concerning the
text itself, its source, encodings, and revisions as well as detailed
descriptive information that can be used by researchers in analysing
the text.  The richness of the header will depend on the nature and
intended use of the text.  At one extreme, an encoder may expect that
the header will only provide bibliographic information about the text
adequate to local needs.  At the other, wishing to ensure that their
texts can be used for the widest range of applications, encoders will
want to document as explicitly as possible both bibliographic and
descriptive information in such a way that no prior or ancillary
knowledge about the text is needed in order to process it.  The
header, in the latter case, will be very full, approximating the kind
of documentation often supplied in the form of a manual.  Most texts
will lie somewhere between these extremes; textual corpora in
particular will tend toward the latter extreme.</p>
<p>For a successful and complete mapping from the TEI header to other
standards and formats, the TEI header should be as complete as
possible.  <!-- LB: targetted section has been deleted:  
Therefore, many tags that are listed as optional in the
"Minimal and Recommended Headers" section of this chapter should be
considered "recommended" for TEI headers that require mapping to other
standards and formats. --> When deciding which information
to include in a TEI header that will be mapped to another metadata
standard and the format or structure of that header information, the
following should be kept in mind:
<list>
<item>The header should provide full bibliographic information on the
encoded text, its source, where the text can be located, and any
restrictions governing its use.</item>
<item>The header should contain useful information about the encoding of
the text itself.  In this regard, it is highly recommended that the
encoding description be as complete as possible.  The Guidelines do
not require that the encoding description be included in the header
(since some simple transcriptions of small items may not require it),
but in practice a header without an encoding description
would prove difficult mor impossible to map satisfactorily to most other
metadata formats.</item>
<item>The header should be amenable to automatic processing, particularly
for loading into databases and for the creation of publications,
indexes, and finding aids, without undue editorial intervention.  For
this reason, two recommendations are made regarding the format or
structure of the header: first, where there is a choice between a
prose content model and one that contains a formal series of
specialized elements, <emph>wherever possible and appropriate the
specialized elements should be preferred to unstructured prose</emph>.
For instance, the source description can contain either a free-prose
citation (tagged <gi>bibl</gi> or even <gi>p</gi>) or a
<gi>biblStruct</gi> element, which provides a more rigorous structure
for the bibliographic information (see examples in section <ptr target="#COBI"/>).  The more structured <gi>biblStruct</gi> element is
more suitable for automatic processing, and is therefore recommended
over the less structured alternatives whenever the header is to be
mapped to another standard.  Second, with respect to corpora,
information about each of the texts within a corpus should be included
in the overall corpus-level <gi>teiHeader</gi>.  That is, source
information, editorial practices, encoding descriptions, and the like
should be included in the relevant sections of the corpus
<gi>teiHeader</gi>, with pointers to them from the headers of the
individual texts included in the corpus.  There are three reasons for
this recommendation: first, the corpus-level header will contain the
full array of bibliographic and documentary information for each of
the texts in a corpus, and thus be of great benefit to remote users,
who may have access only to metadata from the corpus-level header;
second, such a layout is easier for the coder to maintain than
searching for information throughout a text; and third, generally
speaking, this practice results in greater overall consistency,
especially with respect to bibliographic citations.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The distribution and retrieval of TEI header metadata enable
resource discovery by other means. The mappings to MARC and Dublin Core
discussed in the remainder of this section provide two examples of
how TEI header metadata may be re-used and re-purposed.</p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="SHMARC"><head>Header Elements and their Relationship to the MARC Record</head>
<!--<p>This entire section is undergoing review by professional catalogers and members of the
TEI in Libraries SIG </p>-->
<!-- jawalsh: This section needs to be reviewed by catalogers.  Natasha and I are planning to have
     catalogers at Indiana and/or North Carolina do such a review -->
<p>This section offers some guidance to both cataloguers and
bibliographic analysts who want to load metadata from TEI headers into a
MARC-based retrieval system. Because there are variations in
cataloguing practice across local sites, among bibliographic utilities
(such as OCLC and RLIN), and differences in MARC usage in different
countries, only tentative advice is possible. Note that the following
examples are based on USMARC, <emph>not</emph> UNIMARC.<note place="bottom">For
more information on UNIMARC, see <bibl>Brian P. Holt,
<title>UNIMARC Manual</title> (London, U.K.: IFLA Universal
Bibliographic Control and International MARC Programme, British Library,
1987)</bibl>. For USMARC, see <bibl> Walt Crawford, <title>MARC
for library use: understanding USMARC</title> (Boston: G.K. Hall,
1989)</bibl>, <bibl><title>USMARC format for bibliographic data,
including content designation</title> (Washington, D.C.: Library of
Congress, 1987)</bibl>, and <bibl>Deborah J. Byrne, <title>MARC
manual : understanding and using MARC records</title> (Englewood, Colo.:
Libraries Unlimited, Inc., 1991)</bibl>.</note>
UNIMARC offers cataloguers in different countries the opportunity to
combine different national practices in a single MARC format, and is the
preferred variety of MARC records for distribution
across national boundaries. The implementation of UNIMARC, however,
will be affected by local practice and by guidelines offered by the
bibliographic utilities. Though UNIMARC is a stable format, the
guidelines for its implementation are not sufficiently known or
stabilized to be included in this chapter.</p>
<p>There are some major differences between the MARC record and the TEI
header that will cause problems for librarians trying to map from the
TEI header to the MARC record. The most important
difference between the MARC record and the TEI header is the function of
each. <!-- Despite the efforts and claims of some members of the library
community, the MARC record remains fundamentally an electronic version
of the catalogue card, with the limitations of its model.--><!-- Natasha: I am not sure that we can  go with this statement anymore??? thatÕs why we need catalogers to see it Ð I am sure my catalogers will agree to do it.--><note place="bottom">The
primary function of the MARC record when it was
first designed in the mid-1960s was to allow for the electronic
distribution of cataloguing records in support of card production. See
<bibl>Henriette Avram, <title>The MARC Pilot Project</title>
(Washington D.C.: Library of Congress, 1968), p. 3.</bibl> For
discussion of the relationship between the MARC record and the catalogue
card, see <bibl>Michael Gorman, <title level="a">After AACR2R: The Future of the
Anglo-American Cataloging Rules</title>, in Richard Smiraglia, ed.,
<title>Origins, Content and Future of AACR2 Revised</title> (Chicago:
American Library Association, 1992)</bibl>.</note>
The catalogue card is a unitary record for a physical object containing
complex <emph>bibliographic data</emph> of varying sorts. The catalogue
card points to the physical object. The TEI header provides full
bibliographic information (as would a card), as well as documentary
non-bibliographic information that supports the analysis, either by
humans or machines, of the electronic text documented by header. Most
of this analytical information, which is found in the profile description,
encoding description, and revision history, has little direct provision
for it in the MARC record,
and if retained must be recorded as unstructured notes (55XX) fields.
Notes fields usually do not have the structure to support machine
retrieval and analysis, while properly formatted profile, encoding, and
revision descriptions lend themselves to retrieval, can support machine
processing (including analysis), and point directly to the electronic
text attached to the header. Moreover, the electronic text points back
to the relevant elements in the header.</p>
<p>Though this section offers some advice on where the profile,
encoding, and revision descriptions might go in a MARC record, for
practical reasons a repository might want create a codebook from these
divisions of the header, and create a MARC record from the file
description only. The MARC record should contain a reference to the
codebook.</p>
<p>Subfields (or delimiters) are conventionally indicated by the
dollar sign.</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="SHFD"><head>MARC Fields for the File Description</head>
<p>Note that there is no provision for the <soCalled>Main
Entry</soCalled> (or USMARC <ident type="field">1XX</ident> fields) in the TEI
header. The main entry should be constructed, using appropriate name
authority control, by the cataloguer from information derived from the
header that indicates who is primarily responsible for the
intellectual content of the work. There is an <gi>author</gi> element,
but the form of the name will have to be checked by a cataloguer
before the main entry is constructed.
<list type="gloss">
<label><gi>titleStmt</gi></label><item> corresponds to title and statement of
responsibility fields in MARC, typically <ident type="field">240</ident> (for uniform
title) and <ident type="field">245</ident> (for title proper).</item>
<label><gi>title</gi></label><item> <ident type="field">240 $a</ident> (for uniform titles) or
<ident type="field">245 $a</ident> fields. Put any subtitles in <ident type="field">24X $b</ident>.
Insert the constant, <q>[computer file]</q> in the <ident type="field">24X $h gmd</ident>
subfield.  Put any alternate titles in <ident type="field">246 $a.</ident></item>
<label><gi>author</gi></label><item><ident type="field">100 $a, $b, $c, $q</ident>.  The form of the name will typically need to be checked by a cataloguer who will be consulting name authority files.</item>
</list></p>
<p>The elements <gi>sponsor</gi>, 
<gi>funder</gi>, and <gi>principal</gi> all belong in the <ident type="field">245 $c</ident> subfield:
statement of responsibility, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><titleStmt>
   <title>Two stories by Edgar Allen Poe: electronic
      version</title>
   <author>Poe, Edgar Allen (1809-1849)</author>
   <respStmt>
      <resp>compiled by</resp>
      <name>James D. Benson</name>
   </respStmt>
</titleStmt></egXML>
This might be tagged in MARC as:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">245 Two stories by Edgar Allen Poe :$belectronic version ;
 compiled by $cJames D. Benson.</egXML>
<!-- Natasha:
I do not agree completely with this Ð we need to consult with catalogers. I only know for sure that our catalogers map resp like illustrated by to MARC 700-711.
Also, our local practice maps funding information to MARC 536 field, ex.:
536;   ;a Funding from the Institute of Museum and Library Services supported the electronic publication of this title. $
-->
</p>
<p>The  <gi>edition</gi> and <gi>name</gi> (within responsibility
statement) elements correspond with MARC fields <ident type="field">250
$a</ident> and <ident type="field">250 $b</ident> respectively, as in the
following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><editionStmt>
   <edition>Student's edition,
       <date>June 1987</date>
   </edition>
   <respStmt>
      <resp>New annotation by</resp>
      <name>George Brown</name>
   </respStmt>
</editionStmt></egXML>
<!-- N.B. the awkward tagging here is required by the fact    -->
	<!-- that editionStmt *can* contain phrase data.  It ought    -->
	<!-- to be just p instead. (msm)                              -->
This might be tagged in MARC as:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">250  $aStudent's edition, June, 1987, new annotation by
  $bGeorge Brown.</egXML>
<!-- Natasha:
In our local practice, catalogers record information about this particular electronic edition in the MARC 250 field. For example, for for ÒChristoph von Graffenried's Account of the Founding of New BernÉÓ (http://docsouth.unc.edu/nc/graffenried/menu.html) :
250 $a Electronic ed.
ÒIncidents in the Life of a Slave GirlÓ by Harriet Jacobs (http://docsouth.unc.edu/jacobs/menu.html) shows as a second edition, with a relevant note about the first edition:
250 $a Electronic ed., 2nd ed.
500 $a Second ed. has updated encoding and formatting, and replaces the 1st ed. published in 1998
-->
</p>
<p>The <gi>extent</gi> element is analogous to the
<soCalled>Physical Description</soCalled> MARC field.  Fields
<ident type="field">256</ident> or <ident type="field">3XX</ident> are
appropriate, depending on local practice. 
The children of the <gi>publicationStmt</gi> element may be put in MARC <ident type="field">260</ident>.  The 
<gi>pubPlace</gi> element corresponds with field <ident type="field">260
$a</ident>; the 
<gi>publisher</gi>, <gi>distributor</gi>, or <gi>authority</gi>
elements correspond with the MARC field <ident type="field">260 $b</ident>; while the <gi>date</gi> element in
this context
corresponds with the <ident type="field">260 $c</ident>, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><publicationStmt>
   <publisher>Columbia University Press</publisher>
   <pubPlace>New York</pubPlace>
   <date>1993</date>
</publicationStmt></egXML>
This may be tagged in MARC as:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">260 $aNew York :$bColumbia University Press, $c1993.</egXML></p>
<p>Local practice will determine appropriate MARC fields for
<gi>address</gi>, <gi>idno</gi>, and <gi>availability</gi>.
Restrictions on access should normally be placed in the
<ident type="field">506</ident> field, while the place where an item may be ordered
will be located in a local notes (<ident type="field">590</ident>) field.  If local
practice warrants it, the address of the publisher should be indicated
in the <ident type="field">260</ident> field.
<!-- Natasha: If URL is used, it usually corresponds to MARC 856. -->
<!-- jawalsh: Natasha, I agree we may want to mention 856, but is there a tag in TEI that is regularly used in this self-referential manner?  That is, is there a TEI element encoders use to include the URL for the TEI document (or for a transformed HTML or other version of the document?)-->
<!-- LB: this is a FAQ. The most obvious candidate imo would be an idno
     type="uri" or "purl" or whatever" but there's no reason not to
     propose a specific new element if you think this would be better  -->
</p>
<p>The series <gi>title</gi> and the <gi>idno</gi> should be placed in
the appropriate <ident type="field">490</ident> fields (series untraced), if series
authority checking needs to be done.  Further, because the TEI elements do
not differentiate between name, conference, or title series, there is
no simple mechanical method for determining which MARC tag (<ident type="field">410,
411,</ident> etc.)  should be used.  Safe practice would be to load any
series statements into <ident type="field">490</ident> fields, and then to conduct
authority work on those fields.
</p>
<p>The <gi>notesStmt</gi> element is  usually reserved for general note
(<ident type="field">5XX</ident>) fields.</p>
<p>The <gi>sourceDesc</gi> can be mapped to be a <soCalled>source of
data</soCalled> note (<ident type="field">537</ident> in RLIN MDF format) with the
print constant <q>Transcribed from:</q> at the beginning of the note. <!-- Natash: It corresponds to MARC 534; jawalsh: What is "it"? The whole <sourceDesc>?-->
The <gi>biblStruct</gi> itself can be mapped onto a <ident type="field">581</ident>
field (note on primary publication) using the ISBD format to separate
each data element.</p>
<p>The <gi>scriptStmt</gi>, <gi>recordingStmt</gi>,
<gi>recording</gi>, <gi>equipment</gi>, and <gi>broadcast</gi>
elements do not easily map to existing MARC fields, and should be
put into a local notes field (<ident type="field">590</ident>) treating the TEI element
introducing each component as a print constant at the head of the
field in order to facilitate future local processing and retrieval.
Example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><scriptStmt>
   <bibl>
      <author>CNN Network News</author>
      <title>News Headlines</title>
      <date>12 Jun 1991</date>
   </bibl>
</scriptStmt></egXML>
This may be tagged in MARC thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">590  <scriptStmt>
<bibl>
   <author>CNN Network News</author>
   <title>News Headlines</title>
   <date> 12 Jun 1991</date>
</bibl>
</scriptStmt></egXML>
Example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><recordingStmt>
   <recording type="video" dur="P10M">
      <equipment>
         <p>Recorded from FM radio to chrome tape</p>
      </equipment>
      <broadcast>
         <bibl>         
            <title>Britain's pleasure parade</title>
            <author>BBC Radio 4 FM</author>
            <editor role="interviewer">Robin Day</editor>
            <editor role="interviewee">Margaret Thatcher</editor>
            <series> <title>The World Tonight</title> </series>
            <date>27 Nov 89</date>
         </bibl>
      </broadcast>
   </recording>
</recordingStmt></egXML>
This can be tagged in MARC as:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">590 <recordingStmt>
<recording type="video" dur="P10M">
   <equipment>
      <p>Recorded from FM radio to chrome tape</p>
   </equipment>
   <broadcast>
      <bibl>
         <title>Britain's pleasure parade</title>
         <author>BBC Radio 4 FM</author>
         <editor role="interviewer">Robin Day</editor>
         <editor role="interviewee">Margaret Thatcher</editor>
         <series> <title>The World Tonight</title> </series>
         <date>27 Nov 89</date>
      </bibl>
   </broadcast>
</recording>
</recordingStmt></egXML></p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="SHED"><head>MARC Fields for the Encoding Description</head>
<p>The <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element provides useful information
documenting the relationship between an electronic text and the source
or sources from which it was derived. The <gi>projectDesc</gi>,
<gi>samplingDecl</gi>, <gi>editorialDecl</gi>, and <gi>refsDecl</gi>
elements provide details of decisions and rationales used about the
process and purposes of the project, how text was sampled, principles
of editorial practice, and how canonical references are constructed.
The <ident type="field">567</ident> field (notes on methodology) appears to be the
most appropriate for this sort of information, though this field is
normally intended for methodologies characterizing the social
sciences. Practically, it would be wise to transcribe the
<gi>projectDesc</gi>, <gi>editorialDecl</gi>, <gi>refsDecl</gi>, and
<gi>classDecl</gi> elements directly as one or more 567 fields without
intervention, with the element name at the beginning of each field,
and any TEI tagging left intact. This may facilitate any
locally-developed retrieval software.</p>
<!-- Natasha: Our local practice is to use also 516 field. -->
<p>Example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><encodingDesc>
  <projectDesc>
    <p>Texts were collected to illustrate the full range of
      twentieth-century spoken and written Swedish, written by native
      Swedish authors.</p>
  </projectDesc>
  <samplingDecl>
    <p>Sample of 2000 words taken from the beginning of the text.</p>
  </samplingDecl>
  <editorialDecl>
    <interpretation>
      <p>Errors in transcription controlled by using the SUC spell
        checker, v.2.4</p>
    </interpretation>
  </editorialDecl>
</encodingDesc></egXML>
This may be tagged in MARC as:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">567  
<projectDesc>
      <p>Texts were collected to illustrate the
      full range of twentieth-century spoken and written
      Swedish, written by native Swedish authors.</p>
   </projectDesc>567  <samplingDecl>
      <p>Sample of 2000 words taken from the
     beginning of the text.</p>
   </samplingDecl>567  <editorialDecl>
      <interpretation>
         <p>Errors in transcription controlled
      by using the SUC spell checker, v. 2.4</p>
      </interpretation>
   </editorialDecl></egXML></p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="SHPD"><head>MARC Fields for the Profile Description</head>
<p>The profile description is the most problematic element in the TEI
header for librarian cataloguers, because it provides a detailed
description of the <emph>non-bibliographic</emph> aspects of the text,
specifically the languages and sublanguages used, the situation in which
it was produced, and the participants and their setting.  This
information can be used for retrieval purposes or in
machine-supported analysis of the text.  The information can be loaded
into a separate <soCalled>codebook</soCalled> and referenced by the MARC
record.  While some components of the profile description have clear counterparts in MARC, little guidance can be offered on the appropriate MARC
location for many of the elements that make up the profile description. One option is
to load the profile description into a
MARC record for archival and possibly retrieval purposes, then the
contents of the profile description may be mapped into a locally-defined
notes field (<ident type="field">59X</ident>) with its TEI tagging intact, as in the examples
above.
<!-- jawalsh:  I think we can do better than the above paragraph.  I've started to revise it, but the suggestion in P4 that there it's not really possible to provide mapping guidance for the whole of the profile desciption is untrue.  There are things in there that can be cleanly mapped to MARC. -->
</p>
<p>Elements from the profile description that suggest clear mappings to MARC include the individual <gi>language</gi> children of <gi>langUsage</gi> which correspond to MARC 041. 
<!--
Natasha: possible example:
<langUsage>  maps to MARC 041:
<language>
  <language id="eng">English</language> 
  <language id="lat">Latin</language> 
  <language id="fre">French</language> 
  <language id="ger">German</language>
In MARC: 
041	1 	$a eng $a fre $a ger $h fre $h ger
-->
</p>
<p>The metadata typically contained in <gi>textClass</gi> corresponds to MARC 6XX fields.
<!-- jawalsh: This statement needs good examples.  It's hard to describe in prose, because the mapping is not
from <textClass> to MARC 6XX.  It's from textClass/keywords/list/item to MARC 6XX. -->
<!-- Natasha: possible example:
excerpts from the MARC record for ÒChristoph von Graffenried's Account of the Founding of New BernÉÓ (http://docsouth.unc.edu/nc/graffenried/menu.html) shows LCSH assigned to the title:
600	10	$a Graffenried, Christoph von, $c Baron, $d 1661-1743.
651	 0	$a New Bern (N.C.) $x History.
650	 0	$a Swiss Americans $z North Carolina.
650	 0	$a Palatine Americans $z North Carolina.
650	 0	$a Whites $z North Carolina $x Relations with Indians.
651	 0	$a North Carolina $x Description and travel $v Early works to 1
651	 0	$a Virginia $x Description and travel $v Early works to 1800.
651	 0	$a North Carolina $x History $y Colonial period, ca. 1600-1775.
651	 0	$a North Carolina $x Politics and government $y To 1775.
-->
</p>
<!-- jawalsh: Do we want a separate section on MODS or a note to catalogers that they use the TEI<->MARC mapping for guidance on MODS? -->
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="SHRD"><head>MARC fields for the Revision Description</head>
<p>The revision history (<gi>revisionDesc</gi>) logs all changes to a
machine readable file whether or not these constitute a new edition of
the file.  Aside from the edition area of the MARC record, there are
no MARC fields that deal specifically with changes of this sort.  This
information might be best included in a <soCalled>codebook</soCalled>,
rather than a MARC record. As before, the simplest way of approaching
this problem is to include the material with its TEI tagging intact as a
locally-defined note (<ident type="field">59X</ident>) in order to support future
local processing.<!-- Natasha: I think our catalogers record the local notes in MARC 9XX. We really have to check that.--></p></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="SHDC"><head>Header Elements and their Relationship to Dublin Core</head>
<p>
&lt;!-- TEI Header / Dublin Core discussion to go here. --&gt;
</p>
</div>
<!-- Natasha:
WE CAN ALSO GIVE A LOOK-UP TABLE OF CORRESPONDING TEIHEADER ELEMENTS AND MARC FIELDS. THE SAME FOR DC AND MODS, ETC.)-->
</div>
