<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="TD" n="27">
<head>Documentation Elements</head>
<p>This chapter describes a module which may be used for the
documentation of the XML elements and element classes which make up
any markup scheme, in particular that described by the TEI Guidelines,
and also for the automatic generation of schemas or DTDs conforming to
that documentation. It should be used also by those wishing to
customize or modify these Guidelines in a conformant manner, as
further described in chapters <ptr target="#MD"/> and <ptr target="#CF"/> and may also be useful in the documentation of any
other comparable encoding scheme, even though it contains some aspects
which are specific to the TEI and may not be generally applicable.</p>
<p>An overview of the kind of processing environment envisaged for the
module described by this chapter may be helpful. In the remainder of
this chapter we refer to software which provides such a processing
environment as an <term>ODD processor</term><note place="foot">ODD is
short for <q>One Document Does it all</q>, and was the name invented
by the original TEI Editors for the predecessor of the system
currently used for this purpose. See further Rahtz et al
2002</note>. Like any other piece of XML software, an ODD processor
may be instantiated in many ways: the current system uses a number of
XSLT stylesheets which are freely available from the TEI, but this
specification makes no particular assumptions about the tools which
will be used to provide an ODD processing environment.</p>
<p>As the name suggests, an ODD processor uses a single XML document
to generate multiple outputs. These outputs will include:
<list>
<item>formal reference documentation for elements, attributes, element
classes, patterns etc. like those provided in <ptr target="#REFTAG"/>;</item>
<item>detailed descriptive documentation, embedding some parts of the
formal reference documentation, such as the tag description lists
provided in this and other chapters of these Guidelines;</item>
<item>declarative code for one or more XML schema languages,
specifically RELAX NG or W3C Schema.</item>
<item>declarative code for fragments which can be assembled to make up
an XML Document Type Declaration.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>The input required to generate these outputs consists of running
prose, and special purpose elements documenting the components
(elements, classes, etc.) which are to be declared
in the chosen schema language. All of this input is encoded in XML
using the module defined by this chapter. In order to support more
than one schema language, this module uses a comparatively high level
model which can then be mapped by an ODD processor to the specific
constructs appropriate to the schema language in use. Although some
modern schema languages such as RELAX NG or W3Schema natively support
self-documentary features of this kind, we have chosen to retain the
ODD model, if only for reasons of compatibility with earlier versions
of these Guidelines. We do however use the ISO standard XML schema
language RELAX NG (<ptr target="http://www.relaxng.org"/>) as a means
of declaring content models, rather than inventing a completely new
XML-based representation for them.</p>
<p> In the TEI abstract model, a markup scheme (a <term>schema</term>)
consists of a number of discrete <term>modules</term>, which can be
combined more or less as required. Each major chapter of these
Guidelines defines a distinct module. Each module declares a number of
<term>elements</term> specific to that module, and may also populate
particular <term>classes</term>. All classes are declared globally;
particular modules extend the meaning of a class by adding elements or attributes
to it. Wherever possible, element content models are defined in terms
of classes rather than in terms of specific elements. Modules can also declare particular
<term>patterns</term>, which act as short-cuts for commonly used
content models or class references.</p>
<p>In the present chapter, we discuss the elements needed to support
this system. In addition, section <ptr target="#TDphrase"/> discusses
some general purpose elements which may be useful in any kind of
technical documentation, wherever there is need to talk about
technical features of an XML encoding such as element names and
attributes. Section <ptr target="#TDmodules"/> discusses the elements
which are used to document XML <term>modules</term> and their high
level components. Section <ptr target="#TDcrystals"/> discusses the
elements which document  XML elements and their attributes,
element classes, and generic patterns or macros. Finally, section <ptr target="#TDformal"/> gives an overview of the whole module.</p>
<div type="div2" xml:id="TDphrase"><head>Phrase Level Documentary Elements</head>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TDphraseTE"><head>Phrase Level Terms</head>
<p>In any kind of technical documentation, the following phrase-level
elements may be found useful for marking up parts of a markup language
or other formal language when these occur within the body of running text.
<specList>
  <specDesc key="att"/>
  <specDesc key="code"/>
  <specDesc key="eg"/>
  <specDesc key="egXML"/>
  <specDesc key="gi"/>
  <specDesc key="tag"/>
  <specDesc key="val"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>As an example of the recommended use of these elements, we quote from
an imaginary TEI working paper:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>The <gi>gi</gi> element is used to tag
element names when they appear in the text; the
<gi>tag</gi> element however is used to show how a tag as
such might appear. So one might talk of an occurrence of the
<gi>blort</gi> element which had been tagged
<tag>blort type='runcible'</tag>. The
<att>type</att> attribute may take any name token as
value; the default value is <val>spqr</val>, in memory of
its creator.</p></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>code</gi> and <gi>egXML</gi> elements are used to mark
strings of formal code, or passages of markup. The first of these is
intended for use in citing brief passages in some formal language such
as a programming language, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<p>If the variable <ident>z</ident> has a value of zero, a statement 
such as <code>x=y/z</code> will usually cause a fatal error.</p>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>If the cited phrase is a mathematical or chemical formula, the more
specific <gi>formula</gi> element defined by the
<ident type="module">figures</ident> module (<ptr target="#FTFOR"/>) may be more
appropriate. </p>
<p>The <gi>eg</gi> element may be used to enclose any kind of example,
which will typically be rendered as a distinct block, possibly using
particular formatting conventions, when the document is processed. It
is a specialised form of the more general <gi>q</gi> element provided
by the TEI core module. In documents containing 
examples of XML markup, the <gi>egXML</gi> element should be used for
preference, as further discussed below in <ptr target="#TDeg"/>, since
the content of this element can be checked for well-formedness. </p>
<p>These elements are all members of the class
<ident type="class">model.egLike</ident>, which is turn a member of the general
<ident type="class">phrase</ident> class. When this module is included in a schema, this class is
expanded to include these elements, and they are therefore available
at any point that a phrase level element is available. </p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TDphraseEA"><head>Element and Attribute Descriptions</head>
<p>Within the body of a document using this module, the following
elements may be used to reference parts of the specification elements
discussed in section <ptr target="#TDcrystals"/>, in particular the
brief prose descriptions these provide for elements and attributes.
<specList>
<specDesc key="specList"/>
<specDesc key="specDesc"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>TEI practice requires that a <gi>specList</gi> listing the elements
under discussion introduce each subsection of a module's
documentation. The source for for the present section, for example, begins
as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div3><head>Element and attribute descriptions</head>
<p>Within the body of a document using this module, the following
elements may be used to reference parts of the specification elements
discussed in section <ptr target="#TDcrystals"/>, in particular the
brief prose descriptions these provide for elements and attributes.
<specList>
<specDesc key="specList"/>
<specDesc key="specDesc"/>
</specList></p>
<p>TEI practice requires that a <gi>specList</gi> listing the elements
...
</p><!-- ... --></div3>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>When formatting the <gi>ptr</gi> element in this example, an ODD
processor might simply generate the section number and title of the
section referred to, perhaps additionally inserting a link to the
section. In a similar way, when processing the <gi>specDesc</gi>
elements, an ODD processor must recover relevant details of the
element being specified (<gi>specList</gi> and <gi>specDesc</gi> in
this case) from their associated declaration elements: typically, the
details recovered will include a brief description of the element and
its attributes. These, and other data, will be stored in a specification
element elsewhere within the current document, or they may be supplied by the
ODD processor in some other way, for example from a database. For this
reason, the link to the required specification element is always made
using a TEI-defined key rather than an XML IDREF value. The ODD
processor uses this key as a means of accessing the specification
element required. There is no requirement that this be performed using
the XML ID/IDREF mechanism, but there is an assumption that the
identifier be unique.</p>
<p>A <gi>specDesc</gi> generates in the documentation the identifier,
and also the contents of the <gi>desc</gi> child of whatever
specification element is indicated by its <att>key</att> attribute,
together with any associated attribute list, as in the example
above.</p>
<specGrp xml:id="TDSG1" n="Phrase-level elements for tag documentation">
&att;
&code;
&eg;
&egXML;
&gi;
&ident;
&tag;
&val;
&specList;
&specDesc;
</specGrp>
</div>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="TDmodules"><head>Modules and Schemas</head>
<p>As mentioned above, the primary purpose of this module is to facilitate
the documentation of an XML schema derived from the TEI Guidelines. The following elements are
provided for this purpose:
<specList>
<specDesc key="schemaSpec"/>
<specDesc key="moduleSpec"/>
<specDesc key="moduleRef"/>
<specDesc key="specGrp"/>
<specDesc key="specGrpRef"/>
<specDesc key="attRef"/>
</specList>
A <term>module</term> is a convenient way of grouping together element
and other declarations and associating an externally-visible name with
the group. A <term>specification group</term> performs essentially the
same function, but the resulting group is not accessible outside the
scope of the ODD document in which it is defined, whereas a module can
be accessed by name from any TEI schema.  Modules, elements, and their
attributes, element classes, and patterns are all individually
documented using further elements described in section <ptr target="#TDcrystals"/> below; part of that specification includes the
name of a module to which the component belongs. An ODD processor
generating XML DTD or schema fragments from a document marked up
according to the recommendations of this chapter will generate such
fragments for each <gi>module</gi> element found. For example, the
chapter documenting the TEI module for names and dates contains a
module specification like the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> <moduleSpec xml:id="XDND" ident="namesdates">
  <altIdent type="FPI">Names and Dates</altIdent>
  <desc>Additional elements for names and dates</desc>
</moduleSpec>
</egXML>
together with specifications for all the elements, classes, and
patterns which make up that module, expressed using
<gi>elementSpec</gi>, <gi>classSpec</gi>, or <gi>patternSpec</gi>
elements as appropriate. (These elements are discussed in section <ptr
target="#TDcrystals"/> below) Each of those specifications carries a
<att>module</att> attribute, the value of which is
<code>namesdates</code>. An ODD processor encountering the
<gi>moduleSpec</gi> element above can thus generate a schema fragment
for the TEI <ident type="module">namesdates</ident> module that
includes declarations for all the elements (etc.) which reference
it. </p>
<p>In most realistic applications, it will be desirable to combine
more than one module together to form a complete <term>schema</term>.
A schema consists of references to one or more modules or
specification groups, and may also contain explicit declarations or
redeclarations of elements (see further <ptr target="#TDbuild"/>). Any
combination of modules can be used to create a schema: the distinction
between base and additional tagsets in earlier versions of the TEI
scheme has not been carried forward into P5. </p>
<p>A schema can combine references to TEI modules with references to
other (non-TEI) modules using different namespaces, for example to
include mathematical markup expressed using MathML in a TEI
document. By default, the effect of combining modules is to allow all
of the components declared by the constituent modules to coexist
(where this is syntactically possible: where it is not — for
example, because of name clashes — a schema cannot be
generated). It is also possible to over-ride declarations contained by
a module, as further discussed in section <ptr target="#TDbuild"/></p>
<p>It is often convenient to describe and operate on sets of
declarations smaller than the whole, and to document them in a
specific order: such collections are called <term>specGrps</term>
(specification groups). Individual <gi>specGrp</gi> elements are
identified using the global <att>xml:id</att> attribute, and may then be
referenced from any point in an ODD document using the
<gi>specGrpRef</gi> element. This is useful if, for example, it is
desired to describe particular groups of elements in a specific
sequence. Note however that the order in which  element declarations
appear within the schema code generated from a <gi>moduleSpec</gi>
element cannot be altered, and is not affected by the order of
declarations within a <gi>specGrp</gi>. </p>
<p>An ODD processor will generate a piece of schema code
corresponding with the declarations contained by a <gi>specGrp</gi>
element in the documentation being output, and a cross reference to
such a piece of schema code when processing a <gi>specGrpRef</gi>. For
example, if the input text reads
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>This module contains three red elements:
<specGrp xml:id="RED">
<elementSpec ident="beetroot"><!-- ... --></elementSpec>
<elementSpec ident="east"><!-- ... --></elementSpec>
<elementSpec ident="rose"><!-- ... --></elementSpec>
</specGrp>
and two blue ones:
<specGrp xml:id="BLUE">
<elementSpec ident="sky"><!-- ... --></elementSpec>
<elementSpec ident="bayou"><!-- ... --></elementSpec>
</specGrp></p>
</egXML>
then the output documentation will replace the two <gi>specGrp</gi>
elements above with a representation of the schema code declaring the
elements <gi>beetroot</gi>, <gi>east</gi>, and <gi>rose</gi> and that
declaring the elements <gi>sky</gi> and <gi>bayou</gi>
respectively. Similarly, if the input text contains elsewhere a
passage such as
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div>
<head>An overview of the imaginary module</head>
<p>The imaginary module contains declarations for coloured things:
<specGrpRef target="#RED"/>
<specGrpRef target="#BLUE"/>
</p></div></egXML>
then the <gi>specGrpref</gi> elements may be replaced by an
appropriate piece of reference text such as <q>The RED elements were
declared in section 4.2 above</q>, or even by a copy of the relevant
declarations. As stated above, the order of declarations within the
imaginary module described above will not be affected in any
way. Indeed, it is possible that the imaginary module will contain
declarations not present in any specification group, or that the
specification groups will refer to elements that come from different
modules.  Specification groups are always local to the document in
which they are defined, and cannot be referenced externally (unlike
modules). </p>

<specGrp xml:id="TDSG2" n="Modules and Specification Groups">
&moduleRef;
&moduleSpec;
&schemaSpec;
&specGrp;
&specGrpRef;
&stringVal;
</specGrp>
</div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="TDcrystals"><head>Specification Elements</head>
<p>The following elements are used to specify elements, classes, and
patterns for inclusion in a given module:
<specList>
<specDesc key="elementSpec"/>
<specDesc key="classSpec"/>
<specDesc key="macroSpec"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>Unlike most elements in the TEI scheme, each of these elements has
a fairly rigid internal structure consisting of a large number of
child elements which are always presented in the same order. For this
reason, we refer to them informally as
<soCalled>crystals</soCalled>. Furthermore, since these elements all
describe markup objects in broadly similar ways, they have several
child elements in common. In the remainder of this section, we discuss
first the elements which are common to all the specification elements,
and then those which are specific to a particular type.  </p>
<p>Specification elements may appear at any point in an ODD document,
both between and within paragraphs as well as inside a
<gi>specGrp</gi> element, but the specification element for any
particular component may only appear once (except in the case where a
modification is being defined; see further <ptr target="#TDbuild"/>). The order in which they appear will not affect
the order in which they are presented within any schema module
generated from the document. In documentation mode, however, an ODD
processor will output the schema declarations corresponding with a
specification element at the point in the text where they are
encountered, provided that they are contained by a <gi>specGrp</gi>
element, <!--. It will usually be convenient to group such declarations
together in some kind of logical sequence using the <gi>specGrp</gi>
element --> as discussed in the previous section. An ODD processor will also
associate all declarations found with the nominated module, thus
including them within the schema code generated for that module, and
it will also generate a full reference description for the object
concerned in a catalogue of markup objects. These latter two actions
always occur irrespective of whether or not the declaration is
included in a <gi>specGrp</gi>. </p>
<specGrp xml:id="TDSG3" n="Specification elements">
&elementSpec;
&classSpec;
&macroSpec;
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TDcrystalsCE"><head>Common Elements</head>
<p>This section discusses the child elements common to all of the specification
elements. These child elements  are used to specify the naming, description,
exemplification, and classification of the specification elements.</p>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TDcrystalsCEdc"><head>Description of Components</head>
<p><specList>
<specDesc key="remarks"/>
<specDesc key="listRef"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>A <gi>desc</gi> element is used to provide a brief
characterization of the intended function of the element, class,
value etc. being documented.</p>
<p>The <gi>remarks</gi> element contains any additional
commentary about how the item concerned may be used, details of
implementation-related issues, suggestions for other ways of treating
related information etc., as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><elementSpec module="core" ident="foreign">
<!--... -->
<remarks>
    <p>This element is intended for use only where no other element
is available to mark the phrase or words concerned.  The global
<att>xml:lang</att> attribute should be used in preference to this element
where it is intended to mark the language of the whole of some text
element.</p>
    <p>The <gi>distinct</gi> element may be used to identify phrases
belonging to sublanguages or registers not generally regarded as true
languages.</p>
  </remarks>
<!--... -->
</elementSpec></egXML>
</p>
<p> A specification element will usually conclude with a list of
references, each tagged using the standard <gi>ptr</gi> element, and
grouped together into a <gi>listRef</gi> element: in the case of the
<gi>foreign</gi> element discussed above, the list is as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COHQHF"/>
  </listRef>
</egXML></p>
</div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TDeg"><head>Exemplification of Components</head>
<p><specList>
<specDesc key="exemplum"/>
  <specDesc key="eg"/> 
  <specDesc key="egXML"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>The <gi>exemplum</gi> element is used to combine a single
illustrative example with an optional paragraph of commentary
following or preceding it. The illustrative example itself may be
marked up using either the <gi>eg</gi> or the <gi>egXML</gi>
element.</p>
<p>If an example contains  XML markup, it should be marked up using
the <gi>egXML</gi> element. In such a case, it will clearly be necessary to
distinguish the markup within the example from the
markup of the document itself. In an XML schema environment, this is
easily done by  nominating a different name
space for the  <gi>egXML</gi> element. For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>The <gi>term</gi> element may be used 
to mark any technical term, thus :
<egXML>
  This <term>recursion</term> is 
  giving me a headache.</egXML></p>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>Alternatively, the XML tagging within an example may be
<soCalled>escaped</soCalled>, either by using entity
references, or by wrapping the whole example in a CDATA marked
section:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>The <gi>term</gi> element may be used 
to mark any technical term, thus :
<egXML><![CDATA[
  This <term>recursion</term> is 
  giving me a headache.]]></egXML></p>
</egXML>
or, equivalently:
<eg><![CDATA[<p>The <gi>term</gi> element may be used 
to mark any technical term, thus :
<eg><![CDATA[
  This &lt;term>recursion&lt;/term> is 
  giving me a headache.]]&gt;</eg>
]]></eg>
</p>
<p>If the XML contained in an example is not well-formed then it must
either be enclosed in a CDATA marked section, or
<soCalled>escaped</soCalled> as above: this applies whether the
<gi>eg</gi> or <gi>egXML</gi> is used. If it is well-formed but not
valid, then it should be enclosed in a CDATA marked section within an
<gi>egXML</gi>.</p>
<p>An <gi>egXML</gi> element should not be used to tag non-XML
examples: the general purpose <gi>eg</gi> or <gi>q</gi> elements
should be used for such purposes.</p>
</div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TDcrystalsCEcl"><head>Classification of Components</head>
<p>In the TEI scheme elements are assigned to one or more
<term>classes</term>, which  may themselves have subclasses. The
following elements are used to indicate class membership:
<specList>
<specDesc key="classes"/>
<specDesc key="memberOf" atts="key"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>The <gi>classes</gi> element appears within either the
<gi>elementSpec</gi> or <gi>classSpec</gi> element. It specifies the
classes of which the element or class concerned is a member by means
of one or more <gi>memberOf</gi> child elements. Each such element
references a class by means of its <att>key</att> attribute. Classes
themselves are defined by the <gi>classSpec</gi> element described in
section <ptr target="#TDCLA"/> below.</p>
<p>For example, to show that the element <gi>gi</gi> is a member of the class
<ident type="class">model.xmlPhrase</ident>, the  <gi>elementSpec</gi> which documents this
element contains the following <gi>classes</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><classes>
  <memberOf key="model.xmlPhrase"/>
</classes>
</egXML></p>

<specGrp xml:id="TDSG4" n="Common specification elements">
<!--&gloss;-->
&remarks;
&listRef;
&exemplum;
<!--eg.odd;-->
<!--&egXML;-->
&classes;
&memberOf;
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TDTAG"><head>Element Specifications</head>
<p>The <gi>elementSpec</gi> element is used to document an element type,
together with its associated attributes.  In addition to the elements
listed above, it may contain the following subcomponents:
<specList>
<specDesc key="content"/>
<specDesc key="attList" atts="org"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>The content of the element <gi>content</gi> may be
expressed in one of two ways. It may use a schema language of some
kind, as defined by a pattern called
<code>macro.schemapattern</code>, which is declared in the
<ident type="module">tagdocs-decl</ident> module, defined by this
chapter. Alternatively, the legal content for an element may be fully
specified using the <gi>valList</gi> element, described in <ptr target="#TDATT"/> below. </p>
<p>In the case of the TEI
Guidelines, element content models are defined using RELAX NG
patterns, but the user may over-ride this by redefining this
pattern.</p>
<p>Here is a very simple example
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
    <rng:text xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
</egXML>
This content model uses the RELAX NG namespace, and will be copied
unchanged to the output when RELAX NG schemas are being generated. When
an XML DTD is being generated, an equivalent declaration (in this
case <code>(#PCDATA)</code>) will be output.</p>
<p>Here is a more complex example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
    <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:ref name="fileDesc"/>
      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="model.headerPart"/>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>
      <rng:optional>
        <rng:ref name="revisionDesc"/>
      </rng:optional>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
</egXML>
This is the content model for the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element,
expressed in the RELAX NG syntax, which again is copied unchanged to
the output during schema generation. The equivalent DTD notation
generated from this is <code>(fileDesc, (%model.headerPart;)*,
revisionDesc?)</code>.
</p>
<p>The RELAX NG language does not formally distinguish element names,
class names, or macro names: all names are patterns which are handled
in the same way, as the above example shows. Within the TEI scheme,
however, different naming conventions are used to distinguish amongst
the objects being named. Unqualified names (<code>fileDesc</code>,
<code>revisionDesc</code>) are always element names. Names prefixed
with <code>model.</code> or <code>att.</code> (e.g. <code>model.headerPart</code>) are always class
names. In DTD language, element classes are represented by parameter
entities (<code>%model.headerPart;</code> in the above example) See further
<ptr target="#ST"/>.</p>
<!-- more examples needed -->
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TDATT"><head>Attribute List Specification</head>
<p>The <gi>attList</gi> element is used to document information about a
collection of attributes, either within a <gi>elementSpec</gi>, or within a
<gi>classSpec</gi>.  An attribute list can be organized either as a
group of attribute definitions, all of which are understood to be
available, or as a choice of attribute definitions, of which only one
is understood to be available. An attribute list may also contain
nested attribute lists.  </p>
<p>The <gi>attDef</gi> element is used to 
document a single attribute, using an appropriate
selection from the common elements already mentioned and the
following which are specific to attributes:
<specList>
<specDesc key="attDef" atts="usage"/>
<!--specDesc key="equiv"/-->
<specDesc key="datatype"/>
<specDesc key="defaultVal"/>
<specDesc key="valDesc"/>
<specDesc key="valList"/>
<specDesc key="valItem"/>
<!--specDesc key="desc"/>
<specDesc key="remarks"/-->
</specList>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>attList</gi> within a <gi>elementSpec</gi> is used to specify
only the attributes which are specific to that particular
element. Instances of the element may carry other attributes which are
declared by the classes of which the element is a member.  These extra
attributes, which are shared by other elements, or by all elements,
are specified by an <gi>attList</gi> contained within a
<gi>classSpec</gi> element, as described in section <ptr target="#TDCLA"/> below. </p>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TD-datatypes"><head>Datatypes</head>
<p>The <gi>datatype</gi> element is used to state what kind of value
an attribute may have, using whatever facilities are provided by the
underlying  schema language. For the TEI scheme, expressed in
RELAX NG, elements from the RELAX NG namespace may be used, for example
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><datatype>
  <rng:text xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
</datatype></egXML>
permits any string of Unicode characters not containing markup, and is
thus the equivalent of <code>CDATA</code> in DTD language. 
</p>
<p>The RELAX NG language also provides support for a number of
primitive datatypes which may be specified here, using the
<gi>rng:data</gi> element: thus one may write
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><datatype>
  <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="Boolean"/>
</datatype></egXML>
to specify that an element or attribute's contents should conform to
the W3C definition for Boolean. </p>
<p>Although only one child element may be given, this might be a
selector such as <val>rng:choice</val> to indicate multiple
possibilities:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><datatype>
<rng:choice xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
  <rng:data type="Date"/>
  <rng:data type="Float"/>
</rng:choice>
</datatype></egXML>
which would permit either a date or a real number. In fact, the child
element might be a <code>rng:list</code> element to indicate that a
sequence of values is required, a <code>rng:param</code> element to
specify a regular expression, or even a list of explicit
<code>rng:value</code>s. Such usages are permitted by the scheme
documented here, but are not recommended when it is desired to remain
independent of a particular schema language, since the full generality
of one schema language cannot readily be converted to that of
another. In the TEI abstract model, datatyping should preferably be
carried out either by explicit enumeration of permitted values (using
the TEI-specific <gi>valList</gi> element described below), or by
definition of an explicit pattern, using the TEI-specific
<gi>macroSpec</gi> element.</p>
</div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TDATTvs"><head>Value Specification</head>
<p>The <gi>valDesc</gi> element may be used to specify 
constraints on data content in an informal way: for example
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><valDesc>must point to another <gi>align</gi>
    element logically preceding this
    one.</valDesc></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><valDesc>Values should be Library of Congress subject
headings.</valDesc></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><valDesc>A bookseller's surname,
 taken from the list in <title>Pollard and Redgrave</title></valDesc></egXML>
</p>
<p>As noted above, the <gi>datatype</gi> element also constrains the
possible values for an attribute. The <gi>valDesc</gi> can be used to
specify further constraints. For example, to specify that an attribute
<att>age</att> can take positive integer values less than 100, the
datatype <ident type="datatype">data.numeric</ident> might be used in combination with
a <gi>valDesc</gi> such as <q>values must be positive integers less
than 100</q>. </p>
<p>More usually, however, where constraints on values are explicitly
enumerated, the <gi>valList</gi> element is used, as in the
following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><valList type="closed">
  <valItem ident="req"><gloss>required</gloss></valItem>
  <valItem ident="mwa"><gloss>mandatory when applicable</gloss></valItem>
  <valItem ident="rec"><gloss>recommended</gloss></valItem>
  <valItem ident="rwa"><gloss>recommended when applicable</gloss></valItem>
  <valItem ident="opt"><gloss>optional</gloss></valItem>
 </valList>
</egXML>
Since this value list specifies that it is of type <val>closed</val>,
only the values enumerated and glossed above are legal, and an ODD
processor will typically enforce these constraints in the schema
fragment generated. </p>
<p>The <gi>valList</gi> element is also used to provide illustrative examples
for the values permitted and their significance, or to gloss the
meaning of values implied by an attribute's datatype.
</p>
</div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TDATTex"><head>Examples</head>
<p>The following <gi>attList</gi> demonstrates some of the
possibilities; for more detailed examples, consult the tagged version of
the reference material in these Guidelines.
<!-- replace this example if we change the definition of gloss list!  -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><attList>
    <attDef ident="type">
      <desc>describes the form of the list.</desc>
      <datatype><rng:text xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/></datatype>
      <defaultVal>simple</defaultVal>
      <valList type="semi">
        <valItem ident="ordered">
          <gloss>list items are numbered or lettered. </gloss>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="bulleted">
          <gloss>list items are marked with a bullet or other 
                 typographic device. </gloss>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="simple">
          <gloss>list items are not numbered or bulleted.</gloss>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="gloss">
          <gloss>each list item glosses some term or
            concept, which is given by a label element preceding
           the list item.</gloss>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <remarks>
        <p>The formal syntax of the element declarations allows
        <gi>label</gi> tags to be omitted from lists tagged <tag>list
        type="gloss"</tag>; this is however a semantic error.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList> </egXML>
 </p>
<p>In the following example, the <att>org</att> attribute is used to
indicate that instances of the element concerned may bear  either a <att>bar</att>
attribute or a <att>baz</att> attribute, but not both. The
<att>bax</att> attribute is always available:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><attList>
<attDef ident="bax">
  <!-- ... -->
</attDef>
<attList org="choice">
<attDef ident="bar">
  <!-- ... -->
</attDef>
<attDef ident="baz">
  <!-- ... -->
</attDef>
</attList>  
</attList>
</egXML>
</p>
</div>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TDCLA"><head>Element Classes</head>
<p>The element <gi>classSpec</gi> is used to document an <term>element
class</term> or <soCalled>class</soCalled>, as defined in section <ptr target="#STEC"/>.  It has the
following components, additional to those already mentioned:
<specList>
<specDesc key="classSpec" atts="type"/>
<specDesc key="attList"/>
<!-- specDesc key="remarks"/>
<specDesc key="classes"/>
<specDesc key="memberOf" atts="key"/>
<specDesc key="ptr"/>
<specDesc key="equiv"/--></specList>
</p>
<p>The attribute <att>type</att> is used to distinguish between
<soCalled>model</soCalled> and <soCalled>attribute</soCalled>
classes. In the case of attribute classes, the attributes which define
membership in the class are documented by an <gi>attList</gi> element
contained within the <gi>classSpec</gi>.  Members of the class
documented by a <gi>classSpec</gi> point to it by supplying its
identifier as the value of the <att>key</att> attribute on a
<gi>memberOf</gi> element, given as a child of the <gi>classes</gi>
element in the <gi>elementSpec</gi> that defines the element
concerned. For example, the <gi>elementSpec</gi> for the element
<gi>hi</gi> contains the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><classes>
  <memberOf key="model.hiLike"/>
</classes>
</egXML>
which indicates that the <gi>hi</gi> element is a member of the class
with identifier <ident type="class">model.hiLike</ident>. The <gi>classSpec</gi>
documenting this class is as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><classSpec type="model" ident="model.hiLike">
<desc>groups phrase-level elements related to highlighting that have no specific semantics </desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.highlighted"/>
  </classes>
</classSpec>
</egXML>
which indicates that the class <ident type="class">model.hiLike</ident> is actually
a member (or subclass) of the class <ident type="class">model.highlighted</ident>.
 </p>
<p>When a model class is referenced in the content model of an element
(i.e. in the <gi>content</gi> of an <gi>elementSpec</gi>), its
meaning will depend on the value of the <att>generate</att>
attribute on the class declaration, and also on the name used to reference the class. </p>

<p>The default and usual behaviour is to replace the class
reference by an alternated list of all the current members of the
class. For example, suppose that  the members of the class
<ident type="class">model.hiLike</ident> are elements  <gi>hi</gi>,  <gi>it</gi>,
and <gi>bo</gi>. Then a content model such as
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
  <rng:optional xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
   <rng:ref name="model.hiLike"/>
</rng:optional></content></egXML>
would be equivalent to the explicit content model:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
  <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
   <rng:choice>
     <rng:ref name="hi"/>
     <rng:ref name="it"/>
     <rng:ref name="bo"/>
   </rng:choice>
</rng:zeroOrMore></content></egXML> and would generate, in DTD
language, a model such as <code>(hi|it|bo)*</code>. However, if the <att>generate</att>
attribute on the <gi>classSpec</gi>
defining <ident type="class">model.hiLike</ident> had the value <val>sequence</val>, a
content model referencing the class as
<code>model.hiLike_sequence</code> would be equivalent   to the
following explicit content model:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
  <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
     <rng:ref name="hi"/>
     <rng:ref name="it"/>
     <rng:ref name="bo"/>
</rng:zeroOrMore></content></egXML> and would generate, in DTD
language, a model such as <code>(hi,it,bo)*</code>. Similarly, a value of
<val>sequenceOptional</val> for this attribute (referenced as
model.hiLike_sequenceOptional) would be equivalent to:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
  <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
     <rng:optional><rng:ref name="hi"/></rng:optional>
     <rng:optional><rng:ref name="it"/></rng:optional>
     <rng:optional><rng:ref name="bo"/></rng:optional>
</rng:zeroOrMore></content></egXML> and would generate, in DTD
language, a model such as <code>(hi?,it?,bo?)*</code>.</p>
<p>The repeatability of members of a class may also be specified
independently, using the same mechanism. For example, a value
of <val>sequenceRepeatable</val> for the <att>generate</att> attribute would be equivalent to:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
  <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
     <rng:oneOrMore><rng:ref name="hi"/></rng:oneOrMore>
     <rng:oneOrMore><rng:ref name="it"/></rng:oneOrMore>
     <rng:oneOrMore><rng:ref name="bo"/></rng:oneOrMore>
</rng:zeroOrMore></content></egXML> and would generate, in DTD
language, a model such as <code>(hi+,it+,bo+)*</code>.   Similarly, a value
of <val>sequenceOptionalRepeatable</val> for the <att>generate</att> attribute would be equivalent to:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><content>
  <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
     <rng:zeroOrMore><rng:ref name="hi"/></rng:zeroOrMore>
     <rng:zeroOrMore><rng:ref name="it"/></rng:zeroOrMore>
     <rng:zeroOrMore><rng:ref name="bo"/></rng:zeroOrMore>
</rng:zeroOrMore></content></egXML> and would generate, in DTD
language, a model such as <code>(hi*,it*,bo*)*</code>.</p>
<p>The generate attribute may specify more than one possible value.
for example a value of <val>sequence alternates</val> would make
available both a content model such as  <code>(hi,it,bo)*</code>,
which would be referenced as <ident type="class">model.hiLike_sequence</ident>, and a content
model such as <code>(hi|it|bo)*</code>, which would be referenced as
<ident type="class">model.hiLike_alternates</ident>.</p>
<p>The sequence in which members of a class appear in a content model when one of the
sequence options is used is that in which the elements are declared. </p>

<p>When a <gi>classSpec</gi> contains an <gi>attList</gi> element, all
the members of that class inherit the attributes specified by it. For
example, the class <ident type="class">att.interpLike</ident> defines a small set of
attributes common to all elements which are members of that
class: those attributes are listed by the <gi>attList</gi> element
contained by the <gi>classSpec</gi> for
<ident type="class">att.interpLike</ident>. When processing the documentation
elements for elements which are members of that class, an ODD
processor is required to extend the <gi>attList</gi> (or equivalent)
for such elements to include any attributes defined by the
<gi>classSpec</gi> elements concerned.  There is a single global
attribute class, <ident type="class">att.global</ident>.
<!-- eh what ? -->
<!-- Membership of an attribute class can be inherited by any class, but
model-only classes may not include attribute-only classes amongst their
members.  For further discussion of the TEI class system,
see section <ptr target="STEC"/>.-->
 </p>


<specGrp xml:id="TDSG5" n="Element specification elements">
&content;
&macro.schemapattern;
&attList;
&attDef;
&attRef;
&datatype;
&defaultVal;
&valDesc;
&valItem;
&valList;
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TDENT"><head>Pattern Documentation</head>
<p>The <gi>macroSpec</gi> element is used to document patterns not
otherwise documented by the elements described in this chapter.  Its
chief uses are to provide systematic documentation of the parameter
entities used within TEI DTD fragments and to describe common
content models, but it may be used for any purpose.  It has the
following components additional to those already introduced:
 <specList>
<specDesc key="macroSpec" atts="type"/>
<specDesc key="remarks"/>
<specDesc key="stringVal"/>
<!-- specDesc key="ptr"/>
<specDesc key="equiv"/-->
</specList>
</p>
<!--<p>Note that the <gi>pattern</gi> element is taken from the RELAX NG name
space, and therefore does not need to be declared above. It should be
supplied in preference to the <gi>stringVal</gi> element if the intention
is to document an RELAX NG pattern for which no SGML equivalent exists.-->
</div>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="TDbuild"><head>Building a Schema</head>
<p>The specification elements, and several of their children, are all members of
the <ident type="class">att.identified</ident> class, from which they inherit the
following attributes:

<specList><specDesc key="att.identified"/></specList>
</p>
&att.identified;
<!-- shd this be in a specGrp? but what would it produce? -->
<p>These attributes are used by an ODD processor to determine how
declarations are to be combined to form a schema or DTD, as further
discussed in this section.</p>
<p>As noted above, a TEI schema is defined by a <gi>schemaSpec</gi>
element containing an arbitrary mixture of explicit declarations for
objects (i.e. elements, classes, patterns, or macro specifications)
and references to other objects containing such declarations
(i.e. references to specification groups, or to modules). A major
purpose of this mechanism is to simplify the process of defining user
customizations, by providing a formal method for the user to combine
new declarations with existing ones, or to modify particular parts of
existing declarations.</p>
<p>In the simplest case, a user-defined schema might simply combine
all the declarations from two nominated modules:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><schemaSpec ident="example">
<moduleRef key="teistructure"/>
<moduleRef key="linking"/>
</schemaSpec></egXML>
An ODD processor, given such a document, would combine the
declarations which belong to the named modules, and deliver the result
as a schema of the requested type. It might also generate documentation for
all and only the elements declared by those modules.</p>
<p>A schema might also include declarations for new elements, as in
the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><schemaSpec ident="example">
<moduleRef key="teiheader"/>
<moduleRef key="verse"/>
<elementSpec ident="soundClip">
<classes><memberOf key="model.pPart.data"/></classes>
</elementSpec>
</schemaSpec></egXML>
A declaration for the element <gi>soundClip</gi>, which is not defined in the TEI
scheme, will be added to the output schema. This element will also be added to
the existing TEI class <ident type="class">model.pPart.data</ident>, and will thus be
avilable in TEI conformant documents.</p>
<p>A schema might also include re-declarations of existing elements, as
in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><schemaSpec ident="example">
<moduleRef key="teiheader"/>
<moduleRef key="teistructure"/>
<elementSpec ident="head" mode="change">
<content><rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.xtext"/></content>
</elementSpec>
</schemaSpec>
</egXML>
The effect of this is to redefine the content model for the element
<gi>head</gi> as plain text, by over-riding the <gi>content</gi> child
of the selected <gi>elementSpec</gi>. The attribute specification
<code>mode="change"</code> has the effect of over-riding only those
children elements of the <gi>elementSpec</gi> which appear both in the
original specification and in the new specification supplied above:
<gi>content</gi> in this example. Note that if the value for
<att>mode</att> were <val>replace</val>, the effect would be to
replace all children elements of the original specification with the 
the children elements of the new specification, and thus (in this
example) to delete all of them except <gi>content</gi>. </p>

<p>A schema may not contain more than two declarations for any given
component. The value of the <att>mode</att> attribute is used to
determine exactly how the second declaration (and its constituents)
should be combined with the first. The following table summarizes how
a processor should resolve duplicate declarations; the term
<term>identifiable</term> refers to those elements which can have a
<att>mode</att> attribute:
<table>
<row role="label">
<cell>mode value</cell>
<cell>existing declaration</cell>
<cell>effect</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>add</cell>
<cell>no</cell>
<cell>add new declaration to schema; process its children in add mode</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>add</cell>
<cell>yes</cell>
<cell>raise error</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>replace</cell>
<cell>no</cell>
<cell>raise error</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>replace</cell>
<cell>yes</cell>
<cell>retain existing declaration; process new children in replace
mode; ignore existing children</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>change</cell>
<cell>no</cell>
<cell>raise error</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>change</cell>
<cell>yes</cell>
<cell>process identifiable children according to their modes;
process unidentifiable children in replace mode; 
retain existing children where no replacement or change
is provided </cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>delete</cell>
<cell>no</cell>
<cell>raise error</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>delete</cell>
<cell>yes</cell>
<cell>ignore existing declaration and its children</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="TDformal"><head>Formal Declaration</head>

<p>This module makes available the following components:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DTDDTD" ident="tagdocs">
<altIdent type="FPI">Documentation Elements</altIdent>
<desc>Documentation of TEI modules</desc>
</moduleSpec>

The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>
<p>The elements described in this chapter are all members of one of
three classes: <ident type="class">model.oddDecl</ident>, <ident type="class">model.oddRef</ident>, or <ident type="class">model.xmlPhrase</ident>, with the exceptions of
<gi>schemaSpec</gi> (a member of <ident type="class">model.divPart</ident>)
and both <gi>eg</gi> and <gi>egXML</gi> (members of <ident type="class">model.common</ident> and <ident type="class">model.egLike</ident>). All of these classes are
declared along with the other general TEI classes, in the basic
structure module documented in <ptr target="#ST"/>. </p>

<p>In addition, some elements are members of the
<ident type="class">att.identified</ident> class, which is documented in <ptr target="#TDbuild"/> above, and make use of the
<code>macro.schemapattern</code> pattern, which is documented in <ptr target="#TDTAG"/> above. 
</p>
<specGrp>
<specGrpRef target="#TDSG1"/>
<specGrpRef target="#TDSG2"/>
<specGrpRef target="#TDSG3"/>
<specGrpRef target="#TDSG4"/>
<specGrpRef target="#TDSG5"/>
</specGrp>

</div>
</div>
