<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_lite.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Building TEI P5 locally</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p>Publication Information</p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Information about the source</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <p>Alhough the Jenkins servers provide a complete validation service for any
                modifications to the TEI project, developers may also like to check their
                modifications locally before committing them to the server, as an optional
                additional step in the development process. A local build of TEI P5 may also be
                useful during development and experimentation.</p>
            <p>This document describes briefly how to build a software environment for such a
                purpose. It assumes that you have already installed subversion, and that you have
                plenty of disk space. </p>
            <div>
                <head>Ubuntu or other Debian-based Linux distributions</head>
                <p>The following procedure has been tested on a fresh installation of Ubuntu 14.04.
                    Some modification may be needed for other distributions. </p>
                <p>Open a terminal window and type the following shell commands : </p>
                <list rend="numbered">
                    <item>Create folders to hold the source files. I like to keep the TEI Source and
                        the TEI Stylesheets separate but this is not important. <eg>mkdir TEI-Source
                            Stylesheets</eg></item>
                    <item>Use subversion to check out a fresh copy of the TEI and Stylesheets source
                        trees and place them in the folders you just created <eg> svn co
                            https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk TEI-Source</eg>
                        <eg>svn co https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets Stylesheets</eg> You can of
                        course use git rather than svn to get a copy of the Stylesheets if you
                        prefer. Or you can elect not to maintain a local copy of the Stylesheets at
                        all, but simply install the tei-xsl package from the Oxford repository (see
                        below).</item>
                    <item> You must have some sort of functioning java before trying to install the
                        Stylesheets on your local system (you won't get far without them). We
                        recommend something like this : <eg>sudo apt-get install openjdk-7-*</eg>
                        <eg>cd Stylesheets/trunk; sudo make install</eg>
                    </item>
                    <item>You now need to install a mixed bag of XML tools since the build process
                        uses several different XML validators. Start with the following: <eg>sudo
                            apt-get install jing trang ant libxml2-utils curl </eg> The easiest way
                        to get the remainder is from the debian repository at Oxford, though you
                        could also get them individually elsewhere, To use the Oxford repo, you need
                        to add it to your <ident>sources.list</ident> and install its public key.
                        The procedure is described at <ptr target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/teideb/"
                        />
                    </item>
                    <item>The two remaining required validators (onvdl and rnv) are not available in
                        package form from the usual repositories, so installing them requires you
                        either to use the <q>unsupported and experimental</q> archive at Oxford, or
                        to do some more fiddling about. First, if you are using the Oxford repo,
                            <eg>sudo apt-get install onvdl rnv </eg> is all you need. </item>
                    <item>Alternatively, you can download and install the ONVDL JAFR files as
                        follows <eg>wget www.oxygenxml.com/InstData/Editor/onvdl/onvdl-2007517.zip;
                            unzip onvdl-2007517.zip ; sudo mv onvdl-2007517/bin /usr/share/onvdl
                        </eg>. You may then need to set up a suitable command to run the jar file.
                        For example: <eg>sudo cat 'java -Xss2048k -jar /usr/share/onvdl/onvdl.jar
                            ${1+"$@"}' > /usr/bin/onvdl </eg></item>
                    <item>On a 64 bit architecture, you will in any case need to build rnv from source because
                        the rnv package in the Oxford repo contains only the 32 bit version,
                        which does not work. <eg>sudo apt-get install libexpat1-dev; wget
                            http://ftp.davidshen.net/PreTI/RNV/RNV.ZIP; unzip ~/Downloads/RNV.ZIP;
                            cd ~/Downloads/rnv-1.7.8; make; sudo mv rnv /usr/bin</eg> This step
                        should not be necessary on a 32-bit machine. Or after the package gets
                        updated. </item>
                    <item>Now you're ready to boogie. <eg>cd TEI-Source; make clean; make</eg> will
                        delete the results of any previous attempts, and build everything from fresh
                        using whatever is in your TEI-Source directory. It will also run all the
                        testfiles, and generate a new HTML source tree for P5. For other outputs,
                        see below. </item>
                </list>
                <p>You can of course run parts of the Makefile separately. For example, run "make
                    check" to run the TEI test suite; "make validate" to validate the P5 source;
                    make exemplars to check that all the TEI explars still work; run "make ebook" or
                    "make mobi" to produce an Ebook or Mobi version of the Guidelines respectively.
                    "make pdf" will try to build the fancy PDF version of the Guidelines, but it
                    won't get far unless you have a working LiveTex environment and the requisite
                    fonts. (see <ptr target="#PDF"/> below) </p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Macintosh</head>
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Windows</head>
                <p/>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>What can possibly go wrong?</head>
                <p>(Explain the expected-results thing)</p>
            </div>
            <div>
                <head>Producing PDF on Ubuntu</head>
                <p>The commands <ident>teitopdf</ident> and <ident>teitoslides</ident> expect to
                    find LiveTex installed on your system, as does the command "make pdf". This
                    means you need to install the following packages: <eg>sudo apt-get install
                        texlive texlive-xetex texlive-latex-extra </eg></p>
                <p>You'll also probably need something to read the PDF: try <eg>sudo apt-get install
                        evince adobereader-en</eg></p>
                <p>And you will also need several fonts, especially if you aim to produce the PDF
                    version of P5. <eg>sudo apt-get install ttf-linux-libertine ttf-kochi-mincho </eg> should do it.</p>
            </div>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
