<?xml version = "1.0" encoding = "utf-8"?>

<!-- Translation to Spanish (Alex B)
	487 element names, 453 translated to Spanish, 34 remain to be translated
	202 attribute names,
	331 value names,
	690 descriptions in English, 182 translated to Spanish

General things to check after translation is done:

- verify that all accented characters in tag names have their accent
- verify that there are no repeated element names in Spanish
- contrast description translations with the opinion of experts of the respective fields of expertise

-->

<!--
Probleme: <argument> 
               <byline>
	       <catRef>
	       <classCode>
	       <classDecl>
	       <closer>
	       <creation>
	       <dateline>
	       <del> Korrektor oder andere Fassung
	       <div>
	       <divGen>
	       <editor>???
	       <gi> -> <en>?
	       <ident>
	       <lb> -> <zu>
	       <notesstmt> -> notesgroup
	       <pb> <su>
	       <principal>
	       <rs> Bezug nehmende Zeichenkette
	       <s> -> Satz
	       <samplingDecl>
	       <sic>
	       tag != Tag
	       <taxonomy>
	       <trailer>
-->
<i18n>   
	<element ident = "TEI">   
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single TEI-conformant document, comprising a TEI header and a text, either in isolation or as part of a teiCorpus element.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un único documento TEI, compuesto de una cabecera TEI (TEI header) y un cuerpo de texto (text), aislado o como parte de un elemento corpusTei (teiCorpus).</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "ab">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ba"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any arbitrary component-level unit of text, acting as an anonymous container for phrase or inter level elements analogous to, but without the semantic baggage of, a paragraph.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cualquier unidad de texto arbitraria a nivel de componente, actuando como recipiente anónimo para elementos frase o internivel, análogos a, pero sin el bagaje semántico de, un párrafo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "abbr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "abrev"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "abreviation"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "abrev"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Abkürzung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an abbreviation of any sort.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una abreviatura de cualquier clase.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "accMat">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "matAdj"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains details of any significant additional
material which may be closely associated with the manuscript being
described, such as non-contemporaneous documents or fragments bound in
with the manuscript at some earlier historical period.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene detalles sobre cualquier material adicional significativo que
pueda estar estrechamente  asociado al manuscrito que esta siendo descripto, tal como documentos
no contemporáneos o fragmentos ligados al manuscrito en algún periodo histórico anterior.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "acquisition">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "adquisicion"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any descriptive or other information
concerning the process by which a manuscript or manuscript part entered the holding
institution. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cualquier información descriptiva o de otro tipo
acerca del proceso por el cual un manuscrito o parte de un manuscrito ingresó en la institución
que lo conserva.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "activity">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "actividad"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a brief informal description of what a participant in a
language interaction is doing other than speaking, if anything.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción informal y breve de lo que un
participante en una interacción verbal está haciendo además de hablar.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "actor">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "actor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "acteur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "actor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Darsteller"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">name of an actor appearing within a cast list.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">nombre de un actor que aparece dentro de una lista de personajes.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "add">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "adicion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "addendum"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "adenda"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Ergänzung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains letters, words, or phrases inserted in the text by an
author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cartas, palabras, o frases insertadas en el texto por
un autor, escriba, anotador, o corrector.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "addName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreAdic"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an additional name component, such as a nickname, 
epithet, or alias, or any other descriptive phrase used within a
personal name.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un componente adicional del nombre, tal como un apodo,
epíteto, o seudónimo, o cualquier otra frase descriptiva usada dentro de un nombre personal.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "addSpan">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "inicioAdic"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the beginning of a longer sequence of text added by an
author, scribe, annotator or corrector (see also the element
add).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca el principio de una secuencia más larga de texto agregada
por un autor, escriba, anotador o corrector (ver también el elemento adicion - add).
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "additional">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "adicional"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups additional information relating to the
modern bibliography for a manuscript, its current curatorial status, and
other associated materials. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">agrupa información adicional relacionada
con la bibliografía moderna de un manuscrito, su estado de conservación
actual, y otros materiales asociados.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "additions">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "adiciones"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of any significant additions found
within a manuscript, such as marginalia or other annotations. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción de cualquier agregado significativo
encontrado en un manuscrito, como ser notas al margen o de otra índole. 
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "addrLine">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "líneaDirección"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ligneAdresse"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "linDireccio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "AdressZeile"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one line of a postal or other address.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una línea de una dirección postal o de otro tipo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "address">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "dirección"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "adresse"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "direccio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Adresse"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a postal or other address, for example of a
publisher, an organization, or an individual.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una dirección postal o de otro tipo, por ejemplo
de una editorial, una organización, o un individuo.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "adminInfo">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoAdmin"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information about the present
custody and availability of the manuscript, and also about the record description itself. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene información sobre la presente custodia y
disponibilidad del manuscrito, y también sobre la propia descripción del registro. 
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "affiliation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "afiliación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an informal description of a person's present
or past affiliation with some
organization, for example an employer or sponsor.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción informal de la afiliación
presente o pasada de una persona con alguna organización, por ejemplo un
empleador o patrocinador.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "alt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "alt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies an alternation or a set of choices among elements or passages.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">identifica una alternancia o un conjunto de opciones entre elementos o pasajes.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "altGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoAlt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups a collection of alt elements and possibly pointers.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">agrupa una colección de elementos alt y posiblemente punteros.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "altIdent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "identAlt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies the recommended XML name for an element, class,
  attribute, etc. in some language.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">proporciona el nombre XML recomendado para un elemento,
clase, atributo, etc. en algún idioma.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "altIdentifier">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "identificadorAlt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any form of alternative  identifier used for
a manuscript, such as a former catalogue number,  ocellus
nominum, or nickname. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cualquier forma de
identificador alternativo usada en un manuscrito, tal como un número de catálogo
anterior, ocellus nominum, o apodo.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "analytic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "analítico"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains bibliographic elements describing an item (e.g. an
article or poem) published within a monograph or journal and not as an
independent publication.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene elementos bibliográficos que describen
un ítem (por ejemplo un artículo o poema) publicado dentro de una monografía o 
publicación periódica y no como publicación independiente.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "anchor">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "anclaje"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "marge"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "marcador"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Anker"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">attaches an identifier to a
point within a text, whether or not it corresponds with a textual
element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">coloca un identificador en un punto
dentro de un texto, corresponda o no con un elemento textual.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "app">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "apa"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one entry in a critical apparatus, with an optional
lemma and at least one reading.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una entrada en un aparato
crítico, con un lema opcional y por lo menos una lectura.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "arc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "arco"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">encodes an arc, the connection from one node to another in a graph.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">codifica un arco, la conexión de un nodo a otro en un grafo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "argument">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "argumento"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a formal list or prose description of the topics addressed by
	a subdivision of a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">una lista formal o la descripción en prosa de los temas tratados en una subdivisión de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "att">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "atr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of an attribute appearing within running text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el nombre de un atributo que aparece dentro de texto corriente.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "attDef">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "defAtr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the definition of a single attribute.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la definición de un único atributo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "attList">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaAtr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains documentation for all the attributes associated with this
element, as a series of attDef elements.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la documentación de todos los atributos asociados con este elemento, como una serie de elementos defAtr (attDef).</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "author">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "autor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "auteur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "author"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Autor"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in a bibliographic reference, contains the name of the author(s),
personal or corporate,
of a work; the primary statement of responsibility for any
bibliographic item. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">en una referencia bibliográfica, contiene el nombre del autor(es), personal o corporativo,
 de un trabajo; la declaración de responsabilidad primaria para cualquier objeto bibliográfico. 
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "authority">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "autoridad"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "autorite"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "autoritat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Autorität"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies the name of a person or other agency responsible for
making an electronic file available, other than a publisher or
distributor.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">da el nombre de una persona u agencia, que no sea un editor o distribuidor, responsable de facilitar un archivo electrónico.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "availability">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "disponibilidad"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "disponibilite"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "disponibilitat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Erhältlichkeit"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies information about the availability of a text, for
example any restrictions on its use or distribution, its copyright
status, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">da información sobre la disponibilidad de un texto, por ejemplo
 cualquier restricción en su uso o distribución, el estado de sus derechos de autor, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "back">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "anexos"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "annexes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "annexos"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Nachspann"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any appendixes, etc. following the main part of a
text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cualquier apéndice, etc., después de la parte principal de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "bibl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "bibl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Bibl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a loosely-structured bibliographic citation of which    
the sub-components may or may not be explicitly tagged. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una cita bibliográfica parcialmente estructurada de la que los sub-componentes pueden o no etiquetarse explícitamente. </desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "biblFull">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "biblCompleta"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "biblComplete"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "biblCompl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "BiblKompl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a fully-structured bibliographic citation, in which all
components of the TEI file description
are present.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una cita bibliográfica totalmente estructurada en la que todos los componentes de la descripción de archivo TEI están presentes.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "biblScope">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "alcanceBibl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "AbastBibl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "BiblUmfang"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines the scope of a bibliographic reference, for example as a
list of pagenumbers, or a named subdivision of a larger work.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">define el alcance de una referencia bibliográfica, por ejemplo como
una lista de números de página, o como una subdivisión con nombre de un trabajo más grande.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "biblStruct">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "estrucBibl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a structured bibliographic citation, in which only
bibliographic subelements appear and in a specified order. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una cita bibliográfica estructurada en la que sólo aparecen subelementos bibliográficos y en un orden especificado.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "bicond">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "bicond"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a biconditional feature-structure constraint; both
consequent and antecedent are specified as feature structures or groups
of feature structures; the constraint is satisfied if both
subsume a given feature structure, or if both do not.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">define una restricción de rasgo-estructura bi-condicional; tanto el consecuente como el antecedente se especifican como estructuras de rasgo o grupos de estructuras de rasgo; la restricción se satisface si ambos subsumen una estructura de rasgos dada, o si ambos no lo hacen.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "binary">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "binario"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents the value for a feature-value specification which can take either
  of a pair of values.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa el valor de una especificación de rasgo-valor que puede tomar cualquiera de un par de valores.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "binding">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "encuadernación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of one binding, i.e. type of covering, boards, etc. applied to a manuscript</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción de una encuadernación, es decir el tipo de cubierta, etc., aplicados a un manuscrito</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "bindingDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descEncuadernación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the present and former bindings of a manuscript, either
as a series of paragraphs or as a series of distinct binding elements,
one for each binding of the manuscript. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe las encuadernaciones actual y previas de un manuscrito, ya sea como una serie de párrafos o como una serie de elementos encuadernación (binding) distintos, uno por cada encuadernación del manuscrito. </desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "birth">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nacimiento"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information about a person's birth, such as its date
and place.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene información sobre el nacimiento de una persona, como ser su fecha y lugar.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "bloc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "bloque"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a geo-political unit containing one or more nation states.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">una unidad geo-política que contiene uno o más países.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "body">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cuerpo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "corps"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "cos"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Körper"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the whole body of a single unitary text, excluding any front or back matter.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el cuerpo completo de un único texto unitario, excluyendo cualquier tipo de prólogo (front) o epílogo (back).</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "broadcast">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "emisión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a broadcast used as the source of a spoken text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe una emisión de un programa usada como fuente de un texto oral.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "byline">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "mencionResp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "donnesResp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "mencioResp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "VonZeile"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the primary statement of responsibility given for a work
on its title page or at the head or end of the work.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la declaración primaria de responsabilidad dada para un trabajo en su página de título o en la cabecera o final del trabajo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "c">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "c"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a character.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa un carácter.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "caesura">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cesura"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the point at which a metrical line may be divided.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca el punto en el cual una línea métrica puede ser dividida.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "camera">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cámara"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a particular camera angle or viewpoint in a screen play.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe un ángulo de cámara o punto de vista particular en una obra para la pantalla.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "caption">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "leyenda"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the text of a caption or other text displayed as part of a film script or screen play.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el texto de un subtítulo/leyenda u otro texto desplegado como parte de un guión cinematográfico u obra para la pantalla.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "case">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "caso"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains grammatical case information given by a dictionary for a given form.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene información del caso gramatical dada por un diccionario para una forma dada.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "castGroup">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoPers"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "grupPers"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups one or more individual castItem
elements within a cast list.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">agrupa uno o más elementos pers (castItem) individuales dentro de una lista de personajes.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "castItem">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pers"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "pers"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single entry within a cast list, describing
either a single role or a list of non-speaking roles.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una única entrada dentro de una lista de personajes, describiendo un único rol o una lista de roles mudos.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "castList">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaPers"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "listePers"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llistPers"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single cast list or dramatis personae.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una única lista del personajes o dramatis personae.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "catDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descCat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "catDesc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "descCat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "KategorieBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes some category within a taxonomy
or text typology, either in the form of a brief prose description
or in terms of the situational parameters used by the TEI
formal textDesc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe una categoría dentro de una taxonomía o tipología de texto, ya sea en forma de una descripción breve en prosa o mediante los parámetros circunstanciales usados por el elemento formal descTexto (textDesc) de TEI.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "catRef">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "refCat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "refCat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "refCat"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies one or more defined categories
within some taxonomy or text typology.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">especifica una o más categorías definidas dentro de una taxonomía o tipología de texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "catchwords">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "reclamos"/>      
		<!-- check: it is not reclamo !!! -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains discussion of the catchwords found within a manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la discusión de los reclamos encontrados dentro de un manuscrito.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "category">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "categoria"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "categorie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "categoria"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Kategorie"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an individual descriptive category, possibly nested
within a superordinate category, within a user-defined taxonomy.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una categoría descriptiva individual, posiblemente anidada dentro de una categoría superordinada, dentro de una taxonomía definida por el usuario.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "cb">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "limCol"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the boundary between one column of a text and the next in a standard reference system.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca el límite entre una columna de texto y la siguiente en un sistema de referencia estándar.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "cell">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "celda"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "cellule"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "cel.la"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one cell of a table. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una célda de una tabla. </desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "certainty">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "certeza"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the degree of certainty or uncertainty associated with
some aspect of the text markup.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">indica el grado de certeza o incertidumbre asociado con algún aspecto del marcado del texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "change">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cambio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "changement"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "canvi"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Änderung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">summarizes a particular change or correction made
to a particular version of an electronic text which is
shared between several researchers.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">resume un cambio particular o corrección hecha a una versión particular de un texto electrónico que es compartido entre varios investigadores.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "channel">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "canal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the medium or the channel by which a text is delivered or experienced. For a written text, this might be print, manuscript, e-mail, etc.; for a spoken one, radio, telephone, face-to-face, etc.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe el medio o el canal por el cual un texto es entregado, transmitido o percibido. Para un texto escrito, éste puede ser impresión, manuscrito, e-mail, etc.; para un texto oral: radio, teléfono, cara-a-cara, etc.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "char">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "carácter"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides descriptive information about a character. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">proporciona información descriptiva sobre un carácter. </desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "charDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descCar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides descriptive information about characters or glyphs.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">proporciona información descriptiva sobre carácteres o glifos.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "charName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nomCar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of a character, expressed following Unicode conventions. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el nombre de un carácter, expresado siguiendo las convenciones de Unicode. </desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "charProp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "propCar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a name and value for some property of the parent
character or glyph. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">proporciona un nombre y valor para alguna propiedad del carácter o glifo padre.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "cit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "citaCompl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "citCompl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "citaCompl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ZitatKompl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a quotation from some other document, together with a bibliographic
reference to its source.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">una cita de algún otro documento, junto con una referencia bibliográfica a su fuente.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "cl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a grammatical clause.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa una cláusula gramatical.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "classCode">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "codClasif"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "codeClassification"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "CodClassif"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the classification code used for this text in some
standard classification system.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el código de clasificación usado para este texto en algún sistema de clasificación estándar.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "classDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declClase"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "declClasses"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DeclClasse"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one or more taxonomies defining any classificatory
codes used elsewhere in the text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una o más taxonomías que definen cualquier código clasificatorio usado en otra parte del texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "classSpec">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "especifClase"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains reference information for a TEI element class; 
that is a group of 
  elements which appear together in  content models, or 
  which share some common attribute, or both.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene información de referencia sobre una clase de elementos TEI; éstas son grupos de elementos que aparecen juntos
 en los modelos de contenidos, o qué comparten algún atributo común, o ambas cosas a la vez.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "classes">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "clases"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies all the classes of which the documented element or
class is a member or subclass.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">especifica todas las clases de las cuales el elemento o clase documentado es un miembro o subclase.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "closer">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cierre"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "finTexte"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "cierre"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Abschluss"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups together dateline, byline, salutation, and similar
phrases appearing as a final group at the end of a
division, especially of a letter.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">agrupa la fecha (dateline), pie de autor (byline), saludo (salutation),
 y frases similares que aparecen como grupo final al final de una división, sobre todo en una carta.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "code">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "codigo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "code"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "codig"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Code"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains literal code.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene código literal.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "col">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "col"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one column of a multi-column reference edition.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una columna de una edición de referencia multi-columna.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "coll">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "col"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains (or points to) several feature structures which together provide
  a value for their parent feature element, organized as indicated by the
  value of the org attribute.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene (o apunta a) algunas estructuras de rasgo que juntas dan un valor a su elemento de rasgo padre, organizadas según indica el valor del atributo org.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "collation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "compaginación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of how the leaves or bifolia are physically arranged.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción de cómo se colocan las hojas o bifolios físicamente.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "collection">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "colección"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of a collection of manuscripts, not necessarily located within a single repository.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el nombre de una colección de manuscritos, no necesariamente ubicada dentro de un solo repositorio.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "colloc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "coloc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a collocate of the headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una colocación del vocablo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "colophon">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "colofón"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the text of any colophon
attached to a particular manuscript item: that is, an inscription,
usually found at a break point such as the end of a text or codex,
usually containing information about the production of the manuscript,
such as the name of the scribe, the date and place of the copying, the
person who commissioned the copying, etc. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el texto de cualquier colofón vinculado a un elemento particular del manuscrito: es decir, una inscripción,
normalmente encontrada en un punto de corte como por ejemplo el final de un texto o códice; normalmente contiene información sobre la
producción del manuscrito, tal como el nombre del escriba, la fecha y lugar de la copia, la persona que comisionó la copia, etc. 
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "cond">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cond"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a conditional feature-structure constraint; the consequent
and the antecedent are specified as feature structures or
feature-structure groups; the constraint is satisfied if both the
antecedent and the consequent subsume a given feature
structure, or if the antecedent does not.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">define una restricción de estructura de rasgos condicional; el consecuente y el antecedente se especifican
 como estructuras de rasgo o grupos de estructuras de rasgo; la restricción se satisface si el antecedente y el consecuente subsumen
 una estructura de rasgos dada, o si el antecedente no lo hace.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "condition">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "condición"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of the physical condition of the manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción de la condición física del manuscrito. </desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "constitution">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "constitución"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the internal composition of a text or text sample,
for example
as fragmentary, complete, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe la composición interior de un texto o de una muestra del texto, por ejemplo como fragmentario, completo, etc.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "content">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "contenido"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the text of a declaration for the schema documented.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el texto de una declaración para el esquema documentado.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "corr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "corr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Korr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the correct form of a passage apparently erroneous in the copy text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la forma correcta de un pasaje aparentemente erróneo en el texto de la copia.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "correction">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "corrección"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">states how and under what circumstances corrections have been made in the text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">establece cómo y bajo qué circunstancias se han hecho las correcciones en el texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "country">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "país"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in an address, gives the name of the nation, country, colony, or
commonwealth; in a place name given as a hierarchy of geo-political
units, the country is larger or administratively superior
to the region and smaller than the bloc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">en una dirección, da el nombre de la nación, país, colonia, o comunidad de naciones;
 en un nombre de lugar dado como una jerarquía de unidades geo-políticas, el país es más grande o
 administrativamente superior a la región y más pequeño que el bloque.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "creation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "creacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "creation"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "creacio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information about the creation of a text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene información sobre la creación de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "custEvent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "eventoCust"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a single event during the custodial history of a manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe un solo evento durante la historia de la custodia de un manuscrito.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "custodialHist">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "histCust"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of a manuscript's custodial history, either
as running prose or as a series of dated custodial events. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción de la historia de la custodia de un manuscrito,
 ya sea como prosa corriente o como una serie de eventos custodiales fechados. 
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "damage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "daño"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an area of damage to the text witness.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un área de daño al testigo de texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "datatype">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tipoDeDato"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the declared value for an attribute, by referring to any datatype defined by the chosen schema language.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">especifica el valor declarado para un atributo, refiriéndose a cualquier tipo de datos definido por el tipo de esquema escogido.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "date">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fecha"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "date"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "data"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Datum"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a date in any format.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una fecha en cualquier formato.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "dateRange">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "rangoFecha"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains two dates or another phrase delimiting a time period.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene dos fechas u otra frase delimitando un periodo de tiempo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "dateStruct">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "estrucFecha"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an internally structured representation of a date.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una representación internamente estructurada de una fecha.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "dateline">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "data"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ligneDate"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "data"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a brief description of the place, date, time, etc. of
	production of a letter, newspaper story, or other work, prefixed or
	suffixed to it as a kind of heading or trailer. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción breve del lugar, fecha, tiempo, etc. de producción de una carta,
 noticia periodística, u otro trabajo, prefijado o sufijado a él a modo de encabezado o pie.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "day">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "día"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the day component of a structured date.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">el componente día de una fecha estructurada.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "decoDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descDeco"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of the decoration of a manuscript, either as a sequence of paragraphs, or as a sequence of topically organised decoNote elements.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción de la decoración de un manuscrito, ya sea como una sucesión de párrafos, o como una sucesión de elementos notaDeco (decoNote) organizados por tema.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "decoNote">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "notaDeco"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a note describing either a decorative component of a manuscript, or a fairly homogeneous class of such components.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una nota que o describe un componente decorativo de un manuscrito, o una clase bastante homogénea de tales componentes.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "def">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "def"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains definition text in a dictionary entry.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el texto de la definición en una entrada de diccionario.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "default">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "predefinido"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides default value for a feature.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">provee el valor predefinido o por defecto de un rasgo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "defaultVal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "valPorDefecto"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the default declared value for an attribute.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">especifica el valor por defecto declarado para un atributo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "del">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "supr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "suppr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "supr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a letter, word or passage deleted, marked as deleted,
or otherwise indicated as superfluous or spurious in the copy text by an
author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una carta, palabra o pasaje anulado, marcado como suprimido, o 
señalado como superfluo o espurio, por un autor, escriba, anotador, o corrector, en el texto de la copia.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "delSpan">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "rangoSupr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the beginning of a longer sequence of text deleted,
marked as deleted, or otherwise signaled as superfluous or spurious by an
author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca el principio de una sucesión más larga de texto suprimido,
 marcado como anulado, o  señalado como superfluo o espurio por un autor, escriba, anotador, o corrector.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "depth">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "profundidad"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a measurement measured across the spine. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una medida tomada a lo ancho del lomo. </desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "derivation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "derivación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the nature and extent of originality of this text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe la naturaleza y grado de originalidad de este texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "desc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "desc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a brief description of the purpose and application for
an element, attribute, or attribute value.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una breve descripción del propósito y aplicación de un elemento, atributo, o valor del atributo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "dictScrap">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "trozoDic"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">encloses a part of a dictionary entry in which other phrase-level dictionary elements are
        freely combined.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">abarca una parte de una entrada de diccionario en la cual se combinan libremente otros elementos de diccionario de nivel de frase.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "dicteg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ejDic"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">(in a dictionary) contains an example text containing at least one occurrence of the word
        form, used in the sense being described; examples may be quoted from (named) authors or contrived.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">(en un diccionario) contiene un texto de ejemplo con al menos una ocurrencia de la forma de la palabra,
 usada con el significado descrito; los ejemplos pueden ser cita de autores reconocidos o creados.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "dimensions">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "dimensiones"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any kind of dimensional specification. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cualquier forma de especificación dimensional.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "distance">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "distancia"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">that part of a relative temporal or spatial expression which indicates
the distance between the place or time denoted by it and the place or
time referred to within it.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">esa parte de una expresión temporal o espacial relativa que indica la
 distancia entre el lugar o tiempo denotado por ella y el lugar o tiempo referidos dentro de ella.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "distinct">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "diferenciado"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies any word or phrase which is regarded as linguistically
distinct, for example as archaic, technical, dialectal, non-preferred,
etc., or as forming part of a sublanguage. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">identifica cualquier palabra o frase que se considere lingüísticamente
diferente, como ser arcaísmos, tecnicismos, expresiones dialectales, no
preferidas, etc., o como parte de un sublenguaje.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "distributor">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "distribuidor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "distributeur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "distribuidor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Verteiler"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies the name of a person or other agency responsible for the
distribution of a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">da el nombre de una persona o agencia responsable de la distribución de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a subdivision of the front, body, or back of a text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una subdivisión de los preliminares (front), cuerpo (body), o anexos (back) de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div0">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div0"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the largest possible subdivision of the body of a text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la mayor subdivisión posible del cuerpo de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div1">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div1"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a first-level subdivision of the front, body, or back
of a text (the largest, if
div0 is not used, the second largest if it is).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una subdivisión de primer nivel de los preliminares, cuerpo, o anexos de un texto
 (la más grande si no se usa div0, la segunda más grande si sí se usa).
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div2">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div2"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a second-level subdivision of the front, body, or back of a  text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una subdivisión de segundo nivel de los preliminares, cuerpo, o anexos de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div3">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div3"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a third-level subdivision of the front, body, or back of a
 text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una subdivisión de tercer nivel de los preliminares, cuerpo, o anexos de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div4">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div4"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a fourth-level subdivision of the front, body, or back of a
 text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una subdivisión de cuarto nivel de los preliminares, cuerpo, o anexos de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div5">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div5"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a fifth-level subdivision of the front, body, or back of a
 text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una subdivisión de quinto nivel de los preliminares, cuerpo, o anexos de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div6">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div6"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a sixth-level subdivision of the front, body, or back of a
 text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una subdivisión de sexto nivel de los preliminares, cuerpo, o anexos de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "div7">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "div7"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the smallest possible subdivision of the front, body or
back of a text, larger than a paragraph.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la subdivisión más pequeña posible de los preliminares, cuerpo, o anexos de un texto, pero mayor que un párrafo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "divGen">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "genDiv"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "genDiv"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "genDiv"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the location at which a textual division generated
automatically by a text-processing application is to appear.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">indica el lugar donde debe aparecer una división de texto generada automáticamente por una aplicación de procesamiento de texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "docAuthor">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "autorDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "auteurDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "autorDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "DokAutor"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of the author of the document, as given on the
title page (often but not always contained in a byline).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "docDate">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fechaDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "dateDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "dataDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "DokDatum"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the date of a document, as given
(usually) on a title page.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene la fecha de un documento, como viene dada (normalmente) en una página del título.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "docEdition">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "edicionDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "editionDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "edicioDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "DokAusgabe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an edition statement as presented on a title page of a
document.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "docImprint">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "impresionDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "impressionDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "impresioDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "DokImpressum"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the imprint statement (place and date of publication,
publisher name), as given
(usually) at the foot of a title page.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "docTitle">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tituloDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "titreDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "TitolDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "DokTitel"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the title of a document, including all its
constituents, as given on a title page.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el título de un documento, incluyendo todos sus componentes, como viene dado en una página de título.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "domain">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "dominio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the most important social context in which the text was
realized or for which it is intended, for example private vs. public,
education, religion, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe el contexto social principal en el cual el texto fue dado a conocer
 o para cual fue pensado, por ejemplo ámbito privado o público, educación, religión, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "eLeaf">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "hojaE"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides explicitly for a leaf of an embedding tree, which may also
be encoded with the eTree element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "eTree">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "arbolE"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides an alternative to tree element for representing
ordered rooted tree structures.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "edition">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "edicion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "edition"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "edicio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Ausgabe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the particularities of one edition of a text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe las particularidades de una edición de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "editionStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoEdicion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "infoEdition"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "infoEdicio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "AusgabeInfo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups information relating to one edition of a text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">agrupa información relacionada con una edición de un texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "editor">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "editor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "editeur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "editor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Redakteur"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">secondary statement of responsibility for a
bibliographic item, for example the name of an individual, institution
or organization, (or of several such) acting as editor, compiler,
translator, etc. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "editorialDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declEditorial"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "declEditorial"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DeclEditorial"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "RedaktionsErkl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides details of editorial principles and practices applied
during the encoding of a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "education">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "educación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a brief prose description of the
educational background of a participant.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "eg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ej"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ex"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ej"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "bsp"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single example demonstrating the use of an element or
attribute. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "egXML">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ejXML"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single example demonstrating the use of an XML element or
  attribute. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "elementSpec">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "especifElem"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">documents the structure, content, and purpose of a single
element type.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "emph">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "enfasis"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "emphase"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "emfasis"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Betonung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks words or phrases which are stressed or emphasized for
linguistic or rhetorical effect.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "encodingDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descEtiquetado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descCodage"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DescEtiquetat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "KodierBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">documents the relationship between an electronic text and the
source or sources from which it was derived.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "entry">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entrada"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a reasonably well-structured dictionary entry.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una entrada de diccionario razonablemente bien estructurada.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "entryFree">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entradaLibre"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a dictionary entry which does not necessarily conform to the constraints imposed
        by the entry element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una entrada de diccionario que no cumple necesariamente las restricciones impuestas por el elemento entrada (entry).</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "epigraph">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "epigrafe"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "epigraphe"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "epigraf"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Epigraph"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a quotation, anonymous or attributed, appearing at
the start of a section or chapter, or on a title page. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "epilogue">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "epílogo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the epilogue to a drama,  typically spoken by an actor
out of character, possibly in association with a particular performance
or venue.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "equipment">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "equipo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides technical details of the equipment and media used for
an audio or video recording used as the source for a spoken text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "equiv">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "equiv"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies a component which is considered equivalent to the
  parent element, either by co-reference, or by external link.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "etym">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "etim"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">encloses the etymological information in a dictionary entry.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "event">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "evento"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">any phenomenon or occurrence, not necessarily vocalized or
communicative, for example incidental noises or other events affecting
communication.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "exemplum">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ejemplo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single example demonstrating the use of an element,
  together with optional paragraphs of commentary.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "expan">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "expansión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the expansion of an abbreviation.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "explicit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "explícito"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the text of any explicit attached 
to a particular manuscript item, that is, the closing words of a text or a section of
a text, sometimes used as a kind of title,  possibly followed by one or more rubrics or colophons.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "extent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "extension"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "extension"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "extensio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Größe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the approximate size of the electronic text as stored on
some carrier medium, specified in any convenient units.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "f">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "r"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a feature value specification, that
  is, the association of a name with a value of any of several different types.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declR"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">declares a single feature, specifying its name, organization,
range of allowed values, and optionally its default value.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fDescr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descR"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes in prose what is represented by the feature being
declared and its values.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fLib">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "biblR"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">assembles library of feature elements.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "factuality">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "realismo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the extent to which the text may be regarded as
imaginative or non-imaginative, that is, as describing a fictional
or a non-fictional world. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe hasta que punto el texto puede considerarse como imaginativo
 o no imaginativo, es decir, que describe un mundo de ficción o no.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "figDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descImagen"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descImage"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "descImatge"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Bildbeschreibung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a brief prose description of the appearance or content
of a graphic figure, for use when documenting an image without
displaying it.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "figure">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "imagen"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "image"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "imatge"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Abbildung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the location of a graphic, illustration, or figure.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fileDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descArchivo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descFichier"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DescArxiu"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "FileBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a full bibliographic description of an electronic
file.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "filiation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "filiación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information concerning the manuscript's filiation, i.e. its relationship to other surviving manuscripts of the same text, its protographs, antigraphs and apographs.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "firstLang">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "primerIdioma"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the first language of a participant.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">especifica el primer idioma de un participante.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "foliation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "foliación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the numbering system or systems used to count the leaves or pages in a codex.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe el sistema o los sistemas de numeración usados para contar las hojas o páginas en un códice.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "foreName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreDePila"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a forename, given or baptismal name.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un nombre de pila, o bautismal.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "foreign">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "extranjero"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "etranger"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "extranger"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "fremd"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies a word or phrase as belonging to some language other than that of the surrounding text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">identifica una palabra o frase como perteneciente a algún idioma que no sea el del texto circundante.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "forest">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "bosque"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides for groups of rooted trees.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">provee grupos de árboles con raíz.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "forestGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoBosques"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides for groups of forests.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">provee grupos de bosques.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "form">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "forma"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups all the information on the written and spoken forms of one headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">agrupa toda la información sobre las formas escritas y orales de un vocablo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "format">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "formato"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of the physical format of the manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción del formato físico del manuscrito.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "formula">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fórmula"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "formule"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "formula"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Formel"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a mathematical or other formula.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una fórmula matemática o de otro tipo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "front">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "preliminares"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "preliminaires"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "preliminars"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Vorspann"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any prefatory matter (headers,
title page, prefaces, dedications, etc.)
found  at the start of a document, before the main body.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cualquier materia introductoria (los títulos, la página del título, los prólogos,
 las dedicatorias, etc.) encontradas al comienzo de un documento, antes del cuerpo principal.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fs">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "er"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a feature structure, that is, a
  collection of feature-value pairs organized as a
structural unit.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa una estructura de rasgos, es decir, una colección de pares de rasgo-valor organizados como una unidad estructural.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fsConstraints">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "restriccionesEr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies constraints on the content of well formed feature
structures.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">especifica restricciones en el contenido de estructuras de rasgo bien formadas.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fsDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declEr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">declares one type of feature structure.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">declara un tipo de estructura del rasgo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fsDescr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descrEr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes in prose what is represented by the type of feature
structure declared in the enclosing fsDecl.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe en prosa lo que se representa mediante el tipo de estructura de rasgos declarada en el elemento declEr (fsDecl) de nivel superior.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fsdDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declDsr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the feature system declaration which contains
definitions for a particular type of feature structure.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">identifica la declaración de sistema de rasgo que contiene las definiciones para un tipo particular de estructura de rasgos.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "funder">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "financiacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "financement"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "financiacio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Finazierung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the name of an individual, institution, or organization
responsible for the funding of a project or text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">especifica el nombre de un individuo, institución, u organización responsable de financiar un proyecto o texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fvLib">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "biblRv"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">assembles a library of reusable feature value elements
  (including complete feature structures).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">recopila una biblioteca de elementos de valor de rasgo reusables (incluyendo estructuras de rasgo completas).</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "fw">      
		<!-- fw: forme work -->
		      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a running head (e.g. a header,
footer), catchword, or similar material
appearing on the current page.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "g">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "g"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a non-standard character or glyph.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa un carácter no estándar o glifo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "gap">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "laguna"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "blanc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "blanc"/>      
		<equiv lnag = "de" value = "Lücke"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates a point where material has been omitted in a
transcription, whether for editorial reasons described in the TEI
header, as part of sampling practice, or because the material is
illegible or inaudible.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">indica un punto en una transcripción dónde el material se ha omitido, sea por razones
 editoriales descritas en el cabezal TEI (teiHeader), sea como parte de una práctica de muestreo, o porque el
 material es ilegible o inaudible.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "gen">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "gen"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the morphological gender of a lexical item, as given in the dictionary.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">identifica el género morfológico de un elemento léxico, según aparece en el diccionario.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "genName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoGeneracional"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a name component used to indicating generational
information, such as Junior, or a number used in a monarch's
name.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un componente del nombre usado para indicar información generacional, como Junior, o un número usado en el nombre de un monarca.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "geog">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "geog"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a common noun identifying some geographical feature 
contained within a geographic name, such as valley,
mount etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un nombre común que identifica algún rasgo geográfico contenido dentro de un nombre geográfico, como ser valle, montaña etc.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "geogName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreGeog"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a name associated with  some geographical feature such as
 Windrush Valley or Mount Sinai.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">un nombre asociado con algún rasgo geográfico como Valle Windrush o Monte Sinai.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "gi">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "idGral"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "idGral"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "idGral"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name (generic identifier) of an element.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "gloss">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "glosa"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "gloss"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "glossa"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Glosse"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies a phrase or word used to provide a gloss or
definition for some other word or phrase. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "glyph">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "glifo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides descriptive information about a character glyph. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">proporciona información descriptiva sobre un glifo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "glyphName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreGlifo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of a glyph, expressed following Unicode
conventions for character names. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el nombre de un glifo, expresado según las convenciones de Unicode para nombres de carácteres.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "gram">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "gram"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">within an entry in a dictionary or a terminological data file, contains grammatical
        information relating to a term, word, or form.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "gramGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoGram"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups morpho-syntactic information about a lexical item, e.g. pos, gen, number, case, or
        itype (inflectional class).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "graph">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grafo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">encodes a graph, which is a collection of nodes, and arcs which
connect the nodes.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "group">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "groupe"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "grup"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Gruppe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the body of a composite text, grouping together a
sequence of distinct texts (or groups of such texts) which are regarded
as a unit for some purpose, for example the collected works of an
author, a sequence of prose essays, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "hand">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "calígrafo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">used in the header to define each distinct scribe or
handwriting style.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">usado en el título para definir cada escriba o estilo de caligrafía diferente.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "handDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descCalig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of all the different kinds of writing  used in a manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción de todos los tipos de caligrafía diferentes usados en un manuscrito.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "handList">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaCalig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a series of hand elements listing the
different hands of the source.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una serie de elementos calígrafo (hand) que listan los diferentes calígrafos del documento fuente.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "handNote">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "notaCalig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a particular style
or hand distinguished within a manuscript.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">describe un estilo o caligrafía particular que destaca en un manuscrito.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "handShift">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cambioCalig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the beginning of a sequence of text written in a new
hand, or of a change in the scribe, writing style, ink or character
of the document hand.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca el principio de una secuencia de texto escrito con una nueva caligrafía,
 o un cambio de escriba, estilo de escritura, tinta o carácter de la caligrafía del documento.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "head">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "encabezado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "titreSec"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "capçalera"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Kopf"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any heading, for example, the title of a section,
or the heading of a list or glossary.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "headItem">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "encabezamientoItem"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the heading for the item or gloss column in a
glossary list or similar structured list.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "headLabel">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "encabezamientoEtiqueta"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the heading for the label or term column in a
glossary list or similar structured list.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "height">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "altura"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a measurement measured along the axis parallel to the spine. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "heraldry">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "heráldica"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a heraldic formula
or phrase occurring within such components as blazons, coats of arms, etc. found
within a manuscript .
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "hi">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "resaltado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "miseEnEvidence"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "subratllat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "hh"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks a word or phrase as graphically distinct from the
surrounding text, for reasons concerning which no claim is
made. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "history">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "historia"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en"> groups elements
describing the full history of a manuscript or manuscript part.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "hom">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "hom"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups information relating to one homograph within an entry.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "hour">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "hora"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the hour component of a temporal expression</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">el componente hora de una expresión temporal</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "hyph">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "silab"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a hyphenated form of a dictionary headword, or hyphenation information in some
        other form.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una forma de vocablo de diccionario separada en sílabas mediante guiones, o información del corte en sílabas en algún otro formato.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "hyphenation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "silabeo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">summarizes the way in which hyphenation in a source text has been
treated in an encoded version of it.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">resume la forma en que la separación en sílabas mediante guiones de un texto
 fuente ha sido tratada en una versión digital del mismo.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "iNode">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "iNodo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents an intermediate (or internal) node of a tree.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "ident">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ident"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "identifieur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ident"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ident"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies or names any kind of object</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "idno">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "numId"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "numId"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "numId"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "IdNum"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies any standard or non-standard number used to identify a
bibliographic item.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "if">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "si"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a conditional default value for a feature; the condition
is specified as a feature structure, and is met if it
subsumes the feature structure in the text for which a
default value is sought.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "iff">      
		<!-- if and only if -->
		      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "sii"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">separates the condition from the consequence in a bicond
element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "ihs">      
		<!-- ihs: independent header system - to be abolished -->
		      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "sei"/>      
		<!-- sei: sistema de encabezamiento independiente -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a set of TEI Headers exchanged independently of
their associated text or group elements.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "imprimatur">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "imprimátur"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a formal statement authorizing the publication of
a work, sometimes required to appear on a title page or its verso.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una declaración formal autorizando la publicación de un trabajo,
 que a veces se exige que aparezca en una página de título o en su reverso.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "imprint">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "impresion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "impression"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "impressio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Impressum"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups information relating to the publication or distribution
of a bibliographic item.  
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "incipit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "íncipit"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the text of any incipit
attached to a particular manuscript item, that is, the opening words of
a text, frequently used as a form of identifier for it; it may be
preceded by one or more rubrics, and may be defective.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el texto de cualquier íncipit vinculado a un elemento particular del manuscrito,
 es decir,  las palabras de apertura de un texto, frecuentemente usado a modo de identificador;
 puede ser precedido por una o más rubricas, y puede ser defectivo.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "index">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "indice"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "index"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "index"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Index"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks a location to be indexed for whatever purpose.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "institution">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "institución"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of an
organization, such as a University or Library, within which a
manuscript repository is located. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "interaction">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "interacción"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the extent, cardinality and nature of any interaction
among those producing and experiencing the text, for example in the
form of response or interjection, commentary etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "interp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "interp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "interp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "interp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Interp"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides for an interpretative annotation which can be
linked to a span of text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "interpGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "interpGrp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "interpGrp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "interpGrp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "InterpGruppe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">collects together interp tags.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "interpretation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "interpretación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the scope of any analytic or interpretive information
added to the text in addition to the transcription. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "item">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "elem"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "element"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "elem"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Punkt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one
component of a list.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "itype">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tipoI"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the inflectional class associated with a lexical item.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "join">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "unión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies a possibly fragmented segment of text, by pointing
at the possibly discontiguous elements which compose it.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "joinGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoUnión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups a collection of join elements and possibly
pointers.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "keywords">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "palabrasClave"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "motsCle"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "paraulesClau"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "SchlüsselWörter"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a list of keywords or phrases identifying the topic or
nature of a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "kinesic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "expresión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">any communicative phenomenon, not necessarily vocalized, for
example a gesture, frown, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">cualquier fenómeno comunicativo, no necesariamente vocalizado, como por ejemplo un gesto, fruncir el entrecejo, etc.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "l">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "verso"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "verso"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "vers"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Vers"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single, possibly incomplete, line of verse.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "label">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "rotulo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "label"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "retol"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Beschriftung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the label associated with an item in a list; in
glossaries, marks the term being defined.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lacunaEnd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "finLaguna"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the end of a lacuna in a mostly complete textual
witness.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">indica el fin de una laguna en un testigo textual mayoritariamente completo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lacunaStart">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "inicioLaguna"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the beginning of a lacuna in the text of a mostly
complete textual witness.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">indica el inicio de una laguna en el texto de un testigo textual mayoritariamente completo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lang">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "idioma"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">name of a language mentioned in etymological or other linguistic discussion.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "langKnown">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "idiomasConocidos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an informal description of a person's competence in
different languages, dialects, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "langUsage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "usoIdiomas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "utilisationLangue"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "UsosLlengues"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "BenutzteSprachen"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the languages, sublanguages, registers, dialects etc.
represented within a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "language">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "idioma"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "langue"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llengua"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Sprache"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">characterizes a single language or sublanguage
used within a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "layout">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "disposición"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of ruling technique and layout.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lb">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "finLin"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "finLigne"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "fiLin"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "zu"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the start of a new (typographic) line in some
edition or version of a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lbl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "etiq"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in dictionaries, contains a label for a form, example, translation, or other piece of
        information, e.g. abbreviation for, contraction of, literally, approximately, synonyms:, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">en diccionarios, contiene la etiqueta de una forma, ejemplo, traducción, u otra pieza
 de información, por ejemplo, abreviatura, contracción, uso literal, uso aproximado, sinónimos, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "leaf">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "hoja"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">encodes the leaves (terminal nodes) of a tree.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">códifica las hojas (nodos terminales) de un árbol.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lem">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lema"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the lemma, or base text, of a textual variation.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene el lema, o texto base, de una variación textual.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grpVerso"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "grpVers"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "grpVers"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "VersGruppe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a group of verse lines functioning as a formal unit,
e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lg1">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lg1"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a first-level (i.e. largest) group of verse lines
functioning as a formal unit e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph,
etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un grupo de líneas de verso de primer nivel (es decir, el más alto)
 que funcionan como una unidad formal, como por ejemplo una estrofa, estribillo, párrafo de verso, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lg2">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lg2"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a second-level (i.e. second largest) group of verse lines
functioning as a formal unit e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph,
etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un grupo de líneas de verso de segundo nivel (es decir, segundo más alto)
 que funcionan como una unidad formal, como por ejemplo una estrofa, estribillo, párrafo de verso, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lg3">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lg3"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a third-level (i.e. third largest) group of verse lines
functioning as a formal unit e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph,
etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un grupo de líneas de verso de tercer nivel (es decir, tercero más alto)
 que funcionan como una unidad formal, como por ejemplo una estrofa, estribillo, párrafo de verso, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lg4">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lg4"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a fourth-level (i.e. fourth largest) group of verse lines
functioning as a formal unit e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph,
etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un grupo de líneas de verso de cuarto nivel (es decir, cuarto más alto)
 que funcionan como una unidad formal, como por ejemplo una estrofa, estribillo, párrafo de verso, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "lg5">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lg5"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a fifth-level (i.e. smallest) group of verse lines
functioning as a formal unit e.g. a stanza, refrain, verse paragraph,
etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene un grupo de líneas de verso de quinto nivel (es decir, el más bajo)
 que funcionan como una unidad formal, como por ejemplo una estrofa, estribillo, párrafo de verso, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "line">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "línea"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one line of a reference edition.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "link">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "enlace"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines an association or hypertextual link
among elements or passages, of some type
not more precisely specifiable by other elements.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "linkGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoEnlace"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a collection of associations or hypertextual links.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "list">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lista"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "liste"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llista"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Liste"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any sequence of items organized as a list.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "listBibl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaBibl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "listeBibl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llistBibl"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ListeBibl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a list of bibliographic citations of any kind. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "listRef">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaRef"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies a list of significant references to places where this
  element is discussed, in the current document or elsewhere.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "localName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreLocal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a locally defined name for some property. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "locale">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "escenario"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a brief informal description of the nature of a
place for example a room, a restaurant, a park bench etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una descripción informal breve de la naturaleza de un lugar
 por ejemplo un cuarto, un restaurante, un banco del parque, etc.
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "locus">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "locus"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a location within a manuscript or manuscript part, usually as a (possibly discontinuous) sequence of folio references. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">define un lugar dentro de un manuscrito o parte manuscrita, normalmente como una sucesión (posiblemente discontinua) de referencias a folios.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "m">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "m"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a grammatical morpheme.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa un morfema gramatical.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "macroSpec">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "especifMacro"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">documents the function and implementation of a pattern. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "mapping">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "mapeo"/>      
		<!-- this is a bad translation, it's unofficial Spanish, but very widely used - there is no good one-word translation for mapping in Spanish -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one or more
	 characters which are related to the parent character or glyph
	 in some respect, as specified by the type
	 attribute.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene uno o más carácteres relacionados de alguna forma
              con el carácter o glifo padre, según se especifica mediante el atributo tipo (type).
		</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "material">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "material"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a phrase describing the material of which any part of a manuscript or binding is composed. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una frase que describe el material de cual está compuesta cualquier parte de un manuscrito o encuadernación.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "measure">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "medida"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a word or phrase referring to some quantity of
an object or commodity, usually comprising a number, a unit, and a
commodity name.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "meeting">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "reunión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in bibliographic references,
contains a description of the meeting or conference from which
the bibliographic item derives.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "memberOf">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "miembroDe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies  class membership of the parent element or class.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "mentioned">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "mencionado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "mentionne"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "anomenat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "erwähnt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks words or phrases mentioned, not used.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "metDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declMet"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">documents the notation employed to represent a metrical pattern
	when this is specified as the value of a met,
	real, or rhyme attribute on any structural element
	of a metrical text (e.g. lg, l, or
	seg).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "metSym">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "simbMet"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">documents the intended significance of a particular character or
character sequence within a metrical notation, either explicitly or in
terms of other symbol elements in the same metDecl.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "milestone">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "mojon"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "bornes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "fita"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "MeilenStein"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the boundary between sections of a text, as indicated by
changes in a standard reference system.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "minute">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "minuto"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the minute component of a structured time-expression.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">el componente minuto de una expresión de tiempo estructurada.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "moduleRef">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "refMódulo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">references a module which is to be incorporated into a schema.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "moduleSpec">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "specifMódulo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">documents the structure, content, and purpose of a single
module, i.e. a named and externally visible group of declarations.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "monogr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "monogr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains bibliographic elements describing an item (e.g. a book
or journal) published as an independent item (i.e. as a separate
physical object).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "month">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "mes"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the month component of a structured date.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">el componente mes de una fecha estructurada.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "mood">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "modo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information about the grammatical mood of verbs (e.g. indicative, subjunctive, imperative)</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene información sobre el modo verbal (por ejemplo indicativo, subjuntivo, imperativo)</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "move">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "movimiento"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the actual entrance or exit of one or more characters on stage.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca la verdadera entrada o salida de uno o más personajes en escena.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "msContents">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "contManusc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the intellectual content of a
manuscript or manuscript part either as a series of paragraphs or as a
series of structured manuscript items. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "msDescription">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descManusc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of a single identifiable
manuscript or manuscript part
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "msIdentifier">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "idManusc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the information required to identify
a given manuscript or manuscript part uniquely within its holding institution. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "msItem">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "itemManusc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes an individual work or item within the intellectual 
content of a manuscript or manuscript part. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "msPart">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "parteManusc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information about an originally distinct manuscript or manuscript fragment now forming part of a composite manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "musicNotation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "notaciónMus"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains description of type of musical notation.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "name">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombre"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "nom"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nom"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Name"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a proper noun or noun phrase.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "nameLink">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nexoNombre"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a connecting phrase or link used within a name but not
regarded as part of it, such as  van der or of.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una frase o nexo de conexión usado dentro de un nombre pero que no se considera parte de él, como ser "van der" o "del".</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "node">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nodo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">encodes a node, a possibly labeled point in a graph.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">codifica un nodo, un punto posiblemente etiquetado en un gráfo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "normalization">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "normalización"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the extent of normalization or regularization of the
original source carried out in converting it to electronic form.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "note">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nota"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "note"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nota"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Vermerk"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a note or
annotation.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "notesStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoNotas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "infoNotes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "infoNotas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "VermerksGruppe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">collects together any notes providing information about a text
additional to that recorded in other parts of the bibliographic
description.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "num">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Nummer"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a number, written in any form.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "number">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "número"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates grammatical number associated with a form, as given in a dictionary.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "numeric">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "numérico"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a numeric value or range of values for a feature.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "oRef">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "refOrt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in a dictionary example, indicates a reference to the orthographic form(s) of the headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "oVar">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "varOrt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in a dictionary example, indicates a reference to variant orthographic form(s) of the headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "occasion">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ocasión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a temporal expression (either a date or a time)
given in terms of a named occasion such as a holiday,
a named time of day, or some notable event.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "occupation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ocupación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an informal description of a person's trade,
profession or occupation.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "offset">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "desplazamiento"/>      
		<!-- check -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">that  part of a relative temporal or spatial expression
which indicates the direction of the offset between the two place
names, dates, or times involved in the expression. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "opener">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entrada"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "debutTexte"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "entrada"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Eröffnung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups together dateline, byline, salutation, and similar
phrases appearing as a preliminary group at the start of a
division, especially of a letter.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "orgDivn">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "divOrg"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates a division, branch or department specified
in an organizational name.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "orgName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreOrg"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an organizational name. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "orgTitle">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "títuloOrg"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the proper name component of an organizational
name. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "orgType">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tipoOrg"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates a part of the organization name which contains
information about the organization's structure or function.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "orig">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "original"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Original"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the original form of a reading, for which a
regularized form is given in an attribute value.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "origDate">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fechaOrig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any form of date, used to identify the
date of origin for a manuscript or manuscript part. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "origPlace">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lugarOrig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any form of place name, used to identify the
place of origin for a manuscript or manuscript part. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "origin">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "origen"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any descriptive or other information
concerning the origin of  a manuscript or manuscript part. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "orth">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ortog"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the orthographic form of a dictionary headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "p">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "p"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "p"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks paragraphs in prose.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca párrafos en prosa.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "pRef">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "refP"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in a dictionary example, indicates a reference to the pronunciation(s) of the headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "pVar">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "varP"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in a dictionary example, indicates a reference to variant pronunciation(s) of the headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "page">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pag"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks pages in a reference edition.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">marca páginas en una edición de referencia.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "particDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descPartic"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the identifiable speakers, voices, or other participants
in a linguistic interaction. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "particLinks">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lazosPartic"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the relationships or social links existing between
participants in a linguistic interaction. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "pause">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pausa"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a pause either between or within utterances.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "pb">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "finPag"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "finPage"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "fiPag"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "su"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the boundary between one page of a text and the next
in a standard reference system.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "per">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pers"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an indication of the grammatical person (1st, 2nd, 3rd, etc.) associated with a
        given inflected form in a dictionary.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "performance">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "actuación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a section of front or back matter describing how a
dramatic piece is to be performed in general or how it was performed
on some specific occasion. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "persName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombrePers"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a proper noun or proper-noun phrase referring to
a person, possibly including any or all of the person's forenames,
surnames, honorifics, added names, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "person">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "persona"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a single participant in a language interaction. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "personGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoPers"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a group of individuals treated as a single person for
analytic purposes.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "phr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "frase"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a grammatical phrase.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa una frase gramatical.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "physDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descFis"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a full physical description of a
manuscript, either as a sequence of paragraphs, or as a series of more
specialised elements.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "placeName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreLugar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an absolute or relative place name. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "pos">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the part of speech assigned to a dictionary headword (noun, verb, adjective, etc.)</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "postBox">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "apdoCorreo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a number or other identifier for some postal delivery
point other than a street address. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "postCode">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "codPostal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a numerical or alphanumeric code used as part of a
postal address to simplify sorting or delivery of mail. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "preparedness">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "gradoPreparac"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the extent to which a text may be regarded as
prepared or spontaneous. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "principal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "principal"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "principal"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "principal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies the name of the principal researcher responsible for the
creation of an electronic text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "profileDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descPerfil"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descProfil"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DescPerfil"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ProfilBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a detailed description of non-bibliographic aspects of a
text, specifically the languages and sublanguages used, the situation in
which it was produced, the participants and their setting.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "projectDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descProyecto"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descProjet"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "descProjecte"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ProjektBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes in detail the aim or purpose for which an electronic
file was encoded, together with any other relevant information
concerning the process by which it was assembled or collected.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "prologue">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "prólogo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the prologue to a drama,  typically spoken by an actor out of
character, possibly in association with a particular performance or venue.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "pron">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pron"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the pronunciation(s) of the word.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "provenance">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "procedencia"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any descriptive or other information
concerning a single identifiable episode during the history of a manuscript
or manuscript part, after its creation but before its acquisition. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "ptr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "puntero"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Zeiger"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a pointer to another location in the current document
in terms of one or more identifiable elements.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "pubPlace">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lugarPublicacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "lieuPublication"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llocPublicacio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "VeröffentlichungsOrt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of the place where a bibliographic item was
published.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "publicationStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoPublicacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "infoPublication"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "infoPublicacio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "VeröffentlichungsInfo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups information concerning the publication or distribution
of an electronic or other text. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "publisher">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "editorial"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "publieur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "editorial"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Verlag"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides the name of the organization responsible for
the publication or distribution of a bibliographic item.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "purpose">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "propósito"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">characterizes a single purpose or communicative function of the
text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "q">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cit"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "citation"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "c"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "z"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a quotation or apparent quotation — a representation of
speech or thought marked as being quoted from someone else (whether in
fact quoted or not); in narrative, the words are usually those of a
character or speaker; in dictionaries, q may be used to mark
real or contrived examples of usage.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "quotation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "specCita"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies editorial practice adopted with respect to quotation
marks in the original. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "quote">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cita"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a phrase or passage attributed by the narrator or
author to some agency external to the text. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "rdg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lect"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single reading within a textual variation.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "rdgGrp">      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">within a textual variation,
groups two or more readings perceived to have a genetic
relationship or other affinity.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "re">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "re"/>      
		<!-- check -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a dictionary entry for a lexical item related to the headword, such as a compound
        phrase or derived form, embedded inside a larger entry.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "recordHist">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "regHist"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides information about the source and
revision status of the parent manuscript description itself. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "recording">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grabación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">details of an audio or video recording event
used as the source of a spoken text, either directly or from
a public broadcast. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "recordingStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoGrabación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a set of recordings used in transcription of a
spoken text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "ref">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ref"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Verweis"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a reference to another location in the current document,
in terms of one or more identifiable elements, possibly modified by
additional text or comment.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "refsDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declReferenc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "declRef"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DeclReferencia"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "VerweisErkl"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies how canonical references are constructed for this text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "reg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "norm"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "norm"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a reading which has been regularized or normalized
in some sense.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "region">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "región"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in an address, contains the state, province, county or region
name; in a place name given as a hierarchy of geo-political
units, the region is larger or administratively
superior to the settlement and
smaller or administratively less important than the
country.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "relation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "relación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes any kind of relationship or linkage amongst a specified
group of participants.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "remarks">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "comentarios"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any commentary or discussion about the usage of an
element, attribute, class, or entity not otherwise documented within the
containing element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "rendition">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "formato"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "format"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "format"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Formatierung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies information about the intended rendition of one or more
elements.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "repository">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "repositorio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of a repository (usually
a distinct physical building) within which manuscripts are stored, forming part
of an institution. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "residence">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "residencia"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a person's present or past places of residence.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "resp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "resp"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a phrase describing the nature of a person's
intellectual responsibility.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "respStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoResp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "infoResp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "infoResp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "VerantInfo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies a statement of responsibility for someone responsible for
the intellectual content of a text, edition, recording, or series, where
the specialized elements for authors, editors, etc. do
not suffice or do not apply.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "respons">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "respons"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the individual(s) responsible for some aspect of the
markup of particular element(s).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "restore">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "restauración"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates restoration of text to an earlier state by
cancellation of an editorial or authorial marking or instruction.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "revisionDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descRevision"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descRevision"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DescRevision"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ÄnderungsBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">summarizes the revision history for a file.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "role">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "papel"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "role"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "paper"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the name of a dramatic role, as given in a cast list.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "roleDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descPapel"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descRole"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a character's role in a drama.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "roleName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "rolNombre"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a name component which indicates that the referent has a
particular role or position in society, such as an official title or
rank.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "root">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "raíz"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents the root node of a tree.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">representa el nodo raíz de un árbol.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "row">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fila"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ligne"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "fila"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Reihe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one row of a table. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "rs">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cadRef"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "chaineReferente"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "cadRef"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a general purpose name or referring string.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "rubric">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "rúbrica"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the text of any rubric or heading attached to a particular manuscript item, that is, a  string of words whereby a
manuscript signals a text division (e.g. beginning, book, chapter, end)
which is in some way set off from the text itself, usually in red ink,or by use of different size or type of script, lining, or other such visual device.  
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "s">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "oracion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "phrase"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "oracio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a sentence-like division of a text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "salute">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "saludo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "salutations"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "salutacio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Gruß"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a salutation or greeting prefixed to a foreword,
dedicatory epistle, or other division of a text, or the
salutation in the closing of a letter, preface, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "samplingDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declMuestreo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "declEchantillon"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DeclExemples"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a prose description of the rationale and methods used
in sampling texts in the creation of a corpus or collection.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "schema">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "esquema"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">generates a TEI-conformant schema and documentation for it.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "scriptStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoGuión"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a citation giving details of the script used for
a spoken text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "seal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "sello"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of one seal or similar
  attachment applied to a manuscript
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "sealDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descSello"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the seals or other external items attached to a manuscript, either
as a series of paragraphs or as a series of distinct seal elements,
possibly with additional decoNotes. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "secfol">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "segfol"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">The word or words that a cataloguer, typically medieval but possibly modern as well, might take from a fixed point in all the codices he is describing (the beginning of the second leaf, the beginning of the second column, the beginning of the penultimate leaf, the end of the penultimate leaf, and so on) in order to provide a unique identifier to the particular codex.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "second">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "segundos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the second component of a structured time-expression.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">el componente segundos en una expresión de tiempo estructurada.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "seg">      
		<!-- stands for: segment -->
		      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "seg"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any arbitrary phrase-level unit of text (including
other seg elements).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene cualquier unidad de texto arbitraria a nivel de frase (incluyendo otros elementos seg).</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "segmentation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "segmentación"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the principles according to which the text has been
segmented, for example into sentences, tone-units, graphemic strata,
etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "sense">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "significado"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups together all information relating to one word sense in a dictionary entry
        (definitions, examples, translation equivalents, etc.)
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "series">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "serie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Serie"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information about the series in which a book or other
bibliographic item has appeared.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "seriesStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoSerie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "infoSeries"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "infoSerie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "SerionInfo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups information about the series, if any, to which
a publication belongs.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "set">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of the setting, time, locale, appearance,
etc., of the action of a play, typically found in the front matter of
a printed performance text (not a stage direction).
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "setting">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entorno"/>      
		<!-- escenario o entorno -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes one particular setting in which a language interaction
takes place.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "settingDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descEntorno"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the setting or settings within which a language
interaction takes place, either as a prose description or as a
series of setting elements.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "settlement">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "poblado"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of the smallest component of a
place name expressed as a hierarchy of geo-political or
administrative units as in Rochester, New York;
Glasgow, Scotland.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "shift">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cambio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the point at which some paralinguistic feature of a series of
utterances by any one speaker changes.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "sic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "citaTextual"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains text reproduced although apparently incorrect or
inaccurate.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "signatures">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "firmas"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains discussion of the leaf or quirte signatures found within a codex.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "signed">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "firmado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "signe"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "signat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "gezeichnet"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the closing salutation, etc., appended to a foreword,
dedicatory epistle, or other division of a text. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "soCalled">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "denominado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "aussiAppele"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "anomenat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "sogenannt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a word or phrase for which the author or narrator
indicates a disclaiming of responsibility, for example by the use
of scare quotes or italics.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "socecStatus">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "estatusSocEc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an informal description of a person's perceived social or
economic status.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "sound">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "sonido"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a sound effect or musical sequence specified within a
screen play or radio script.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "source">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fuente"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the original source for the information contained with a manuscript description. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "sourceDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descFuente"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descSource"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DescFont"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "QuellenBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies a description of the source text(s) from
which an electronic text was derived or generated.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "sp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "dialogo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "dialogue"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "dialeg"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Dialog"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">An individual speech in a performance text, or a passage
	  presented as such in a prose or verse text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "space">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "espacio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the location of a significant space in the copy text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "span">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">associates an interpretative annotation directly with a span of
text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "spanGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">collects together span tags.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "speaker">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "hablante"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "parleur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "parlant"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Sprecher"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">A specialized form of heading or label, giving the name of
one or more speakers in a dramatic text or fragment.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "specDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descEspec"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates that a description of the specified element should
          be included at this point within a tagList.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "specGrp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "grupoEspec"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any convenient grouping of specifications for use within
  the current module.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "specGrpRef">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "refGrupoEspec"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates that the  declarations contained by the
  specGrp referenced should be inserted at this point.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "specList">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaEspec"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks where a list of descriptions is to be inserted into the prose documentation.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "sponsor">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "patrocinador"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "sponsor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "patrocinador"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Sponsor"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the name of a sponsoring organization or
institution.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "stage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "acotacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "miseEnScene"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "acotament"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Bühne"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains any kind of stage direction within a dramatic text or
fragment.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "state">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "estado"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies one component of a canonical reference defined by
the milestone method.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "stdVals">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "valsEstándar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the format used when standardized date or number
values are supplied.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "step">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "paso"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies one component of a canonical reference defined by
the stepwise method.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "street">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "calle"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a full street address including any name or number identifying a
building as well as the name of the street or route on which it is
located.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "stress">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "acentuación"/>      
		<!-- can be acentuación or énfasis -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the stress pattern for a dictionary headword, if given separately.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "string">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cadena"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a string value for a feature.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "stringVal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "valCadena"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the intended expansion for the entity documented
by an patternSpec element, enclosed by quotation marks.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "subc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "subc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains subcategorization information (transitive/intransitive, countable/non-countable, etc.)</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "summary">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "resumen"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a brief summary of the
intellectual content of an item, provided by the cataloguer 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "superEntry">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "superEntrada"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups successive entries for a set of homographs.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "supplied">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "suministrado"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">signifies text supplied by the transcriber or editor in place
of text which cannot be read, either because of physical damage or
loss in the original or because it is illegible for any
reason.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "support">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "soporte"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a description of the physical
  components supporting the inscription.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "surname">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "apellido"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a family (inherited) name, as opposed to a given,
baptismal, or nick name.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "surrogates">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "sustitutos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains information about any digital or
photographic representations of the manuscript being described which
may exist in the holding institution or elsewhere. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "syll">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "sil"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the syllabification of the headword.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "symbol">      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a  symbolic feature value.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "table">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tabla"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "tableau"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "taula"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Tabelle"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains text displayed in tabular form, in
rows and columns.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "tag">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "etiqueta"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains text of a complete start- or end-tag, possibly
including attribute specifications, but excluding the opening and
closing markup delimiter characters.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "tagUsage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "usoEtiquetas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "utilisationEtiquettes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "UsEtiquetes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "TagBenutzung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies information about the usage of a specific element
within a text. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "tagsDecl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "declEtiquetas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "declEtiquettes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "DeclEtiquetes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "TagBeschr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides detailed information about the tagging applied to an SGML or XML document.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "taxonomy">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "taxonomia"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "taxonomie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "taxonomia"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a typology used to classify texts either implicitly, by
means of a bibliographic citation, or explicitly by a structured
taxonomy.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "tech">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tec"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes a special-purpose stage direction that is not
meant for the actors.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "teiCorpus">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "corpusTei"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the whole of a TEI encoded corpus, comprising a
single corpus header and one or more TEI elements, each containing
a single text header and a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "teiFsd2">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "teiDsr2"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a feature system declaration.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "teiHeader">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cabeceraTei"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "enteteTei"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "capçaleraTei"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "TeiKopf"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies the descriptive and declarative information making
	up an electronic title page prefixed to every TEI-conformant
	text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "term">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "termino"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "terme"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "terme"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Fachausdruck"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single-word, multi-word, or symbolic designation which
is regarded as a technical term.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "text">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "texto"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "texte"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "text"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Text"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single text of any kind, whether unitary or
composite, for example a poem or drama, a collection of essays, a novel,
a dictionary, or a corpus sample.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "textClass">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "claseTexto"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "classeTexte"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ClasseText"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "TextKlasse"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups information which describes the nature or topic of a text
in terms of a standard classification scheme, thesaurus, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "textDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descTexto"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a description of a text in terms of its
situational parameters.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">proporciona una descripción de un texto mediante sus parámetros circunstanciales.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "textLang">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "idiomasTexto"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the languages and writing systems used by a
manuscript (as opposed to its description, which is described in the langUsage element)
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "then">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entonces"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">separates the condition from the default in an if, or
the antecedent and the consequent in a cond element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "time">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "hora"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "heure"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "hora"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Zeit"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a phrase defining a time of day in any format.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "timeRange">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lapsoTemp"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains two times or another phrase indicating a time period.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "timeStruct">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "estrucTemp"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains an internally structured representation for a time of day.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "timeline">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "líneaTemp"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a set of ordered points in time which can be linked to
elements of a spoken text to create a temporal alignment of that text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "title">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "titulo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "titre"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "titol"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Titel"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the title of a work, whether article, book, journal, or
series, including any alternative titles or subtitles.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "titlePage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "portada"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "titrePage"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "portada"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "TitelSeite"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the title page of a text, appearing within the front
or back matter. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "titlePart">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "parteTitulo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "titrePartie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "partTitol"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "TeilTitel"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a subsection or division of the title of a work, as
indicated on a title page.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "titleStmt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "infoTitulo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "infoTitre"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "infoTitol"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "TitelInfo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">groups information about the title of a work and those
responsible for its intellectual content.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "tns">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tiempoGram"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the grammatical tense associated with a given inflected form in a dictionary.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "tr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a translation of the headword or an example.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "trailer">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "final"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "chute"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "final"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Ende"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a closing title or footer appearing at the end of
a division of a text. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "trans">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "trad"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains translation text and related information (within an entry in a multilingual dictionary).</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "tree">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "árbol"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">encodes a tree, which is made up of a root, internal nodes,
leaves, and arcs from root to leaves.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">codifica un árbol, compuesto de una raíz, nodos interiores, hojas, y arcos de la raíz a las hojas.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "triangle">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "triángulo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides for an underspecified eTree, that is,
an eTree with information left out.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "u">      
		<!-- stands for: utterances -->
		      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "u"/>      
		<!-- need a Spanish translation for utterance -->
		      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a stretch of speech usually preceded and followed by
silence or by a change of speaker.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "unclear">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "incierto"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "incertain"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "incert"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "unklar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a word, phrase, or passage which cannot be transcribed
with certainty because it is illegible or inaudible in the source.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "unicodeName">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreUnicode"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains the name of a registered Unicode normative or
informative property. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "usg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "uso"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains usage information in a dictionary entry.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vAlt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vAlt"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a feature value which is the disjunction of the
  values it contains.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vColl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vCol"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a feature value which is the result of collecting
  together the feature values it combines, using the organization
  specified by the ORG attribute.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vDefault">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vDefecto"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">declares the default value to be supplied when a feature structure
does not contain an instance of f for this name; if
unconditional, it is specified as one (or, depending on the value of
the org attribute of the enclosing fDecl) more
fs elements or primitive values;
if conditional, it is specified as
one or more if elements; if no default is specified, or no
condition matches, the value none is assumed.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vNot">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vNeg"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a feature value which is the negation of its content.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vRange">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vRango"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines the range of allowed values for a feature, in the form of
an fs, vAlt, or primitive value;
for the value of an f to be valid, it must be
subsumed by the specified range; if the f
contains multiple values (as sanctioned by the org attribute),
then each value must be subsumed by the vRange.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "val">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "val"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single attribute value.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "valDesc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descVal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies any semantic or syntactic constraint on the value that
an attribute may take, additional to the information carried by the
datatype element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "valItem">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "itemVal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single value and gloss  pair for an attribute.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "valList">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaVal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains one or more valItem elements defining possible
  values for an attribute.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "value">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "valor"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a single value for some property, attribute, or other
  analysis.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "var">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates that the feature value is shared with other values
  bearing the same label within the current scope.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "variantEncoding">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "codifVariantes"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">declares the method used to encode text-critical variants.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vername">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nombreVer"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">serves as the root element for a concurrent markup stream which
will be used to mark page and line numbers of a reference edition of the
text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "view">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vista"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the visual context of some part of a screen play in
terms of what the spectator sees, generally independent of any
dialogue.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vocal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vocal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">any vocalized but not necessarily lexical phenomenon, for example
voiced pauses, non-lexical backchannels, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "vol">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "vol"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">marks the individual volumes of a reference edition.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "w">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pal"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">represents a grammatical (not necessarily orthographic) word.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "watermarks">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "marcasAgua"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a detailed description of the watermarks identified in the paper of which a manuscript is composed.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "week">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "semana"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the week component of a structured date.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">el componente semana de una fecha estructurada.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "when">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cuando"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates a point in time either relative to other elements in the
same timeline tag, or absolutely.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "width">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ancho"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a measurement measured along the axis perpendicular to the spine. </desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "wit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "testig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a list of one or more sigla of witnesses attesting a
given reading, in a textual variation.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "witDetail">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "detalleTestigos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives further information about a particular witness, or
witnesses, to a particular reading.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "witEnd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "finTestigos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the end, or suspension, of the text of a fragmentary
witness.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "witList">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "listaTestigos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a list of all the witnesses referred to in
wit elements or wit attributes
within the critical apparatus.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "witStart">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "inicioTestigos"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the beginning, or resumption, of the text of a
fragmentary witness.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "witness">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "testigo"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains either a description of a single witness referred to
within the critical apparatus, or a list of witnesses which is to be
referred to by a single sigil.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "writing">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "escritura"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a passage of written text revealed to participants in the course
of a spoken text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">un pasaje de texto escrito revelado a los participantes durante el transcurso de un texto hablado.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "xptr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ptExt"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ptExt"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ptExt"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "xZeiger"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a pointer to another location in the current document
or an external document.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">define un puntero a otra ubicación en el documento actual o en un documento externo.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "xr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "rext"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a phrase, sentence, or icon referring the reader to some other location in this or another text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">contiene una frase, sentencia, o icono que deriva al lector a alguna otra ubicación en este u otro texto.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "xref">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "refExt"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "refExt"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "refExt"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "xVerweis"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">defines a reference to another location in the current document,
or an external document, using an extended pointer notation,
possibly modified by additional text or comment.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">define una referencia a otra ubicación en el documento actual, o en un documento externo, usando una notación de puntero extendido, posiblemente modificada por un texto adicional o comentario.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<element ident = "year">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "año"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the year component of a date.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">el componente año en una fecha.</desc>   
	</element>   
	<attribute ident = "abbr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the abbreviation in its unexpanded form.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "absolute">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies an absolute value for the time.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "active">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of active participants
   (or addressors) producing parts of the text. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "adj">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the identifiers of the nodes which are both adjacent to and
adjacent from the current node.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "adjFrom">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the identifiers of the nodes which are adjacent from the current
node.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "adjTo">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the identifiers of the nodes which are adjacent to the current node.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "age">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the age group to which the participant belongs.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "agent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "agente"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "agent"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "agent"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">In the case of text omitted from the transcription because of
damage or other phenomenon  resulting from an identifiable cause,
signifies the causative agent.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ana">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates one or more elements containing interpretations of the
element on which the ana attribute appears.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "anchored">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "anclado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "emarge"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ancorat"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the copy text shows the exact place of reference
for the note.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "arity">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the maximum number of children of the root and internal
nodes of the tree.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "assertedValue">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides an alternative value for the aspect of the markup in
question—an alternative generic identifier, transcription,
or attribute value, or the identifier of an anchor element (to
indicate an alternative starting or ending location).  If an
assertedValue is given, the confidence level specified by
degree applies to the alternative markup specified by
assertedValue; if none is given, it applies to the markup
in the text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "atts">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies attribute names for which descriptions should
          be obtained.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "baseForm">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the morpheme's base form.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "baseType">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the name of the feature structure type from which this
type inherits features and constraints; if this type declares a feature
with the same name as a feature of the base type, the definition within
this fsDecl overrides the inherited definition.  The
fsConstraints are inherited only if this fsDecl
does not specify any; otherwise the constraints in this fsDecl
override.  When no baseType is specified, no features
or constraints are inherited.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "calendar">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "calendario"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "calendrier"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "calendari"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Kalendar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the system or calendar to which the date belongs.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "cause">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">classifies the reading as original or non-original, according to
some typology of possible origins.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "cert">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">signifies the degree of certainty ascribed to the expansion of
the abbreviation.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "certainty">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "certeza"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "certainement"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "cert"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the degree of precision to be attributed to the date.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "character">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes other characteristics of the hand,
particularly those related to the quality of the writing.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "children">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a list of identifiers of the elements which are the children of
the root node.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "class">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the text types or classifications applicable to this
item
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "code">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies an occupation code defined within the
classification system or taxonomy defined by the scheme
attribute.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "cols">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "cols"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "colonnes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "cols"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Spalten"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the number of columns in each row of the table.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "columns">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of columns per page</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "contemporary">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies whether or not the binding is contemporary with the majority of its contents</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "copyOf">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "copia"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to an element of which the current element is a copy.
 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "corr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a correction for the apparent error in the copy text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "corresp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to elements that correspond to the current element in some
way.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "crdate">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fechaCreac"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "dateCreation"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "dataCreac"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies when the pointer was created.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "creator">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "creador"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "createur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "creador"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the creator of the TEI Header.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "date">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the date of birth in an ISO standard form (yyyy-mm-dd).</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "dateCreated">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fecha.creacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "date.creation"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "data.creacio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates when the first version of the header was created.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "dateUpdated">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "fecha.actualizacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "date.actualisation"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "data.actualitzacio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates when the current version of the header was created.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "decls">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies one or more declarable elements within the
header, which are understood to apply to the element bearing this
attribute and its content.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "default">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "error"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "defaut"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "errada"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether or not this element is selected by default when
its parent is selected.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "defective">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the explicit as given is defective, i.e. incomplete.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "degree">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the degree of confidence assigned to the aspect
of the markup named by the locus attribute.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "delim">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies a delimiting string following the reference
          component.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "depend">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">The name of a module on which this object depends.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "desc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a description of the omitted text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "dim">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the space is horizontal or vertical.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "direct">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "directo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "direct"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "directe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">may be used to indicate whether the quoted matter is regarded
as direct or indirect speech.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "discrete">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the sound overlaps the surrounding speeches
or interrupts them.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "doc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "doc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "doc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "doc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the document within which the desired
  location is to be found.
  
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "doctype">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tipoDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "typeDoc"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "tipusDoc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the document type within which this
		reference declaration is used.
	  
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "domains">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">optionally specifies the identifiers of the elements
		within which all elements indicated by the contents of this
		element lie.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "dur">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the length of this element in time, using either
         specific units or the units specified on the associated temporal
         alignment.
   
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ed">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates which edition or version the milestone applies to.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "end">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the location within a temporal alignment at which
   this element ends.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "enjamb">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates that the end of a verse line is marked by enjambement.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "entity">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entidad"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "entite"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "entitat"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">names the external entity within which the graphic image of
the figure is stored.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "eol">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether or not end-of-line hyphenation has been
	retained in a text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "evaluate">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "evaluar"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "evaluer"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "evaluar"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the intended meaning
when the target of a pointer is itself a pointer.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "evidence">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the nature of the evidence supporting the reliability or
  accuracy of the dating.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "exact">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the precision to be attached to either or both dates
specified.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "exclude">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "excloure"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to elements that are in exclusive alternation with the
current element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "expan">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "desarr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "expansion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "desen"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives an expansion of the abbreviation.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "expand">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives an expanded form of information presented more concisely in the dictionary</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "extent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "extension"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "extension"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "extensio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates approximately how much text has been omitted from the
transcription, in letters, minims, inches, or any appropriate unit,
either because of editorial policy or because a deletion, damage, or
other cause has rendered transcription impossible.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "fVal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">references any element which can be used to represent the
  value of a feature.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "feats">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">references the feature-value specifications making up this feature structure.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "feature">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">a
paralinguistic feature.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "first">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether or
not this is the first or main scribe of the document.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "follow">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides an identifier of
the element which this node
follows.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "form">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies how quotation marks are indicated within the
text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "from">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "desde"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "de"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "desDe"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "von"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the start of the destination of the pointer, as an
expression in the TEI extended-pointer notation.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "fsd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "dsr"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the external entity containing the feature system
declaration; an entity declaration in the document's DTD subset must
associate the entity name with a file on the
system.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "full">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the name component is given in full, as an
abbreviation or simply as an initial.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "function">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "funcion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "funcio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Funktion"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">characterizes the function of the segment.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "gi">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ig"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ig"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ig"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">the name (generic identifier)
of the element indicated by the tag.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "given">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates conditions assumed in the assignment of a
degree of confidence.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "gradual">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the writing is revealed all at once or
        gradually.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "hand">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "mano"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "main"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ma"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Hand"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">in the case of text omitted from the transcription because of
deliberate deletion by an identifiable hand, signifies the hand which
made the deletion.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "hands">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of distinct hands identified within the manuscript</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "height">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "alto"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "hauteur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "altura"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Höhe"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">The display height of the image</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "id">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "id"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "id"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "id"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "id"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a unique identifier for the element bearing the ID value.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ident">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ident"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ident"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ident"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ident"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of occurrences of this element within the text
which bear a distinct value for the global id attribute. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "inDegree">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the in degree of the node, the number of nodes which
are adjacent from the given node.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "included">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates which other witnesses are included in a witness group.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "index">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "indice"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "index"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "index"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Index"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates which index (of several) the index entry belongs to.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ink">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes tint or type
of ink, e.g. brown.  May also be used to indicate the writing medium, e.g. pencil,
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "inst">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ejemp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "exemp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "exem"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to instances of the analysis or interpretation represented
by the current element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "interval">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the numeric portion of a time interval</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "iterated">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether or not the phenomenon is repeated.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "key">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "clave"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "cle"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "clau"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides an alternative identifier for the object being named,
such as a database record key.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "label">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies a label for the variable.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "label2">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a second label for a node.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "lang">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "idioma"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "langue"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llengua"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Sprache"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the language of the element content, usually using a
two- or three-letter code from ISO
639.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "langKey">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies a pre-defined identifier for the chief language used in the manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "lemma">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the word's lemma (dictionary entry form).</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "length">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the fixed length of the reference component.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "level">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nivel"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nivell"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether this is the title of an article, book, journal,
series, or unpublished material.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "level1">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nivel1"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "niveau1"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nivell1"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the form under which the index entry is to be made.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "level2">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nivel2"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "niveau2"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nivell2"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the second-level form, if any.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "level3">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nivel3"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "niveau3"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nivell3"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the third-level form, if any.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "level4">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nivel4"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "niveau4"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nivell4"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the fourth-level form, if any.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "loc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the location of the variation, when the
location-referenced method of apparatus markup is used.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "location">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the apparatus appears within the running text
or
external to it.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "locus">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the precise location of the uncertainty in the
markup: applicability of the element, precise position of the
start- or end-tag, value of a specific attribute, etc.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "mainLang">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates dominant language of hand.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "marks">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether or not quotation marks have been retained as
       content within the text. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "max">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies an upper bound for the numeric value represented.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "medium">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the tint or type of ink, e.g. brown, or other
writing medium, e.g. pencil,
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "mergedin">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a reference to another element, where the original appears as a merged form.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "met">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a user-specified encoding for the conventional
metrical structure of the element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "method">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the method adopted to indicate corrections within the
         text.
   
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "mode">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">states whether the alternations gathered in this collection are exclusive or inclusive.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "module">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">Supplies the name of the module in which this object is to
      be defined.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "mutual">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the relationship holds equally amongst all the
participants.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "n">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "n"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "n"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "n"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "n"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a number (or other label) for an element, which is not
necessarily unique within the document.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "name">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a name for the feature.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "new">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the new state of the paralinguistic feature specified.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "next">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "siguiente"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "suivant"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "seguent"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "nächstes"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to the next element of a virtual aggregate of which the
current element is part.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "norm">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a normalized form of information given by the source text in a
                non-normalized form
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "notAfter">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the latest possible date for the event.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "notBefore">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the earliest possible date for the event.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "notation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "notacion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "notation"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "anotacio"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates what notation is used for the pronunciation, if more than one occurs in
                the machine-readable dictionary. 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ns">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the namespace to which this element belongs</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "occurs">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "apariciones"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "occurences"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "aparicions"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of occurrences of this element within the text.
 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "old">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the old hand.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "opt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the element is optional or not</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ord">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether or not the tree is ordered, or if it is
partially ordered.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "order">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">states the order of the graph, i.e., the number of its nodes.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "org">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "organiz"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "org"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "organit"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Organisation"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies how the content of the division is organized.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "orig">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the unregularized form of the text as found in the source
copy.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "origin">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">designates the origin of the timeline, i.e. the time at which it
begins.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "otherLangs">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">one or more codes identifying any other languages used in the manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "outDegree">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the out degree of the node, the number of nodes which
are adjacent to the given node.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "parent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides the identifier of the element which is the parent of this node.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "part">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "parte"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "partie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "part"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies whether or not the division is fragmented by
		some other structural element, for example a speech which is
		divided between two or more verse stanzas.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "passive">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of passive participants
   (or addressees) to whom a text is directed
   or in whose presence it is created or performed.
   
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "pattern">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies a regular expression defining any value that is
		legal for this notation.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "perf">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the performance or performances in which this movement
		occurred as specified.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "place">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lugar"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "lieu"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "lloc"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">if the the addition is written into the copy text, indicates
where
the additional text is written.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "predeclare">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">Says whether the class should be treated as global, and so
      needs predefining in the core.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "prev">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "anterior"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "preced"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "anterior"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "letztes"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to the previous element of a virtual aggregate of which the
current element is part.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "real">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a user-specified encoding for the actual realization
of the conventional metrical structure applicable to the element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "reason">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "razon"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "raison"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "rao"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Begründung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the reason for omission.  Sample values include
sampling, illegible, inaudible,
irrelevant, cancelled, cancelled and illegible.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ref">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to a description of the  character or glyph intended.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "refunit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">names the unit (book, chapter, canto, verse, ...) identified
by this step in a canonical reference.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "reg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a normalized or regularized form of the name used.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "rend">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "formato"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "format"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "format"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates how the element in question was rendered or presented in
the source text.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "render">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "format"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the identifier of a rendition element which
defines how this element is to be rendered.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "resp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "resp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "resp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "resp"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates who is responsible for the interpretation.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "result">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the name of an element
which this aggregation
may be understood to represent.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "rhyme">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the rhyme scheme applicable to a group of verse lines.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "role">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "papel"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "role"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "paper"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the nature of the intellectual responsibility</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "rows">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "filas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "lignes"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "files"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Zeilen"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the number of rows in the table.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "ruledLines">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of ruled lines per column</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "sameAs">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "mateixQue"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to an element that is the same as the current element.
 
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "sample">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "muestra"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "echantillon"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "mostra"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether this division is a sample of the
		original source and if so, from which part.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "scale">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">The scale factor to the apply to the image to make it the
  desired display size
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "scheme">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "esquema"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "schema"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "esquema"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the controlled vocabulary within which the set of
  keywords concerned is defined.
   
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "scope">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies how widely this  hand is used in the manuscript.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "scribe">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives a standard name or other identifier for the scribe
believed to be responsible for this hand.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "script">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to a bibliographic citation in the header giving
      a full description of the source or script of the writing.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "select">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "select"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">selects one or more alternants; if one alternant is selected, the
ambiguity or uncertainty is marked as resolved.  If more than one
alternant is selected, the degree of ambiguity or uncertainty is marked
as reduced by the number of alternants not selected.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "sex">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the sex of the participant.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "sic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the original form of the apparent error in the copy text.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "sigil">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the sigil for one witness or for one group of
witnesses to which readings are assigned in a critical apparatus.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "since">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the reference point for determining the time of the
current when element, which is obtained by adding the interval to the
time of the reference point.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "size">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">states the size of the graph, i.e., the number of its arcs.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "social">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies how the phrase is distinct diastatically</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "sort">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the sort order of the name component in relation
to others within the personal name.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "source">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the authority for any normalization carried out.
    
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "space">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies how the phrase is distinct diatopically</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "split">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">gives the list of split values for a merged form</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "start">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the location within a temporal alignment
      at which this element begins.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "status">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "estado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "statut"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "estat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Status"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates whether the header is new or has been substantially
        revised.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "style">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates recognized
writing styles.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "subtype">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "subtipo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "soustype"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "subtipus"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a sub-categorization of the element, if needed</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "synch">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to elements that are synchronous
with the current
element.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "targFunc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">describes the function of each of the values of the
		targets attribute of the enclosed link,
		join or alt tags.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "targOrder">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ordenObjetivo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "ordreObjectif"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "OrdreObjectiu"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">where more than one identifier is supplied as the value of the
target attribute, this attribute specifies whether the order
in which they are supplied is significant.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "targType">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tipoObjetivo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "typeObjectif"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "tipusObjectiu"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the kinds of elements to which this pointer may point.
  
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "target">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "objetivo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "objectif"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "objectiu"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the categories concerned
   
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "targetEnd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "finObjetivo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "finObjectif"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "fiObjectiu"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">points to the end of the span to which the note is attached, if
the note is not embedded in the text at that point.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "targets">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">supplies identifiers of associated page images</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "terminal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies whether the symbol is defined in terms of other
symbols (terminal="N") or in prose
(terminal="Y").
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "time">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies how the phrase is distinct diachronically</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "to">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "hasta"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "a"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "fins"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the endpoint of the destination of the pointer, as an
expression in the TEI extended pointer notation.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "trans">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the nature of the transition between this utterance
          and the previous one.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "trunc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies whether the value represented should be
	  truncated to give an integer value.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "type">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tipo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "type"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "tipus"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Typ"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">characterizes the element in some sense, using any convenient
 classification scheme or typology.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "unit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "unidad"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "unite"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "unitat"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Einheit"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates what kind of state is changing at this milestone.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "units">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">names the units used for the measurement.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "uri">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">references the underlying concept of which the parent is a
  representation by means of some external identifier
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "url">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">The target URL</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "usage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "uso"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "usage"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "us"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Benutzung"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the approximate percentage (by volume) of the text
which uses this language.
   
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "value">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "valor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "valeur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "valor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Wert"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the character or character sequence being documented.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "varSeq">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">provides a number indicating the position of this reading in a
sequence, when there is reason to presume a sequence to the variants
on any one lemma.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "version">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">The version of the TEI scheme</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "wScale">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates the scale used to express the value of the
		weights attribute value.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "weights">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">If mode is excl, each weight states the
		probability that the corresponding alternative occurs.  If
		mode="incl" each weight states the probability that
		the corresponding alternative occurs given that at least one
		of the other alternatives occurs.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "where">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the direction of a stage movement.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "who">     
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "quién"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "qui"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "qui"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "wer"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">identifies the speaker of a piece of direct speech.</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "width">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ancho"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ample"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Breite"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">The display width of the image</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "wit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">contains a list of one or more sigla indicating the witnesses
which begin or end at this point.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "writtenLines">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the number of written lines per colum</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "wsd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "dse"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "dse"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">specifies the entity containing the writing system
   declaration used for representing texts in this language.
   
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<attribute ident = "zone">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "zona"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "zone"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "zona"/>      
		<desc xml:lang= "en">indicates time zone or place name wherever this is necessary to
		evaluate a temporal expression.
		</desc>      
		<desc xml:lang= "es">.</desc>   
	</attribute>   
	<value ident = "C">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "DBK">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "F">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "I">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "L">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "M">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "N">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "R">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "TEI">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "Y">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "S"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "O"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "s"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "a">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "abb">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "abbr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "abbr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "abbr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "abbr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "abbr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "abbr"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "abbrev">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "abbreviated">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "abridgment">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "absent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "acronym">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "act">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "acto"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "acte"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "add">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "add"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "add"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "add"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "add"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "add"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "affix">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "all">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "todo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "tous"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "tot"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "allusion">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "alt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "am">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "am"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "am"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "am"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "animate">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "app">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "aparato"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "app"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "aparell"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "area">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "art">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "att.name">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "atts">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "audio">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "auth">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "autor"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "auteur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "autor"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "bag">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "binding">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "block">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "book">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "libro"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llibre"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "bot">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "both">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ambas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "lesDeux"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "ambdues"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "bottom">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "abajo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "bas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "avall"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "box">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "bracketed">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "branches">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "brevigraph">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "bulleted">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "business">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "negoci"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "canto">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "cap">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "cardinal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "catch">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "cf">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "change">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "change"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "change"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "change"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "canvi"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "change"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "chapter">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "capitulo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "capítol"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Kapitel"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "character">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "choice">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "closed">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "colloc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "column">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "comp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "comp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "comp"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "complete">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "completa"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "complet"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "completa"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "komplett"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "compo">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "composite">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "compuesto"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "compose"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "compost"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Zusammenstellung"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "compound">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "conjecture">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "contraction">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "corporate">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "corpus">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "count">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "currency">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "data">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "data"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "data"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "def">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "delete">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "delivery">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entrega"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "derivative">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "desc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "descriptive">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "descriptiva"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "descriptive"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "descriptiva"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "beschreibend"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "directed">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "dom">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "domestic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "double-end-point">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "dt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "ed">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "education">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "end">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "final"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "fin"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "final"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Ende"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "endloc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "entertain">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "entrance">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "entrada"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "epe">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "erasure">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "etym">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "excessEnd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "excessStart">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "excl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "exit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "salida"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "eixida"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Exit"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "express">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "external">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "f">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "fact">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "false">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "fiction">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "figlist">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "final">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "foot">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pie"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "pied"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "peu"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Fuß"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "footer">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "foreign">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "foreign"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "foreign"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "foreign"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "extranger"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "foreign"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "formulaic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "fraction">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "frag">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "frags">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "free">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "libre"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "libre"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "lliure"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "frei"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "from">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "full">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "ge">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "gen">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "geo">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "geographic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "gi">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "gloss">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "govt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "gram">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "group">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "hard">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "header">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "high">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "hint">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "hom">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "horizontal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "hyper">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "illus">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "image">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "inapplicable">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "incl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "index">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "inflected">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "inform">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "infralinear">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "init">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "initial">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "inicial"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "initial"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "inicial"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "inline">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "enlinea"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "enligne"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "enLinea"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "interlinear">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "entrelineas"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "interligne"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "entreLineas"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "internal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "issue">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "j">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "label">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "lang">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "latching">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "leaves">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "left">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "izq"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "gauche"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "esquerra"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "links"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "lemma">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "length">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "light">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "line">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "list">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "lista"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "list"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "list"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "llista"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "list"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "location">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "localitzacio"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Ort"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "location-referenced">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "loud">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "low">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "m">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "main">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "major">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "many">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "marginbot">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "marginleft">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "marginright">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "margintop">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "mass">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "medial">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "media"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "moyen"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "mitjana"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "medium">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "military">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "miniatures">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "minor">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "mixed">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "barrejat"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "model">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "modifier">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "modificat"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "most">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "mwa">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "n">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "n"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "n"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "n"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "n"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "new">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "nuevo"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "nouveau"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "nou"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "neu"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "no">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "no"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "non"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "no"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "nein"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "nohyph">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "none">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "ninguno"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "aucun"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "cap"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "nonstd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "novelistic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "novelistic"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "num">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "num"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "num"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "obj">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "one">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "uno"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "un"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "un"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "eins"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "onstage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "open">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "opposite">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "opt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "ordered">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "ordinal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "organization">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "original">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "orthographic">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "other">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "overlap">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "overleaf">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "overstrike">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pag">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "page">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pages">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "parallel">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "parallel-segmentation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "part">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "parte"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "part"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Teil"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "partial">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pause">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pe">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "perc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "percentage">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "personal">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "persuade">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "phrase">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pitch">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pl">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "plagiarism">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "plev">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "plural">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pm">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "pm"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "pm"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "pm"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "poem">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "poema"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "poema"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Gedicht"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pos">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pref">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pricked">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "prop">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "proper">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "prp">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "pt">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "por"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "por"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "por"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "por"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "por"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "public">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "range">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "real">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "rec">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "reg">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "reg"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "reg"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "reg"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "reg"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "reg"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "religious">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "rend">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "replace">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "req">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "restricted">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "restringido"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "restreint"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "restringit"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "revised">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "revision">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "rhythm">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "right">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "der"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "droite"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "dreta"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "rechts"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "role">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "papel"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "role"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "paper"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "root">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "ruled">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "rwa">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "s">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "s"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "s"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "s"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "s"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "s"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "scene">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "escena"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "escene"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "scripted">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "section">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "seccion"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "secció"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "self">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "semi">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "set">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "setting">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "posicio"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "shortEnd">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "shortStart">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "sig">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "silent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "simple">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "simple"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "simple"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "single">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "singular">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "smooth">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "social">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "sole">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "some">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "sound">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "spoken">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "stanza">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "estrofa"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "estrofa"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Strophe"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "startloc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "std">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "strong">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "style">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "sub">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "secundario"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "segondaire"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "secundario"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "subj">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "subordinate">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "subpunction">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "substantive">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "suff">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "superscription">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "supplemental">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "suppliedContent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "supralinear">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "suspension">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "sw">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "syn">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "tablist">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "tags">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "tempo">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "tension">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "text">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "text"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "text"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "text"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "text"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "text"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Text"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "theme">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "thought">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "time">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "time"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "time"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "time"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "temps"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "time"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Zeit"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "title">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "title"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "title"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "title"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "titol"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "title"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Titel"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "to">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "toc">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tablaContenidos"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "taulaContinguts"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "top">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "arriba"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "haut"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "dalt"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "tr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "tur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "tur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "tur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "tur"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "tur"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "traditional">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "transcr">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "transcr"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "transcr"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "transcribedContent">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "transducer">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "transitionNetwork">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "translation">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "Übersetzung"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "true">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "u">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "undirected">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "uni">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "uniform">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "uniforme"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "uniforme"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "uniform"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "unit">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "unknown">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "desconocido"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "inconnu"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "desconegut"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "unbekannt"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "unremarkable">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "unremarkable"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "pt" value = "unremarkable"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "unremarkable"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "noImp"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "it" value = "unremarkable"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "update">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "actualizado"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "actualise"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "actualitzat"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "variant">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "verb">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "verbTable">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "verso">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "vertical">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "video">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "voice">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "volume">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "w">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "weak">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "weight">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "world">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "written">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "ws">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "x">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "xref">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = ""/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "y">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "s"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "o"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "si"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ja"/>   
	</value>   
	<value ident = "yes">      
		<equiv xml:lang= "es" value = "si"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "fr" value = "oui"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "ca" value = "si"/>      
		<equiv xml:lang= "de" value = "ja"/>   
	</value>
</i18n>
