<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
  xmlns:s="http://www.ascc.net/xml/schematron" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  xml:lang="en" >
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>ODD chaining for Idiots</title>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p> Unpublished draft</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>authored from scratch</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc><change when="2016-10-22">Uploaded for Council review</change>
      <change when="2016-10-21">Drafted first part on train from Paris to La Souterraine;l then lost half of it by shutting lid in a hurry without saving first : doh.
        </change></revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>What is this for?</head>
        <p>This little guide is intended to explain the mechanism of <term>ODD chaining</term>. An
          ODD file specifies a particular view of the TEI, by selecting particular elements,
          attributes, etc. from the whole of the TEI. But you can also refine such a specification
          further, making your ODD derive from another one. In principle you can chain together ODDs
          in this way as much as you like. You can use this feature in several different ways: <list>
            <item>you can add additional restrictions to an existing ODD, for example by changing
              the value list of an attribute</item>
            <item> you can further reduce the subset of elements provided by an existing ODD</item>
            <item>you can add new elements or modules to an existing ODD</item>
          </list></p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>How does it work?</head>
        <p>An ODD can of course contain nothing but free standing declarations, using elements such
          as <gi>elementSpec</gi>, <gi>classSpec</gi> alone. But most TEI ODDs are made by reference
          to the huge existing collection of such declarations provided by the TEI Guidelines. An
          ODD such as <ident>TEI Lite</ident> or <ident>TEI Bare</ident> is composed of
            <emph>references</emph> to the objects it uses, expressed by means of elements such as
            <gi>moduleRef</gi>, <gi>elementRef</gi>, or <gi>classRef</gi>. These references (and
          also any additional free standing declarations) are collected together within a
            <gi>schemaSpec</gi> element which specifies the schema the ODD is intended to generate.
          This element has a useful but little known attribute <att>source</att> the purpose of
          which is to state where exactly the objects referenced by the schema specification (the
          free standing declarations) are to be found. By default, when an ODD specifies no source,
          it is assumed that they are to be collected from the most recent release of the TEI
          Guidelines. You can modify this behaviour by supplying a different of URL. For example, a
            <gi> schemaSpec</gi> with its attribute<att> source</att> set to <val>tei:2.4.0</val>
          would search for declarations in release 2.4.0 of the Guidelines. One with the value
            <val>mySuperODD.subset.xml</val> will go looking for declarations in a file of that name
          in the current source tree. And one with the value
            <val>http://example.com/superODDs/anotherSubset.xml</val> will go looking for it at the
          URL indicated. </p>
        <p>It's important to understand that the resource indicated by the <att>source</att>s
          attribute must contain complete and explicit specification elements: <gi>elementSpec</gi>
          rather than <gi>elementRef</gi>, <gi>classSpec</gi> rather than <gi>classRef</gi> and so
          on. It may of course contain other elements, but these will be ignored entirely in the
          construction of a schema. A file called <ident>p5subset.xml</ident>, provided as part of
          every TEI release, is an example of such a resource: it contains specifications for every
          single TEI element, class, macro, and datatype, but nothing else much. If the
            <att>source</att> parameter is not supplied, the most recently available version of this
          file is what will be used during the processing of an ODD.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Processing an ODD</head>
        <p>Let's look more closely at the way the TEI defines a very light weight schema called
            <ident>TEI Bare</ident>. Its schema specification element begins like this : <egXML
            xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <schemaSpec ident="tei_bare" xml:lang="en">
              <moduleRef key="core" include="p list item label head author title"/>
              <moduleRef key="tei"/>
              <moduleRef key="header"
                include="teiHeader fileDesc titleStmt publicationStmt sourceDesc"/>
              <moduleRef key="textstructure" include="TEI text body div front back"/>
              <classSpec ident="att.global" mode="change" module="tei" type="atts">
                <attList>
                  <attDef ident="xml:space" mode="delete"/>
                  <attDef ident="rend" mode="delete"/>
                  <attDef ident="xml:base" mode="delete"/>
                </attList>
              </classSpec>
              <classSpec ident="att.fragmentable" mode="delete" module="tei" type="atts"/>
            </schemaSpec>
          </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>No <att>source</att> is specified, so declarations for the elements requested here will
          be taken from the current <ident>p5subset.xml</ident>. </p>
        <p>Note that this ODD contains both references and specifications: there are references to
          modules (which may be thought of as short hand for references to elements) and
          specifications for classes (<gi>classSpec</gi>), rather than references
          (<gi>classRef</gi>). The reference to the module <ident>tei</ident> brings with it
          specifications for most TEI classes, including these two. An ODD processor will therefore
          have to resolve duplicate class specifications for the classes <ident>att.global</ident>
          and <ident>att.fragmentable</ident>. The required resolution is indicated by the value of
          the <att>mode</att> attribute: if this is <val>delete</val> then both declarations are to
          be ignored, and the class is therefore suppressed; if it is <val>change</val> then the two
          declarations are to be merged, with any part of it present in the second specification
          over-riding that in the first. In this case, the effect will be to suppress the three
          attributes mentioned. </p>
        <p>If you'd like to check that this ODD does what you expect, and you have oXygen installed
          with a recent version of the TEI Frameworks, just download the file
            <ident>tei_bare.odd</ident>, and tell oXygen to apply the predefined transformation
            <ident>TEI ODD to HTML</ident> to it. This will produce a mini-manual for the TEI Bare
          customization in HTML format, near the beginning of which you should see a list of
          elements like this: </p>
        <p><graphic url="teibare-1.png"/>
        </p>
        <p>You may like to check that the modifications to the attribute class
            <ident>att.global</ident> indicated above have indeed been performed, by looking at its
          documentation in this mini-manual.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Rolling your own subset</head>
        <p>In the preceding step, we processed <ident>tei_bare</ident> with reference to the default
          p5subset, i.e with respect to the whole of the TEI. Suppose, however, that we would like
          to use TEI bare as the starting point for another customization. We could simply edit the
          source of TEI Bare, and add our further modifications there, but that would soon become
          unmanageable if we were dealing with a larger customization as starting point. Instead, we
          will use TEI bare itself as our source. To do this, as noted above, we need to generate a
            <soCalled>compiled</soCalled> version of TEI bare containing only specification elements
          in which all the references have been resolved. This is easily done using the stylesheet
            <ident>odd2odd.xsl</ident> which is supplied as part of the TEI Stylesheet package, but
          is not currently included in the TEI oXygen framework. There is however a command line
          utility <ident>teitoodd</ident> which does the job, and it is also easy to set up your own
          oXygen transformation to do it. We leave this as an exercise for the reader.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Chaining : subsetting </head>
        <p>Suppose we now have a compiled version of TEI_bare in the file
            <ident>TEI_bare.compiled.xml</ident>. Processing the following schema specification
          should produce exactly the same results as we received from the uncompiled version. </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="Bare-prime" source="tei_bare.compiled.xml" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="header"/>
            <moduleRef key="core"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
          </schemaSpec></egXML>
        <p>This works because each of the <gi>moduleRef</gi> elements here refers to the module
          (i.e. set of elements etc.) <emph>available in the compiled ODD</emph> rather than to the
          module as defined in the whole TEI. Note also that simply supplying the compiled ODD as
          source for a schema is not enough : we must also specify which of the declarations it
          contains we want to use: <foreign>nihil ex nihilo fit</foreign>...! </p>
        <p>However, the reason we started down this path was not to find yet another way of doing
          the same thing. Let's now make a reduced version of TEI_bare in which the <gi>head</gi>
          element is missing. </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="Bare-minus" source="tei_bare.compiled.odd" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="header"/>
            <moduleRef key="core" except="head"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
          </schemaSpec></egXML>
        <p>And, just for completeness, here is another way of achieving the same effect: </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="Bare-minus" source="tei_bare.compiled.odd" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="header"/>
            <moduleRef key="core"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
            <elementSpec module="core" ident="head" mode="delete"/>
          </schemaSpec></egXML>
        <p>Note that we cannot suppress or modify anything which is not already present in the
          compiled ODD specified by the <att>source</att> attribute. This approach to ODD chaining
          works best in a situation where we first define an ODD which combines all the elements
          (etc.) that we ever plan to use, and then derive individual subset schemas from them, for
          example, one for manuscripts, one for early modern print, one for modern print etc. This
          approach has been adopted by, for example, the Deutsches Text Archive: see <ptr
            target="I dont know where"/>. </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Chaining : supersetting</head>

        <p>But ODD chaining is not restricted to subsetting. Suppose we want to take our
          pre-existing tei_bare schema and <emph>add</emph> declarations from some other module. We
          could of course laboriously copy all the declarations we want into our
          <gi>schemaSpec</gi>, but it would be much nicer not to have to do that. Suppose we want to
          add to our bare schema everything provided by the <ident>gaiji</ident> module. That
          module was not included when we defined our compiled version of TEI bare, though it is of
          course available in the full TEI. Here's one way of doing it:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="Bare-plus" source="tei_bare.compiled.odd" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="header"/>
            <moduleRef key="gaiji" source="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/odd/p5subset.xml"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
          </schemaSpec></egXML>
        <p>The <gi>moduleRef</gi> which pulls in the gaiji module uses its own <att>source</att> attribute to specify
        where to find the declarations for that module. No sense looking for them in <ident>tei_bare.compiled.odd</ident>: they're not there. Instead, we will
        collect them from the online copy of  the compiled ODD which provides the whole TEI Guidelines, as noted above., Of course we can also 
        do the usual kind of subsetting : for example </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="Bare-plus" source="tei_bare.compiled.odd" start="TEI">
              <moduleRef key="tei"/>
              <moduleRef key="header"/>
              <moduleRef key="gaiji" source="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/odd/p5subset.xml" include="g char glyph"/>
              <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
            </schemaSpec></egXML>
        <p>This ODD will give us everything in tei_bare along with just g, char, and glyph from the default gaiji module.  We could achieve the same effect by explicitly
        naming the elements we want,  and again specifying where they are to be found: </p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="Bare-plus" source="tei_bare.compiled.odd" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
          <moduleRef key="header"/>
          <elementRef key="g" source="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/odd/p5subset.xml"/>
          <elementRef key="char" source="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/odd/p5subset.xml"/>
          <elementRef key="glyph" source="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/odd/p5subset.xml"/>
          <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
          </schemaSpec></egXML>
        <p>We can  use this technique to put back an element which was deleted from the compiled schema. For example, the <gi>q</gi> element is not
          available in  tei_bare, but we can easily get it back. We can even specify which version of the <gi>q</gi> element we want: in this case, we will get the version
          defined in TEI P5 release 3.0.0 :</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="Bare-plus" source="tei_bare.compiled.odd" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="header"/>
            <elementRef key="q" source="tei:3.0.0"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
          </schemaSpec></egXML>
       <!-- still to come:
            chaining two or more customisations not involving p5 subset
            class and attribute tweaking
            what else? -->
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
