<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>How to Update your ODD</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Working paper for review by the TEI Council</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change when="2016-12-11">Correct typos; add dataFacet</change>
         <change when="2016-10-06">Circulate draft to council</change>
         <change when="2016-10-01">Started draft on way home from Vienna</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>What is this for?</head>
            <p>This little guide is intended to simplify and clarify the task of maintaining or updating an
               existing TEI customization (an ODD), in particular an ODD which was written before release 3.0
               of TEI P5. That release introduced several new features intended to remove the system's
               reliance on other schema languages. These changes are colloquially known as
                  <soCalled>purification</soCalled> because their motivation was to ensure that all aspects of
               a TEI specification should be encoded using TEI and nothing else (<note place="end">see further
                     <ref target="https://jtei.revues.org/842"><title>Resolving the Durand
                     Conundrum</title></ref></note>); they affect only the way that the content model of an
               element or the datatype of an attribute are defined, but for completeness we have included
               reminders about some other customization features that you may wish to review.</p>
            <p/>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>It ain't broke: why fix it?</head>
            <p>Since release 2.0 it has been possible to tie any ODD file to a particular release of the
               Guidelines. If you know approximately the date of the release of TEI P5 against which your ODD
               was first compiled, you can use the <att>source</att> attribute on the <gi>schemaSpec</gi>
               element it contains to ensure that the schema generated from it continues to use the TEI
               definitions contained in that particular source. This has the obvious advantage that you don't
               have to do any work to maintain it, but some equally obvious disadvantages: <list>
                  <item>You can't use any of the new features, corrections, or other improvements introduced
                     in TEI P5 <emph>after</emph> the date your ODD was created;</item>
                  <item>Your TEI usage risks becoming increasingly divergent from the mainstream, so that
                     interchange with others will become increasingly difficult.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Nothing in digital form is ever really finished. It's more than likely that the requirements of
               your project will have changed a little since your ODD was first designed. It's almost
               inevitable that as your project evolves, you'll have come across things you'd do differently if
               you could start all over again. Reviewing your ODD is a very good way of thinking about doing
               that. </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Good things to review</head>
            <p>Here's a little checklist of things you might want to review in the light of experience: <list>
                  <item>Which elements are you actually using? Beginners often think that it's better to allow
                     almost any kind of content in their schema: an extreme case of this misapprehension leads
                     people to use TEI All for everything. It may well be that your project started out a bit
                     uncertain about the kind of data it would have to be able to handle. But now you've
                     encoded umpteen gazillion pages of Whatever, you surely know a bit better the kind of
                     things that crop up. And every element you allow for in your schema is another element
                     you need to explain to your encoders, document, find examples for, and check that it is
                     being used consistently (if it is used at all). It's also another element that the poor
                     benighted software developer you finally got funding for has to be prepared to handle in
                     that swish new interface you've been promising yourself forever.</item>
                  <item>Reducing the number of elements permitted by your schema makes it easier for you to
                     concentrate on the quality of your documentation, for example by introducing examples
                     more appropriate to your project than those provided by vanilla TEI (which somehow manage
                     to be both general and very specialised).</item>
                  <item>The same considerations apply to attributes, and in particular their range of values.
                     At the outset you may not have been sure what values to permit for the <att>foo</att>
                     attribute on your <gi>bar</gi> elements, so you allowed anything. Now you have discovered
                     that some of your encoders gave this attribute the value <val>centre</val>, others used
                        <val>center</val>, and yet others used <val>middle</val>, all meaning (probably) the
                     same thing. Now that you know what values you want, add a <gi>valList</gi> to your ODD to
                     insist on them, and do some data cleanup.</item>
                  <item>Has the circus moved on? You may have spent a lot of time and effort defining new
                     elements or attributes not available in the TEI at the time, only to find that the TEI
                     (independently or as a result of your good work) has subsequently decided to implement
                     exactly what you did, or something like it. Maybe you can remove your old modifications
                     and be pure TEI again. Even if the TEI decided to do things differently from you, it
                     might be worth looking at the TEI version of your smart idea to see if it can be adapted
                     to your needs! </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>And yes, it's quite likely that as a result of this review, you may well need to change all
               your data as well as your schema. But that's a simple matter of XSLT programming ...</p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Content Model Revision</head>
            <p>In days of yore, (i.e. releases P1 to P3 inclusive) TEI Content Models were expressed in the
               SGML language. The first XML release TEI P4, and all releases of P5 prior to 3.0 used the ISO
               standard RELAX NG language for this purpose. But from the start, a design goal of the TEI was
               to define an encoding scheme independent of any implementation metalanguage. The TEI has always
               used its own <soCalled>ODD</soCalled> language to define components which are then processed to
               produce documentation in a variety of formats (HTML, PDF, ePub etc.) and schemas in a number of
               different languages (RELAX NG, W3C Schema, and XML DTD). At release 3.0 this principle was
               extended to the definition of content models, which previously had been expressed using the
               RELAX NG language, but which are now expressed using some special purpose TEI elements (<note
                  place="end">The authoritative source of information on these is of course chapter 22 of the
                  Guidelines <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html"
                        ><title>Documentation Elements</title></ref>. In any disagreement between what is
                  stated there and what is suggested here, the former is correct.</note>) </p>
            <p>If your customization changed the content model of any element, it will have done so using
               expressions in RELAX NG, typically using a <gi>rng:ref</gi> element to provide the name of a
               pattern. For example, suppose your customization defined a new element with a content model of
                  <code>macro.phraseSeq</code>. In the <gi>elementSpec</gi> defining your new element, there
               will be a <gi>content</gi> element containing something like <code>&lt;rng:ref
                  name="macro.phraseSeq"/></code>. To keep in step with the current TEI P5 release, you need
               to change this RELAX NG content to its equivalent in the ODD language which is
                  <code>&lt;macroRef key="macro.phraseSeq"/></code>. </p>
            <p>In the ODD language, references to different kinds of object (elements, classes, macros, etc.)
               in a content model are represented by different element types, specifically
               <gi>elementRef</gi>, <gi>classRef</gi>, <gi>macroRef</gi>. Hence, a RELAX NG content model in
               the form <code>&lt;rng:ref name="x"></code> will become <code>&lt;elementRef key="x"/></code>
               if <ident>x</ident> names an element, <code>&lt;classRef key="x"/></code> if it names a class,
               and <code>&lt;macroRef key="x"/></code> if it names a macro. </p>
            <p>Content models can of course be much more complicated. If your RELAX NG model uses an
               alternation or a sequence of components, you will need to use one of the ODD elements
                  <gi>alternate</gi> and <gi>sequence</gi> to wrap them rather than the RELAX NG
               (semi)equivalents <gi>rng:choice</gi> and <gi>rng:group</gi> respectively. For example, this
               RELAX NG model says that a <gi>foo</gi> can contain either a <gi>bar</gi> or a <gi>baz</gi>:
               <egXML xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><rng:choice>
                     <rng:ref name="bar"/><rng:ref name="baz"/></rng:choice></egXML>
                Its equivalent in pure ODD would be
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><alternate>
                     <elementRef key="bar"/><elementRef key="baz"/></alternate></egXML>
            </p>
            <p>If some components of your content model are optional or repeatable, you will have used the
               RELAX NG elements <gi>rng:oneOrMore</gi> or <gi>rng:zeroOrMore</gi>. In ODD optionality and
               repeatability are expressed using attributes <att>minOccurs</att> and <att>maxOccurs</att>,
               which can be supplied for any of the elements discussed so far. For example, a RELAX NG content
               model such as
               <egXML xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><rng:oneOrMore><rng:choice>
                        <rng:ref name="bar"/><rng:ref name="baz"/></rng:choice></rng:oneOrMore></egXML>
                has the following equivalent in pure ODD
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><alternate minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                     <elementRef key="bar"/><elementRef key="baz"/></alternate></egXML>
            </p>
            <p>An empty element is indicated in the RELAX NG language by a special pattern called
                  <gi>rng:empty</gi>. In the ODD language, however, we indicate that an element has no content
               by supplying an empty <gi>content</gi> element in its specification. </p>
            <p>The ODD language also provides a few more special-purpose component elements for content
               models: <gi>textNode</gi>, <gi>valList</gi>, and <gi>anyElement</gi>. </p>
            <p>The <gi>textNode</gi> element is provided as a replacement for the built-in RELAX NG pattern
                  <gi>rng:text</gi>. There are no restrictions on where it may be placed in an ODD content
               model, although existing schema languages mostly permit it to appear only in mixed content
               models like the following:
               <egXML xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                     <textNode/>
                     <elementRef key="foo"/>
                  </alternate></egXML>
            </p>
            <p>The RELAX NG language allows a number of other components within a content model, some of which
               are difficult to convert, but few of which are likely to appear in a pre-existing TEI ODD. If
               your ODD used the RELAX NG element <gi>rng:value</gi> to specify content explicitly, this must
               be expressed in an ODD as a <gi>valItem</gi> within a <gi>valList</gi>. If your ODD used the
               RELAX NG element <gi>rng:element</gi> to specify that any element is permitted at this point in
               a content model, you can do something similar with the ODD <gi>anyElement</gi> element. In
               general, however, the presence of any of the following in your old content model will require
               manual intervention: <gi>rng:anyName</gi>
               <gi>rng:attribute</gi>
               <gi>rng:data</gi>
               <gi>rng:element</gi>
               <gi>rng:except</gi>
               <gi>rng:name</gi>
               <gi>rng:nsName</gi>
               <gi>rng:param</gi>
               <gi>rng:value</gi></p>
            <p>Here are some example <gi>content</gi> elements taken from the content models of existing TEI
               elements: <table>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>RELAX NG Specification</cell>
                     <cell>ODD equivalent</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
 xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <content>
    <rng:oneOrMore>
       <rng:ref name="cell"/>
    </rng:oneOrMore>
 </content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <elementRef key="cell" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
 </content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
 xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <content>
    <rng:zeroOrMore>
       <rng:choice>
          <rng:text/>
          <rng:ref name="model.limitedPhrase"/>
          <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
       </rng:choice>
    </rng:zeroOrMore></content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
       <textNode/>
       <classRef key="model.limitedPhrase"/>
       <classRef key="model.global"/>
    </alternate>
 </content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
 xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <content>
    <group xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
       <zeroOrMore>
          <ref name="analytic"/>
       </zeroOrMore>
       <oneOrMore>
          <ref name="monogr"/>
          <zeroOrMore>
             <ref name="series"/>
          </zeroOrMore>
       </oneOrMore>
       <zeroOrMore>
          <choice>
             <ref name="model.noteLike"/>
             <ref name="model.ptrLike"/>
             <ref name="relatedItem"/>
             <ref name="citedRange"/>
          </choice>
       </zeroOrMore>
    </group>
 </content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <sequence>
       <elementRef key="analytic" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
       <sequence minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
          <elementRef key="monogr"/>
          <elementRef key="series" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
       </sequence>
       <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
          <classRef key="model.noteLike"/>
          <classRef key="model.ptrLike"/>
          <elementRef key="relatedItem"/>
          <elementRef key="citedRange"/>
       </alternate>
    </sequence>
 </content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Attribute values and datatypes</head>
            <p>As noted above, you may wish to change your existing ODD to be more precise in the way that
               attribute values are specified. If you decide to introduce a <gi>valList</gi> (semi-closed or
               closed) to constrain the possible values of an attribute you will also need to change its
                  <gi>datatype</gi> to reference <ident>teidata.enumerated</ident>. </p>
            <p>If the <gi>datatype</gi> element appears in your ODD already, you will need to change it to use
               a <gi>dataRef</gi> element pointing to one of the predefined <ident>teidata</ident> datatype
               specifications. A set of predefined data specifications using RELAX NG has been retained for
               compatibility reasons, but these will probably be withdrawn by the end of 2017. </p>
            <p>Proceed as follows: <list>
                  <item>if your existing <gi>datatype</gi> contains something like <code>&lt;rng:ref
                        name="data.xxxx"/></code>, change it to <code>&lt;dataRef
                     key="teidata.xxxx"/></code></item>
                  <item>if your existing <gi>datatype</gi> contains something like <code>&lt;rng:data
                        type="xxxx"/></code>, change it to <code>&lt;dataRef name="xxxx"/></code>
                  </item>
                  <item>if a component of your existing <gi>datatype</gi> contains something like
                        <code>&lt;rng:param name='pattern'/></code> you will need to either <list>
                        <item>add an attribute <att>restriction</att> to the <gi>datatype</gi>, giving as
 value the content of the <gi>rng:param</gi> element</item>
                        <item>or (if the parameter cannot be expressed as a regular expression, and if the
 datatype uses the <att>name</att> attribute) re-express the parameter as a TEI
    <gi>dataFacet</gi></item>
                     </list></item>
                  <item>If the datatype being defined permits multiple values, alternation, or anything else
                     other than a single value, you must define it in a <gi>dataSpec</gi> element, using the
                     same components as an element content model (<gi>alternate</gi>, <att>maxOccurs</att>,
                     etc.) Note that although the <gi>datatype</gi> element permits only a single
                        <gi>dataRef</gi> child, it is itself repeatable, so that you can say (for example)
                        <q>this attribute takes at least three pointer values</q>. </item>
               </list></p>
            <p>Here are some example <gi>content</gi> elements taken from the data specifications used by some
               existing TEI datatypes: <table>
                  <row role="label">
                     <cell>RELAX NG Specification</cell>
                     <cell>ODD equivalent</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <data xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="NCName"/>
 </content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <dataRef name="NCName"/>
 </content>
                        </egXML>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <data xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="nonNegativeInteger">
       <param name="maxInclusive">100</param>
    </data>
 </content></egXML>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <dataRef name="nonNegativeInteger" restriction="[0-9][0-9]?"/>
 </content></egXML>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
 <choice xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
       <data type="float">
          <param name="minExclusive">0.0</param>
          <param name="maxExclusive">1.0</param>
       </data>
       <value>regular</value>
       <value>irregular</value>
       <value>unknown</value>
    </choice>
 </content></egXML>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <alternate>
       <dataRef name="float">
          <dataFacet name="minExclusive" value="0"/>
          <dataFacet name="maxExclusive" value="1"/>
       </dataRef>
       <valList>
          <valItem ident="regular"/>
          <valItem ident="irregular"/>
          <valItem ident="unknown"/>
       </valList>
    </alternate>
 </content></egXML>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
                  <row role="data">
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <choice xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
       <rng:value>high</rng:value>
       <rng:value>medium</rng:value>
       <rng:value>low</rng:value>
       <rng:value>unknown</rng:value>
    </choice>
 </content></egXML>
                     </cell>
                     <cell>
                        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <content>
    <valList type="closed">
       <valItem ident="high"/>
       <valItem ident="medium"/>
       <valItem ident="low"/>
       <valItem ident="unknown"/>
    </valList>
 </content></egXML>
                     </cell>
                  </row>
               </table></p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>My head hurts: where's the script?</head>
            <p>Yes, there is a script or two you can experiment with if you find this all too daunting. They
               were used to transform the whole of the pre-3.0 TEI Guideline specifications
               semi-automatically. They deal with 99% of the situations you are likely to encounter, but
               they're not guaranteed! You can find them on Github at <ptr
                  target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/tree/dev/P5/Scripts"/>: use them in good health, but at
               your own risk.</p>
            <p>Don't hesitate to share your experience, good or bad, on the TEI discussion list, by raising a
               ticket on Github, or by contributing to the TEI wiki. The TEI is a community effort! </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
