<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright TEI Consortium. Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences See the file COPYING.txt for details $Date$ $Id$ -->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="linking" ident="ab">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>anonymous block</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">익명 구역</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">匿名區塊</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">bloc anonyme</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">bloque anónimo</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">blocco anonimo</gloss>
  <desc>contains any arbitrary component-level unit of text, acting as an anonymous container for phrase or inter level elements analogous to, but without the semantic baggage of, a paragraph.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">의미적 부담 없이, 문단과 유사한 구 또는 상호층위 요소에 대한 익명 전달체로 기능하는 임의적 성분-층위 단위를 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含文件中任何隨機組合性層次的單元，匿名收容類似一個段落、但不包含段落語義的字詞或中間層元素。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 任意の部分的テキスト単位を示す．特定の意味はなくとも，段落に相当する， 句レベル・挿入レベルの単位として無名単位になる． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-10-05" xml:lang="fr">contient une unité de texte quelconque, de niveau "composant", faisant office de contenant anonyme pour une expression ou des éléments de niveau intermédiaire, analogue à un paragraphe mais sans sa portée sémantique.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene cualquier unidad textual a nivel de componente que actua como un contenedor anónimo de sintagmas o de elementos de internivel similares al párrafo pero sin la carga semántica de este último.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una qualsiasi unità testuale a livello di componente che funge da contenitore anonimo di sintagmi o elementi interlivello simili al paragrafo ma senza il bagaglio semantico di quest'ultimo</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.pLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.declaring"/>
    <memberOf key="att.fragmentable"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.paraContent"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div type="book" n="Genesis">
        <div type="chapter" n="1">
          <ab>In the beginning God created the heaven and the earth.</ab>
          <ab>And the earth was without form, and void; and 
               darkness was upon the face of the deep. And the 
               spirit of God moved upon the face of the waters.</ab>
          <ab>And God said, Let there be light: and there was light.</ab>
          <!-- ...-->
        </div>
      </div>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The <gi>ab</gi> element may be used at the encoder's discretion to mark any component-level elements in a text for which no other more specific appropriate markup is defined.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2009-10-06">
    <p>L'élément <gi>ab</gi> peut être utilisé à la discrétion de l'encodeur pour marquer dans un texte tout élément de niveau composant pour lequel aucune méthode appropriée de balisage plus spécifique n'est définie.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 要素<gi>ab</gi>は，符号化する人が望むあらゆる単位レベルで，適切な 要素が規定されていない場合に，自由に使用することが出来る． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#SASE"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
