<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright TEI Consortium.
  Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
  See the file COPYING.txt for details
  $Date$
  $Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" type="atts" ident="att.sortable">
  <desc>provides attributes for elements in lists or groups that are sortable, but whose sorting key cannot be derived mechanically from the element content.</desc>
  <attList>
      <attDef ident="sortKey" usage="opt">
        <equiv/>
        <desc>supplies the sort key for this element in an index, list or group which contains it.</desc>
        <datatype>
          <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.word"/>
        </datatype>
        <valDesc>a sequence of characters which, when sorted with the other values, will produced
          the desired order; specifics of sort key construction are application-dependent.</valDesc>
        <valDesc version="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">toute séquence de caractères qui, lorsqu'ils sont triés avec les autres valeurs, produisent l'ordre souhaité ; les détails de construction d'une clé de tri
          dépendent des applications</valDesc>
        <exemplum xml:lang="en">
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">David's other principal backer, Josiah
            ha-Kohen <index indexName="NAMES"><term sortKey="Azarya_Josiah_Kohen">Josiah ha-Kohen b. Azarya</term></index> b. Azarya, son of one of the last gaons of Sura was David's own first
            cousin.</egXML>
        </exemplum>
        <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Verne_Vingt"> Je me suis
            procuré une <term>clef anglaise</term> pour dévisser les écrous qui attachent le canot à
            la coque du Nautilus. Ainsi tout est prêt.</egXML>
        </exemplum>
        <remarks>
          <p>The sort key is used to determine the sequence and grouping of entries in an index.</p>
          <p>Dictionary order often differs from the collation sequence of machine-readable character
            sets; in English-language dictionaries, an entry for <mentioned>4-H</mentioned> will often
            appear alphabetized under <q>fourh</q>, and <mentioned>McCoy</mentioned> may be
            alphabetized under<q>maccoy</q>, while <mentioned>A1</mentioned>,
            <mentioned>A4</mentioned>, and <mentioned>A5</mentioned> may all appear in numeric order
            <soCalled>alphabetized</soCalled> between <q>a-</q> and <q>AA</q>. The sort key is
            required if the orthography of the dictionary entry does not suffice to determine its
            location.</p>
        </remarks>
        <remarks xml:lang="fr">
          <p>La clé de tri est utilisée pour déterminer la séquence et le groupement d'entrées dans un
          index.</p>
          <p>La structure d'un dictionnaire diffère souvent de l'ordre de collation des jeux de
            caractères lisibles par la machine ; dans des dictionnaires de langue anglaise, une entrée
            pour <mentioned>4-H</mentioned> apparaîtra souvent alphabétiquement sous <q>fourh</q>, et
            <mentioned>McCoy</mentioned>peut être classé alphabétiquement sous <q>maccoy</q>, tandis que <mentioned>A1</mentioned>, <mentioned>A4</mentioned> et <mentioned>A5</mentioned>
            apparaîtront tous dans un ordre alphanumérique entre <q>a-</q> et <q>AA</q>. La clef de
            tri est exigée si l'orthographe de l'entrée du dictionnaire n'est pas suffisante pour
            déterminer son emplacement.</p>
        </remarks>
        <remarks xml:lang="es">
          <p>La clave de ordenación se utiliza para determinar la secuencia y agrupar las entradas en
            un índice.</p>
        </remarks>
        <remarks xml:lang="ja">
          <p> 当該属性は，索引中の項目の一連やグループを決めるために使用され る．当該属性がない場合，当該要素の内容が，並び替えのために使用 される． </p>
            <p> 辞書順序は，機械可読文字集合の照合順序とは，多くの場合異なって いる．例えば，英語の場合，辞書項目<mentioned>4-H</mentioned>は，
              文字化された<q>fourh</q>の所に出てくる．また，項目 <mentioned>McCoy</mentioned>は，<q>maccoy</q>の所に出てくるだ
              ろう．しかし，項目<mentioned>A1</mentioned>, <mentioned>A4</mentioned>,
              <mentioned>A5</mentioned>らは，文字 順の<q>a-</q>と<q>AA</q>との間で，数字順で出てくる．
              当該並び替えキーは，当該辞書が採る正書法では，場所の特定が十分 に行えない場合に，必要となる． </p>
        </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#ST"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
