<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="DECLABL" type="atts" ident="att.declarable">
  <desc>provides attributes for those elements in the TEI Header which
  may be independently selected by means of  the special purpose <att>decls</att> attribute.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">특별한 목적의 <att>decls</att> 속성을 통해서 독립적으로 선택될 수 있는 TEI 헤더의 요소에 대한 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供屬性，用於TEI標頭內可單獨以特殊目的的屬性<att>decls</att>選出的元素。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  特定の働きを持つ属性<att>decls</att>で独自に選択されたTEIヘダー中の
  要素に関する属性を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs pour les éléments dans
      l'en-tête TEI qui peuvent être choisis indépendamment au moyen de l'attribut
      <att>decls</att>prévu dans ce but </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos para los elementos contenidos en el encabezado que pueden ser seleccionados autónomamente mediante el atributo <att>decls</att> adecuado.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">individua attributi per gli elementi contenuti nell'intestazione che possono essere selezionati autonomamente grazie all'apposito attributo <att>decls</att></desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="default" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates whether or not this element is selected by default when
its parent is selected.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">그 부모가 선택될 때 기본값으로 이 요소가 선택되었는지를 표시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">當父元素被選擇時，指出此元素是否會被選擇。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      親要素が選択された場合に，当該要素がデフォルトとして選択されるか
      どうかを示す．
	</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">Indique si oui ou non cet élément est affecté par
          défaut quand son élément parent a été sélectionné.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica si el elemento es seleccionado automáticamente o no  cuando es seleccionado el padre</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica se l'elemento è selezionato automaticamente quando è selezionato il genitore</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.truthValue"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>false</defaultVal>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="true">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>This element is selected if its parent is selected</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">그 부모가 선택된다면 이 요소가 선택된다.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">若父元素被選擇，則此元素會被選擇。</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">Este elemento se selecciona si sus padres son seleccionados</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
          親要素が選択された場合，当該要素が選択される．
          </desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">cet élément est choisi si son parent
est choisi</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">l'elemento è selezionato se è selezionato il genitore</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="false">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>This element can only be selected explicitly, unless it is the
only one of its kind, in which case it is selected if its parent is selected.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이런 유형 중 유일한 경우가 아니라면, 이 요소는 명시적으로만 선택될 수 있다. 유일한 경우에는, 그 부모가 선택된다면 이 요소가 선택된다.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">此元素僅能被明確選擇，若此元素為其類別中之唯一，則父元素被選擇時，此元素會被選擇。</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">Este elemento sólo se puede seleccionar explícitamente, a menos que sea el único de su clase, en este caso se selecciona si su padre es seleccionado.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
          当該要素は，明示的にのみ選択される．または，親要素が選択され，
          これが唯一の選択肢であるときのみに，これは選択される．
          </desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">cet élément ne peut être sélectionné
qu'explicitement, à moins qu'il ne soit le seul de ce type, auquel cas
il est selectionné si son parent a été choisi</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">l'elemento deve essere esplicitamente selezionato, a meno che non sia l'unico del suo genere, nel qual caso è selezionato se è selezionato il genitore</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>The rules governing the association of declarable elements with
    individual parts of a TEI text are fully defined in chapter <ptr target="#CCAS"/>. Only one element of a particular type may have a
    <att>default</att> attribute with a value of <val>true</val>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Les règles régissant l'association d'éléments déclarables avec des parties
                individuelles d'un texte TEI sont entièrement définies au chapitre . Un seul élément
                d'un type particulier peut avoir un attribut <att>default</att> avec une valeur
                    <val>true</val>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Las reglas que gobiernan la asociación de los elementos declarables con las partes individuales de un texto de TEI se definen completamente en el capítulo <ptr target="#CCAS"/>. Solamente un elemento de un tipo determinado puede tener algún atributo de <att>valor por defecto</att> con un valor de <val>verdad</val>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    このような選択可能要素の関連性を決める規則は，
    <ptr target="#CCAS"/>において詳しく規定されている．
    属性値<val>true</val>をとるのは，ひとつの要素だけである．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CCAS"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
