<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="DECLING" type="atts" ident="att.declaring">
  <desc>provides attributes for elements which may be independently associated with a particular declarable element within the header, thus overriding the inherited default for that element.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">헤더에서 선언 가능한 어떤 요소와 독립적으로 연관될 수 있는 속성을 제공한다. 이를 통해 그 요소의 상속된 기본값은 무효가 된다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供元素屬性，這些元素可單獨與標頭中一特定可宣告元素相關連，因此超越該特定元素本身的預設值。
    </desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  TEIヘダーにある特定の宣言可能要素向けの属性を示す．これにより，当該
  要素の継承値を上書きすることになる．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs pour les éléments qui peuvent
    être associés  indépendamment à un élément particulier déclarable dans l'en-tête TEI, ignorant
      ainsi la valeur dont cet élément devrait hériter par défaut</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos a los elementos que pueden ser asociados autonomamente a un elemento determinado declarado en el encabezado, no teniendo en cuenta el default heredato por aquel elemento.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna attributi agli elementi che possono essere autonomamente associati a un determinato elemento dichiarato nell'intestazione, non tenendo conto del default ereditato per quell'elemento</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="decls" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>identifies one or more <term>declarable elements</term> within the
header, which are understood to apply to the element bearing this
attribute and its content.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">헤더 내의 하나 이상의 <term>declarable elements</term>을 식별하며, 이 속성과 내용을 포함하는 요소에 적용되는 것으로 간주된다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指明標頭內一個或多個可宣告元素，可應用於帶有此屬性與內容的元素上。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      TEIヘダーにある，1つ以上の<term>宣言可能要素</term>を示す．
      当該属性を持つ要素や内容に適応されると解釈される．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">identifie un ou plusieurs<term>éléments
            déclarables </term>dans l'en-tête TEI, qui sont destinés à s'appliquer à l'élément
          portant cet attribut et à son contenu. </desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">identifica uno o más <term>elementos declarables</term> al interno del encabezado, los cuales son válidos para el elemento al cual es adscrito el atributo en cuestión y su contenido.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">identifica uno o più <term>elementi dichiarabili</term> all'interno dell'intestazione,
i quali sono validi per l'elemento a cui è assegnato l'attributo in questione e il suo contenuto</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>must identify a set of declarable elements of different types. </valDesc>
      <valDesc version="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">doit identifier un jeu d'éléments déclarables de différents types.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>The rules governing the association of declarable elements
with individual parts of a TEI text are fully defined in chapter <ptr target="#CCAS"/>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Les règles régissant l'association d'éléments déclarables avec des parties
                individuelles d'un texte TEI sont entièrement définies au chapitre .</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Las reglas que gobiernan la asociación de los elementos declarables con las partes individuales de un texto de TEI se definen completamente en el capítulo <ptr target="#CCAS"/>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    宣言可能要素の関連性を決める規則については，<ptr target="#CCAS"/>
        を参照のこと．
     </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CCAS"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
