<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" predeclare="true" module="verse" xml:id="METRICAL" type="atts" ident="att.metrical">
  <desc>defines a set of attributes which certain elements may use to
represent metrical information. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">운율 정보를 표시하기 위하여 특정 요소들이 사용할 수 있는 속성 집합을 정의한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">定義一組特定元素所使用、表示詩行韻律的屬性。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  特性の要素が韻律情報を示す属性を定義する．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">définit un ensemble d'attributs que certains
      éléments peuvent utiliser pour représenter de l'information métrique.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define un grupo de atributos utilizados dentro de determinados elementos para representar información métrica</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce un insieme di attributi utilizzati entro determinati elementi per rappresentare informazioni relative alla metrica</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="met" usage="rec">
      <gloss>metrical structure, conventional</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">관례적 운율 구조</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">estructura métrica, convencional</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">structure métrique, canonique</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">struttura metrica, convenzionale</gloss>
      <desc>contains a user-specified encoding for the conventional
metrical structure of the element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">요소의 관례적 운율 구조에 대하여 사용자가 명시한 부호화를 포함한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">包含使用者定義的標記，用於一般韻律結構。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該要素の通常韻律構造を示す，ユーザ定義のデータを含む．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">contient un encodage spécifié par l'utilisateur pour la structure métrique conventionnelle de l'élément.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una codificación definida por el usuario de la estructura métrica convencional del elemento.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una codifica, definita dall'utente, della struttura metrica convenzionale dell'elemento</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="token"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>May contain either a standard term for the kind of metrical
unit (e.g. <mentioned>hexameter</mentioned>) or an encoded representation for the
metrical pattern (e.g. <mentioned>+--+-+-+-+-</mentioned>). In either case, the
notation used should be documented by a <gi>metDecl</gi> element
within the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of the associated header.</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">Peut contenir, soit un terme normalisé désignant le type d'unité métrique (par exemple <mentioned>hexamètre</mentioned>),  soit une représentation codée du modèle métrique (par exemple <mentioned>+--+-+-+-+-</mentioned>). 
        Dans les autres cas, la notation utilisée peut être documentée par un élément <gi>metDecl</gi> dans l'élément  <gi>encodingDesc</gi>de l'en-tête associé.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Where this attribute is not specified, the metrical
pattern for the element concerned is understood to be inherited
from its parent.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Lorsque l'attribut <att>met</att> n'est pas présent, le modèle métrique de
                        l'élément courant est considéré comme hérité de l'élément parent.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
      当該属性の値が付与されていない場合，当該要素の韻律パタンは，親要
      素にある内容を継承すると解釈される．
      </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="real" usage="opt">
      <gloss>metrical structure, realized</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">실현된 운율 구조</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">estructura métrica, realizada</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">structure métrique réelle</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">struttura metrica, attuata</gloss>
      <desc>contains a user-specified encoding for the actual realization
of the conventional metrical structure applicable to the element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">요소에 적용 가능한 관례적 운율 구조의 실제 실현에 대하여 사용자가 명시한 부호화를 포함한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">包含使用者定義的標記，適用於一般標記結構的實際表現情形。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該要素に当てはまる通常韻律構造の実現形を，ユーザーの定義で示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">contient un encodage, spécifié par l'utilisateur, de la réalisation effective de la structure métrique conventionnelle applicable à l'élément.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene un codificación definida por el usuario para la realización efectiva de la estructura métrica convencional aplicable al elemento.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una codifica, definita dall'utente, dell'effettiva realizzazione della struttura metrica convenzionale applicabile all'elemento</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="token"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>May contain either a standard term for the kind of metrical
unit (e.g. <mentioned>hexameter</mentioned>) or an encoded representation for the
metrical pattern (e.g. <mentioned>+--+-+-+-+-</mentioned>). In either case, the
notation used should be documented by a <gi>metDecl</gi> element
within the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of the associated header.</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">Peut contenir, soit un terme normalisé désignant le type d'unité métrique (par exemple <mentioned>hexamètre</mentioned>),  soit une représentation codée du modèle métrique (par exemple <mentioned>+--+-+-+-+-</mentioned>). 
        Dans les autres cas, la notation utilisée peut être documentée par un élément <gi>metDecl</gi> dans l'élément  <gi>encodingDesc</gi>de l'en-tête associé.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Where this attribute is not specified, the metrical
realization for the element concerned is understood to be identical
to that specified or implied for the <att>met</att> attribute.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Lorsque l'attribut <att>real</att> n'est pas présent, la réalisation métrique
                        de l'élément concerné est considérée comme identique à celle spécifiée de
                        manière explicite ou implicite au moyen de l'attribut <att>met</att>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
      当該属性の値が付与されていない場合，当該要素の韻律パタンは，親要
      素にある内容を継承すると解釈される．
      </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="rhyme" usage="rec">
      <gloss>rhyme scheme</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">운 스키마</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">esquema de la rima</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">schéma rimique</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">schema rimico</gloss>
      <desc>specifies the rhyme scheme applicable to a group of verse lines.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">시행 군집에 적용 가능한 운 스키마를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">標明適用於一詩行組的押韻組合。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      韻文の行集合に当てはまる韻構造を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">spécifie quel schéma de rimes a été appliqué à un
          groupe de lignes versifiées.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica el esquema de la rima de un grupo de versos.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica lo schema rimico di un gruppo di versi</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="token"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>By default, the
rhyme scheme is expressed as a string of alphabetic
characters each corresponding with a rhyming line.  Any non-rhyming
lines should be represented by a hyphen or an X.  Alternative notations
may be defined as for <att>met</att> by use of the <gi>metDecl</gi>
element in the TEI header.</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">Par défaut, le schéma de rimes est exprimé sous la forme d'une chaîne de caractères alphabétiques correspondant chacun à une ligne rimée. 
        Toute ligne non rimée doit être repésentée par un tiret ou un X. Des notations alternatives peuvent être définies comme pour l'attribut <att>met</att> en utilisant l'élément <gi>metDecl</gi> dans l'en-tête TEI.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>When the default notation is used, it does not make sense to
specify this attribute on any unit smaller than a line.  Nor does the
default notation provide any way to record internal rhyme, or to specify
non-conventional rhyming practice. These extensions would require
user-defined alternative notations.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Lorsque la notation par défaut est utilisée, cela n'a pas de sens de
                        renseigner l'attribut <att>rhyme</att> pour une unité plus petite qu'une
                        ligne de vers. La notation par défaut ne donne aucun moyen de noter une rime
                        interne, non plus que de spécifier une utilisation non conventionnelle des
                        rimes. Ces extensions requièrent des notations différentes définies par
                        l'utilisateur de la TEI.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
	デフォルトの表記法が使用される時，この属性を行以下の単位に付与
      することには，意味がない．デフォルトの表記法は，内部の韻を記録す
      るものではない．また，通常でない押韻を特定するものでもない．
      これらの拡張には，ユーザが定義した別の表記法が求められるだろう．
      </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#VEME"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
