<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="TYPED" type="atts" ident="att.typed">
  <desc>provides attributes which can be used to classify or subclassify elements in any way. </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">요소의 분류 또는 하위분류에서 사용될 수 있는 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供可依任何方法將元素分類或次要分類的一般屬性。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  要素を分類するための属性を示す．
</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-05-29" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs qui peuvent être
      utilisés pour classer ou interclasser des éléments de n'importe quelle façon.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos genéricos utilizables para cualquier clasificación o subclasificación de elementos.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna degli attributi generici utilizzabili per qualsiasi classificazione e sottoclassificazione di elementi</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>characterizes the element in some sense, using any convenient
 classification scheme or typology.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">다양한 분류 스키마 또는 유형을 사용해서 요소의 특성을 기술한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">用合適的分類標準或類型來描述該元素。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該要素の分類を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2009-05-29" xml:lang="fr">caractérise l'élément en utilisant n'importe quel système ou typologie de classification approprié.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">caracteriza el elemento utilizando una clasificación o tipología funcional.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">caratterizza l'elemento utilizzando una classificazione o tipologia funzionale</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <remarks>
        <p>The <att>type</att> attribute is present on a number of elements, not all of which are members of <ident type="class">att.typed</ident>.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="subtype" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <gloss versionDate="2009-05-29" xml:lang="fr">sous-type</gloss>
      <desc>provides a sub-categorization of the element, if needed</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">필요하다면 요소의 하위범주를 제시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">若有需要，提供該元素的次要分類</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      必要であれば，当該要素の下位分類を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">donne une sous-catégorisation de l'élément, si
          c'est nécessaire.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona, si es necesario, una subcategorización del elemento.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">stabilisce, se necessario, una sottocategorizzazione dell'elemento</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <remarks>
        <p>The <att>subtype</att> attribute may be used to provide any
sub-classification for the element, additional to that provided by its
<att>type</att> attribute.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>L'attribut <att>subtype</att> peut être employé pour fournir une
                        sous-classification pour cet élément, en plus de celle fournie par son
                        propre attribut <att>type</att>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>El atributo <att>subtipo</att> se puede utilizar para proporcionar cualquier subclasificación para el elemento, adicional a ésa proporcionada por su
<att>tipo</att> de atributo.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
	属性<att>subtype</att>は，属性<att>type</att>に加えて，当該要
    素の下位分類を示すために使われる．
    </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks versionDate="2011-11-26">
    <p>When appropriate, use values from an established typology. Otherwise, define a typology using
the <gi>classification</gi> element of the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> within
the associated TEI header, or as a list within one of the components
of the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element, or informally as descriptive prose within
the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p> La typologie utilisée peut être formellement définie au moyen de
                    l'élément <gi>classification</gi> qui se trouve dans
                l'élément<gi>encodingDesc</gi> de l'en-tête TEI associé, ou bien sous forme d'une
                liste dans un des composants de l'élément <gi>encodingDesc</gi>, ou encore d'une
                manière informelle sous forme d'une description dans l'élément <gi>encodingDesc</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>La tipología usada se puede definir formalmente usando la <gi>clasificación</gi> del elemento del <gi>encodingDesc</gi> dentro del encabezado TEI asociado, o como lista dentro de uno de los componentes del <gi>encodingDesc</gi> elemento, o informalmente como prosa descriptiva dentro del elemento <gi>encodingDesc</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    当該分類は，TEIヘダーの要素<gi>encodingDesc</gi>にある要素
    <gi>classification</gi>で定義される．または，要素
    <gi>encodingDesc</gi>の下位要素のいずれかで定義される．または，要
    素<gi>encodingDesc</gi>の中で，散文的に記述される．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#STECAT"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
