<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="DATCAT" type="atts" ident="att.datcat"
 xmlns:dcr="http://www.isocat.org/ns/dcr">
  <desc>introduces <att>dcr:datacat</att> and <att>dcr:ValueDatacat</att> attributes that may be used to 
    align XML elements or attributes with the appropriate Data Categories (DCs) defined by the ISO 12620:2009 
    standard and stored in the Web repository called ISOCat at <ref target="http://www.isocat.org/">http://www.isocat.org/</ref>.</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="datcat" usage="opt" ns="http://www.isocat.org/ns/dcr">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>contains a PID (persistent identifier) that aligns the given element with the appropriate 
        Data Category (or categories) in ISOcat.</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="valueDatcat" usage="opt" ns="http://www.isocat.org/ns/dcr">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>contains a PID (persistent identifier) that aligns the content of the given
        element or the value of the given attribute with the appropriate simple Data
        Category (or categories) in ISOcat.</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
    <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>In this example <att>dcr:datcat</att> relates the feature name to the data category
      "partOfSpeech" and <att>dcr:valueDatcat</att> the feature value to the data category
      "commonNoun". Both these data categories reside in the ISOcat DCR at <ref
        target="http://www.isocat.org">www.isocat.org</ref>, which is the DCR used by ISO
      TC37 and hosted by its registration authority, the MPI for Psycholinguistics in
      Nijmegen.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fs>
        <f
          name="POS"
          dcr:datcat="http://www.isocat.org/datcat/DC-1345"
          fVal="common noun"
          dcr:valueDatcat="http://www.isocat.org/datcat/DC-1256"
        />
      </fs>
    </egXML>
    </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>ISO 12620:2009 is a standard describing the data model and procedures for a Data
      Category Registry (DCR). Data categories are defined as elementary descriptors in a
      linguistic structure. In the DCR data model each data category gets assigned a
      unique Peristent IDentifier (PID), i.e., an URI. Linguistic resources or preferably
      their schemas that make use of data categories from a DCR should refer to them using
      this PID. For XML-based resources, like TEI documents, ISO 12620:2009 normative
      Annex A gives a small Data Category Reference XML vocabulary (also available online
      at <ref target="http://www.isocat.org/12620/">http://www.isocat.org/12620/</ref>),
      which provides two attributes, <att>dcr:datcat</att> and
      <att>dcr:valueDatcat</att>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#DIMVLV"/>
    <ptr target="#FSSY"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
