<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei"
	   type="atts" ident="att.pointing">
  <desc>defines a set of attributes used by all elements which point
  to other elements by means of one or more URI references.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">하나 이상의 URI 참조를 통해서 다른 요소를 가리키는 모든 요소에 의해 사용된 속성 집합을 정의한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">定義一組與其他元素相連結的所有元素皆使用的屬性，連結是使用ㄧ個或多個統一資源識別符 (URI) 參照。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  URIにより要素を参照する要素に共通して付与される属性を定義する．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">définit un ensemble d'attributs utilisés par tous les éléments qui pointent vers d'autres éléments au moyen d'une ou de plusieurs références URI.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define un conjunto de atributos usados por todos los elementos que señalan a otros elementos a través de uno o más URI.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce un insieme di attributi usati da tutti gli elementi che puntano ad altri elementi tramite uno o più URI</desc>
  <attList>

    <attDef ident="target" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>specifies the destination of the reference by supplying one or more URI References</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">하나 혹은 다수의 URI 참조를 제시하여 참조의 목적지를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">用一個或多個統一資源識別符參照 (URI References) 來說明參照所指位置。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> ひとつ以上のURIで，参照先を特定する． </desc>
      <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">précise la cible de la référence en donnant une ou
        plusieurs références URI</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica la destinación de una referencia
        proporcionando una o más referencias URI.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica la destinazione di un riferimento, fornendo
        uno o più riferimenti URI</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>One or more syntactically valid URI references, separated by whitespace. Because
        whitespace is used to separate URIs, no whitespace is permitted inside a single URI. If a
        whitespace character is required in a URI, it should be escaped with the normal mechanism,
        e.g. <code>TEI%20Consortium</code>.</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">Une ou plusieurs références URI syntactiquement valables, séparée par
        un espace. Puisqu' un espace blanc est employé pour séparer des URIs, aucun espace blanc
        n’est autorisé à l'intérieur d' un URI. Si un espace blanc est requis dans un URI, il
        devrait être traité normalement , par exemple avec le mécanisme
        <code>TEI%20Consortium</code>.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
<!--
    <attDef ident="type" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>categorizes the pointer in some respect, using any
      convenient set of categories.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">임의의 범주 집합을 사용해서 어떤 방식으로 포인터를 범주화한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">用任何合宜的類別，在某方面將指標分類。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該ポインタの種類を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">classe le pointeur selon un aspect quelconque, en utilisant tout ensemble approprié de catégories.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona una clasificación para el indicador utilizando una taxonomía funcional.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">fornisce una classificazione per il puntatore utilizzando una tassonomia funzionale</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>The type should indicate the intended function of the
      pointer, or the rhetorical relationship between its source and
      target.</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">Le type doit indiquer la fonction attendue du pointeur ou la relation rhétorique entre source et cible.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
-->    <attDef ident="evaluate" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <gloss version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">évalué</gloss>
      <desc>specifies the intended meaning when the target of a
      pointer is itself a pointer.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">포인터의 대상이 포인터일 때 의도된 의미를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">若指標的目標本身為指標，則在此說明其用意。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該ポインタの参照先がポインタである場合，その意図を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">détermine le sens attendu, si la cible d'un pointeur est elle-même un pointeur.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el significado previsto cuando la meta de un indicador es también un indicador. </desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il significato previsto quando la destinazione di un puntatore è essa stessa un puntatore</desc>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="all">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>if the element pointed to is itself a pointer, then
	  the target of that pointer will be taken, and so on, until
	  an element is found which is not a pointer.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">만약 지시되는 요소가 포인터라면, 포인터의 대상은 포인터가 아닌 요소가 발견될 때까지 계속 연결된다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">若指向的元素本身為指標，則該指標的目標會被移除，依此類推，直到找到一個非指標的元素為止。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">si el elemento que señala a sí mismo es un indicador, entonces el target de ese indicador será tomado, y así sucesivamente, hasta que se encuentre un elemento que no sea un indicador.</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
	  参照先の要素がポインターである場合，そのポインターの参照先へ
	  と展開する．これを，参照先がポインターでなくなるまで続ける．
	  </desc>
          <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">si l'élément pointé est lui-même un pointeur, alors on prendra la cible de ce pointeur, et ainsi de suite jusqu'à trouver un élément qui n'est pas un pointeur.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">se l'elemento puntato è esso stesso un puntatore, allora sarà presa la destinazione di quel puntatore e così via fino a trovare un elemento che non è un puntatore</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="one">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>if the element pointed to is itself a pointer, then
	  its target (whether a pointer or not) is taken as the target
	  of this pointer.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">지시된 요소가 포인터라면, 그 대상(포인터이든지 아니든지)은 이 포인터의 대상으로 취급된다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">若指向的元素本身為指標，則該指標的目標(無論是否為指標)會作為這項指標的目標。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">si el elemento que señala a sí mismo es un puntero, entonces el target (puntero o no) se toma como el target de este puntero.</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
	  参照先の要素がポインターである場合，(そのポインターの参照先
	  がどうであれ)そのポインターが参照先になる．
	  </desc>
          <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">si l'élément pointé est lui-même un pointeur, alors sa cible (qui est ou non un pointeur) devient la cible retenue.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">se l'elemento puntato è esso stesso un puntatore, allora la sua destinazione (che sia un puntatore o meno) è presa come destinazione del puntatore</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="none">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>no further evaluation of targets is carried out
	  beyond that needed to find the element specified in the
	  pointer's target.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">포인터의 대상에서 명시된 요소를 발견할 필요가 없을 때 더 이상의 대상에 대한 평가는 수행되지 않는다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">尋找指標的目標元素時，未對目標進行不必要的延伸評估。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">no se realiza ninguna otra evaluación de los targets más allá de la necesaria para encontrar el elemento especificado en el target del puntero.</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
	  当該ポインターの参照先から先にあるリンクへの展開は行わない．
	  </desc>
          <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">aucune évaluation ultérieure des cibles n'est menée au-delà de la recherche de l'élément désigné dans la cible du pointeur.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">non viene condotta altra valutazione delle destinazioni se non quella necessaria a rintracciare l'elemento specificato nella destinazione del puntatore</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <remarks>
        <p>If no value is given, the application program is
          responsible for deciding (possibly on the basis of user
          input) how far to trace a chain of pointers.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Si aucune valeur n'est fournie, c'est au programme d'application de décider
                        (éventuellement à partir d'une donnée entrée par l'utilisateur) jusqu'où
                        retracer une chaîne de pointeurs.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
	値がない場合，ソフトウェア側がポインター連鎖の扱いを決める(恐
	  らく利用者が指示を元に行われる)．
	  </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COXR"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
