<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" predeclare="true" module="verse" xml:id="METRICAL" type="atts" ident="att.metrical">
  <desc>defines a set of attributes which certain elements may use to
represent metrical information. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce un insieme di attributi utilizzati entro determinati elementi per rappresentare informazioni relative alla metrica</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define un grupo de atributos utilizados dentro de determinados elementos para representar información métrica</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="met" usage="rec">
      <gloss>metrical structure, conventional</gloss>
      <desc>contains a user-specified encoding for the conventional
metrical structure of the element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una codifica, definita dall'utente, della struttura metrica convenzionale dell'elemento</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una codificación definida por el usuario de la estructura métrica convencional del elemento.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">ユーザー定義の韻律表記法を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="token"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>May contain either a standard term for the kind of metrical
unit (e.g. <mentioned>hexameter</mentioned>) or an encoded representation for the
metrical pattern (e.g. <mentioned>+--+-+-+-+-</mentioned>). In either case, the
notation used should be documented by a <gi>metDecl</gi> element
within the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of the associated header.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Where this attribute is not specified, the metrical
pattern for the element concerned is understood to be inherited
from its parent.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="real" usage="rwa">
      <gloss>metrical structure, realized</gloss>
      <desc>contains a user-specified encoding for the actual realization
of the conventional metrical structure applicable to the element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una codifica, definita dall'utente, dell'effettiva realizzazione della struttura metrica convenzionale applicabile all'elemento</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene un codificación definida por el usuario para la realización efectiva de la estructura métrica convencional aplicable al elemento.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">ユーザー定義による，韻律構造の実際の出現形を表記する方法を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="token"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>May contain either a standard term for the kind of metrical
unit (e.g. <mentioned>hexameter</mentioned>) or an encoded representation for the
metrical pattern (e.g. <mentioned>+--+-+-+-+-</mentioned>). In either case, the
notation used should be documented by a <gi>metDecl</gi> element
within the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of the associated header.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Where this attribute is not specified, the metrical
realization for the element concerned is understood to be identical
to that specified or implied for the <att>met</att> attribute.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="rhyme" usage="rec">
      <gloss>rhyme scheme</gloss>
      <desc>specifies the rhyme scheme applicable to a group of verse lines.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica lo schema rimico di un gruppo di versi</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica el esquema de la rima de un grupo de versos.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">特定の韻構造を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="token"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>By default, the
rhyme scheme is expressed as a string of alphabetic
characters each corresponding with a rhyming line.  Any non-rhyming
lines should be represented by a hyphen or an X.  Alternative notations
may be defined as for <att>met</att> by use of the <gi>metDecl</gi>
element in the TEI header.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>When the default notation is used, it does not make sense to
specify this attribute on any unit smaller than a line.  Nor does the
default notation provide any way to record internal rhyme, or to specify
non-conventional rhyming practice. These extensions would require
user-defined alternative notations.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p/>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#VEME"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
