<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="textcrit"  type="atts" ident="att.witnessed">
  <desc>supplies the attribute used to identify the witnesses
  supporting a particular reading in a critical apparatus.</desc>
  <classes/>

  <attList>
    <attDef ident="wit" usage="opt">
      <gloss>witness or witnesses</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">비교 대상 텍스트</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">testimonio o testimonios</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">témoin ou témoins</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">testimone o testimoni</gloss>
      <desc>contains a list of one or more pointers indicating the witnesses
which attest to a given reading.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">제시된 독법을 증명하는 비교 대상 텍스트를 나타내는 하나 이상의 포인터 목록을 포함한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含一個或多個指標的一份列表，連結到已知對應本的版本。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該解釈を証す文献を示す1つ以上のポインタのリストを示す．
      </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">contient une liste comprenant un ou plusieurs pointeurs qui désignent
					les témoins attestant d'une leçon donnée.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una lista de uno o más indicadores que muestran los testimonios que presentan una determinada lectura.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una lista di uno o più puntatori indicanti i testimoni che attestano una determinata lettura</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>A space-delimited series of sigla; each sigil should correspond
to a witness or witness group and occur as the value of the
<att>xml:id</att> attribute on a <gi>witness</gi> element elsewhere in the
document.</valDesc>
      <valDesc versionDate="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">une série d'abréviations délimitées par un espace : chaque abréviation doit correspondre à un témoin 
        ou à un groupe de témoins et apparaître sous la forme d'une valeur de l'attribut <att>xml:id</att> d'un élément <gi>witness</gi> se trouvant 
      ailleurs dans le document.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>If the apparatus contains readings only for a single
witness, this attribute may be consistently omitted.</p>
        <p>This attribute may occur both within an apparatus
gathering variant readings in the transcription of an individual
witness and within an apparatus gathering readings from different
witnesses.</p>
        <p>Additional descriptions or alternative versions of the sigla referenced may be
supplied as the content of a child <gi>wit</gi> element.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Si l'apparat ne contient que des leçons relatives à un seul témoin, cet attribut peut être systématiquement omis. </p>
        <p>Cet attribut peut figurer à la fois dans un apparat qui réunit des variantes de leçons dans la transcription d'un témoin isolé et à l'intérieur d'un apparat qui réunit des leçons provenant de différents témoins.</p>
        <p>On peut donner des descriptions supplémentaires ou des versions alternatives d'abréviations référencées de témoins comme contenu d'un élément enfant <gi>wit</gi>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
        当該校勘資料中で，1つの現存資料に複数の解釈が含まれている場合，
        当該属性は常に省略されるかもしれない．
        </p>
        <p>
        当該属性は，ひとつの文献からの転記に対する各種の解釈を集めた校
        勘資料中で使用されるかもしれない．また，複数の文献中における各
        種の解釈を集めた校勘資料中でも使用されるかもしれない．
        </p>
        <p>
        当該文献記号の追加的な記述や他の版に関する情報は，子要素
        <gi>wit</gi>の内容として示されるかもしれない．
        </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>

  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#TCAPLL"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
