<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" module="certainty" xml:id="CERTAIN" usage="opt" ident="certainty">
  <desc>indicates the degree of certainty or uncertainty associated
  with some aspect of the text markup. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il grado di certezza o incertezza associato a un determinato aspetto del la codifica del testo</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">Indica el grado de certeza o incertidumbre asociado a algun aspecto del marcaje de texto.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">マークアップの確信度を示す．</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:ref name="macro.glossSeq"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="target" usage="req">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points at the elements whose markup is
      uncertain.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica elementi la cui codifica è incerta</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala los elementos cuyo marcaje es incierto.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">確信度の対象となる要素を
      示す．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a series of one or more identifiers (URIs), separated by white space</valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Elizabeth went to <persName xml:id="ESX">Essex</persName>
	<certainty target="#ESX" locus="gi" degree="0.6"/></egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>If more than one identifier is given, the
        <gi>certainty</gi> element is interpreted as applying to all.
        If no identifier is present on the element being annotated,
        the attribute should give the identifier of a <gi>ptr</gi>
        element which points at the element being annotated; for
        further discussion of this indirect pointing mechanism, see
        chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="locus" usage="req">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates the precise location of the uncertainty in the
	markup: applicability of the element, precise position of the
	start- or end-tag, value of a specific attribute,
	etc.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la posizione dell'incertezza nella codifica: l'applicabilità dell'elemento, la precisa posizione del marcatore iniziale o finale, il valore di un singolo attributo, ecc.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la posición precisa de la incertidumbre en el marcaje: aplicabilidad del elemento, posición precisa del comienzo y del final de la etiqueta, valor de un atributo específico, etc.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該確信度が指定要素の
	何についてのことかを示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valList type="semi">
        <valItem ident="gi">
          <gloss>element name</gloss>
          <desc>uncertain whether the element used actually applies
	    to the passage.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">è incerto se l'elemento usato sia applicabile al brano in questione</desc>
          <desc version="2007-06-14" xml:lang="es">it is uncertain whether the element used actually applies to the passage.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">es incierto si el elemento usado realmente se aplica al pasaje...</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="startLoc">
          <gloss>start location</gloss>
          <desc>start-tag may not be correctly located.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">el comienzo de la etiqueta puede no estar situado correctamente.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="endLoc">
          <gloss>end location</gloss>
          <desc>end-tag may not be correctly located.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">el final de la etiqueta puede no estar situado correctamente.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="location">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>both the start-tag and the end-tag may not be
	    correctly located.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">sia il marcatore iniziale che quello finale potrebbero non essere posizionati correttamente</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">ambos, el comienzo y el final de la etiqueta pueden no estar situados correctamente.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="attrName">
          <gloss>attribute name</gloss>
          <desc>the value given for the attribute name is
	    uncertain.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">el valor dado para el nombre del atributo es incierto.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="transcribedContent">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>the content of the element may not be a correct
	    transcription of the source text.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">il contenuto dell'elemento potrebbe non essere una trascrizione corretta del testo originario</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">el contenido del elemento puede no ser una transcripción correcta del texto fuente.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="suppliedContent">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>the content of the element may not have been
	    correctly supplied by the reader, e.g. as in the cases of
	    corr and abbrev elements.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">il contenuto dell'elemento potrebbe non essere stato indicato dal lettore, ad esempio con gli elementi corr e abbrev</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">el contenido del elemento puede no haber sido proporcionado correctamente por el lector, p.ej. como en los casos de los elementos corr y abbrev.</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <remarks>
        <p>If the name of an attribute is supplied, it must be
	  prefixed by <code>att.</code>.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="assertedValue" usage="rec">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>provides an alternative value for the aspect of the markup in
question—an alternative generic identifier, transcription,
or attribute value, or the identifier of an <gi>anchor</gi> element (to
indicate an alternative starting or ending location).  If an
<att>assertedValue</att> is given, the confidence level specified by
<att>degree</att> applies to the alternative markup specified by
<att>assertedValue</att>; if none is given, it applies to the markup
in the text.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna un valore alternativo all'apetto della codifica in questione, un identificatore generico, una trascrizione, il valore di un attributo, o l'identificatore di un elemento <gi>anchor</gi> (per indicare una posizione di inizio o fine alternativa). Se viene fornito un attributo <att>assertedValue</att>, il livello di sicurezza specificato dall'attributo <att>degree</att> si applica alla codifica alternativa specificata dall'attributo <att>assertedValue</att>; se non viene fornito alcun attributo, si applica alla codifica del testo.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona un valor alternativo para
          el aspecto del marcaje en cuestion, un identificador
          genérico alternativo, transcripción, o valor de atributo, o
          de identificador de un elemento <gi>anchor</gi> (para
          indicar una posición de comienzo y fin alternativa). Si un
          <att>assertedValue</att> viene dado, el nivel de confianza
          especificado por <att>degree</att> se aplica al marcaje
          alternativo especificado por <att>assertedValue</att>; si no
          viene dado ninguno, se aplica al marcaje en el texto.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">確信度に依存して，選択可能性のある代替値を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
          <rng:ref name="data.name"/>
          <rng:ref name="data.word"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>generic identifier, attribute value, location (e.g.
indicated by a reference to an <gi>anchor</gi> element or to an
<gi>ptr</gi> element), or other appropriate alternative
value.</valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <certainty target="#ESX" locus="gi" assertedValue="place" degree="0.2"/>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>This attribute makes it possible to indicate the
degree of confidence in a specific alternative to some aspect
of the markup. In the example above the encoder is expressing
the likelihood (.2) that the generic identifier should be
<gi>place</gi> rather than <gi>persName</gi>, which is the coded
element.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
<!--    <attDef ident="desc" usage="rec">
	<equiv/>
	<desc>further describes the uncertainty in prose, perhaps
indicating its nature, cause, or the justification for the
degree of confidence asserted.</desc>
      <datatype><rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/></datatype>
      <valDesc>a prose description of how and why the markup is
uncertain.</valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <certainty target="#ESX" locus="gi" degree="0.2"
  desc="Time of writing indicates the Earl rather than the town" /></egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>In a given project, it may be possible to enumerate
a finite list of recognized types and causes of uncertainty; in
such cases, it will be useful to control the vocabulary used in
this attribute, to aid later mechanical manipulation.  It is
not possible to suggest such a controlled vocabulary for
general use.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef> -->
    <attDef ident="given" usage="rec">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates conditions assumed in the assignment of a degree
      of confidence.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica le condizioni presunte nell'assegnare un grado di certezza</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica las condiciones asumidas en la asignación de un grado de confianza </desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該確信度が成立する前提
      条件部分を示す．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a pointer to a characterization of the conditions which
      are assumed in the assignment of a degree of
      confidence.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>A project may wish to control the vocabulary used in this
	attribute.</p>
        <p>The envisioned typical value of this attribute would be the
	identifier of another <gi>certainty</gi> element or a list of
	such identifiers. It may thus be possible to construct
	probability networks by chaining <gi>certainty</gi> elements
	together. Such networks would ultimately be grounded in
	unconditional <gi>certainty</gi> elements (with no value for
	<att>given</att>). The semantics of this chaining would be
	understood in this way: if a <gi>certainty</gi> element is
	specified, via a reference, as the assumption, then it is not
	the attribution of uncertainty that is the assumption, but
	rather the assertion itself. For instance, in the example
	above, the first <gi>certainty</gi> element indicates that the
	confidence in the identification of the new scribe as
	<mentioned>msm</mentioned>. The second indicates the degree of
	confidence that <mentioned>Essex</mentioned> is a personal
	name, given that the new scribe is <mentioned>msm</mentioned>.
	Note that the given in the second <gi>certainty</gi> element
	is not the assertion that the likelihood that msm is the new
	scribe is 0.6, but simply the assertion that msm is the new
	scribe; this is a recommended convention to facilitate
	building networks.</p>
        <p>The ambitious encoder may wish to attempt complex networks
or probability assertions, experimenting with references to
other elements or prose assertions, and deploying feature
structure connectives such as <gi>alt</gi>, <gi>join</gi>, and
<gi>not</gi>.  However, we do not believe that the
<gi>certainty</gi> element gives, at this time, a comprehensive
ambiguity-free system for indicating certainty.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="degree" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates the degree of confidence assigned to the aspect
of the markup named by the <att>locus</att> attribute.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il grado di certezza assegnato ad un aspetto della codifica  indicato dall'attributo <att>locus</att>.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el grado de confianza asignado al aspecto del marcaje llamado por el atributo <att>locus</att></desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該確信度の程度を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref name="data.probability"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <p>(For discussion of this example, see section <ptr target="#CECECE"/>)</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Earnest went to <anchor xml:id="A1"/> old
<persName xml:id="SYB">Saybrook</persName>.
<certainty xml:id="c1" target="#SYB" locus="gi" degree="0.6"/>
<certainty target="#SYB" locus="startLoc" given="#c1" degree="0.9"/>
<certainty xml:id="C-c2" target="#SYB" locus="gi" assertedValue="persName" degree="0.4"/>
<certainty target="#SYB" locus="startLoc" given="#C-c2" degree="0.5"/>
<certainty target="#SYB" locus="startLoc" assertedValue="#a1" given="#c1" degree="0.5"/></egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CECECE"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
