<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" module="core" xml:id="CHOICE" usage="opt" ident="choice">
  <gloss/>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">標記選擇</gloss>
  <desc>groups a number of alternative encodings for the same point in
  a text.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">匯集文件中對於同一部分文字所有可供替換的不同標記。</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">raggruppa un numero di codifiche alternative per la stessa porzione di testo.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">agrupa un número de codificaciones alternativas para el mismo punto en un texto.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">テキスト中の同じ場所を，異なる符号化方式で符号化する際の，
その方式の集合．</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.pPart.editorial"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:zeroOrMore>
      <rng:choice>
        <rng:ref name="model.choicePart"/>
        <rng:ref name="choice"/>
      </rng:choice>
    </rng:zeroOrMore>
  </content>
  <exemplum>
    <p>An American encoding of <title>Gulliver's Travels</title> which
    retains the British spelling but also provides a version
    regularized to American spelling might be encoded as follows.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>Lastly, That, upon his solemn oath to observe all the above
   articles, the said man-mountain shall have a daily allowance of
   meat and drink sufficient for the support of <choice><sic>1724</sic><corr>1728</corr></choice> of our subjects,
   with free access to our royal person, and other marks of our
   <choice><orig>favour</orig><reg>favor</reg></choice>.</p>
    </egXML>
<!-- Gulliver's Travels -->
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>Because the children of a  <gi>choice</gi> element all
    represent alternative ways of encoding the same sequence, it is
    natural to think of them as mutually exclusive. However, there may
    be cases where a full representation of a text requires the
    alternative encodings to be considered as parallel. </p>
    <p>Note also that <gi>choice</gi> elements may self-nest.</p>
    <p>For a specialized version of <gi>choice</gi> for encoding multiple
    witnesses of a single work, see section <ptr target="#TCAPLL"/>.</p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
