<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="transcr" ident="damageSpan">
  <gloss>damaged span of text</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">텍스트의 손상 구간</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">fragmento de texto dañado</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">partie de texte endommagée</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">porzione di testo danneggiata</gloss>
  <desc>marks the beginning of a longer sequence of text which is
  damaged in some way but still legible.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">어떤 방식으로 손상되었지만 여전히 읽을 수 있는 긴 텍스트 연쇄 시작부를 표시한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">marca el inicio de una secuencia de texto larga dañada de alguna manera pero aún legible.</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  読める程度の損傷がある，一連のテキストの始点を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2009-11-16" xml:lang="fr">marque le début d'une longue partie de texte,
endommagée d'une manière quelconque mais toujours lisible.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">segnala l'inizio di una sequenza più estesa di testo danneggiata ma ancora leggibile</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.global.edit"/>
    <memberOf key="att.damaged"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <empty xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
  <constraintSpec ident="spanTo" scheme="isoschematron">
    <constraint>
      <assert xmlns="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" test="@spanTo">The spanTo= attribute of
	<name/> is required.</assert>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <!-- FC j'ai traduit ici la contrainte schematron -->
  <constraintSpec ident="spanTo_fr" scheme="isoschematron" xml:lang="fr">
    <constraint>
      <assert xmlns="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" test="@spanTo">L'attribut spanTo est requis.</assert>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>Paragraph partially damaged.  This is the undamaged
portion <damageSpan spanTo="#a34"/>and this the damaged
portion of the paragraph.</p>
      <p>This paragraph is entirely damaged.</p>
      <p>Paragraph partially damaged; in the middle of this
paragraph the damage ends and the anchor point marks
the start of the  <anchor xml:id="a34"/> undamaged part of the text. ...</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>Paragraph partially damaged. This is the undamaged portion <damageSpan spanTo="#fr_a34"/>and
          this the damaged portion of the paragraph.</p>
      <p>This paragraph is entirely damaged.</p>
      <p>Paragraph partially damaged; in the middle of this paragraph the damage ends and the
          anchor point marks the start of the <anchor xml:id="fr_a34"/> undamaged part of the text.
        ...</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>此段部份毀損。這裡是完好的部份，<damageSpan spanTo="#zh-tw_a34"/>而此為毀損的部份。</p>
      <p>此段全部毀損。</p>
      <p>段落有部份毀損，損壞處止於段落的中間，以屬性anchor標示<anchor xml:id="zh-tw_a34"/>未損內文的重新出現處。</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>Both the beginning and ending of the damaged sequence must be
    marked: the beginning by the <gi>damageSpan</gi> element, the ending
    by the target of the <att>spanTo</att> attribute: if no other
    element available, the <gi>anchor</gi> element may be used for
    this purpose.</p>
    <p>The damaged text must be at least partially legible, in order
    for the encoder to be able to transcribe it. If it is not legible
    at all, the <gi>damageSpan</gi> element should not be used. Rather, the
    <gi>gap</gi> or <gi>unclear</gi> element should be employed, with the value of the <att>reason</att> attribute
    giving the cause. See further sections <ptr target="#PHDA"/> and
 <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" version="2009-11-16">
    <p>Le début et la fin de la partie de texte endommagée doivent être marqués : le début, par l'élément <gi>damageSpan</gi>, la fin au moyen de la cible de l'attribut <att>spanTo</att> :
                si aucun autre élément n'est disponible, l'élément <gi>anchor</gi> est utilisé à cette fin.</p>
    <p>Le texte endommagé doit être au moins partiellement lisible, afin que l'encodeur soit
                capable de le transcrire. S'il n'est pas lisible du tout, l'élément
                <gi>damageSpan</gi> ne devrait pas être utilisé. L'élément <gi>gap</gi> ou
                    <gi>unclear</gi> devrait être plutôt employé, avec un attribut <att>reason</att>
        dont la valeur donnerait la cause de cette lecture impossible. Voir les autres sections <ptr target="#PHDA"/> et <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    当該損傷部分の始点と終点は符号化されなければならない．始点は要素
    <gi>damageSpan</gi>で示される．終点は属性<att>spanTo</att>で示される．
    (指示対象として適切な)他の要素がない場合は，要素<gi>anchor</gi>が
  使用される．
  </p>
    <p>
    当該テキストの損傷部分は，少なくとも一部は読むことができ，符号化す
  る人は転記ができるものでなければならない．読めない場合には，当該要素
  <gi>damageSpan</gi>は使用すべきではない．この場合は，要素
  <gi>gap</gi>または要素<gi>unclear</gi>が，読めない理由を示す属性
  <att>reason</att>と共に使用されるべきである．この詳細については
  <ptr target="#PHDA"/>と<ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>を参照のこと．
  </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#PHDA"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
