<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright 2005 TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<macroSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" module="tei" type="dt" ident="data.numeric">
  <gloss/>
  <desc>defines the range of attribute values used for numeric values</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define la gama de valores de atributos para valores numéricos.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce la gamma di valori di attributi usati per valori numerici</desc>
  <content>
    <rng:choice>
      <rng:data type="double"/>
      <rng:data type="decimal"/>
    </rng:choice>
  </content>
  <remarks>
    <p>Any numeric value that can be represented as a decimal number.</p>
    <p>In addition, the range of values that can be represented in an
    IEEE double precision (i.e., 64-bit) floating point number may be
    represented using scientific notation. Roughly that range is
    ±10⁻³²³ to
    ±10³⁰⁸.</p>
    <p>To represent a number expressed in scientific notation,
    <soCalled>exponential notation</soCalled> is used in the attribute
    value. The significand (sometimes called the mantissa) is written
    as a decimal number, followed by the letter
    <mentioned>E</mentioned>, followed by an integer exponent. <!-- to
    which a base of 10 should be raised and the result multiplied by
    the signficand --> The multiplication sign and the base itself
    (<mentioned>10</mentioned>) are implied. Either the significand or
    the exponent (or both) may be a negative number, in which case it
    should be preceded by a minus sign. There should be no whitespace
    separating the significand from the <mentioned>E</mentioned> from
    the exponent. E.g., 3×10⁸ can be expressed as
    <val>3E8</val>.</p>
    <p>Other examples of scientific notation include:
    <list><item><val>10E10</val> (the speed of light in centimetres per second)</item><item><val>9.12E-31</val> (the mass of an electron in Kg)</item><item><val>4E11</val> (estimated number of stars in our galaxy)</item><item><val>-1.76E11</val> (electron charge to mass quotient in coulombs per Kg)</item></list>
    </p>
    <p>Either <mentioned>e</mentioned> or <mentioned>E</mentioned> may
    be used to separate the significand from the exponent, however
    these Guidelines recommend <mentioned>E</mentioned> be used both
    for consistency with other standards bodies and to avoid confusion
    with the mathematical constant <code>e</code>.</p>
  </remarks>
</macroSpec>
