<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<macroSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  module="tei" type="dt" ident="data.duration.iso">
  <desc>defines the range of attribute values available for representation of a duration in time
    using ISO 8601 standard formats</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">ISO 8601 표준 형식을 사용하여 시간의 지속을 나타내는 속성 값 범위를 정의한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">以ISO 8601標準格式定義表示一段持續性時間的屬性值範圍 </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> ISO 8601にある標準形式を使い，時間幅を表現する当該属性値の範囲を定義 する． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">définit la gamme de valeurs d'attributs disponibles pour
    la représentation d'une durée dans le temps utilisant l'ISO 8601 qui concerne les formats
    standards</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define la gama de valores de atributos posibles para
    representar la duración en el tiempo usando formatos estàndards ISO 8601.</desc>
  <content>
    <?tei winita need to improve this regexp to match duration better --sb ?>
    <rng:data type="token">
      <rng:param name="pattern">[0-9.,DHMPRSTWYZ/:+\-]+</rng:param>
    </rng:data>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <time dur-iso="PT0,75H">three-quarters of an hour</time>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <date dur-iso="P1,5D">a day and a half</date>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <date dur-iso="P14D">a fortnight</date>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="und">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <time dur-iso="PT0.02S">20 ms</time>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>A duration is expressed as a sequence of number-letter pairs, preceded by the letter P; the
      letter gives the unit and may be Y (year), M (month), D (day), H (hour), M (minute), or S
      (second), in that order. The numbers are all unsigned integers, except for the last, which may
      have a decimal component (using either <code>.</code> or <code>,</code> as the decimal point;
      the latter is preferred). If any number is <mentioned>0</mentioned>, then that number-letter
      pair may be omitted. If any of the H (hour), M (minute), or S (second) number-letter pairs are
      present, then the separator <code>T</code> must precede the first <soCalled>time</soCalled>
      number-letter pair.</p>
    <p>For complete details, see ISO 8601 <title>Data elements and interchange formats — Information
        interchange — Representation of dates and times</title>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 時間幅は，先頭文字Pに続いて，数値-文字のペア列で示される． 文字は単位を示している．Y(年), M(月), D(日), H(時間), M(分), S(秒)
      の順番になる．数値は符号のない整数である．但し，最後に10進数の 表記記号(小数点を示す<code>.</code>または<code>,</code>．後者が望
        ましい)をとることはある．数値が<mentioned>0</mentioned>の場合， 数値-文字のペアは省略されることがある． H(時間), M(分),
      S(秒)が数値-文字のペアを作る場合，区切子 <code>T</code>を先頭にして<soCalled>時間</soCalled>を示す数値-文字 のペアを示す必要がある． </p>
    <p> 詳細については，ISO 8601<title>Data elements and interchange formats - Information interchange -
        Representation of dates and times</title>を参照のこと． </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Une durée est exprimée par une suite de paires alphanumériques, précédée par la lettre P ;
      la lettre donne l'unité et peut être Y (année), M (mois), D (jour), H (heure), M (minute), ou
      S (seconde), dans cet ordre. Les nombres sont des entiers non signés à l'exception du dernier,
      qui peut comporter une décimale (en utilisant soit <code>.</code> soit <code>,</code> pour la
      virgule ; la dernière possibilité est préférable). Si un nombre est <mentioned>0</mentioned>,
      alors la paire alphanumérique peut être omise. Si les paires alphanumériques H (heure), M
      (minute), ou S (seconde) sont présentes, alors le séparateur <code>T</code> doit précéder la
      première paire alphanumérique <soCalled>time</soCalled>.</p>
    <p>Pour des détails complets, voir ISO 8601 <title>Data elements and interchange formats —
        Information interchange — Representation of dates and times</title>.</p>
  </remarks>
</macroSpec>
