<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<macroSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  module="tei" type="dt" ident="data.numeric">
  <desc>defines the range of attribute values used for numeric values.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">수치에 사용되는 속성 값의 범위를 정의한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">定義用於數值的屬性值範圍 </desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 数値をとる属性値の範囲を定義する． </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">définit la gamme des valeurs d'attributs utilisées pour
    des valeurs numériques</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define la gama de valores de atributos para valores
    numéricos.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce la gamma di valori di attributi usati per
    valori numerici</desc>
  <content>
    <rng:choice>
      <rng:data type="double"/>
      <rng:data type="token">
        <rng:param name="pattern">(\-?[\d]+/\-?[\d]+)</rng:param>
      </rng:data>
      <rng:data type="decimal"/>
    </rng:choice>
  </content>
  <remarks>
    <p>Any numeric value, represented as a decimal number, in floating point format, or as a ratio.</p>
    <p>To represent a floating point number, expressed in scientific notation, <soCalled>E
      notation</soCalled>, a variant of <soCalled>exponential notation</soCalled>, may be used. In
      this format, the value is expressed as two numbers separated by the letter E. The first
      number, the significand (sometimes called the mantissa) is given in decimal format, while the
      second is an integer. The value is obtained by multiplying the mantissa by 10 the number of
      times indicated by the integer. Thus the value represented in decimal notation as 1000.0 might
      be represented in scientific notation as 10E3.</p>
    <p>A value expressed as a ratio is represented by two integer values separated by a solidus (/)
      character. Thus, the value represented in decimal notation as 0.5 might be represented as a
      ratio by the string 1/2.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 10進数を作る数値． </p>
    <p> また，IEEE倍精度浮動小数点(64bit長)をとることもできる．例えば， ±10⁻³²³ から ±10³⁰⁸など． </p>
    <p> 科学的数値を評点する際，<soCalled>指数表現</soCalled>は，属性値と して記述される．
      10進数による仮数部，続いて記号<mentioned>E</mentioned>，続いて指数 部がくる．
      <!-- to which a base of 10 should be raised and the result multiplied by
    the signficand -->
        乗算記号と底(<mentioned>10</mentioned>)は省略される．仮数部と指数 部には負になるかもしれない．記号<mentioned>E</mentioned>と指数部を
      分けるために空白文字を入れる必要はない．例えば，3×10⁸ は <val>3E8</val>と書かれる． </p>
    <p> 他の例として，以下のようなものがある． <list>
        <item><val>3E10</val> (光の速度(cm/秒))</item>
        <item><val>9.12E-31</val> (電子の質量(kg))</item>
        <item><val>4E11</val> (銀河系にある恒星の数(推定値))</item>
        <item><val>-1.76E11</val> (電子の電荷(クローン))</item>
      </list>
    </p>
    <p> 仮数部と指数部を分ける記号は<mentioned>e</mentioned>または <mentioned>E</mentioned>のどちらでもよいが，当ガイドラインでは
        <mentioned>E</mentioned>を使うことを推奨する．これは，他の規格との 整合性を保ち，数学における定数との混同を避けるためである． </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks version="2009-10-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <p> Toute valeur numérique, représentée en nombre décimal, notée en virgule flottante ou
      en fraction.</p>
    <p>Pour représenter un nombre en virgule flottante, exprimé en notation scientifique,
        <soCalled>E notation</soCalled>, une variante de la <soCalled>notation
      exponentielle</soCalled>peut être utilisée. Dans ce format, la valeur est exprimée par deux
      nombres séparés par la lettre E. Le premier facteur, le significande (parfois appelé mantisse)
      est donné sous forme décimale, tandis que le second est un entier. La valeur est obtenue en
      multipliant la mantisse par 10 fois le nombre indiqué par l'entier. Ainsi la valeur
      représentée en notation décimale 1000.0 pourrait être représentée en notation
      scientifique 10E3.</p>
    <p>Une valeur exprimée en fraction est représentée par deux nombres entiers séparés par une
      barre oblique (/). Ainsi, la valeur représentée en notation décimale 0.5 pourrait être
      représentée en fraction par la chaîne de caractères 1/2.</p>
  </remarks>
</macroSpec>
