<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright TEI Consortium. 
  Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
  See the file COPYING.txt for details
  $Date$
  $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="del">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>deletion</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">삭제</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">刪除</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2008-12-09" xml:lang="fr">suppression</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">cancelación</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">cancellatura</gloss>
  <desc>contains a letter, word, or passage deleted, marked as deleted, or otherwise indicated as
    superfluous or spurious in the copy text by an author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">삭제된 것으로 표시되었거나, 저자, 전사자, 부호화자 또는 수정작업자에 의해 사본 텍스트에서
    불필요하거나 위조된 것으로 표시되어 삭제된 문자, 단어, 단락을 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標記在文本中，由作者、抄寫者、註解者、或更正者刪除、標上刪除記號、或者標明為多餘或偽造的字母或單字。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 著者・筆写者・注釈者・校正者により，削除または削除として符号化または
    余分なものまたは間違いとして示されている，文字，単語，句を示す． </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">contient une lettre, un mot ou un passage supprimé,
    marqué comme supprimé, sinon indiqué comme superflu ou erroné dans le texte par un auteur, un
    copiste, un annotateur ou un correcteur.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una letra, palabra o pasaje cancelado, marcado
    como omitido o bien como supérfluo o espurio en el texto por el autor, transcriptor, glosador o
    corrector.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene un carattere, parola o brano cancellati,
    codificati come cancellati, o altrimenti indicati come superflui o spuri, nella copia originale
    da parte di un autore, copista, commentatore o correttore.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
    <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.paraContent"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="mul">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
      <l><del rend="overtyped">Mein</del> Frisch <del rend="overstrike" type="primary">schwebt</del>
        weht der Wind</l>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <del rend="overstrike"><gap reason="illegible" quantity="5" unit="character"/></del>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Gide_Journal">
      <p>[...] mais il y reste quelque chose de mystérieux, de furtif. <del rend="overtyped">Je</del> On cesse un instant d'y penser; <del rend="overstrike">les </del>mes yeux se
          ferment ou <del rend="overstrike">s'attardent sur </del> se détournent sur un livre... On
          relève la tête: il est là </p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <l><del rend="改寫">雨</del> 風 <del rend="改寫" type="primary">飄</del> 吹來涼爽。</l>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>Degrees of uncertainty over what can still be read, or whether a deletion was intended may be
      indicated by use of the <gi>certainty</gi> element (see <ptr target="#CE"/>).</p>
    <p>This element should be used for deletion of shorter sequences of text, typically single words
      or phrases. The <gi>delSpan</gi> element should be used for longer sequences of text, for
      those containing structural subdivisions, and for those containing overlapping additions and
      deletions.</p>
    <p>The text deleted must be at least partially legible in order for the encoder to be able to
      transcribe it (unless it is restored in a <gi>supplied</gi> tag). Illegible or lost text within a 
      deletion may be marked using the <gi>gap</gi> tag to signal that text is present but has not
      been transcribed, or is no longer visible. Attributes on the <gi>gap</gi>
      element may be used to indicate how much text is omitted, the reason for omitting it, etc. If
      text is not fully legible, the <gi>unclear</gi> element (available when using the additional
      tagset for transcription of primary sources) should be used to signal the areas of text which
      cannot be read with confidence in a similar way.</p>
    <p>There is a clear distinction in the TEI between <gi>del</gi>, which is a statement of the
     the or a later scribe's intent to cancel or remove text, and elements such as 
      <gi>gap</gi> or <gi>unclear</gi> which signal the editor's decision to omit or inability to read the text
      remaining.
    See further sections <ptr target="#PHOM"/> and, for the close association of the
      <gi>del</gi> tag with the <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>,
        <gi>unclear</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> elements (the latter three tags available when using
      the additional tagset for transcription of primary sources), <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>.</p>
    <p>The <gi>del</gi> tag should not be used for deletions made by editors or encoders. In these
      cases, either <gi>corr</gi>, <gi>surplus</gi> or <gi>gap</gi> should be used.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cf. <gi>gap</gi>.</p>
    <p>Les degrés d'incertitude sur ce qui est encore lisible peuvent être indiqués par l'emploi de
      l'élément <gi>certainty</gi> (voir <ptr target="#CE"/>).</p>
    <p>Cet élément doit être utilisé pour la suppression de courtes séquences de texte, généralement
      des mots ou des expressions. Il faut utiliser l'élément <gi>delSpan</gi> pour les séquences de
      texte plus longues, celles qui contiennent des divisions structurelles, et celles qui
      contiennent un chevauchement d'ajouts et de suppressions.</p>
    <p>Le texte supprimé doit être au moins partiellement lisible, afin que l'encodeur soit en
      mesure de le transcrire. La partie illisible du texte à l'intérieur d'une suppression peut être
      marquée au moyen de la balise <gi>gap</gi> pour signaler la présence de texte non transcrit.
      La quantité de texte omise, la raison de l'omission, etc., peuvent être indiqués au moyen des
      attributs de l'élément <gi>gap</gi>. Si le texte n'est pas entièrement lisible, l'élément
        <gi>unclear</gi> (disponible avec le jeu additionnel de balises pour la transcription des
      sources primaires) doit être utilisé pour signaler les zones de texte ne pouvant pas être lues
      de manière fiable. Voir les sections suivantes <ptr target="#PHOM"/> et, pour l'association
      étroite entre les balises <gi>del</gi> et <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi> et
        <gi>supplied</gi> (ces trois dernières balises étant disponibles avec le jeu additionnel de
      balises pour la transcription de sources primaires), voir la section <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>.</p>
    <p>La balise <gi>del</gi> ne doit pas être utilisée pour les suppressions par des éditeurs
      scientifiques ou des encodeurs. Dans ce cas, il faut utiliser soit la balise <gi>corr</gi>,
      soit la balise <gi>gap</gi>. </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p><gi>gap</gi>を参照のこと．</p>
    <p> 当該解釈の確信度は要素<gi>certainty</gi>で示される (<ptr target="#CE"/>を参照のこと)． </p>
    <p> 当該要素は，短いテキスト部分，例えばひつとの単語や句が削除されてい る時に使用されるべきである．要素<gi>delSpan</gi>は，より大きなテキ
      スト部分，例えば，下位構造を含むものや追加と削除をともに含むような ものが削除されているときに使用されるべきである． </p>
    <p> 当該削除されているテキストは，少なくとも転記するに充分なほどには読 めるものでなければならない．全く読めないのであれば，要素
        <gi>del</gi>は使うべきではない．この場合には，要素<gi>gap</gi>を使 い，転記できない単一のテキスト部分を示すべきである．この際，属性
      <att>reason</att>により転記ができない理由が削除であることを示すこ とができる．全てが読めるわけではないという場合には，要素
      <gi>unclear</gi>を使い，確信が持てないが読めるひとつのテキスト部分 を示すべきである．詳しくは，<ptr target="#PHOM"/>を参照のこと．
        また，要素<gi>del</gi>と要素<gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi>,
      <gi>supplied</gi>との関係については， <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>を参照のこと(damageとsuppliedは元資料を転記
      するための追加モジュールを使用する際に使うことができる)． </p>
    <p> 要素<gi>del</gi>は，編集者や符号化する人による削除部分に使用される べきではない．この場合は，要素<gi>corr</gi>または要素<gi>gap</gi>
      が使われるべきである． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COEDADD" type="div3"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
