<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="transcr" xml:id="DELSPAN" usage="opt" ident="delSpan">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>deleted span of text</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">porzione di testo cancellata</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">fragmento de texto omitido</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">削除範囲</gloss>
  <desc>marks the beginning of a longer sequence of text deleted,
marked as deleted, or otherwise signaled as superfluous or spurious by an
author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">segnala l'inizio di una porzione di testo più lunga cancellata, indicata come cancellata, o indicata come superflua o spuria da un autore, un trascrittore, un annotatore o un correttore</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala el inicio de un fragmento largo de texto omitido, o marcado como cancelado o como supérfluo o espurio, por un autor, un transcriptor, un comentarista o un corrector.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja"> 削除されるテキスト部分の始点を示す．</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.global.edit"/>
    <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.authorialIntervention"/>
    <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
  </classes>
  <content xmlns:s="http://www.ascc.net/xml/schematron" xmlns:tei="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <rng:empty xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
    <s:pattern name="spanTo_required">
      <s:rule context="tei:delSpan">
        <s:assert test="@spanTo">The spanTo= attribute of <s:name/> is required.</s:assert>
      </s:rule>
    </s:pattern>
  </content>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>Paragraph partially deleted.  This is the undeleted
portion <delSpan spanTo="#a23"/>and this the deleted
portion of the paragraph.</p>
      <p>Paragraph deleted together with adjacent material.</p>
      <p>Second fully deleted paragraph.</p>
      <p>Paragraph partially deleted; in the middle of this
paragraph the deletion ends and the anchor point marks
the resumption <anchor xml:id="a23"/> of the text. ...</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>Both the beginning and ending of the deleted sequence must be
    marked: the beginning by the <gi>delSpan</gi> element, the ending
    by the target of the <att>spanTo</att> attribute.</p>
    <p>The text deleted must be at least partially legible, in order
    for the encoder to be able to transcribe it. If it is not legible
    at all, the <gi>delSpan</gi> tag should not be used. Rather, the
    <gi>gap</gi> tag should be employed to signal that text cannot be
    transcribed, with the value of the <att>reason</att> attribute
    giving the cause for the omission from the transcription as
    deletion. If it is not fully legible, the <gi>unclear</gi> element
    should be used to signal the areas of text which cannot be read
    with confidence. See further sections <ptr target="#PHOM"/> and,
    for the close association of the <gi>delSpan</gi> tag with the
    <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi> and
    <gi>supplied</gi> elements, <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>.</p>
    <p>The <gi>delSpan</gi> tag should not be used for deletions made
    by editors or encoders. In these cases, either the <gi>corr</gi>
    tag or the <gi>gap</gi> tag should be used.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#PHAD"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
