<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright TEI Consortium.
    Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
    See the file COPYING.txt for details
    $Date$
    $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="foreign">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>foreign</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">외국어</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">外文</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">étranger</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">extranjero</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">straniero</gloss>
  <desc>identifies a word or phrase as belonging to some language other than that of the
                surrounding text. </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">주변 텍스트와 다른 언어로 사용된 단어나 구를 표시한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標明所屬語言不同於週遭文字的字詞。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 記述のベースで使われている言語と異なる言語による語句を定義する． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">reconnaît un mot ou une expression comme
                appartenant à une langue différente de celle du contexte. </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">identidica una palabra o frase perteneciente a otra
                lengua distinta de la del resto del texto en que se incluye.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">identifica una parola o un sintagma appartenente ad
                una lingua diversa da quella del testo circostante.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.emphLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.phraseSeq"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#DRPAL-eg-44">This is
                        heathen Greek to you still? Your <foreign xml:lang="la">lapis
                        philosophicus</foreign>?</egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#fr-ex-Queneau_Journ">
      <p>Pendant ce temps-là, dans le bureau du rez- de-chaussée, les secrétaires faisaient du
            <foreign xml:lang="en">hulla-hoop</foreign>.</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> 整天窩在家裏看卡通打電動，你是<foreign xml:lang="ja">御宅族</foreign>嗎?</egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The global <att>xml:lang</att> attribute should be supplied for this element to
                        identify the language of the word or phrase marked. As elsewhere, its value
                        should be a language tag as defined in <ptr target="#CHSH"/>.</p>
    <p>This element is intended for use only where no other element is available to mark
                        the phrase or words concerned. The global <att>xml:lang</att> attribute
                        should be used in preference to this element where it is intended to mark
                        the language of the whole of some text element.</p>
    <p>The <gi>distinct</gi> element may be used to identify phrases belonging to
                        sublanguages or registers not generally regarded as true languages.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>L'attribut global <att>xml:lang</att> doit être fourni dans cet élément pour
                        identifier la langue à laquelle appartiennenent le mot ou l'expression
                        balisée. Comme ailleurs, sa valeur devrait être une balise de langue définie
                        dans <ptr target="#CHSH"/>.</p>
    <p>Cet élément n'est utilisé que lorsqu'il n'y a pas d'autre élément disponible pour
                        baliser l'expression ou les mots concernés. L'attribut global
                        <att>xml:lang</att> doit être préféré à cet élément lorsqu'il s'agit de
                        caractériser la langue de l'ensemble d'un élément textuel.</p>
    <p>L'élément <gi>distinct</gi> peut être utilisé pour identifier des expressions
                        appartenant à des variétés de langue ou à des registres qui ne sont pas
                        généralement considérés comme de vraies langues.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>El atributo global <att>xml:lang</att> se debe suministrar para que este
                        elemento identifique la lengua de la palabra o de la frase marcada. Como en
                        otras partes, su valor debe ser una etiqueta de lengua según lo definido en
                                <ptr target="#CHSH"/>.</p>
    <p>Este elemento se reserva para los casos en que no hay disponible otro elemento
                        para marcar la frase o las palabras referidas. Es preferente el uso del
                        atributo global <att>xml:lang</att> a este elemento donde se quiere marcar
                        la lengua del conjunto de un cierto elemento del texto.</p>
    <p> El elemento <gi>distinto</gi> se puede utilizar para identificar las frases que
                        pertenecen a sublenguajes o a registros no considerados generalmente como
                        lenguas verdaderas.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> マークアップされた語句の言語を特定するには，グローバル属性 <att>xml:lang</att>を使うべきである．その値は<ptr target="#CHSH"/>で 定義されている言語コードであるべきである． </p>
    <p> 当該要素は，当該語句に他の要素が使えない時にのみ使用されることが期 待されている．グローバル属性<att>xml:lang</att>が，テキスト全体の言
                        語を示すために使用されている場合でも，当該要素の言語を指示するために 使用されるべきである． </p>
    <p> 要素<gi>distinct</gi>は，特殊言語，すなわち正統な言語とは一般には 認められていない言語による語句を示す場合にも使われるかもしれない． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COHQHF"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
