<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="iso-fs" ident="fsDecl">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>feature structure declaration</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">자질 구조 선언</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">자질 구조 선언</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">功能結構宣告</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">déclaration de structure de traits</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declaración de estructura de rasgo</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">dichiarazione della struttura di tratti</gloss>
  <desc>declares one type of feature structure.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">하나의 자질 구조 유형을 선언한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">자질 구조의 유형을 선언한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">宣告一種功能結構類型。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  ひとつの素性構造を宣言する．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">déclare un type de structure de traits</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declara un tipo de estructura de rasgo</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">dichiara un tipo di struttura di tratti</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:optional>
        <rng:ref name="fsDescr"/>
      </rng:optional>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="fDecl"/>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
      <rng:optional>
        <rng:ref name="fsConstraints"/>
      </rng:optional>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="req">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>gives a name for the type of feature structure being declared.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">선언되고 있는 자질 구조 유형의 이름을 제시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">선언된 자질 구조의 유형명을 제시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供所宣告的功能結構的類型名稱。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      宣言された素性構造の名前を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">attribue un nom au type de structure de traits
          déclaré.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona un nombre para el tipo de estructura de rasgo que está siendo declarada.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">fornisce il nome per il tipo di struttura di tratti che si sta dichiarando.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any convenient string of characters.</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">toute chaîne de caractères pertinente.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="baseTypes" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>gives the name of one or more typed feature structures
	from which this type inherits feature specifications and
	constraints; 	
	if this type includes a feature specification
	with the same name as that of any of those specified by this
	attribute, or if more than one specification of the same name
	is inherited, then the set of possible values is defined by
	unification. Similarly, the set of constraints applicable is
	derived by combining those specified explicitly within this
	element with those implied by the <att>baseTypes</att>
	attribute. When no <att>baseTypes</att> attribute is specified, no
	feature specification or constraint is inherited.
 
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">유형으로부터 상속받은 자질 명세와 제약으로 구성된 하나 이상의 유형화된 자질 구조의 이름을 제시한다; 만약 이 유형이 속성에 의해 명시된 것과 동일한 이름을 갖는 자질 명세를 포함한다면, 또는 동일 이름의 하나 이상의 명세가 상속된다면, 가능한 값의 집합은 통합에 의해 정의된다. 비슷하게 적용가능한 제약 집합이 <att>baseTypes</att> 속성에 의해 지시된 제약을 가진 요소 내에서 명백하게 명시된 제약의 결합에 의해 도출된다. <att>baseType</att>이 명시되지 않았다면, 어떤 자질 명세 또는 제약도 상속되지 않는다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 유형이 자질 명세와 제약을 상속받는 하나 이상의 유형화된 자질 구조의 이름을 제시한다. 만약 동일 이름의 자질 명세를 이 유형이 포함하거나, 동일 이름의 명세가 여럿이라면, 가능한 값의 집합은 통합에 의해 정의된다. 비슷하게, 적용 가능한 제약들의 집합은 이 요소들 내에서 명시된 자질 명세나 제약과 <att>baseTypes</att> 요소에 의해 의미된 자질 명세나 제약을 결합하여 도출된다. <att>baseTypes</att>가 명시되어 있지 않다면 자질 명세나 제약이 상속되지 않는다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供一個或多個已分類的功能結構名稱，此類型從該功能結構中獲得功能細節與限制；若該類型包含的功能細節名稱同於此屬性所標明的任一功能細節，或者該類型獲得一個以上同名的功能細節，則所有可能的屬性值是為統一定義。同樣地，適用限制的衍生，是將此元素中所明確標明的和屬性<att>baseType</att>所標明的結合。若未使用屬性<att>baseType</att>，則沒有獲得任何功能細節或限制。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      ひとつ以上の素性構造を示す．ここから，属性typeは素性定義・制約を
      継承する．属性typeが当該属性で示されたものと同名の素性定義を含む
      場合，またはひとつ以上の同名素性定義を継承する場合，それらの値は
      統合される．同様に，当該属性<att>baseTypes</att>にある値と，当該
      要素が持つ内容を統合して制約となる．属性<att>baseType</att>が付
      与されていない場合，継承される素性定義や素性制約はない．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-04-16" xml:lang="fr">donne le nom d'une ou plusieurs structures de
          traits "type", de laquelle ou desquelles il hérite des spécifications et des contraintes de traits. Si
          ce type inclut une spécification de traits du même nom que l'une de celles spécifiées par
          cet attribut, ou si plus d'une spécification du même nom est transmise par héritage,
          l'ensemble des valeurs possibles est définie par unification. De même, l'ensemble des
          contraintes applicables résulte de la combinaison de celles qui sont spécifiées
          explicitement à l'intérieur de cet élément et de celles qui découlent de l'attribut
            <att>baseTypes</att>. Quand aucun attribut <att>baseTypes</att> n'est précisé, aucune
          spécification de traits ni contrainte n'est transmise par héritage.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona el nombre de una o más estructura de rasgo dadas, de las cuales este tipo hereda especificaciones de rasgo y restricciones; si este tipo incluye una especificación de rasgo con el mismo nombre que las especificadas por este atributo, o si más de una especificación con el mismo nombre se hereda, entonces el conjunto de posibles valores se definen por la unión de estas. De la misma manera, el conjunto de restricciones aplicable se deriva de la combinación de las restricciones especificadas explícitamente dentro de este elemento con aquellas referidas por el atributo <att>baseTypes</att>. Cuando no se especifica ningún <att>baseTypes</att>, no se hereda ninguna especificación de rasgo o restricción.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">fornisce il nome ad una o più tipi di strutture di tratti dai quali il tipo eredita le specifiche e i vincoli dei tratti;
        se questo tipo include una specifica di tratti con lo stesso nome specificato da questo attributo, o se più di una specifica dello stesso nome è ereditata, allora l'insieme dei possibili valori è definito
        attraverso l'unificazione. In modo analogo, l'insieme dei vincoli applicabile deriva dalla combinazione di quelli specificati in modo esplicito all'interno dell'elemento con quelli sottintesi dall'attributo <att>baseTypes</att>
        Se nessun <att>baseTypes</att> è specificato, nessuna specificazione o vincolo di tratti è ereditata.</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more names as defined by the <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#dt-name">W3C XML
      Specification</ref></valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">un ou plusieurs noms tels que définis par la <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#dt-name">Spécification XML du W3C</ref>.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Inheritance is defined here as a monotonous relation.</p>
        <p>The process of combining constraints
	may result in a contradiction, for example if two
	specifications for the same feature
	specify disjoint ranges of values, and at least one such
	specification is mandatory. In such a case, there is
	no valid representative for the type being defined. </p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>L'héritage est défini ici comme une relation monotone.</p>
        <p>La combinaison de contraintes peut générer une contradiction, par exemple si
                        deux spécifications données pour le même trait présentent des plages
                        disjointes de valeurs et qu'au moins une de ces spécifications est
                        obligatoire. Dans ce cas, il n'y a pas de représentant valide du type
                        défini.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>ここでの継承は，単調な関係である．</p>
        <p>
	複数の制約を統合することで，矛盾が起きるかもしれない．例え
      ば，同じ素性に2つの定義が重なりのない素性値域を指定し，少なくと
      もそのうちの1つが必須である場合である．このような時は，属性type
      にとって妥当な値がなくなる．
      </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible">
      <fsDecl type="SomeName">
        <fsDescr>Describes what this type of fs represents</fsDescr>
        <fDecl name="featureOne">
          <!-- The declaration for featureOne -->
          <vRange>
            <!-- the range of possible values for this feature -->
          </vRange>
        </fDecl>
        <fDecl name="featureTwo">
          <!-- The declaration for featureTwo -->
          <vRange>
            <!-- the range of possible values for this feature -->
          </vRange>
        </fDecl>
        <fsConstraints>
          <!-- Any additional constraints for the feature structure -->
        </fsConstraints>
      </fsDecl>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#FD"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
