<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" module="core" xml:id="GAP" usage="opt" ident="gap">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">material omitido</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">omitted material</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">materiale omesso</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">欠落</gloss>
  <desc>indicates a point where material has been omitted in a
transcription, whether for editorial reasons described in the TEI
header, as part of sampling practice, or because the material is
illegible or inaudible.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica un punto in cui del materiale è stato omesso dalla trascrizione, sia per ragioni editoriali descritte nell'intestazione TEI, come pratica di campionatura, sia perché il materiale è illegibile o incomprensibile.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indicada un punto donde algún material ha sido omitido en una transcripción, bien por criterios de edición descritos en el cabezado TEI, bien como parte de una práctica habitual, o bien porqué el material es ilegible o incomprensible.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja"> TEIヘダーに記載されている編集上の理由で，または，判別不可
 能であるために，転記の際に欠落しているものの場所を示す．</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.global.edit"/>
    <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:ref name="macro.glossSeq"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="reason" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>gives the reason for omission. Sample values include
      <val>sampling</val>, <val>illegible</val>, <val>inaudible</val>,
      <val>irrelevant</val>, <val>cancelled</val>, <val>cancelled and
      illegible</val>.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il motivo dell'omisione. Fra i valori possibili ci sono <mentioned>campionatura</mentioned>, <mentioned>illegibile</mentioned>, <mentioned>incomprensibile</mentioned>, <mentioned>irrilevante</mentioned>, <mentioned>cancellato</mentioned>, <mentioned>cancellato e illegibile</mentioned>.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declara la causa de la
      omisión. Los valores de muestra incluyen <val>sampling
      (ejemplificación)</val>, <val>illegible (ilegible)</val>,
      <val>inaudible (inaudible)</val>, <val>irrelevant
      (irrelevante)</val>, <val>cancelled (cancelado)</val>,
      <val>cancelled and illegible (cancelado e
      ilegible)</val>.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">欠落の理由．判読できない，
      聞き取れない，不適切，取り消しの指示があるなど．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref name="data.word"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any short indication of the reason for the omission.</valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="hand" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>in the case of text omitted from the transcription because of
deliberate deletion by an identifiable hand, signifies the hand which
made the deletion.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">nel caso in cui il testo sia stato volontariamente omesso dalla trascrizione da una mano identificabile, indica la mano autrice dell'omissione</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">en el caso de texto omitido en la transcripción a causa de una supresión deliberada por una mano identidicada, indica la mano que ha ejecutado la omisión.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">転記の際，判読できない手書きの部分を，熟考の上でテキストを省略し
た場合，その理由を記述する．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>must be one of the hand identifiers declared in the document
header (see section <ptr target="#PHDH"/>).</valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="agent" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>In the case of text omitted because of damage, categorizes the cause of the damage, if it can be identified.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">nel caso in cui il testo sia stato omesse a causa di danneggiamento, indica la causa del danno qualora possa essere identificata.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">En el caso de texto omitido a causa de algún daño, identifica (si es posible) la causa de tal daño.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">転記の際，破損のために省略した場合，その破損の種類を記述する．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valList type="open">
        <valItem ident="rubbing">
          <desc>damage results from rubbing of the
  leaf edges</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">daño provocado por el roce de los bordes de hojas</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="mildew">
          <desc>damage results from mildew on the leaf surface</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">daño resultante de la presencia de moho en la superficie del folio.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="smoke">
          <desc>damage results from smoke</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">daño causado por el humo.</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
    </attDef>
<!--    <attDef ident="agent" usage="opt">
	<equiv/>
	<desc>because of
damage or other phenomenon  resulting from an identifiable cause,
signifies the causative agent.</desc>
      <datatype><rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/></datatype>
      <valDesc>any prose description of the agency of damage.</valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
    </attDef>-->
    <attDef ident="extent" usage="opt">
      <desc>indicates approximately how much text has been omitted
      from the transcription (using the unit specified on the
      <att>unit</att> attribute), either because of editorial policy
      or because a deletion, damage, or other cause has rendered
      transcription impossible.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">indicates approximately how much text has been omitted from the transcription, in letters, minims, inches, or any appropriate unit, either because of editorial policy or because a deletion, damage, or other cause has rendered transcription impossible.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica approssimativamente la quantità di testo omessa dalla trascrizione in lettere, uncini, pollici, o altre unità di misura,sia a causa di politica editoriale sia a causa di danneggiamento, o per altre cause che hanno impossibilitato la trascrizione.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica aproximadamente en letras, pulgadas o en alguna otra unidad funcional, cuánto texto ha sido omitido en la transcripción, bien por razones editoriales o bien a causa de una supresión, daño u otra causa que haya provocado que la transcripción sea imposible. </desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">転記の際，編集上の基準に従った結果として，または削除，損傷などの
理由により転記が困難であったために，どの程度のテキストを省略した
のか，文字，インチ，などの単位を使い，その概算を記述する．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref name="data.numeric"/>
      </datatype>
      <remarks>
        <p>It is possible, but not always necessary, to provide
measurements precise to the millimeter or even to the printer's
point. The degree of precision attempted will vary with the purpose
of the encoding and the nature of the material.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="unit" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>names the unit used for describing the extent of the gap</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica las unidades usadas para la medición.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該数値の単位を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valList type="semi">
        <valItem ident="lines">
          <desc>lines of text</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="chars">
          <gloss>characters</gloss>
          <desc>characters of text</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="pages">
          <desc>pages, i.e. one side of a leaf</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="cm">
          <gloss>centimetres</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">centímetros</gloss>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="mm">
          <gloss>millimetres</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">milímetros</gloss>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="in">
          <gloss>inches</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">pulgadas</gloss>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <gap extent="4" unit="chars" reason="illegible"/>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <gap extent="1" unit="essay" reason="sampling"/>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi>, and <gi>del</gi> core tag
    elements may be closely allied in use with the <gi>damage</gi> and
    <gi>supplied</gi> elements, available when using the additional
    tagset for transcription of primary sources. See section <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/> for discussion of which element is appropriate
    for which circumstance.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COEDADD" type="div1"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
