<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="transcr" ident="handShift">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">reprise de main</gloss>
  <desc>marks the beginning of a sequence of text written in a new
hand, or the beginning of a scribal stint.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">새로운 필적으로 기록된 텍스트 연쇄의 시작 또는 필기 부분의 시작을 표시한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標記連續文字中轉換書寫者的開始，或是一個抄寫工作的開始。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  テキストにおける新しい筆致の始まり，または筆写者の仕事の開始を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">marque le début d'une section du texte écrite par une nouvelle main ou le début d'une nouvelle séance d'écriture.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">marca el principio de un fragmento de texto atribuible a otra mano distinta o a un cambio de redactor, estilo de escritura, tinta o letra.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">segnala l'inizio di una porzione di testo attribuibile ad un'altra mano o riconducibile a un cambio di redattore, stile di scrittura, inchiostro o carattere</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
    <memberOf key="att.handFeatures"/>
    <memberOf key="att.responsibility"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:empty xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="new" usage="rec">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>identifies the new hand.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">새 필적을 식별한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">表示新的書寫者。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該新しい筆致を特定する．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">donne l'identifiant de la nouvelle main.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">identifica una nueva mano.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la nuova mano</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>must refer to a <gi>handNote</gi> element, typically but not necessarily
      declared in the current document header (see section <ptr target="#PHDH"/>).</valDesc>
      <valDesc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">doit faire référence à un élément <gi>handNote</gi>, en général déclaré dans l'en-tête TEI (voir la section <ptr target="#PHDH"/>).</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>This attribute serves the same function as the
<att>hand</att> attribute provided for those elements which are members of the
<ident type="class">att.transcriptional</ident> class. It may be
renamed at a subsequent major release. </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <l>When wolde the cat dwelle in his ynne</l>
      <handShift medium="greenish-ink"/>
      <l>And if the cattes skynne be slyk <handShift medium="black-ink"/> and gaye</l>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The <gi>handShift</gi> element may be used either to
denote a shift in the document hand (as from one scribe to another,
on one writing style to another).  Or, it may indicate a shift within
a document hand, as a change of writing style, character or ink. Like
    other milestone elements, it should appear at the point of
    transition from some other state to the state which it describes.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>L'élément <gi>handShift</gi>peut être utilisé soit pour noter un changement de main
dans le document (comme le passage d'un scribe à un autre, d'un style d'écriture à un
autre), soit pour indiquer un changement dans la main, comme un changement d'écriture, de caractère ou d'encre.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    当該<gi>handShift</gi>要素は，文書中における筆致の変わり目(ある筆
      写者から別の筆写者，または，ある書記スタイルから別の書記スタイル
      への変化)を示すために使われるかもしれない．または，同じ筆致にお
      いても，書記スタイルや，文字，インクの変わり目を示すために使われ
      るかもしれない．
      </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#PHDH"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
