<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright TEI Consortium.
    Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
    See the file COPYING.txt for details
    $Date$
    $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="head">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>heading</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">표제부</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標題</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">en-tête</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">encabezamiento</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">titolo</gloss>
  <desc>contains any type of heading, for example the title of a section, or the heading of a list,
    glossary, manuscript description, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">예를 들어 절의 제목 또는 용어집, 원고 기술의 제목 등과 같이 표제부 유형을 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含任何種類的標題，如章節、列表、詞彙表、寫本描述等的標題。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 各種の見出しを示す．例えば，節のタイトル，リストや用語集，手書き資料 の解説などにある見出し． </desc>
  <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">contient tout type d'en-tête, par exemple le titre d'une
    section, ou l'intitulé d'une liste, d'un glossaire, d'une description de manuscrit, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene cualquier tipo de encabezamiento, por ejemplo el
    título de una sección o el encabezado de una lista, glosario, descripción de un manuscrito, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene qualsiasi tipo di titolo, per esempio il titolo
    di una sezione, di una lista, di un glossario, di una descrizione di manoscritto, ecc.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="model.headLike"/>
    <memberOf key="model.pLike.front"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <zeroOrMore xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <choice>
        <text/>
	<ref name="lg"/>
        <ref name="model.gLike"/>
        <ref name="model.phrase"/>
        <ref name="model.inter"/>
	<ref name="model.lLike"/>
        <ref name="model.global"/>
      </choice>
    </zeroOrMore>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>The most common use for the <gi>head</gi> element is to mark the headings of sections. In
      older writings, the headings or <term>incipits</term> may be rather longer than usual in
      modern works. If a section has an explicit ending as well as a heading, it should be marked as
      a <gi>trailer</gi>, as in this example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div1 n="I" type="book">
        <head>In the name of Christ here begins the first book of the ecclesiastical history of
          Georgius Florentinus, known as Gregory, Bishop of Tours.</head>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>In the name of Christ here begins Book I of the history.</head>
          <p>Proposing as I do ...</p>
          <p>From the Passion of our Lord until the death of Saint Martin four hundred and twelve
            years passed.</p>
          <trailer>Here ends the first Book, which covers five thousand, five hundred and ninety-six
            years from the beginning of the world down to the death of Saint Martin.</trailer>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <p xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">L'élément<gi>head</gi>est employé habituellement pour marquer les titres de sections. Dans
        d'anciens textes , les titres des textes conclusifs seront précédés de l'élément
        <gi>trailer</gi>, comme dans cet exemple : </p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Galland_Mille">
      <div type="chapitre">
        <head>Les Mille et une Nuits</head>
        <p>LES chroniques des Sassaniens, anciens rois de Perse, qui avaient étendu leur empire
            dans les Indes, [...]</p>
        <div type="histoire">
          <head>Histoire du Vizir puni</head>
          <p>IL était autrefois un roi, poursuivit-il, qui avait un<lb/> fils qui aimait
              passionnément la chasse. Il lui permettait<lb/> de prendre souvent ce divertissement ;
              [...] </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <trailer>
        <hi rend="majuscule">fin du tome premier.</hi>
      </trailer>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <p xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">L'élément <gi>head</gi> est aussi employé pour donner un titre à d'autres éléments, dans
        une liste par exemple :</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Etudes_Litt"> Les déictiques
        sont des termes qui ne prennent leur sens que dans le cadre de la situation d'énonciation.
          <list type="simple"><head>déictiques</head><item>ici</item><item>hier</item><item>là</item><item>je</item><item>tu</item><item>nous</item><item>vous</item><item/></list>
      </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#biblzh-tw_n6">
      <div1 n="I" type="book">
        <head>三國演義</head>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>第一回 宴桃園豪杰三結義 斬黃巾英雄首立功</head>
          <p>滾滾長江東逝水，浪花淘盡英雄。是非成敗轉頭空。 青山依舊在，几度夕陽紅。 白發漁樵江渚上，慣看秋月春風。一壺濁酒喜相逢。古今多少事，都付笑談中。</p>
          <p>話說天下大勢，分久必合，合久必分。周末七國分爭，并入于秦。...</p>
          <trailer>三人救了董卓回寨。卓問三人現居何職。玄德曰：白身。...畢竟董卓性命如何，且听下文分解。</trailer>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> 除了少數特例，連接詞均用於所有論述，例如描述、記敘、闡述、論說。<list type="simple"><head>連接詞</head><item>上述的</item><item>因此</item><item>在…的對面</item><item>比鄰於</item><item>再次</item><item><!-- ... --></item></list>
      </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>The <gi>head</gi> element is also used to mark headings of other units, such as lists:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">With a few exceptions, connectives are equally
      useful in all kinds of discourse: description, narration, exposition, argument. <list type="simple"><head>Connectives</head><item>above</item><item>accordingly</item><item>across from</item><item>adjacent to</item><item>again</item><item><!-- ... --></item></list>
      </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The <gi>head</gi> element is used for headings at all levels; software which treats (e.g.)
      chapter headings, section headings, and list titles differently must determine the proper
      processing of a <gi>head</gi> element based on its structural position. A <gi>head</gi>
      occurring as the first element of a list is the title of that list; one occurring as the first
      element of a <gi>div1</gi> is the title of that chapter or section.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>L'élément <gi>head</gi> est utilisé pour les titres de tous niveaux ; un logiciel qui
      traitera différemment, par exemple, les titres de chapitres, les titres de sections et les
      titres de listes, devra déterminer le traitement approprié de l'élément <gi>head</gi>
      rencontré en fonction de sa position dans la structure XML. Un élément <gi>head</gi> qui est
      le premier élément d'une liste est le titre de cette liste ; si l'élément <gi>head</gi>
      apparaît comme le premier élément d'un élément <gi>div1</gi>, il sera considéré comme le titre
      de ce chapitre ou de cette section.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 要素<gi>head</gi>は，各種レベル上にある見出しに使用される．例えば， 章や節，リストの見出しを扱うソフトウェアは，構造中の場所により要素
        <gi>head</gi>の扱いを適切に行う必要がある．要素<gi>head</gi>が，リス トの第一項目に出現した場合，それは当該リストのタイトルになる．例えば，
        要素<gi>div1</gi>の第一項目として当該要素が出現した場合，それは章ま たは節の見出しとされる． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <!--    <ptr target="#COLI" type="div2"/>-->
    <ptr target="#DSHD" type="div2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
