<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright TEI Consortium. Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences See the file COPYING.txt for details $Date$ $Id$ -->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" module="linking" ident="link">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr"> lien</gloss>
  <desc>defines an association or hypertextual link among elements or passages, of some type not more precisely specifiable by other elements.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">다른 요소들에 의해 좀 더 명확하게 명시되지 않는 유형의 요소 또는 단락들의 연관 또는 하이퍼텍스트 연결을 정의한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">定義元素或段落之間的關連或超文字連結，其他元素無法將此連結類型作更詳細說明。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 他の要素では上手く示せない，要素や一節間にある関連性やハイパーテキス トリンクを定義する． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">définit une association ou un lien hypertextuel entre des éléments ou des passages, lien dont le type ne peut être spécifié précisément par d'autres éléments.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define una asociación o vínculo hipertextual entre elementos o fragmentos de texto que no es especificable por otros elementos.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce tra elementi o porzioni di testo un'associazione o legame ipertestuale non meglio specificabile da altri elementi</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.pointing"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:empty xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
  <constraintSpec ident="linkTargets1" scheme="isoschematron">
    <constraint>
      <sch:report test="@target and @targets">You may not supply both 
	@target and @targets on <sch:name/></sch:report>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <constraintSpec ident="linkTargets2" scheme="isoschematron">
    <constraint>
      <sch:report test="not(@target) and not(@targets)">You must
	supply either @target or @targets on <sch:name/></sch:report>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <constraintSpec ident="linkTargets3" scheme="isoschematron">
    <constraint>
      <sch:assert test="contains(@target,' ')">You must supply at least two
values for @target on <sch:name/></sch:assert>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="targets" usage="opt"  status="deprecated">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>specifies the identifiers of the elements or passages to be linked or associated. </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">연결 또는 연관된 요소 또는 단락의 확인소를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標明被連結元素或段落的識別符碼。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> リンク付けされれている当該要素または一節の識別子を示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">spécifie les identifiants des éléments ou des passages à lier ou à associer.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica los identificadores de los elementos o divisiones de texto que son enlazados o asociados.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica gli identificatori degli elementi o porzioni di testo da associare</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="2" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>two or more pointers (URIs), separated by whitespace</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2009-10-06">deux pointeurs au moins (URI), séparés par une espace.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>This attribute is deprecated. It is retained for backward compatibility
only; the attribute <att>target</att> should be used for
preference. It is an error to supply both attributes, but one or the
other must be present.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <s n="1">The state Supreme Court has refused to release <rs xml:id="R1"><rs xml:id="R2">Rahway State Prison</rs> inmate</rs> <rs xml:id="R3">James Scott</rs> on bail.</s>
      <s n="2"><rs xml:id="R4">The fighter</rs> is serving 30-40 years
      for a 1975 armed robbery conviction in <rs xml:id="R5">the penitentiary</rs>.</s>
      <!-- ... -->
      <linkGrp type="periphrasis">
        <link target="#R1 #R3 #R4"/>
        <link target="#R2 #R5"/>
      </linkGrp>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>This element should only be used to encode associations not otherwise provided for by more specific elements.</p>
    <p>The location of this element within a document has no significance, unless it is included within a <gi>linkGrp</gi>, in which case it may inherit the value of the <att>type</att> attribute from the value given on the <gi>linkGrp</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2009-10-06">
    <p>Cet élément n’est utilisé que pour encoder des associations ; il n’est pas préconisé pour d’autres éléments plus spécifiques. </p>
    <p> L’emplacement de cet élément dans un document n'a aucune signification, à moins qu'il ne soit inclus dans un élément <gi>linkGrp</gi> ; dans ce cas il peut hériter de la valeur donnée à l’attribut <att>type</att> de l’élément <gi>linkGrp</gi> .</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 当該要素は，他の要素では示すことができない関連性を符号化する際にの み使われるべきである． </p>
    <p> 当該要素が，要素<gi>linkGrp</gi>でまとめられているのでなければ，当 該要素のある場所は重要ではない．要素<gi>linkGrp</gi>の下にある場合， 属性<att>type</att>の値は要素<gi>linkGrp</gi>がもつ値を継承する． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#SAPT"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
