<?xml versionDate="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright TEI Consortium. 
  Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
  See the file COPYING.txt for details
  $Date$
  $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="namesdates" ident="listEvent">
  <gloss>list of events</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2009-03-19">liste d'événements</gloss>
  <desc>contains a list of descriptions, each of which provides information
    about an identifiable event. </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-03-19" xml:lang="fr">contient une liste de descriptions, chacune d'entre elles fournissant des informations sur un événement connu.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.declarable"/>
    <memberOf key="att.sortable"/>
    <memberOf key="model.listLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="model.headLike"/>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="event"/>
          <rng:ref name="listEvent"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="relation"/>
          <rng:ref name="relationGrp"/>
          <rng:ref name="listRelation"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <listEvent>
        <head>Battles of the American Civil War: Kentucky</head>
        <event xml:id="event01" when="1861-09-19">
          <label>Barbourville</label>
          <desc>The Battle of Barbourville was one of the early engagements of
the American Civil War. It occurred September 19, 1861, in Knox
County, Kentucky during the campaign known as the Kentucky Confederate
Offensive. The battle is considered the first Confederate victory in
the commonwealth, and threw a scare into Federal commanders, who
rushed troops to central Kentucky in an effort to repel the invasion,
which was finally thwarted at the <ref target="#event02">Battle of
Camp Wildcat</ref> in October.</desc>
        </event>
        <event xml:id="event02" when="1861-10-21">
          <label>Camp Wild Cat</label>
          <desc>
The Battle of Camp Wildcat (also known as Wildcat Mountain and Camp
Wild Cat) was one of the early engagements of the American Civil
War. It occurred October 21, 1861, in northern Laurel County, Kentucky
during the campaign known as the Kentucky Confederate Offensive. The
battle is considered one of the very first Union victories, and marked
the first engagement of troops in the commonwealth of Kentucky.</desc>
        </event>
        <event xml:id="event03" from="1864-06-11" to="1864-06-12">
          <label>Cynthiana</label>
          <desc>The Battle of Cynthiana (or Kellar’s Bridge) was an engagement
during the American Civil War that was fought on June 11 and 12, 1864,
in Harrison County, Kentucky, near the town of Cynthiana. A part of
Confederate Brigadier General John Hunt Morgan's 1864 Raid into
Kentucky, the battle resulted in a victory by Union forces over the
raiders and saved the town from capture.</desc>
        </event>
      </listEvent>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <!-- text from wikipedia -->
</elementSpec>
