<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="textcrit" ident="listWit">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>witness list</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">비교 대상 텍스트 목록</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">liste de témoins</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">lista dei testimoni</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">lista de testimonios</gloss>
  <desc>lists definitions for all the witnesses referred to by a critical
  apparatus, optionally grouped hierarchically.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">비평적 참조 도구에 의해 참조된 모든 비교 대상 텍스트에 대한 정의 목록. 그리고 이는 계층적 그룹으로 수의적으로 구성된다.</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  校勘資料中で参照されている文献の定義のリストを示す．選択的に，グルー
  プとして構造化されている．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">donne une liste de définitions pour tous les
témoignages cités dans un apparat critique, pouvant être groupées de façon hiérarchique.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">contains a list of all the witnesses referred to in
wit elements or wit attributes
within the critical apparatus.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una lista di tutti i testimoni a cui si fa riferimento negli elementi e attributi relativi ai testimoni nell'apparato critico</desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-14" xml:lang="es">contains a list of all the witnesses referred to in wit elements or wit attributes within the critical apparatus.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene la lista con todos los testimonios a los cuales se hace referencia en los elementos y atributos relativos a los testimonios en el aparato crítico</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.sortable"/>
    <memberOf key="model.listLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <!--      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>-->
      <rng:optional>
        <rng:ref name="model.headLike"/>
      </rng:optional>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="witness"/>
          <rng:ref name="listWit"/>
        </rng:choice>
        <!--        <rng:zeroOrMore>
          <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
        </rng:zeroOrMore>-->
      </rng:oneOrMore>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <listWit>
        <witness xml:id="HL26">Ellesmere, Huntingdon Library 26.C.9</witness>
        <witness xml:id="PN392">Hengwrt, National Library of Wales,
   Aberystwyth, Peniarth 392D</witness>
        <witness xml:id="RP149">Bodleian Library Rawlinson Poetic 149
   (see further <ptr target="#MSRP149"/>)</witness>
      </listWit>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p rend="dataDesc">May contain
a series of <gi>witness</gi>  or <gi>listWit</gi> elements.
</p>
    <p>The provision of a <gi>listWit</gi> element simplifies
the automatic processing of the apparatus, e.g. the reconstruction
of the readings for all witnesses from an exhaustive apparatus.</p>
    <p>Situations commonly arise where there are many more or less
fragmentary witnesses, such that there may be quite distinct groups
of witnesses for different parts of a text or collection of
texts. Such groups may be given separately, or nested within a single
<gi>listWit</gi> element at the beginning of the file listing all the
witnesses, partial and complete, for the text, with the attestation
of fragmentary witnesses indicated within the apparatus by use of the
<gi>witStart</gi> and <gi>witEnd</gi> elements described in section
<ptr target="#TCAPMI"/>.</p>
    <p>Note however that a given witness can only be defined once, and can
therefore only appear within a single <gi>listWit</gi> element. </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p rend="dataDesc">Peut contenir une série d'éléments <gi>witness</gi> ou
                <gi>listWit</gi>.</p>
    <p>Fournir un élément <gi>listWit</gi> simplifie le traitement automatique de l'apparat,
                comme par exemple la reconstitution des leçons pour tous les témoins d'un apparat
                exhaustif. </p>
    <p>C'est un cas qui se produit communément lorsqu'il existe de nombreux témoins plus ou
                moins fragmentaires, de sorte qu'il peut y avoir des groupes pratiquement distincts
                de témoins pour différentes parties d'un texte ou d'une collection de textes. On
                peut donner ces groupes séparément ou bien les réunir à l'intérieur d'un seul
                élément <gi>listWit</gi> au début du fichier listant tous les témoins (parcellaires
                ou complets) pour le texte, accompagnés de l'attestation des témoins fragmentaires
                signalés dans l'apparat par l'utilisation des éléments <gi>witStart</gi> et
                    <gi>witEnd</gi> décrits dans la section .</p>
    <p>Noter cependant qu'un témoin donné ne peut être défini qu'une seule fois et ne peut
                donc figurer que dans un seul élément <gi>listWit</gi>. </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p rend="dataDesc">
    一連の要素<gi>witness</gi>または<gi>listWit</gi>をとるかもしれない．
    </p>
    <p>
    要素<gi>listWit</gi>は，校勘資料を自動処理を容易にするためのもので
  ある．例えば，ある網羅的な校勘資料から，全文献の読みを自動的に再構築
  する場合である．
  </p>
    <p>
    断片的な文献しかないことはよくあるが，この場合，異なる部分ごとに文
  献やテキストをグループ化することもできる．このグループは独立したもの
  であるか，または全文献がリスト化されているファイルの冒頭において，要
  素<gi>listWit</gi>中で入れ子化されているかもしれない．当該校勘資料中
  で，要素<gi>witStart</gi>と<gi>witEnd</gi>により断片的な文献が示され
  る．この詳細は，<ptr target="#TCAPMI"/>を参照のこと．
  </p>
    <p>
    文献は，ただ1回定義されることに注意すること．下が手，要素
  <gi>listWit</gi>中で1回しか出現しない．
   </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#TCAPLL"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
