<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tagdocs" xml:id="MEMBEROF" ident="memberOf">
  <equiv/>
  <desc>specifies  class membership of the parent element or class.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica l'appartenenza a una classe dell'elemento o classe genitori</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica la pertenencia a una clase del elemento o clase padre.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">親要素や親クラスを示す．</desc>
  <classes/>
  <content>
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.xtext"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="key">
      <desc>specifies the identifier for a class of which the documented
 element or class is a member or subclass</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica l'identificatore di una classe di cui l'elemento o classe indicati sono un membro o una sottoclasse</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica el identificador de una clase de la cual el elemento o clase indicados son un miembro o una subclase.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">(名前) 当該要素やクラスの親要素や親クラスを指定する．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="mode" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>specifies the effect of this declaration on its parent
    module.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica el efecto de esta declaración en el módulo del que obtiene el orígen (módulo padre)</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該宣言が親要素に与える影響を示す．</desc>
      <defaultVal>add</defaultVal>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="add">
          <desc>this declaration is added to the current definitions</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">la declaración se añade a las definiciones corrientes.</desc>
          <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">(当該宣言は現行定義に追加される．)</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="delete">
          <desc>this declaration and all of its children are removed from the current setup</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">la declaración y todos sus descendientes son excluidos de la disposición corriente.</desc>
          <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">(当該宣言と当該以下の子要素は，現行定義から外される．)</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <memberOf key="model.divLike"/>
      <memberOf key="att.identified"/>
    </egXML>
    <p>This element will appear in any content model which references
<ident>model.divLike</ident>, and will have attributes defined in
<ident>att.identified</ident> (in addition to any defined explicitly
    for this element).</p>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>Elements or classes which are members of multiple (unrelated)
    classes will have more than one <gi>memberOf</gi> element, grouped
    by a <gi>classes</gi> element. If an element is a member of a
    class C1, which is itself a subclass of a class C2, there is no
    need to state this, other than in the documentation for class
    C1. </p>
    <p>Any additional comment or explanation of the class membership
    may be provided as content for this element.</p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
