<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="iso-fs" ident="vRange">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>value range</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">값의 범위</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">값의 범위</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">功能值範圍</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">gamme de valeurs</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">gama de valores</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">gamma di valori</gloss>
  <desc>defines the range of allowed values for a feature, in the form of
an <gi>fs</gi>, <gi>vAlt</gi>, or primitive value;
for the value of an <gi>f</gi> to be valid, it must be
subsumed by the specified range; if the <gi>f</gi>
contains multiple values (as sanctioned by the <att>org</att> attribute),
then each value must be subsumed by the <gi>vRange</gi>.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">fs, vAlt, 원형 값의 형태로 자질에 대해 허용된 값의 범위를 정의한다; 유효한 자질 값의 경우, 명시된 범위 내에서 포섭되어야 한다; 만약  자질이 (org 속성에 의해 확인된) 다중 값을 포함한다면, 각 값은 vRange 내에서 포섭되어야 한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">fs, vAlt, 또는 원형 값의 형태로 자질에 대한 허용 값의 범위를 정의한다. 유효한 f의 값에 대해서는 명시된 영역에 의해 포섭되어야한다. 만약 f가 (org 속성에 의해 인가된) 다중 값를 포함한다면, 모든 값은 vRange에 의해 포섭되어야 한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">定義有效功能值的範圍，使用fs、vAlt、或原始值格式；一個有效的功能值必須包含在指定範圍之內；若<gi>f</gi>包含多個值 (由屬性<att>org</att>所認可)，則每個值皆必須以<gi>vRange</gi>納入。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  要素<gi>fs</gi>, <gi>vAlt</gi>で示される素性値の範囲を定義する．要素
  <gi>f</gi>の妥当な値は，その範囲内になければならない．要素<gi>f</gi>
  が複数の値をとる場合(属性orgがそれを認めている時)，各値は当該要素
  <gi>vRange</gi>が示す範囲内になければならない．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2009-04-16" xml:lang="fr">définit la plage de valeurs autorisées pour un
    trait, sous la forme d'un <gi>fs</gi>, <gi>vAlt</gi>, ou d'une valeur primitive ; pour que la valeur d'un élément <gi>f</gi>
      soit valide, elle doit être englobée dans la plage spécifiée. Si le <gi>f</gi> contient des valeurs
    multiples (comme prévu par l'attribut <att>org</att>), chacune des valeurs doit être englobée dans
    l'élément <gi>vRange</gi>.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define la gama de valores posibles para un rasgo, en forma de una estructura de rasgo, vAlt, o valor primitivo;  para que el valor de un rasgo sea válido, este debe ser incluido en la gama especificada; si el rasgo contiene valores múltiples (como restringidos por el atributo org), entonces cada valor debe ser incluido por el vRange.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce la gamma di valori ammessi per un tratto, sotto forma di un fs, di un vAlt, o di valore primitivo; affinché il valore di un f sia valido deve essere
    sussunto dalla gamma specificata; se f contiene valori multipli (come sancito dall'attributo org) allora ogni valore deve essere sussunto da vRange.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="model.featureVal"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fDecl name="INV">
        <fDescr>inverted sentence</fDescr>
        <vRange>
          <vAlt>
            <binary value="true"/>
            <binary value="false"/>
          </vAlt>
        </vRange>
        <vDefault>
          <binary value="false"/>
        </vDefault>
      </fDecl>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p rend="dataDesc">May contain any legal feature-value specification.</p>
    <p/>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p rend="dataDesc">Peut contenir n'importe quelle spécification trait-valeur admise.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p rend="dataDesc">
    正しい素性値規定を含むかもしれない．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#FD"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
