<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>Building a TEI Release</title>
        <author>Martin Holmes</author>
        <author>James Cummings</author>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
        <author>Sebastian Rahtz</author>
        <author>David Sewell</author>
        <author xml:id="HC">Hugh Cayless</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <publisher>TEI Technical Council</publisher>
        <date>2016</date>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>This document was originally a section of tcw20.xml, but has now been spun off into its
          own document.</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2016-04-02" who="mdh">Beginning edits arising out of the experiences
      releasing 3.0.0. More to come.</change>
      <change when="2016-03-16" who="KSH">Fixed error in git command as just reported on
        tei-council</change>
      <change when="2016-02-23" who="#HC">Edits for new release process.</change>
      <change when="2015-12-14" who="MDH">Updates for new Jenkins server subdomains.</change>
      <change when="2015-10-07" who="MDH">Update for use of ant build process for oxygen-tei rather
        than the old .sh file.</change>
      <change when="2015-10-04" who="MDH">More updates to account for the shift from SF SVN to
        GitHub.</change>
      <change when="2015-10-03" who="MDH">Updates to account for the shift from SF SVN to
        GitHub.</change>
      <change when="2015-04-06" who="MDH">Updates arising out of release process for 2.8.0.</change>
      <change when="2015-04-06" who="KSH">Added link to http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/IRC</change>
      <change when="2015-04-04" who="MDH">Updates to take account of oxygen-tei's move from Google
        Code to GitHub, along with a couple of other tweaks.</change>
      <change when="2014-01" who="MDH">Updates for changes in procedure ahead of the 2.6.0
        release.</change>
      <change when="2013-11" who="MDH">Updates following move of some code from SourceForge to
        GitHub, and automation of the P5 version number in output.</change>
      <change when="2012-10-25" who="MDH">Updates following Primrose Path release
        experience.</change>
      <change when="2012-07-24" who="KSH">Newsfeed blog is no longer in SourceForge.</change>
      <change when="2012-06-28" who="KSH">A few changes based on messages to tei-council on
        2012-06-19 and 2012-06-20.</change>
      <change when="2012-06-19" who="KSH">Improvements suggested by various Council members based on
        experiences with version 2.1.0.</change>
      <change when="2012-06-16" who="KSH">Explained version numbers and added reminder about
        including readme file in announcement.</change>
      <change when="2012-02-02" who="MDH">Document forked from tcw20.xml.</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>NOTE: THIS DOCUMENT is currently in transition, as we move from keeping our code repository
        on SourceForge and releasing our products there to a process based on GitHub. It is
        therefore potentially incomplete. </p>

      <p>This document aims to provide a set of detailed instructions enabling a "release
        technician" (the Council member tasked with implementing a new release of the TEI) to
        prepare for and manage the release process. It assumes that the new packages will be taken
        from one of the Jenkins servers rather than being built locally by the release technician.
        This is easier and more reliable, because we ensure that the Jenkins servers are regularly
        updated and are correctly configured to build the TEI products.</p>

      <div xml:id="githubPackages">
        <head>Packages on GitHub</head>
        <p>The TEI maintains a number of distinct repository on GitHub, under the
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC">TEIC</ref> organization. The main repository for the developing P5 Guidelines
          and associated schemas is <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI">TEIC/TEI</ref>, and the TEI Stylesheets, the code for
          the Roma web application, and the source code for the Oxygen TEI plugin can be found in
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>, 
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Roma">TEIC/Roma</ref>, and
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/oxygen-tei">TEIC/oxygen-tei</ref> respectively. </p>
        <p>The rest of this section describes how to make a new release for the main
            <ident>P5</ident> package, but similar procedures apply to the others. The instructions
          assume you are working on a Linux or MacOSX system with a command line, and know (more or
          less) how to do basic command-line operations such as running scripts and logging into a
          server with ssh.</p>
      </div>

      <div xml:id="beforeStarting">
        <head>What you will need before you start</head>

        <list type="bulleted">
          <item>An account on GitHub, and committer privileges over the TEI repository. If you have
            ever pushed a change to the master branch TEI repository, you should have all the
            required permissions.</item>
          <item>Shell access on the TEI SourceForge project. Contact one of the admins to have this
            turned on. Normal committers don't have shell access. NOTE: THIS IS ONLY REQUIRED IF WE
            CONTINUE TO RELEASE PRODUCTS THROUGH THE SOURCEFORGE WEBSITE. COUNCIL IS STILL IN THE
            PROCESS OF DECIDING WHETHER WE SHOULD CONTINUE TO DO THIS.</item>
          <item> The release manager will need SSH login access to the tei account on the tei-c.org
            server. This involves two steps: <list type="ordered">
              <item>Generate an SSH key pair (if you don't have one already). If this is new to you,
                look at <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ssh-keygen"
                  >https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ssh-keygen</ref>.</item>

              <item>Send the public key to the Council Chair, who will forward it on to the system
                administrator.</item>
            </list> Make sure you get this set up well in advance of the release day, and make sure
            you can ssh tei@tei-c.org successfully. </item>

          <item>Some familiarity with the two TEI Jenkins Continuous Integration Servers (their URLs
            are below). Take a little time to watch them work, and see how a push to the GitHub
            repository causes them to start building TEI packages. There are three specific build
            jobs associated with P5, and they run in a fixed sequence.</item>
          <item>A nickname for <code>irc.freenode.net</code>, so you can log into
              <code>#tei-c</code> channel for live help from other Council members. For more
            information, see <ref target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/IRC">the TEI wiki page on
              IRC</ref>.</item>
          <item>Several hours of time. You won't be busy all the time, but the process from
            beginning to end takes several hours, especially if something goes a bit wrong and you
            have to retrace your steps. It's best to start first thing in the morning, and prepare
            to be busy all day.</item>
        </list>
        <p> NOTE: THE FOLLOWING ITEMS ARE ONLY RELEVANT IF WE CONTINUE TO RELEASE PRODUCTS ON THE
          SOURCEFORGE WEBSITE. </p>
        <list>
          <item> A copy of the public key that will enable you to sync the release zip with
            SourceForge. <list>
              <item>log in to the tei server (ssh tei@tei-c.org; this requires that you've completed
                the other public key step above).</item>
              <item>cat ~/.ssh/id_rsa.pub and copy the contents to the clipboard.</item>
              <item>paste the result into a text editor and remove any linebreaks added by the
                terminal.</item>
              <item>copy-paste the result into https://sourceforge.net/account/ssh</item>
            </list> What this does is to enable you (when logged in as tei to tei-c.org) to connect
            to SourceForge (as your SF user) to upload the release files. </item>

          <item>Test it by trying to log into SourceForge via ssh from the tei-c.org server:<lb/>
            <code>ssh sfuser,tei@frs.sourceforge.net</code><lb/> where "sfuser" is your SourceForge
            user name. You should not see a prompt for a password (because of the ssh keys you have
            set up). Instead, you should immediately see <q>Welcome! This is a restricted Shell
              Account. You can only copy files to/from here.</q> If you see this, then everything is
            set up correctly.</item>

        </list>
      </div>


      <div xml:id="releaseSteps">
        <head>Step-by-step instructions</head>

        <list type="ordered">
          <head>1-2 weeks before release:</head>
          <item>At least one week before releasing, we enter a review period, during which the only
            changes made to the code to be released should be to fix errors, rather than to add new
            features. A release branch will be created by the release technician, to which ONLY
            release-blocking bug fixes and corrections to typographical errors will be pushed. The
            release technician should announce a temporary hold on pushes to the dev branch on the
            Council list, then create the branch and push it to GitHub using the following commands:<lb/>
            <code>git checkout dev</code> (make sure you start from the dev branch)<lb/>
            <code>git checkout -b release-X.X.X</code><lb/>
            <code>git push -u origin release-X.X.X</code><lb/> After the release branch has been
            pushed, the release technician should inform the Council list and ask the maintainers of
            the TEI Jenkins systems (currently Martin Holmes, Peter Stadler, and James Cummings) to
            add a build of the release branch so that commits pushed there are properly tested. </item>
          <item>Pushes to the release branch should be merged back into dev regularly:<lb/>
            <code>git checkout dev</code><lb/>
            <code>git merge release-X.X.X</code></item>
        </list>
        <list type="ordered">
          <head>On release day:</head>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Ensure that P5/ReleaseNotes/readme-X.X.X.xml has been
            written</hi><lb/> Normally, this will have been created by the TEI Council chair at the
            point when the repository moved from its "alpha" stage to "beta", so you should not have
            to do this, but in case you do: <list>
              <item>Confirm the version number for the new release in consultation with Council. TEI
                version numbers are based on the <ref target="http://www.unicode.org/versions/"
                  >system used by the Unicode Consortium</ref> but with the first digit for major
                changes, the second for schema-changing revisions, and the third for
                non-schema-changing revisions. When the first or second digit is incremented, the
                following digit or digits is set to zero. During initial development, the version
                number is followed by "alpha"; during the pre-release checking stage, it's followed
                by "beta"; and when the release takes place, "beta" is removed and the version
                number has only digits and periods.</item>
              <item>Create the new file by cloning a previous one.</item>
              <item>Consult the git log log to check for all the significant changes since the last
                release. You can do this by opening a terminal in the root of a working copy of the
                TEI repository and running:<lb/>
                <code>git log --after=2015-08-01</code><lb/> where the date is that of the previous
                release. </item>
              <item>Add the new file into the repository with <code>git
                add</code>.<!-- You may also want to set its svn properties. Make 
                sure it has an SVN header block immediately after the XML declaration, and if it doesn't, copy and paste from another 
                file. Then run <code>svn propset svn:keywords 'LastChangedRevision LastChangedBy Id LastChangedDate HeadURL' filename.xml</code>. --></item>
            </list>
          </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Edit the P5/VERSION file to the correct number</hi><lb/> This file
            consists only of the bare version number, followed by "alpha" or "beta":<lb/>
            <code>2.8.2beta</code><lb/> For the release process, you need to remove the letters from
            the end, leaving a pure version number:<lb/>
            <code>2.8.2</code><lb/> This changes the release from beta (or possibly alpha) to the
            actual release version number. After the release process has been completed, the number
            should be incremented appropriately, and "alpha" added to the end of it:<lb/>
            <code>2.8.3alpha</code><lb/> signifying that the versions built subsequent to the
            release are now in the alpha stage. </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Announce a temporary freeze on pushes to the release branch on the
              TEI Technical Council mailing list</hi></item>
          <item>In the P5 directory, do<lb/>
            <code>make changelog</code><lb/> to generate an updated ChangeLog file. Then commit the
            update.
            </item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Merge the release branch into <code>master</code></hi><lb/>
            <code>git checkout master</code><lb/>
            <code>git merge --no-ff -m "YOUR COMMIT MESSAGE" release-X.X.X</code></item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Push your changes</hi> to the git repository, <code>git push origin
              master</code><lb/> and watch Jenkins build P5 for you.<lb/> This should be the final
            push for this version, and it will trigger the Jenkins servers into rebuilding the TEI
            packages. This is where you'll find the Jenkins servers: <list>
              <item><ptr target="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/"/></item>
              <item><ptr target="http://jenkins2.tei-c.org/"/></item>
            </list> And now you wait, and watch the Jenkins servers build the packages. This can
            take a couple of hours, so be patient. Both of the Jenkins servers should behave
            identically, and they should both build all three TEI packages successfully. </item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Ensure all changes have been committed, built, and successfully
              passed tests on the continual integration server</hi><lb/> When all builds have
            completed on both servers, click on the job number of the last build for each of the
            three TEI jobs to make sure that it was triggered by the commit that you made in the
            previous step (you should see your own commit message on the build page). Make sure that
            all builds were successful (they should have green balls next to them). </item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">NOTE: INSTRUCTIONS FROM HERE ON ASSUME THAT WE ARE RELEASING
              PRODUCTS ON THE SOURCEFORGE WEBSITE.</hi>
            <hi rend="bold">Log into TEI server and run the tei-install.sh script:</hi><lb/>
            <code>ssh tei@tei-c.org</code><lb/>
            <code>cd ~/private/git/P5</code> then run <code>git pull</code><lb/>then <code>cd
              Utilities</code> (this is where the scripts are)<lb/> (running git pull will update
            the local copy of the git repository because the scripts in that the release technician
            is using are <emph>in</emph> git. You should <emph>not</emph> be editing these scripts
            locally on tei-c.org instead, edit them and commit them to the git repository. Wherever
            possible there should be no special local magic files.)<lb/> Do the following three
            steps: <list>
              <item>Install locally: <code>./tei-install.sh --package=TEIP5 --version=X.X.X
                  --sfuser=username --install</code> and then <emph>go test the version this puts in
                  the Vault</emph>.</item>
              <item>If that looks good and everyone agrees then: <code>./tei-install.sh
                  --package=TEIP5 --version=X.X.X --sfuser=username --makecurrent</code> and
                then <emph>test that it appears on website correctly</emph>.</item>
              <item>If the website looks right then: <code>./tei-install.sh --package=TEIP5
                  --version=X.X.X --sfuser=username --upload</code> and then move on to the next
                step.</item>
            </list>
            In each of these steps, replace the Xs with your release version. Supply your
            SourceForge user name, and type your SourceForge password when prompted. By default, the
            script will pull the release package from the first Jenkins server, but you can supply
            the URL of the other server if necessary; read the script to see the details. Make sure
            the script completes successfully each time changing the final parameter from --install,
            to --makecurrent, and then --upload. </item>
          
          <item>NOTE (MDH 2016-04-02): STEPS SIMILAR TO THE ABOVE SHOULD BE ADDED TO COVER THE 
          RELEASE AND MAKING CURRENT OF THE STYLESHEETS.</item>

          <item>Still in ~/private/git/P5/Utilities, run<lb/>
            <code>./tei-database-rebuild.sh</code><lb/> This will update the eXist-db used by Roma.
            The script takes no parameters but expects a configuration file in the user’s home
            directory at ~/etc/tei-exist.conf with the appropriate paths and credentials. For the
            main server at tei-c.org this should already be set and no adjustments should be needed.
            This is the database used by Roma, so this operation will ensure that Roma is using the
            new version. Ask Martin, Peter, or James to check the version of P5 used by
            Roma, to ensure that this has succeeded, and fix it manually if it has not. This
            procedure is undergoing revision right now, so it would not be surprising if there were
            a minor glitch here. Eventually, a new process will be put in place and this
            instructions will be updated. </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Check the TEI website and all downloadable files are displaying the
              correct version</hi><lb/> Everything should now be done, so go to <ref
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index-toc.html">the newly
              released version on the TEI site</ref> and browse the Guidelines. Check that your
            version number is displayed in the footer of the page, and check that at least one
            change made since the last release is being reflected online. Visit Roma at <ptr
              target="http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/"/>, and generate a simple schema to confirm it
            works, and check that the version number is right in the footer. </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">NOTE: AGAIN THIS ASSUMES THAT WE ARE STILL RELEASING PRODUCTS ON
              SOURCEFORGE.</hi>
            <hi rend="bold">Make your release the default downloadable version from
            Sourceforge</hi><lb/> Go to the SourceForge site:<lb/>
            <ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/projects/tei/files/TEI-P5-all/"/><lb/> log in, and
            click the information button on your new release. Make it the default download for all
            operating systems. Now make sure that the main Download button links to your package. </item>

          <item>
            <hi rend="bold">Update tags on GitHub</hi><lb/> Every time a new release is made, a
            "tag" is created consisting of a pointer to the state of the P5 tree at release time.
            You can do this from the command line on your own computer. This is how to do it:<lb/>
            <code>git tag -a P5_Release_X.X.X -m "Release X.X.X of the TEI Guidelines."</code><lb/>
            where X.X.X is your new release. Then<lb/>
            <code>git push origin P5_Release_X.X.X</code>
          </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Make a Release on GitHub</hi><lb/> Go to the <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/tags">TEI Tags</ref> page on GitHub. You should
            see the tag you just pushed there. Click on "Add release notes". Give it a title,
            generally "Release X.X.X" and add a link to the release notes README, which should be at
            http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/readme-X.X.X.html. Add a copy of the zipped
            release from <ref
              target="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/tei-2.9.1.zip"
              >Jenkins</ref>. NOTE: THIS STEP WILL BE AUTOMATED SOON.</item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Inform the Debian Package Maintainer of the new release</hi><lb/>
            <emph>Note: This step may change as we review Debian Package Creation</emph> The Debian
            repository can only be updated by its maintainers, so let the Debian Package Maintainer
            know that your release is done, so they can grab the new packages and add them to the
            repository. </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Update the list of <ref
                target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/index.xml#previous">Previous releases of
                P5</ref></hi><lb/> If you have editing privileges on the OpenCMS system on
            tei-c.org, add the new release to the top of the release table. If not, ask one of the
            other Council members who does (currently Hugh Cayless and James Cummings) to make the
            change. </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Update the oXygen-ready distribution of TEI.</hi><lb/> This involves
            building the new package of oxygen-tei, and then updating the distribution file on the
            TEI server so that the oXygen software knows about the new release. You may prefer to
            hand this off to one of the maintainers (currently James Cummings, Syd Bauman or Martin
            Holmes) to do this for you if you're not familiar with the project. <list>
              <item>Check that you have ant (at least version 1.8) installed on your machine.</item>
              <item>Check that the latest versions of the TEI Stylesheets and TEI P5 packages are
                available for download from the SourceForge Files section, since the oxygen-tei
                update/upload script retrieves them from there.</item>
              <item>Check out or update a local copy of the source code from <ref
                  target="https://github.com/TEIC/oxygen-tei"
                  >https://github.com/TEIC/oxygen-tei</ref> to your local system.</item>
              <item>Make sure the build script knows where to find your oxygen.jar file (from the
                Oxygen installed on your system) by copying the file into
                  <code>oxygen-tei/lib</code> or symlinking it.</item>
              <item>cd into the oxygen-tei folder (it should contain folders called "frameworks" and
                "jenkins").</item>
              <item>Run the ant build process with the "release" parameter: <lb/>
                <code>ant release</code><lb/> This builds the plugin using the latest stable
                versions of P5 and the Stylesheets, then offers to upload the result to the TEI's
                SourceForge repo to become a release of the TEI-maintained version of the plugin.
                This also creates an updated updateSite.oxygen file, by retrieving the latest
                updateSite.oxygen file from the tei-c.org site, and asks the user to provide the new
                version number before creating a new version of updateSite.oxygen. It also offers to
                upload that file to tei-c.org, if the user has shell access. </item>
              <!--
              <item>Run the shell script <code>update-and-upload.sh</code>:<lb/>
                <code>./update-and-upload.sh -\-teiversion=x.x.x -\-xslversion=y.y.y -\-sfuser=yoursourceforgeusername</code><lb/>
                where the version numbers are taken from the latest VERSION files in the TEI git repository at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/blob/master/P5/VERSION">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/blob/master/P5/VERSION</ref> (for P5), and the GitHub repository at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/blob/master/VERSION">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/blob/master/VERSION</ref> (for the Stylesheets), and sfuser is your user name on SourceForge. </item>
              <item>Now you need to update the file which the oXygen software uses to update its frameworks. Log into the TEI server as tei@tei-c.org, and then:
                
                <item>cd to <code>/var/www/vhosts/tei-c.org/projects/tei/web/Vault/P5/</code></item>
                
                <item><code>cp x.x.x/oxygen/updateSite.oxygen y.y.y/oxygen/updateSite.oxygen</code> (where <code>x.x.x</code>
                  is the version number of the previous release, and <code>y.y.y</code> is that of the
                  new release you just made).</item>
                
                <item>Edit <code>y.y.y/oxygen/updateSite.oxygen</code> in your preferred text editor.</item>
                
                <item>Change <code>xt:version</code> to match the new version number of the plugin.</item>
                
                <item>Change <code>xt:location</code> to point to the SourceForge [OR GITHUB?] download location for
                  the zip (substituting the correct version numbers of P5 and the Stylesheets): <lb/>
                  
                  <code>http://downloads.sourceforge.net/project/tei/tei-oxygen/teioxygen-2.6.0-7.9.0.zip</code></item>
                
              </item>-->
            </list>
          </item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Inform the TEI Technical Council Chair so they can announce the
              release</hi><lb/> Once you are sure that everything is working correctly, inform the
            Council Chair. They will announce the release to the TEI-L mailing list, including the
            text of P5/ReleaseNotes/readme-X.X.X.xml in plain text form (which can be generated
            using the "readme" profile for teitotxt), and place an announcement on the Text Encoding
            Initiative Newsfeed blog in the category of 'News'. They will also update the table of
            previous releases at <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/index.xml#previous"
              >http://www.tei-c.org/Guidelines/P5/index.xml#previous</ref>.</item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Lift the freeze on committing changes to the repository</hi><lb/>
            Write to the TEI Council list and let them know that they can once again start
            committing changes to the repository.</item>

          <item><hi rend="bold">Inform the Stylesheets maintainer that a new release has been
              completed</hi><lb/> The TEI Stylesheets project depends on the current release of P5,
            and when a new release appears, the tests which are part of the stylesheet build process
            will probably fail, breaking the build. The maintainer will have to change the tests in
            accordance with the new release of P5. This can only be done after the release process
            has been completed. Refer to the TEI Council chair to find out who the current
            Stylesheets maintainer is.</item>
          <item><hi rend="bold">Increment the build number for the next release cycle</hi><lb/>
            After the release process has been completed, the release number in the repository needs
            to be updated. Edit the P5/VERSION file to the correct number. This file contains
            nothing except the bare version number. It should be incremented appropriately, and "a"
            added to the end of it, so if for example the release was number 2.8.2, you would change
            the number in the file to:<lb/>
            <code>2.8.3a</code><lb/> signifying that the versions built subsequent to the release
            are now in the alpha stage. </item>

        </list>

      </div>

    </body>


  </text>
</TEI>

