<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- intended to be valid against the current TEI Lite (P5) schema -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 0.5 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date>17 October 2006</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<availability status="restricted">
	  <p>Copyright 2006 Text Encocing Initiative Consortium</p>
	  <p>Permission to copy in any medium is granted.</p>
	</availability>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>No source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>Changes since the last packaged release (0.4.1, July 2006)
      are listed briefly below (please refer to the ChangeLog in
      directory ReleaseNotes at the Sourceforge archive for a full
      list).</p>
      <p>Following the major architectural changes introduced in the
      previous release, this release has focused on improving the
      prose of several chapters, on extending the suite of available
      examples and templates, and on a number of minor corrections and
      enhancements deriving from Sourceforge feature requests.</p>
      <list>
	<item>Work on rationalising and making consistent the representation of
	dates on various attributes began, but is not yet complete. Elements
	<gi>dateRange</gi> and <gi>timeRange</gi> have been removed. </item>
	<item>Changes in the way that model class references are
	processed by the ODD processor were implemented. These changes
	will help to avoid prolems of inter-module dependency as well
	as enhancing the range of facilities in the ODD
	language.</item>
	<item>At Council's request the XML source files have been
	given longer names reminiscent of their English chapter
	titles.</item>
	<item>The draft chapter on linking and segmentation was
	revised for readability and one of its longer examples was
	enhanced to demonstrate use of SVG graphics within a TEI
	document.</item>
	<item>A first draft of a revision of the chapter on
	non-hierarchic markup was included.</item>
	<item>Several new exemplars and templates were added,
	complementing a major revision of the Roma schema generation
	tool. Each example now includes a template. Examples of the
	use of SVG, XInclude, and MathML have been added. </item>
	<item>Spanish language translations for element descriptions
	etc. were added.</item>
	<item>The process of replacing explicit element or attribute
	references with class references continued in several content
	models and element declarations.</item>
	<item>The P5 colophon was updated. </item>
	<item>A new <gi>age</gi> element was added.</item>
	<item>Numerous minor typographic errors have been corrected.</item>
      </list>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
