<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<macroSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" n="User Extensions" xml:id="TEIEXTE" type="pe" ident="TEI.extensions.ent">
  <desc>supplies the name of a file containing any local modifications
required to the TEI DTDs.</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
TEIが用意したDTDに加える変更点を含むファイル名を示す．
</desc>
  <content/>
  <remarks>
    <p>The contents of the file indicated by this entity are embedded in a
TEI DTD immediately before any other declaration.  By default, the
entity expands to the empty string; the user can override this default
by declaring the entity in the DTD subset with an appropriate
value. Typically this will take the form <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">&lt;!ENTITY %
TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM 'project.ent' &gt;</egXML> where <ident type="file">project.ent</ident> is the name of a file containing
additional entity declarations. These declarations may not reference
any other element or entity within the TEI modules. They are used to
override the default entity declarations provided for the TEI-defined
classes, datatypes, or macros described in chapter <ptr target="#ST"/>.  </p>
    <p>This macro is used only by the XML DTD customization mechanism
defined in TEI P4. The recommended method of TEI customization at P5,
irrespective of schema language, is to define an ODD.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
当該エンティティで示されたファイルの中身は，DTDの中では，他の宣言を行
う前に埋め込む必要がある．デフォルトでは，当該エンティティは，空文字と
して展開される．すなわち，利用者は，当該エンティティを必要な値で宣言す
ることにより，デフォルト値を上書きすることが出来る．
例えば，以下の場合では，<ident type="file">project.ent</ident>は，追加
するエンティティ宣言を含むファイル名を示している．
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
&lt;!ENTITY %TEI.extensions.ent SYSTEM 'project.ent' &gt;
</egXML>
ここで追加する宣言はTEIモジュールにある要素やエンティティを参照しては
いけない．当該エンティティは，デフォルト値として既にTEI規定のクラス，
データ型，マクロとして規定されている(<ptr target="#ST"/>)エンティティ
を上書きするためのものである．
 </p>
    <p>
このマクロは，TEI P4で規定されているDTD修正機能で使われるものである．
TEI P5では，修正を行う場合，使用するスキーマ言語に関係なく，ODDを定義
することが推奨方法になっている．
</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#STOV"/>
  </listRef>
</macroSpec>
