<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/teilite.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>How to edit the TEI Guidelines</title>
        <author>Lou Burnard</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Unpublished first draft for review by TEI Technical council</p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>All my own work</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change when="2011-04-26">merged back in Seb's notes on Jenkins</change>
      <change when="2011-04-13">updated during council meeting</change>
      <change when="2011-03-24">merged with release howto</change>
      <change when="2011-02-19">started first draft</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>This document is intended to set out the way things are
      currently managed  in the
        editing of the source files from which the TEI Guidelines and
	schemas are generated. General notes on the rationale
	for this state -- <emph>why</emph> it is the way it is -- may be added here
        later. The intention is to provide information for Council
      members wishing to contribute actively to the continued
      development and maintenance of those source files, which we
      refer to collectively in this document as the
      <q>Guidelines</q>. </p>
      <div>
        <head>Logical organisation of the Guidelines</head>
        <p>It cannot have escaped your notice that each chapter (almost) of the Guidelines defines a
          distinct module. In theory at least, each chapter is organised in more or less the same
          way: <list>
            <item>it begins with a paragraph explaining what the module is for, and containing a lot
              of links to the individual subsections it contains; </item>
            <item>each subsection introduces a (small) group of elements, usually beginning with a
                <gi>specList</gi>; </item>
            <item>each element is then introduced in turn, usually including an appropriate usage
              example (on examples, see further <ptr target="#examples"/>); </item>
            <item>a <gi>specGrp</gi>. for each group of elements defined may be given at the end of
              each section; </item>
            <item>a <gi>specGrp</gi> for the whole module is given at the end of the chapter: it
              includes the other specifications either directly (by means of an entity reference) or
              indirectly (by means of a <gi>specGrpRef</gi> pointing to a preceding
              <gi>specGrp</gi>).</item>
          </list></p>
<p>The only chapters not organised in this way are those which do not
introduce or define particular modules.  </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Physical organization: the ODD files</head>
        <p>Each element, class, and macro defined in the Guidelines is
	declared within its own XML file,
          containing an <gi>elementSpec</gi>, <gi> classSpec</gi>, or <gi>macroSpec</gi> as
          appropriate. These files are in the directory
	  <ident>Source/Specs</ident>. For example, the file
            <ident>Source/Specs/abbr.xml</ident> contains the element spec for the <gi>abbr</gi> element. </p>
        <p>Each chapter of the Guidelines is stored in a file called
            <ident>Source/Guidelines/xx/YY-name.xml</ident> where xx is the language (currently only en or
          fr), YY is the two letter identifier for each chapter (see <ptr target="#chaptercodes"/>)
          and name is the name of the module being defined by that chapter. </p>
        <p>The file <ident>Source/guidelines-xx.xml</ident> (where xx is either en or fr) is the
            <soCalled>driver file</soCalled> for the whole shebang. It contains system entity
          declarations for each of the documents making up the P5 source. These entities are then
          referenced throughout the source to embed the required
	  component at the right place.<note place="foot">At one point
	we considered using <code>xInclude</code> to do this instead,
	but decided against it for reasons which now escape me.</note></p>
        <p>Hence, to add a new element (say <gi>saintName</gi>) you
	might proceed as follows: <list type="ordered">
            <item>Write a new file <ident>saintName.xml</ident> containing an <gi>elementSpec</gi>
              for your new element and add it to the <ident>Specs</ident> folder. </item>
            <item>Add a declaration like this to the existing driver file <eg>
                <![CDATA[<!ENTITY saintName SYSTEM "Specs/saintName.xml">
              ]]></eg></item>
            <item>Edit the source of the relevant chapter (presumably
                <ident>ND-namesdates.xml</ident>) to include a reference to the element spec (like
              this <code>&amp;saintName;</code>), and also some discussion of its usage. The former
              can appear anywhere, but good practice is to include it in an alphabetic list of such
              declarations near the end of the relevant section. You can also use a
                <gi>specList</gi> to reference the description from your new spec within the body of
              the text, like this:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> 
<p>This module also defines the following canonical element: <specList>
<specDesc key="saintName"/>
</specList></p>
</egXML> </item>
          </list>
        </p>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Style Notes</head>
        <div>
          <head>General</head>
          <p>The Guidelines are a reference manual, not a tutorial. You should not talk down to the
            reader, but assume they have a reasonably well-informed knowledge of the subjects under
            discussion. Make copious use of cross references, rather than repetition.</p>
          <p>Bear in mind however that your reader may not have English as their first language.
            Avoid needlessly complex sentences and unnecessarily obscure terminology. Make sure that
            technical terms are glossed on their first appearance: this should be in the chapter on
            XML in the case of XML-related terminology. If you want to provide other references, do
            so as footnotes, using the <gi>note</gi> element. </p>
          <p>Provide bibliographic citations for any other standards (etc) referenced, following the
            existing style. Do not introduce bibliographic citations simply in order to demonstrate
            your learning.</p>
          <p>A separate document (copied <ref target="#house-style">below</ref>) attempts to
            summarise current <soCalled>house style</soCalled> with reference to well known vexed
            issues about spelling, punctuation, etc. The goal of these rules is to avoid
            inconsistency, and also (wherever possible) to avoid producing text which is markedly
            either British or American English. </p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="examples">
          <head>Examples</head>
          <p>The purpose of an example is to illustrate a specific element or feature. Do not
            include irrelevant encoding which does not contribute to this primary goal. If such
            encoding is unavoidable (eg to make your example valid), then it must be explained in
            the supporting text.</p>
          <p>Wherever possible, choose your examples from real documents and provide bibliographic
            citations for them in the file <ident>BIB-Bibliography.xml</ident>. Use the <att>corresp</att>
            attribute on the <gi>egXML</gi> element to link an example to its source note. Note
            that the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute is mandatory on <gi>exemplum</gi>: this is to
            ensure that the ODD processor knows which examples to choose in a given context.</p>
          <p>All examples should be valid against a modified TEI schema in which any element can act
            as a root element: this validity is checked during the build process. </p>
          <p>As well as a validity check, the build process looks at
          cross-references. Since the Guidelines is a single XML
          document, IDs must be unique across the text and the
          examples.  Consequently, any <att>xml:id</att> attribute
          values appearing in your examples must be unique within the
          text of the whole of the Guidelines. Furthermore, any
          <att>target</att> (etc.) values which do not point to
          anything in the source will be flagged with a warning during
	  the build process. </p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Making a change to the Guidelines</head>
<p>The Guidelines are maintained in a Sourceforge subversion
repository. "Subversion" is a widely-used source control system, and
we don't explain further here how to use. To make changes in the
repository you need to have an account on Sourceforge and "developer"
rights on the TEI project. We don't explain here how to obtain a
sourceforge account: go to the website http://www.sf.net to find more
information about this. To get developer rights, if you don't already
have them, you need to contact
one of the project administrators whose email addresses are listed on
the TEI project page at http://tei.sf.net.</p>

        <list>
          <item>Use a Subversion client to update your local copy of the source text <emph>before</emph>
            you make any changes in it.</item>
          <item>Make your changes. Make sure your source is still valid against the
              <ident>p5odds.rnc</ident> schema. </item>
          <item>If you have a locally installed P5 build environment, make sure you can still build,
            and that the examples are still valid.</item>
          <item>If you don't have a locally-installed P5 build
	  environment, just use subversion to check your updated
	  version back in and wait for the Continuous Integration (CI)
	  server <ident>Jenkins</ident> to assess your work; see
	  further <ptr
	  target="#jenkins"/>. </item>
        </list>
        <p>Error messages may appear at any stage. Please do not leave the source in an invalid
          state (it makes life unnecessarily difficult for others). If you cannot immediately fix a
          validity error, revert your change while you think about it.</p>
        <p>Error messages appearing during the <ident>make test</ident> phase usually indicate that
          your changes are in conflict with the Birnbaum Doctrine, which decrees that changes in the
          Guideline schemas should not invalidate existing documents. You may wish to discuss the
          specific issue with other Council members.</p>
<p>When making changes to the ODDs, it is advisable to add testfiles
to the Test directory to ensure that your changes have been carried
out correctly. <!-- more about test files --></p>


      </div>


      <div xml:id="jenkins">
	<head>Jenkins setup</head>
	<p>Jenkins divides the work of building P5 into three linked
	stages: Test, Documentation and the final assembly. The work they do is as
	follows:
	<list type="ordered">
	  <item>Test stage: this monitors
	  <code>https://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/svnroot/tei/trunk/P5</code>,
	  the part of the TEI sourceforge subversion repository where
	  the P5 source is stored. If any change is detected, it runs <code>make clean validate test exemplars</code></item>
	  <item>Documentation stage: this also updates itself from the Subversion
	  repository before it runs, but is triggered by the success of the Test run, not directly by monitoring Subversion. 
	  It runs <code>make clean dist-doc validate-html</code></item>
	  <item>Final stage: this is triggered by a successful run of
	  the Documentation stage, gets copies of artefacts
	  produced during the first two stages, and then does <code>rm
	  -f dist-source.stamp dist-schema.stamp dist-test.stamp
	  dist-database.stamp dist-exemplars.stamp</code>, followed by
	  <code>make dist deb</code> and <code>make
	  teiwebsiteguidelines</code>. It makes available
	  <code>release/xml/**,
	  release/doc/**,*.zip,tei-p5-*_*,teiwebsiteguidelines.zip</code>
	  on the web.</item>
</list>
	</p>
	<p>See <ptr
	target="https://wiki.jenkins-ci.org/display/JENKINS/Administering+Jenkins"/>
	for details on how to configure   Jenkins. The files currently
	used for this purpose are accessible in the Sourceforge <code>Documents/Editing/Jenkins</code> directory.</p>
<p>The Jenkins plugins which should be installed are as follows:
<list type="gloss">
<label>Copy Artifact Plugin</label>
<item>Adds a build step to copy artifacts from another project.</item>
	
<label>Jenkins CVS Plug-in</label>
<item>Integrates Jenkins with CVS version control system.</item>

<label>Emotional Hudson plugin</label>
<item>This funny plugin changes the expression of Mr. Hudson in the background when your builds fail.</item>
	
<label>Green Balls</label>
<item>Because green is better than blue!</item>
	
<label>Hudson Job Configuration History Plugin</label>
<item>Job history plugin for hudson.</item>
	
<label>Log Parser Plugin</label>
<item></item>
	
<label>Maven Integration plugin</label>
<item></item>
	
<label>Plot plugin</label>
<item>This plugin provides generic plotting (or graphing) capability.</item>
	
<label>Hudson SCP publisher plugin</label>
<item>This plugin uploads build artifacts to repository sites using SCP (SSH) protocol.</item>
	
<label>Jenkins Subversion Plug-in</label>
<item></item>

<label>Hudson WebSVN2 plugin</label>
<item>This plugin integrates WebSVN browser interface for Subversion to Hudson. Entries in change logs will by hyperlinked to the specified files/diffs in WebSVN.</item>
</list>
</p>
      </div>


<div xml:id="svn">
<head>Building the release</head>
<p>The TEI maintains a number of distinct packages on Sourceforge. The
source for all of them is maintained in a Subversion repository. The
main published packages are :
<list type="gloss">
<label>P5</label><item>The main TEI P5 source</item>
<label>Roma</label><item>The web application</item>
<label>Stylesheets</label><item>The stylesheet library</item>
<label>tei-emacs</label><item>TEI customisation of emacs</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Two other packages, <ident>I18N</ident>, which provides input for
the internationalization utilities used in producing P5,   and
<ident>TEIOO</ident> which provides P5 support for Open Office, 
are also maintained, but unpublished.
</p>
<p>The rest of this section describes how to make a new release for
the main <ident>P5</ident> package, but similar procedures apply
to the others. The instructions assume you are working on a Linux or
MacOSX system with a command line, and know (more or less) how to use
the standard GNU <q>make</q> utility.</p>

<div><head>Creating a new file release</head>

<p>First edit the file <ident>VERSION</ident>, and make it say what
you are about to release. Now check that the source is clean and
tested.  When you are happy that these are what you want, do
<code>make dist</code>. This makes a single zip file with all the TEI
P5 deliverables in, called
<code>tei-</code><hi>versionumber</hi><code>.zip</code>.</p>

<p>If you also say <code>make deb</code>, and you have the Debian
devscripts packages installed, six Debian packages will be created
(see further <ptr target="#debian"/> below).</p>

<p>If you do not have a build system yourself, the Jenkins CI server
(currently experimentally at <ptr
target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/jenkins"/>) will watch Subversion,
make all the tests, and rebuild everything after any change. It will
create the zip archive and Debian packages for you.</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="sf">
<head>Uploading file releases to Sourceforge</head>
<p>The zip file <code>tei-</code><hi>versionumber</hi><code>.zip</code>
is what we put up on Sourceforge. If you did not create this in your own
build process, you can take a copy 
from <ptr target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/jenkins/job/TEIP5/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/tei-1.9.0.zip"/>.
You now need to upload this file to the Sourceforge download area by using one 
of the supported methods, such as secure FTP or rsync. For example 
<eg>
rsync -e ssh tei-1.9.0.zip rahtz,tei@frs.sourceforge.net:/home/frs/project/t/te/tei/TEIP5-All
</eg>
Further details of the upload procedure are provided in <ref
target="https://sourceforge.net/apps/trac/sourceforge/wiki/Release%20files%20for%20download">the
Sourceforge Wiki</ref>.
</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="debian">
<head>Making Debian packages</head>
<p>A Debian package
combines a set of source files with Debian-specific metadata and
support files. For each of the 
packages mentioned above, there is a directory under P5 named
<code>debian-</code><hi>packagename</hi>/<code>debian</code>  containing the
necessary additional material. The command <code>make deb</code> goes into
each of the directories and builds the package, creating 6 corresponding .deb, .build and .changes
files. As above, if you cannot build these yourself, grab from 
<ptr target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/jenkins/job/TEIP5/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/"/></p>

<p>Now you can move the Debian files to a repository somewhere
(tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk:/home/tei/teideb, if you have access) and rebuild
the package database. Building Debian packages is extensively
documented on the web, but there is a lot more to it than described
here (such as the content of the control files for post-installation,
pre-removal, init scripts, menus etc).</p>

<p>The important TEI-related Debian packages are
<table>
<row><cell>tei-emacs</cell><cell>TEI Emacs setup</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-oxygen</cell><cell>oXygen XML editor</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p4-doc</cell><cell>TEI Guidelines (P4)</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p4-lite</cell><cell>TEI P4 Lite</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p4-schema</cell><cell>TEI P4 Schemas/DTDs</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p4-xsl</cell><cell>TEI P4 XSLT stylesheets </cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p5-doc</cell><cell>TEI Guidelines</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p5-exemplars</cell><cell>TEI exemplar customiza</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p5-schema</cell><cell>TEI Schemas/DTDs</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p5-source</cell><cell>TEI sources/DTDs</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p5-test</cell><cell>TEI test files</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p5-xsl</cell><cell>TEI XSLT (1.0) stylesheets</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-p5-xsl2</cell><cell>TEI XSLT (2.0) stylesheets</cell></row>
<row><cell>tei-xsl-common</cell><cell>TEI XSLT stylesheets, shared files</cell></row></table>
</p>
<p>Some of these packages have dependencies on other packages, which will get pulled in as
needed (trang, jing etc).</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="web">
<head>Installing files on the TEI web site</head>
<p>Most users of the TEI will want to download and install either the
debian packages or the full release files from sourceforge. For
convenience however we also provide copies of the current dtds, schemas and
stylesheets on the main TEI web site. These copies are provided for
the following reasons: 
<list>
<item>to service the rendering web pages themselves</item>
<item>to let Roma find resources</item>
<item>to provide a service of fixed URLs for DTDs and schemas</item>
</list>
The files are organised as indicated below (<ptr target="#fileOrg"/>). There is a script in <ident>P5/Utilities/tei-install.sh</ident> which can be run to pull
the latest artefacts from Jenkins, and put them in the right place on the TEI
web site. The script requires at least two parameters, one to specify
the Jenkins package name, and the other the version number required : 
<eg>
./tei-install.sh --package=TEIP5 --version=1.9.0
</eg>
</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="roma">
<head>Setting up Roma and eXist</head>
<p>Roma needs access to XSLT stylesheets, P5 Relax NG schemas, and an
eXist database of TEI P5. Where it finds these is determined by the
file <ident>roma/config.php</ident> (on the main TEI web site, this is in the
<ident>/usr/share/tei-roma/</ident> directory). However, this varies between sites, so
what is distributed is <ident>config-dist.php</ident>. </p>

<p>How does TEI P5 get into eXist? Using the script
<ident>tei-database-rebuild</ident>, which is installed into
<ident>/usr/bin</ident>. Running that on the TEI web site will attempt
to install the files into both the standard locations and the 
archive of releases.</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="oxgarage">
<head>Setting up OxGarage</head>
<p>The Roma installation at <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Roma/"/>
depends on the web service supplied by OxGarage
(currently at <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/ege-webservice/"/>) to provide
ODD manipulation.  The OxGarage configuration is set to look for its stylesheets
and copy of TEI P5 in the standard location (under <ident>/usr/share/xml/tei</ident>),
using symbolic links, so no special case is needed to have it take notice of a new
release.</p>
</div>
</div>


      <div>
        <head>Reference section</head>
        <div  xml:id="chaptercodes">
          <head>Chapter codes</head>
<p>Following a lengthy debate in the Council as to whether the
two-character codes originally used to identify individual chapters 
should be dropped in favour of longer more human-readable names, a
compromise solution was reached in which the two character codes were
retained as prefixes to longer human-readable names. The same
two-character codes are also used to identify the HTML and PDF files
generated during the release process.</p>
<p>The following
table shows the correspondence between the printed organization of the
Guidelines and the corresponding filenames. The order is determined by the
driver file <ident>Source/guidelines-xx.xml</ident>, from which the
table is derived.
<table>
<row role="label"><cell>Section</cell><cell>Title</cell><cell>filename</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[i]</cell><cell>Releases of the TEI Guidelines</cell>
<cell>TitlePageVerso.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[ii]</cell><cell>Dedication</cell>
<cell>Dedication.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[iii]</cell><cell>Preface and Acknowledgments</cell>
<cell>FM1-IntroductoryNote.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[iv]</cell><cell>About These Guidelines</cell>
<cell>AB-About.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[v]</cell><cell>A Gentle Introduction to XML</cell>
<cell>SG-GentleIntroduction.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[vi]</cell><cell>Languages and Character Sets</cell>
<cell>CH-LanguagesCharacterSets.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[1]</cell><cell>The TEI Infrastructure</cell>
<cell>ST-Infrastructure.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[2]</cell><cell>The TEI Header</cell>
<cell>HD-Header.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[3]</cell><cell>Elements Available in All TEI Documents</cell>
<cell>CO-CoreElements.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[4]</cell><cell>Default Text Structure</cell>
<cell>DS-DefaultTextStructure.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[5]</cell><cell>Representation of Non-standard Characters and
Glyphs</cell><cell>WD-NonStandardCharacters.xml</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>[6]</cell><cell>Verse</cell><cell>VE-Verse.xml</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>[7]</cell><cell>Performance Texts</cell>
<cell>DR-PerformanceTexts.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[8]</cell><cell>Transcriptions of Speech</cell>
<cell>TS-TranscriptionsofSpeech.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[9]</cell><cell>Dictionaries</cell>
<cell>DI-PrintDictionaries.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[10]</cell><cell>Manuscript Description</cell>
<cell>MS-ManuscriptDescription.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[11]</cell><cell>Representation of Primary Sources</cell>
<cell>PH-PrimarySources.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[12]</cell><cell>Critical Apparatus</cell>
<cell>TC-CriticalApparatus.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[13]</cell><cell>Names, Dates, People, and Places</cell>
<cell>ND-NamesDates.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[14]</cell><cell>Tables, Formulæ, and Graphics</cell>
<cell>FT-TablesFormulaeGraphics.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[15]</cell><cell>Language Corpora</cell>
<cell>CC-LanguageCorpora.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[16]</cell><cell>Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment</cell>
<cell>SA-LinkingSegmentationAlignment.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[17]</cell><cell>Simple Analytic Mechanisms</cell>
<cell>AI-AnalyticMechanisms.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[18]</cell><cell>Feature Structures</cell>
<cell>FS-FeatureStructures.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[19]</cell><cell>Graphs, Networks, and Trees</cell>
<cell>GD-GraphsNetworksTrees.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[20]</cell><cell>Non-hierarchical Structures</cell>
<cell>NH-Non-hierarchical.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[21]</cell><cell>Certainty, Precision, and Responsibility</cell>
<cell>CE-CertaintyResponsibility.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[22]</cell><cell>Documentation Elements</cell>
<cell>TD-DocumentationElements.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[23]</cell><cell>Using the TEI</cell>
<cell>USE.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A1]</cell><cell>Model Classes</cell>
<cell>REF-CLASSES-MODEL.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A2]</cell><cell>Attribute Classes</cell>
<cell>REF-CLASSES-ATTS.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A3]</cell><cell>Elements</cell>
<cell>REF-ELEMENTS.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A4]</cell><cell>Attributes</cell>
<cell>REF-ATTRIBUTES.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A5]</cell><cell>Datatypes and Other Macros</cell>
<cell>REF-MACROS.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A6]</cell><cell>Bibliography</cell>
<cell>BIB-Bibliography.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A7]</cell><cell>Prefatory Notes</cell>
<cell>PrefatoryNote.xml</cell></row>
<row>
<cell>[A8]</cell><cell>Colophon</cell>
<cell>COL-Colophon.xml</cell></row></table>
</p>
<p>In most chapters, the two character code is also used as a prefix
for the <att>xml:id</att> values given to each <gi>div</gi>
element. Note that every <gi>div</gi> element carries an
<att>xml:id</att> value, whether or not it is actually referenced
explicitly elewhere in the Guidelines.
</p>
<p>Note that files with names beginning <code>REF</code> contain
only <gi>divGen</gi> elements: their content, which provides the
reference documentation (sections A1 to A5 inclusive), is
automatically generated during the build process.</p>
  </div>
        <div xml:id="house-style">
<head>House style: preferred orthography</head>
<p>The document <ident>P5/Source/Guidelines/en/style-guide.txt</ident>
lists the following preferences with regard to some commonly
encountered problems of word spacing and hyphenation:

<table>
<row role="label"><cell>Word or Term</cell><cell> Authority/explanation</cell></row>
<row><cell>code point (n.); code-point (adj.)</cell><cell> UCG [discussed on TEI Council list]</cell></row>
<row><cell>cross-reference</cell><cell>MW, OED</cell></row>
<row><cell>data set</cell><cell>       OED</cell></row>
<row><cell>datatype</cell><cell>       [OED, ORDS have 'data type', but Guidelines                       consistently use single word dozens of places]</cell></row>
<row><cell>end-tag</cell><cell>        ORDS</cell></row>
<row><cell>high-level (adj.)   </cell><cell>    MW, OED</cell></row>
<row><cell>line break</cell><cell/></row>
<row><cell>lowercase/uppercase</cell><cell>MW, ORDS</cell></row>
<row><cell>proofread</cell><cell>      MW, OED</cell></row>
<row><cell>start-tag</cell><cell>      ORDS</cell></row>
<row><cell>stylesheet</cell><cell>     ORDS</cell></row>
<row><cell>typeface</cell><cell>       MW</cell></row>
<row><cell>the Web</cell><cell>        ORDS</cell></row>
<row><cell>web page</cell><cell>       ORDS</cell></row>
<row><cell>web site</cell><cell>       ORDS, OED</cell></row>
<row><cell>well-formed</cell><cell>    W3CXML (even in a predicate usage:
                          "the XML is well-formed")</cell></row>
<row><cell>whitespace</cell><cell>     ORDS</cell></row>
</table>
</p><p>The abbreviations cited above are from the following list of
authorities, which may also be consulted for other vexed issues:
<list type="gloss">
<label>        CMS</label><item>    Chicago Manual of Style, 15th ed.</item>
<label>        MW</label><item>     Merriam-Webster's Collegiate Dictionary, 11th ed.</item>
<label>        OED</label><item>    Oxford English Dictionary, 2d
ed. online (<ptr target="dictionary.oed.com"/>)</item>
<label>        ODE</label><item>    Oxford Dictionary of English (aka NODE), 2d ed.</item>
<label>        ORDS</label><item>   O'Reilly Default Stylesheet,
                <ptr target="http://www.oreilly.com/oreilly/author/stylesheet.html"/></item>
<label>        UCG</label><item>    Unicode Consortium Glossary, http://unicode.org/glossary/</item>
<label>        W3CXML</label><item> W3C XML Recommendation, http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/</item>
</list>
</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Naming conventions</head>
          <p>TEI naming conventions have evolved over time, but remain fairly consistent. </p>
          <list type="gloss">
            <label>generic identifiers</label>
            <item>An element and attribute identifiers should be a single natural language word in
              lowercase if possible. If more than one word is conjoined to form a name, then the
              first letter of the second and any subsequent word should be uppercased. Hyphens,
              underscores, dots etc are not used within element or attribute names. </item>
            <label>class names</label>
            <item>Class names are made up three parts: a name, constructed like an element name,
              with a prefix and optionally a suffix. The prefix is one of <code>model.</code> or
                <code>att.</code> and indicates whether this is a model or an attribute class. The
              suffix, if present, is used to indicate subclassing: for example
                <ident>att.linking.foo</ident> is the <ident>foo</ident> subclass of the attribute
              class <ident>att.linking</ident></item>
            <label>xml:id values</label>
            <item>The conventions for these vary somewhat. Most of the older chapters of the
              guidelines have consistently constructed identifiers, derived from the individual
              section headings. Identifiers must be provided for:- <list>
                <item>every <gi>div</gi>, whether or not it is explicitly linked to elsewhere</item>
                <item>every bibliographic reference in the <ident>BIB.xml</ident> file</item>
              </list></item>
          </list>
        </div>
<div xml:id="fileOrg"><head>File release structure</head>
<p>
Currently, the organisation of the <code>/usr/share/xml/tei</code> and
<code>/usr/share/doc/tei-*</code> directories on the TEI web site is
as follows:
<eg>
tei
|-- Test
|-- custom
|   |-- odd
|   |-- schema
|   |   |-- dtd
|   |   |-- relaxng
|   |   `-- xsd
|   `-- templates
|-- odd
|   |-- Exemplars
|   |-- ReleaseNotes
|   |-- Source
|   |   |-- Guidelines
|   |   |   |-- en
|   |   |   |   `-- Images
|   |   |   `-- fr
|   |   |       `-- Images
|   |   |-- Images
|   |   `-- Specs
|   |       |-- 18decembre
|   |       `-- exemples
|   |-- Utilities
|   `-- webnav
|       `-- icons
|-- schema
|   |-- dtd
|   `-- relaxng
|-- stylesheet
|   |-- common
|   |-- common2
|   |-- docx
|   |   |-- from
|   |   |   |-- dynamic
|   |   |   |   `-- tests
|   |   |   |       `-- xspec
|   |   |   |-- graphics
|   |   |   |-- lists
|   |   |   |-- marginals
|   |   |   |-- maths
|   |   |   |-- paragraphs
|   |   |   |-- pass0
|   |   |   |-- pass2
|   |   |   |-- tables
|   |   |   |-- templates
|   |   |   |-- textruns
|   |   |   |-- utils
|   |   |   `-- wordsections
|   |   |-- misc
|   |   |-- to
|   |   |   |-- docxfiles
|   |   |   |-- drama
|   |   |   |-- dynamic
|   |   |   |-- graphics
|   |   |   |-- lists
|   |   |   |-- maths
|   |   |   |-- templates
|   |   |   `-- wordsections
|   |   `-- utils
|   |       |-- graphics
|   |       |-- identity
|   |       |-- maths
|   |       `-- verbatim
|   |-- epub
|   |-- fo
|   |-- fo2
|   |-- html
|   |-- latex
|   |-- latex2
|   |-- nlm
|   |-- odds
|   |-- odds2
|   |-- oo
|   |-- profiles
|   |   |-- bodley
|   |   |   `-- epub
|   |   |-- default
|   |   |   |-- csv
|   |   |   |-- docbook
|   |   |   |-- docx
|   |   |   |-- dtd
|   |   |   |-- epub
|   |   |   |-- fo
|   |   |   |-- html
|   |   |   |-- latex
|   |   |   |-- lite
|   |   |   |-- oddhtml
|   |   |   |-- oo
|   |   |   |-- p4
|   |   |   `-- relaxng
|   |   |-- enrich
|   |   |   |-- docx
|   |   |   |-- fo
|   |   |   |-- html
|   |   |   `-- latex
|   |   |-- iso
|   |   |   |-- docx
|   |   |   |   `-- model
|   |   |   |-- epub
|   |   |   |-- fo
|   |   |   |-- html
|   |   |   |-- latex
|   |   |   |-- schema
|   |   |   `-- tbx
|   |   |-- ota
|   |   |   |-- epub
|   |   |   `-- html
|   |   |-- oucs
|   |   |   |-- docx
|   |   |   |-- epub
|   |   |   `-- p4
|   |   |-- oucscourses
|   |   |   `-- docx
|   |   |-- podcasts
|   |   |   |-- docx
|   |   |   `-- epub
|   |   `-- tei
|   |       `-- epub
|   |-- slides
|   |-- slides2
|   |-- tite
|   |-- tools2
|   |-- xhtml
|   `-- xhtml2
`-- xquery

</eg>
</p></div>

      </div>
    </body>
<back>
<div type="appendix">
<head>Some other (mostly superceded) documents on the topic</head>

<listBibl>
 <bibl ><idno>TEI ED W9</idno>
<title>Points of Style For Drafts of TEI Guidelines</title>
<date>2 Mar 1990</date>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw09.gml">in Waterloo Script format</ref>
</bibl>

<bibl >
<title>Notes on House Style</title>
<idno>TEI ED W11</idno>
<date>14 Sep 1992</date>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw11.gml">in Waterloo script</ref>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw11.txt">formatted text</ref>
</bibl>


 <bibl ><idno>TEI ED W55</idno>
<title>Form for Draft Chapters of the TEI Guidelines</title>
<date >5 june 1996</date>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw55.tei">in TEI P2 format</ref>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw55.htm">in HTML format</ref>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw55.odd">in ODD format</ref>
</bibl>

 <bibl ><idno>TEI ED W57</idno>
<title>Procedures for Correcting Errors in the TEI Guidelines</title>
<date >July 23, 1994</date>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw57.tei">in TEI P2 format</ref>
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw57.htm">in HTML format</ref>
</bibl>

</listBibl>
</div>
</back>  </text>
</TEI>
