<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI.2>
   <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
       <titleStmt>
	 <title>TEI Internationalisation proposal</title>
	 <author>Veronika Lux and Sebastian Rahtz</author>
       </titleStmt>
       <editionStmt>
       <edition><date>21st July 2005</date></edition></editionStmt>
       <publicationStmt>
            <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
	 <p>TEI Web</p>      
       </publicationStmt>
       <sourceDesc>
	 <p>No source</p>
       </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
     </profileDesc>
     <revisionDesc>
       <change>
	 <date>$Date$.</date>
	 <respStmt>
	   <name>$Author$</name>
	 </respStmt>
	 <item>$Revision$</item>
       </change>
     </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
<body>
<div>
<head>Summary</head>
<p>The Text Encoding Initiative Guidelines have been adopted by
projects and institutions in
many countries and used for encoding texts in dozens of languages.
However, the complex encoding of texts at which the TEI excels
needs a close understanding of the 522 available elements, and
non-English speakers are at a considerable disadvantage. 
Mistakes in using the TEI may come from misunderstanding the
explanations in English. The TEI needs to be made more accessible.</p>

<p>This proposal aims:
<list type="ordered">
  <item>to describe the type of internationalisation work which will be of
  maximum benefit to as many people as possible, assuming that
  translating the entire TEI Guidelines into many languages is not
  feasible.</item>
  <item>to describe the technical infrastructure by which
  internationalisation of the TEI material will be maintained and
  integrated into existing tools</item>
  <item>to lay out an initial workplan of languages to be addressed</item>
</list>
</p>

 
<p>From a research point of view, it will be interesting
to compare the TEI tailored documentation system with both
memory-based translation systems (eg. Trados) and with multilingual
document authoring systems (eg. MDA developped at Xerox Research
Center).</p>

<p>The TEI requests a grant of £10000, which it will use to deliver
materials to facilitate use of the TEI in five languages.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>Approach to translation</head>
<p>What do the TEI Guidelines consist of which can be translated?
There are three areas:
<list type="ordered">
  <item>The detailed descriptive prose of the Guidelines chapters</item>
 <item>The element, attribute
  names and suggested attribute values which are put into DTDs and
  schemas. Thus instead of <gi>addrLine</gi>, the TEI user might
  prefer to write <gi>líneaDirección</gi>, <gi>ligneAdresse</gi>,
  <gi>linDireccio</gi> or <gi>AdressZeile</gi>. The TEI has an
  established system for recording such translations, and preserving
  the relationship to the original names so that document instances
  can be put back into canonical form.
 </item>
  <item>The summary technical descriptions of elements or
  attributes. Thus instead of <q>contains a single TEI-conformant
  document, comprising a TEI header and a text, either in isolation or
  as part of a teiCorpus element.</q>, the Spanish-speaking user might
  find it more helpful to read <q>contiene un único documento TEI,
  compuesto de una cabecera TEI (TEI header) y un cuerpo de texto
  (text), aislado o como parte de un elemento corpusTei
  (teiCorpus)</q></item>
</list>
</p>

<p>There have already been six translations of the TEI Lite
documentation into other languages. This has not covered translation
of the element names or technical reference documentation.</p>

<p>The French <emph>Groupe d'experts n° 8</emph> within CN 357
(<emph>Commission de normalisation «Modélisation, production et accès
aux documents»</emph>) of the CG 46 (<emph>Commission générale
«Information et documentation»</emph>) at AFNOR has an interest in TEI
translation. Amongst other goals, this group intends to translate the
definitions of the TEI elements and attributes into French.  So far,
they have worked in a <q>traditional way</q> on some chapters of the
P4 and P5 versions.  Dissemination of the result (French version of
these chapter) is very limited.</p>

<p>Some work has also been undertaken on translating element and
attribute names; Alejandro Bia and Arno Mittelbach have prepared
translation sets of Catalan, Spanish, and German. This work is
integrated into the Roma (<xptr
target="http://www.tei-c.org.uk/Roma/"/>) application, allowing users
to create tailored schemas in one of the supported languages. However,
it is not necessarily the most effective way to proceed; this is
because many of the element names are in an abbreviated form of
English (eg <gi>respStmt</gi>) which are not easy to translate
sensibly, and because the abbreviated names are relatively easy to
recognize for people used to reading Latin script. Using
<gi>infoResp</gi> instead of <gi>respStmt</gi> is not as helpful as
translating <q> supplies a statement of responsibility for someone
responsible for the intellectual content of a text, edition,
recording, or series, where the specialized elements for authors,
editors, etc. do not suffice or do not apply.</q>
</p>


<p>Study of the work described aboves suggests that translating the
reference descriptions, followed by translation of element names, is
likely to be the most effective way to promote the TEI in non-English
speaking communities.
</p>


<p>The TEI documentation is built by assembling units stored in a database
(the source of the TEI Guidelines): translation will be done at the
level of these units. This allows
<list>
<item> Optimization of the translation. The idea would be to work as
in a translation memory, storing units and their translation. Only
modifed units would be translated again.</item>
<item> More advanced localisation of the documentation: users could
get a documentation with crucial technical parts (eg. definitions) in
French if they want to. </item>
</list>
<ptr target="example"/> shows the current display of reference
documentation. The labels in the left-hand column will appear in
translated form, as will the description text. 
<figure url="example.png" id="example" scale="0.5">
<head>Example of reference documentation</head>
</figure>
</p>
<p>It should be noted that the examples are hard to translate, as they
require cultural as well as linguistic localisation. Quotations from
Dickens or Beowulf would like need adapting for a Chinese readership, for
example. This work is beyond the scope of the current proposal.
</p>

</div>

<div>
<head>Language coverage</head>
<p>We do not believe that it is sensible to simply pay a professional
translator to convert the words, even had we funds enough; the
descriptive texts are often short and need genuine experience in text
encoding to translate well. Each translation set will also need to be
validated by other TEI users in the relevant language community. We
therefore propose to invite collaborating institutions to work with us
on each language.</p>

<p>The collaborator will supervise the creation of the
translations as they see fit, and will be offered a maximum of £2000
to assist the process (it could be used for paying graduate students,
for example). The results will then be undergo a check by a second
collaborator; and finally undergo a sanity check by the TEI editors
before final acceptance.</p>

<p>The choice of languages to cover will be driven mainly by the
amount of collaboration we can identify. We expect to cover French,
Spanish and German immediately, and we wish to offer at least one of
the CJK languages. Beyond that, we might expect to find collaborators
for  Portuguese (European or Brasilian), and Italian; and possibly Arabic. </p>

</div>


<div>
<head>Translation infrastructure</head>
<p>The TEI I18N Project will need to develop workflow and
infrastructure to create and deliver its outputs. This will
be in three parts:
<list type="ordered">
<item> A user-friendly environment to allow translators to
easily get the text units to translate and to put their translation in
the database. Translators
will not have to dowload P5 from Sourceforge, find the elements to
translate and send their translation by mail.
It is essential that, if translation is
performed on elementary documentation units, a readable 
document in e.g. French can be produced by assembling
these units, so that translators see the result of their ongoing work
concretely. Just putting translations in a database is not seen as a motivating goal!</item>
<item>Make the necessary technical developments to Roma so that it
permits more advanced documentation localisation. For example, the user
may be permitted to generate the following (where <q>descriptions</q> means
the contents of <gi>gloss</gi> and <gi>desc</gi>):
<list>
<item>canonical (English names, descriptions in English)</item>
<item>local descriptions (English names, descriptions in chosen
language) </item>
<item>local names (names designed to make sense to a speaker of the
chosen language, descriptions in English)</item>
<item>localized (both names and descriptions in chosen
language)</item>
</list>
</item>
<item>Enhancing the delivery infrastructure (XSLT stylesheets to make
HTML and PDF output) so that string constants are available in the
chosen language as well as the text. Thus reference document for an
attribute may talk about <q>Obligatoriu dacă se potriveşte</q> for
Rumanians instead of <q>Mandatory when applicable</q>.</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>


<div>
<head>Deliverables</head>
<p>This project will deliver, over a period of 6 months:
<list type="ordered">
<item>A web-based interface for submitting translations.</item>
<item>For a minimum of five languages, a translation of each element
and attribute name, and their associated description text, maintained
as part of the core TEI P5 source.</item>
<item>Support in the Roma schema-generation tool for producing
schemas and reference documentation in localized form.</item>
</list>
</p>
</div>
 
</body>
   </text>
 </TEI.2>
