<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?tei-web URI-base="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-xsl-common/"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>XSL stylesheets for TEI XML</title>
        <author>Sebastian Rahtz</author>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date>2013-07-20</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <availability status="restricted">
          <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	    Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
	  </licence>
          <licence target="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/BSD-2-Clause">
            <p>Copyright 2013 TEI Consortium.</p>
            <p>All rights reserved.</p>
            <p>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:</p>
            <list>
              <item>Redistributions of source code must retain the
	      above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
	      following disclaimer.</item>
              <item>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the
	      above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the
	      following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other
	      materials provided with the distribution.</item>
            </list>
            <p>This software is provided by the copyright holders and contributors
"as is" and any express or implied warranties, including, but not
limited to, the implied warranties of merchantability and fitness for
a particular purpose are disclaimed. In no event shall the copyright
holder or contributors be liable for any direct, indirect, incidental,
special, exemplary, or consequential damages (including, but not
limited to, procurement of substitute goods or services; loss of use,
data, or profits; or business interruption) however caused and on any
theory of liability, whether in contract, strict liability, or tort
(including negligence or otherwise) arising in any way out of the use
of this software, even if advised of the possibility of such
damage.</p>
          </licence>
          <p>TEI  material can be licensed differently depending on the use you intend to 
make of it. Hence it is made available under both the CC+BY and BSD-2 
licences.  The CC+BY licence is generally appropriate for usages which 
treat TEI content as data or documentation. The BSD-2 licence is 
generally appropriate for usage of TEI content in a software 
environment. For further information or clarification, please contact 
the <ref target="mailto:info@tei-c.org">TEI Consortium</ref>.
	  </p>
        </availability>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p/>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change>
        <date>$Date$.</date>
        <name>$Author$, $Revision$</name>
      </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <div>
        <head>Introduction</head>
        <p>This is a family of XSLT 2.0 stylesheets to transform TEI XML documents
to various formats, including XHTML, LaTeX, XSL Formatting Objects,
ePub, plain text, RDF, JSON;
and to/from Word OOXML (docx) and OpenOfice (odt).
They concentrate on the core TEI
modules which are used for simple transcription and <q>born
digital</q> writing. It is important to understand that they do <hi>not</hi>:
<list><item>cover <hi>all</hi> TEI elements and possible attribute values</item><item>attempt to define a standard TEI processing or rendering
model</item></list>
and should not be treated as the definitive view of the TEI Consortium.</p>
      </div>
          <div>
            <head>Profiles</head>
            <p>The stylesheets support a set of <ident>profiles</ident>, which are
redefined project starting points. They are implemented as a set of directories each of which may have a file
<ident>to.xsl</ident> for one or more of the supported output formats
(<ident>csv</ident>,
<ident>docbook</ident>,
<ident>docx</ident>,
<ident>dtd</ident>,
<ident>epub3</ident>,
<ident>epub</ident>,
<ident>fo</ident>,
<ident>html5</ident>,
<ident>html</ident>,
<ident>ibooks</ident>,
<ident>json</ident>,
<ident>latex</ident>,
<ident>lite</ident>,
<ident>oddhtml</ident>,
<ident>odt</ident>,
<ident>p4</ident>,
<ident>rdf</ident>,
<ident>relaxng</ident>,
<ident>tcp</ident>,
<ident>txt</ident>, and
<ident>xlsx</ident>). There may also be a <ident>from.xsl</ident>
to go <emph>from</emph> the selected format to TEI XML.</p>
          </div>

      <div>
        <head>Using the stylesheets</head>
        <p>The stylesheets are embedded in various services, or can be used on their own to perform
	the transformations. </p>
        <div>
          <head>oXygen editor</head>
          <p>The stylesheets are available for immediate use in the oXygen XML editor,
if you have the TEI framework installed (it is enabled by default). This will make various transformations available
immediately for documents which are detected as TEI. You set up a transformation
	by pressing the icon which looks like this: <graphic url="oxdump1.png"/>. The first time you do this, you should be offered a choice
          of built-in options: <lb/><graphic width="4in" url="oxdump2.png"/>.<lb/> From these, tick (for example) the
	  box by 
            <q>TEI P5 XHTML</q> and click on <code>Apply associated</code>.</p>
          <p>The transformation is run, and the default web browser is fired up with the resulting web
          page.</p>
          <p>If you want to make sure you keep up with the latest versions of these stylesheets, and the TEI P5 schemas, you can subscribe
to the TEI addon (maintained by the TEI Consortium) for oXygen. Go to <code>Add-ons</code> section of oXygen's <code>Preferences</code> and add 
<code>http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/updateSite.xml</code> to the list. Then go to  <code>Help/Manage add-ons</code> and activate the <emph>TEI P5 + XSL</emph>
entry. After a restart, you'll be using the latest version in preference to what is delivered with your copy of oXygen. When updates appear, you'll
be asked if you want to install them.</p>
          <div>
            <head>Rolling your own in oXygen</head>
            <p>In addition to editing the copy of the stylesheets in oXygen, you can sett up a copy of TEI framework, and configure oXygen
	  to look at it. First, grab the current oXygen TEI framework by downloading
	the big zip file from <ptr target="http://code.google.com/p/oxygen-tei/downloads/list"/>. Create a directory in your
	own directory area called <code>oxygenframeworks</code> and unpack
	the zip file into there.</p>
            <p>Start up oXygen, and go to Preferences/Global and
	scroll down on the right to <q>Use custom frameworks</q>, and
	put in your frameworks directory.</p>
            <p>
              <graphic width="3in" url="oxy-changeframeworks.png"/>
            </p>
            <p>Restart oXygen, and check that TEI support is still
	there. You can now edit your copy of the stylesheets, by creating (for example)
 a new profile directory, in
	<code>tei/xml/tei/stylesheet/profiles</code>. For exammple, to create your local profile for Word to TEI, create and a directory
	called <code>local</code>, and under that one called <code>docx</code>. In there, create a file
	called <code>from.xsl</code> which looks like this:
  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" rend="full"><xsl:stylesheet xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:w="http://schemas.openxmlformats.org/wordprocessingml/2006/main" version="2.0" exclude-result-prefixes="w"><xsl:import href="../../default/docx/from.xsl"/></xsl:stylesheet></egXML>
Edit that accordingly, and then choose the <code>local</code> profile in oXygen transformations.</p>
          </div>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>OxGarage web service</head>
          <p>OxGarage<note place="foot">Based on the Enrich Garage Engine
developed by Poznan Supercomputing and Networking Center and Oxford
University Computing Services for the ENRICH project.</note> is a web,
and RESTful, service to manage the transformation of documents between
a variety of formats. The majority of transformations have the TEI
format as a pivot format, using these stylesheets.</p>
          <p>There are instances of OxGarage at <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/ege-webclient/"/>
and
	<ptr target="http://oxgarage.oucs.ox.ac.uk:8080/ege-webclient"/> 
note that the latter is not a fully-supported service, so please do not rely on it for production use.</p>
          <p>OxGarage is open source, and runs as a Java servlet. 
A Debian package is available at <ptr target="http://tei.oucs.ox.ac.uk/teideb/"/>.
Source code is on Github at <ptr target="https://github.com/sebastianrahtz/oxgarage.git"/></p>
          <p>To use OxGarage, got to the web site, click on <emph>Documents</emph> and
select <emph>TEI P5 XML Document</emph> as your input. When you do so a list of
possible conversion targets should appear on the right. Choose, for
example, <emph>Microsoft Word Document (.docx)</emph>. When you've
done this a <emph>Choose File</emph> button should appear on the upper
left. Click the button and navigate to your file. Click the
<emph>Convert</emph> button and open the resulting document in
Microsoft Word.</p>
          <p>By selecting <emph>Show Advanced options</emph> you can access a drop-down list of the
different profiles supported for the current conversion path.</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Command-line scripts</head>
          <p>When the stylesheet package is installed, either by running <code>make install</code> from source,
or installing a Debian package, there are Linux/OSX command-line shell scripts available
(<ident>docbooktotei</ident>,
<ident>docxtotei</ident>,
<ident>odttotei</ident>,
<ident>tcptotei</ident>,
<ident>teitobibtex</ident>,
<ident>teitodocbook</ident>,
<ident>teitodocx</ident>,
<ident>teitodtd</ident>,
<ident>teitoepub</ident>,
<ident>teitoepub3</ident>,
<ident>teitofo</ident>,
<ident>teitohtml</ident>,
<ident>teitohtml5</ident>,
<ident>teitojson</ident>,
<ident>teitolatex</ident>,
<ident>teitoodd</ident>,
<ident>teitoodt</ident>,
<ident>teitopdf</ident>,
<ident>teitordf</ident>,
<ident>teitorelaxng</ident>,
<ident>teitornc</ident>,
<ident>teitoslides</ident>,
<ident>teitotxt</ident>,
<ident>teitoxsd</ident>, and
<ident>xlsxtotei</ident>)
for converting to/from Word, to/from OpenOffice, and to DTD, ePub,
HTML, RDF, Relax NG, plain text, W3C schema etc.  These are
implemented using Ant tasks, so a local installation of Java 1.6+ and Ant
is required.</p>
          <p>The simplest use of the scripts is (eg)
<eg>teitohtml <emph>inputfile</emph> <emph>outputfile</emph></eg>
but there are also a set of options, which you see by giving the command name followed by 
<code>--help</code>:
<eg xml:space="preserve">
<emph>$ teitohtml --help</emph>

TEI conversion: from tei to html

  Usage: /usr/bin/teitohtml [options] inputfile [outputfile]

  Options, binary switches:
  --verbose            # be verbose
  --debug              # be verbose, do not delete intermediate files
  --apphome=/usr/share/xml/tei/stylesheet   # where to find app directory
  --profiledir=/usr/share/xml/tei/stylesheet/profiles    # where to find profile directory
  --profile=default    # which transformation profile to use
  --oxygenlib=/usr/share/oxygen/lib    # where is oxygenlib
  --odd                # perform processing of ODD (if appropriate)
  --localsource=DIR    # where is local copy of source of TEI Guidelines
  --summaryDoc         # only make summary, when doing ODD processing

  Options, shown with defaults:
  --saxonjar=/usr/share/saxon/saxon9he.jar  # location of Saxon jar file
</eg>
</p>
        </div>
        <div>
          <head>Importing the XSL into your own stylesheet</head>
          <p>If, for example, you want to write a customization of the HTML conversion
you can simply refer to the specification <code>xhtml2/tei.xsl</code>
directly with your XSL processor, or install it locally on your own
server.  For more flexibility, you may prefer to reference the
specifications from an XSL wrapper of your own. The minimal
specification would look like this:
<eg><![CDATA[
<xsl:stylesheet 
   xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" version="1.0">
  <xsl:import href="xhtml2/tei.xsl"/>
</xsl:stylesheet>
]]></eg>
You can customize the result by adding to this wrapper file.  The normal result will be a single stream of HTML
which you can save in a file. You can also configure it to produce
multiple output files, one per top-level <gi>div</gi> or <gi>div1</gi>.
</p>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>File structure and customization</head>
        <p>The stylesheets files consist of a number of scripts, and seven 
main directories where most of the work is done:
<list type="gloss"><label>common2</label><item>templates which are independent of output
type, used by the other transformations</item><label>xhtml2</label><item>templates for making HTML output (also used
for ePub)</item><label>latex2</label><item>templates for making LaTeX output</item><label>docx</label><item>conversion to and from Word OOXML format</item><label>odt</label><item>conversion to and from OpenOffice ODF format</item><label>fo2</label><item>templates for making XSL FO output</item><label>odds2</label><item>processing of TEI ODD files</item></list>
Within each directory there is usually a separate file for the templates
which implement each of the TEI modules (eg
<ident>textstructure.xsl</ident>,
<ident>linking.xsl</ident>, or <ident>drama.xsl</ident>); these
are included by a master file <ident>tei.xsl</ident>. This also
includes a parameterization layer in the file
<ident>tei-param.xsl</ident>, and the parameterization file from
the <ident>common2</ident> directory. The <ident>tei.xsl</ident> does
any necessary declaration of constants and XSL keys.</p>
        <p>There are further directories  for other conversions, some which
are built on top of the xhtml one above:
<list type="gloss"><label>bibtex</label><item>conversion to BibTeX</item><label>docbook</label><item>conversion to/from Docbook</item><label>dtd</label><item>ODD conversion to DTD </item><label>epub</label><item>conversion to ePub</item><label>epub3</label><item>conversion to ePub3</item><label>html5</label><item>conversion to HTML5 </item><label>json</label><item>conversion to JSON</item><label>nlm</label><item>conversion to NLM </item><label>rdf</label><item>conversion to RDF (CIDOC CRM)</item><label>slides</label><item>conversion to LaTeX and HTML slides</item><label>tbx</label><item>conversion to TBX</item><label>tcp</label><item>conversion from Text Creation Partnership P4 XML</item><label>tite</label><item>conversion from TEI Tite to normal TEI P5</item><label>txt</label><item>conversion to plain text</item><label>xlsx</label><item>conversion from Microsoft Office spreadsheet format</item></list>
</p>
        <div xml:id="start">
          <head>Documentation of conversions and start points</head>
          <list>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/csv/from.html">Default conversion from CSV</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/csv/to.html">Default conversion to CSV</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/docbook/from.html">Default conversion to Docbook</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/docx/from.html">Default conversion from docx (OOXML)</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/docx/to.html">Default conversion to docx (OOXML)</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/epub/to.html">Default conversion to ePub</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/fo/to.html">Default conversion to XSL FO</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/html/to.html">Default conversion to XHTML</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/latex/to.html">Default conversion to LaTeX</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/odt/from.html">Default conversion from OpenOffice (odt) </ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/odt/to.html">Default conversion to OpenOffice (odt) </ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="profiles/default/p4/from.html">Default conversion from TEI P4</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="tcp/tcp2tei.html">Conversion from TCP EEBO</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="odds2/odd2odd.html">Conversion of ODD file to expanded ODD</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="odds2/odd2relax.html">Conversion of ODD to RELAX NG schema</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="odds2/odd2dtd.html">Conversion of ODD to DTD</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="slides/teihtml-slides.html">Default conversion to HTML slides</ref>
            </item>
            <item>
              <ref target="slides/teilatex-slides.html">Default conversion to LaTeX slides (using beamer package)</ref>
            </item>
          </list>
        </div>
      </div>
      <div>
        <head>Parameters and customizable templates</head>
        <p>The TEI stylesheets are designed to be customized. There
        are several hundred things you can set to change the output in
        various formats.  They are either XSL variables,  named
        templates which you can override, or  empty
	<soCalled>hook</soCalled> templates
into which you can add your own code. You need to understand a little of XSL
        syntax to work with these. If you know a bit more, you can override any of the
        templates in the style files, but then you are on your
        own.</p>
        <p>The <ref target="style.html">Stylebear</ref> web form
  will construct a XSL file for you, with all the variables configured. 
  </p>
        <p>You can also change any of the parameters from within the oXygen editor.
Do this by  going  to the stylesheet configuration.
Untick (eg) TEI P5 XHTML, but keep it highlighted and select
<q>Duplicate</q>. You should see something like this:<lb/>
<graphic width="4in" url="oxygen-duplicate-scenario1.png"/>
<lb/>Select <q>Parameters</q>, and you should see this: <lb/>
<graphic width="4in" url="oxygen-duplicate-scenario2.png"/>
<lb/>Now you can scroll down to find a parameter to change,
press <q>Edit</q> and you'll see a dialogue like this: <lb/>
<graphic width="4in" url="oxygen-duplicate-scenario3.png"/><lb/>
Change the value, press OK to exit each dialogue, and then
  <q>Apply Associated</q> to see the result.</p>
        <p>You might apply, for example, some changes to the HTML rendering, by setting parameters as followws, and
  checking the results: <list><item>Set <code>autoToc</code> to <q>false</q></item><item>Set <code>numberHeadings</code> to false</item><item>Set <code>pageLayout</code> to <q>CSS</q></item><item>Set <code>numberParagraphs</code> to <q>true</q></item></list>
  </p>
          <p> There are 13 areas for customization. In most cases there are
parameters and templates which are specific to one of the three main
output methods (HTML, FO and LaTeX), and those which are common to all
three.</p>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="links">
            <head>Standard page features</head>
            <p>The default behaviour of the system is to construct each HTML page
with per-page navigation bars top and bottom, and a standard set of
navigation links underneath. </p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="layout">
            <head>Layout</head>
            <p>There are a few ways to provide a constant navigation aid,
with a table of links on the left or right. </p>
            <p>Hypertext links present special problems, as we have to choose
whether they should start a new window, occupy all of the current
window, or stay within the frame. These stylesheets implement the
following rules:
<list type="ordered"><item>Any <gi>ref</gi> or <gi>ptr</gi> link stays within the frame</item><item>Any link containing <q>://</q> uses the whole browser window</item><item>Any link starting <q>.</q> uses the whole browser window</item><item>If the stylesheet sets no splitting of the document,
any <gi>ref</gi> or <gi>ptr</gi> link  uses the whole browser
window</item><item>If a <gi>ref</gi> or <gi>ptr</gi> link has a
<ident>rend</ident> attribute value of <q>noframe</q>, the whole browser
window is used</item><item>If a <gi>ref</gi> or <gi>ptr</gi> link has a
<ident>rend</ident> attribute value of <q>new</q>, a new browser window
is started</item></list>
</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="headings">
            <head>Headings</head>
            <p>Headings for sections can be customized in various ways.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="numbering">
            <head>Numbering</head>
            <p>Section headings, figures, tables and notes can be numbered
automatically.  We can set the numbering of front matter and back
matter separately. If you prefer to supply your own numbering, using
the <code>n</code> attribute, you can choose this over automatic
numbering.</p>
            <p>Normally, heading numbers are followed by <q>. </q>, but you can vary
this. This would let you use eg fixed spaces.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="output">
            <head>Output</head>
            <p>You can set a name for the output file(s); if you ask for multiple
output files, this name will be used to create unique filenames for
each section. By default, results will go to wherever your XSLT
processor normally writes (usually standard output).  If you opt to
have files created, you can specify the name of the directory where
the output is to be placed.</p>
            <p>If you are making HTML, do you want a single output page, or a
separate one for each section of the document?   You
can decide to have a different splitting policy for front and
back matter.  </p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="toc">
            <head>Table of contents generation</head>
            <p>You probably want tables of contents built for your document, using
the <gi>div</gi> structure. However, if you have used a <tag>divGen
type="toc"</tag> explicitly, that will also create a table of contents,
so you can suppress the automatic one.  When a table of contents is
created, you choose how many levels of headings it will show.
You can choose whether or not the front and backmatter appear
in the table of contents.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="i18n">
            <head>Internationalization</head>
            <p>At various places, the system has to create text. You can choose
the words it uses (eg translate them to another language).</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="CSS">
            <head>CSS</head>
            <p>Setting up material for the CSS file to accompany HTML output.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="tables">
            <head>Tables</head>
            <p>Default behaviour of table elements.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="figures">
            <head>Figures and graphics</head>
            <p>Sometimes you need to prefix the names of all graphics files with 
a directory name or a URL, or provide a default suffix.
You can also tell <gi>figure</gi> elements whether or not to
produce anything.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="style">
            <head>Style</head>
            <p>You can choose lots of features which affect the font, size, etc
<list><item>What font to use for URLs.</item><item>Whether titles, dates and authors are shown.</item><item>Whether headings of objects are included in cross-references.</item></list>
</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="hook">
            <head>Hooks</head>
            <p>A set of templates which are empty by default; they can be used
to add code at strategic points. The content must be valid XSLT.</p>
          </div>
          <div type="param"  xml:id="misc">
            <head>Miscellaneous and advanced</head>
            <p>Finally, some miscellaneous or advanced features which you probably won't
use much.</p>
          </div>
        </div>

      <div>
        <head>Notes on XSLT processors and XSL FO</head>
        <p>These stylesheets use XSLT 2.0, and have only been tested
        with Saxon (from <ptr
        target="http://saxon.sourceforge.net"/>). An older set of XSLT
        1.0 stylesheets are also available, but is not maintained or
        updated.</p>
        <p>It is up to the user to find out how to run the XSLT
        processor! This may be from within a Java program, from your
        editor, on the command-line, or inside a web server.</p>
        <p>The XSL FO style sheets were developed for use with
        PassiveTeX (<ptr
        target="http://projects.oucs.ox.ac.uk/passivetex/"/>), a
        system using XSL formatting objects to render XML to PDF via
        LaTeX. They have not been extensively tested with the other
        XSL FO implementations.</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
