<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 0.4.1 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date>2 July 2006</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
	<p>TEI Web</p>      
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>No source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <profileDesc>
    </profileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>Notable changes since the last packaged release (0.3.1, January
	2006) are listed briefly below (please refer to the ChangeLog in
	directory ReleaseNotes in the Sourceforge archive for a full list).

	<list>
	  <item>Revision of the TEI class system continues, with the definition
	    of several new classes following on from a systematic review of all
	    content models by the Council (see <ptr
	      target="http://www.tei-c.org/Council/tcw07.xml"/>).</item>

	  <item>
	    Detailed proposals for the encoding of personal data (for example in
	    biographies), developed from those formerly in the Corpus module
	    enhanced by work carried out by the "Personography" activity, have
	    been developed to form a new section of the chapter on names and
	    dates.</item>

	  <item>A new P5 conformant version of the TEI Lite schema was developed,
	    correcting some errors in the existing specification and converting
	    it to ODD format. This revised Lite specification now forms part of
	    the Exemplars suite in the package; the chapter on Modifying the
	    Guidelines has not yet been updated to refer to this new version
	    however.</item>

	  <item>A substantial effort was put into reorganization into a new
	    directory structure for the source (ODD) files from which the
	    Guidelines and schemas are generated. A framework for the
	    production of element specifications and documentation in languages
	    other than English is now in place and has been tested with a new
	    French translation of the TEI Header chapter, and with translations
	    of element specifications into variety of languages. </item>
	  <item>
	    Several stylesheet bugs were fixed and a new CSS style is now used to
	    present an XHTML version of the Guidelines.</item>
	  <item>a new attribute method is provided for the <gi>classSpec</gi> element,
	    which enables the user to determine how the class should be applied
	    when it is used inside a content model </item>
	  <item>elements <gi>dateStruct</gi> and <gi>timeStruct</gi> were removed, and attributes
	    <att>notBefore</att> and <att>notAfter</att> added to
	    <gi>date</gi> and <gi>time</gi>. </item>
	  <item>Removed specifications for mix and gen entities, and some
	    elements no longer used etc.</item>
	  <item>a long-standing error in the usage rules for the attributes of
	    the <gi>relation</gi> element was corrected</item>
	  <item>attributes were added to <gi>schemaSpec</gi> to control production of
	    multilingual versions</item>
	  <item>Several content models (including those of
	    <gi>argument</gi>, <gi>div</gi>, and <gi>divN</gi>) were fixed, mostly to permit
	    global elements more globally.</item>
	</list>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
