<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 2.5.0 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2013-07-26">26 July 2013</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog and SourceForge
        trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>This version of the TEI is an maintenance release to solve minor issues which were found after 
<ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/readme-2.4.0.html">release 2.4.0</ref>. 
      The changes in this release will not affect the majority of users of the TEI Guidelines. These maintenance fixes primarily are  
      related to errors found in the processing of the English and French documentation of the TEI Lite example customization.</p>
     
      <p>Since it was decided by the TEI Technical Council that these errors necessitated a maintenance release,  
      the opportunity has been taken to correct a number of other issues. These include an omission made when the element
      <gi>precision</gi> was first introduced in 2009, explained on the <ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/585/">bug
      report 585</ref>. This gives the element attributes from the <code>att.ranging</code> class which it was always intended to have. 
      Also the <att>xml:space</att> attribute had previously been accidentally removed from the TEI Lite example customization, and this 
      was restored. Because these change the underlying TEI schema, rather than just the prose, the release numbering increases from  
      2.4.* to 2.5.*.</p>

<p>Other non-schema affecting changes include:
<list>
<item>There were a number of improvements to examples or corrections of typos in documentation for:
<list><item><gi>precision</gi></item><item>att.datable</item><item>att.scoping</item><item>att.responsibility</item></list></item>
<item>There were a number of other corrections to the TEI Lite sources.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>
If you find something you think needs to change in the TEI Guidelines, schemas, tools, or website, please submit a feature request or bug ticket at <ref target="http://tei.sf.net/">http://tei.sf.net/</ref> for consideration by the TEI Technical Council. Lists of 
<ref target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/search/?q=status%3Aclosed-wont-fix+or+status%3Aclosed-rejected+or+status%3Aclosed-out-of-date+or+ status%3Aclosed-accepted+or+status%3Aclosed-works-for-me+or+status%3Aclosed+or+status%3Aclosed-duplicate+or+status%3Aclosed-invalid+or+status%3Aclosed-fixed" >closed bugs</ref> and 
<ref target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/search/?q=status%3Aclosed-wont-fix+or+status%3Aclosed-later+or+status%3Aclosed-rejected+or+status%3Aclosed-out-of-date+or+status%3Aclosed-accepted+or+status%3Aclosed-remind+or+status%3Aclosed+or+status%3Aclosed-duplicate+or+status%3Aclosed-invalid+or+status%3Aclosed-fixed">closed feature requests</ref> are available on the site. 
</p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
