<?xml version="1.0"?>
<?tei-web URI-base="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-xsl-common/"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>XSL stylesheets for TEI XML</title>
        <author>Sebastian Rahtz</author>
      </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>
		    <date>2010-02-12</date>
                  </edition>
               </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<availability status="restricted">
	  <licence target="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/3.0/">
	    Distributed under a Creative Commons Attribution-ShareAlike 3.0 Unported License
	  </licence>
	  <licence target="http://www.opensource.org/licenses/BSD-2-Clause">
	    <p>Copyright 2011 TEI Consortium.</p>
	    <p>All rights reserved.</p>
	    
	    <p>Redistribution and use in source and binary forms, with or without modification, are permitted provided that the following conditions are met:</p>
	    <list>
	      <item>Redistributions of source code must retain the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer.</item>
	      <item>Redistributions in binary form must reproduce the above copyright notice, this list of conditions and the following disclaimer in the documentation and/or other materials provided with the distribution.</item>
</list>


<p>This software is provided by the copyright holders and contributors
"as is" and any express or implied warranties, including, but not
limited to, the implied warranties of merchantability and fitness for
a particular purpose are disclaimed. In no event shall the copyright
holder or contributors be liable for any direct, indirect, incidental,
special, exemplary, or consequential damages (including, but not
limited to, procurement of substitute goods or services; loss of use,
data, or profits; or business interruption) however caused and on any
theory of liability, whether in contract, strict liability, or tort
(including negligence or otherwise) arising in any way out of the use
of this software, even if advised of the possibility of such
damage.</p>
</licence>
	  <p>TEI  material can be licensed differently depending on the use you intend to 
make of it. Hence it is made available under both the CC+BY and BSD-2 
licences.  The CC+BY licence is generally appropriate for usages which 
treat TEI content as data or documentation. The BSD-2 licence is 
generally appropriate for usage of TEI content in a software 
environment. For further information or clarification, please contact 
the <ref target="mailto:info@tei-c.org">TEI Consortium</ref>.
	  </p>
	</availability>	  
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p></p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>$Date$.</date>
            <respStmt>
               <name>$Author$</name>
            </respStmt>
            <item>$Revision$</item>
         </change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
<body>
<div><head>Introduction</head>
<p>This is a set of XSLT 2.0 specifications to transform TEI XML documents
to XHTML, to LaTeX, to XSL Formatting Objects, to/from OOXML (docx), to/from OpenOfice (odt) and to ePub
format.  The files can be downloaded from the Releases area of <ptr
target="http://tei.sf.net"/>.  They concentrate on the simpler TEI
modules, but adding support for other modules is fairly easy. In the
main, the setup has been used on <q>new</q> documents, ie reports and
web pages that have been authored from scratch, rather than
traditional TEI-encoded existing material.
</p>

<p>There is a <ref target="ChangeLog">change log</ref> file
available.</p>

<p>The XSL FO style sheets were developed for use with PassiveTeX (<ptr
target="http://projects.oucs.ox.ac.uk/passivetex/"/>),
a system using XSL formatting objects to render XML to PDF via
LaTeX. They have not  been extensively tested with the
other XSL FO implementations.</p>
</div>

<div>
<head>File organisation</head>
<p>The main stylesheets are divided into four directories:
<list type="gloss">
<label>common</label><item>templates which are independent of output type</item>
<label>fo</label><item>templates for making XSL FO output</item>
<label>html</label><item>templates for making HTML output</item>
<label>latex</label><item>templates for making LaTeX output</item>
</list>
Within each directory there is a separate file for the templates
which implement each of the TEI modules (eg
<ident>textstructure.xsl</ident>,
<ident>linking.xsl</ident>, or <ident>drama.xsl</ident>); these
are included by a master file <ident>tei.xsl</ident>. This also
includes a parameterization layer in the file
<ident>tei-param.xsl</ident>, and the parameterization file from
the <ident>common</ident> directory. The <ident>tei.xsl</ident> does
any necessary declaration of constants and XSL keys.</p>

<p>There are further directories  for special-purposes
conversions:
<list type="gloss">
<label>epub</label><item>conversion to ePub</item>
<label>odt</label><item>conversion to and from OpenOffice Writer format</item>
<label>docx</label><item>conversion to and from Word OOXML format</item>
<label>odds</label><item>processing of TEI ODD files</item>
<label>rdf</label><item>conversion to RDF</item>
<label>txt</label><item>conversion to plain text</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>The final important directory is <ident>profiles</ident>, which has
a set of predefined project starting points, each of which may have a file
<ident>to.xsl</ident> for one or more of the supported output formats
(<ident>csv</ident>, <ident>dtd</ident>, <ident>html</ident>,
<ident>odt</ident>, <ident>docbook</ident>, <ident>epub</ident>,
<ident>latex</ident>, <ident>p4</ident>, <ident>docx</ident>,
<ident>fo</ident>, <ident>lite</ident>, and
<ident>relaxng</ident>). There may also be a <ident>from.xsl</ident>
to go <emph>from</emph> the selected format to TEI XML.</p>
<p>For example, to convert TEI to HTML in the default mannner, the user may run
<ident>profiles/default/html/to.xsl</ident> on the selected input file. Other starting points are
listed below.</p>

<p>For the brave, there are Linux/OSX command-line shell scripts
<ident>docxtotei</ident>, <ident>odttotei</ident>,
<ident>teitodocx</ident>, <ident>teitodtd</ident>,
<ident>teitoepub</ident>, <ident>teitoepub3</ident>,
<ident>teitohtml</ident>, <ident>teitoodt</ident>,
<ident>teitordf</ident>, <ident>teitorelaxng</ident>,
<ident>teitornc</ident>, <ident>teitotxt</ident>, and
<ident>teitoxsd</ident> for converting to Word, OpenOffice, DTD, ePub,
HTML, RDF, Relax NG, plain text, W3C schema etc.  These aare
implemented using Ant tasks, which are also available within the
oXygen XML editor as part of the TEI framework.</p>

<p>Any other use of the stylesheets, eg by referencing individual
modules, is not supported and requires good understanding of XSL.</p>
</div>

<div xml:id="start">
  <head>Documentation of generic start points</head>
<list>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/csv/from.html">Default conversion from CSV</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/csv/to.html">Default conversion to CSV</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/docbook/from.html">Default conversion to Docbook</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/docx/from.html">Default conversion from docx (OOXML)</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/docx/to.html">Default conversion to docx (OOXML)</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/epub/to.html">Default conversion to ePub</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/fo/to.html">Default conversion to XSL FO</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/html/to.html">Default conversion to XHTML</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/latex/to.html">Default conversion to LaTeX</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/oo/from.html">Default conversion from OpenOffice (odt) </ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/oo/to.html">Default conversion to OpenOffice (odt) </ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/default/p4/from.html">Default conversion to TEI P4</ref></item>
<item><ref target="odds/odd2odd.html">Conversion of ODD file to expanded ODD</ref></item>
<item><ref target="odds/odd2relax.html">Conversion of ODD to RELAX NG schema</ref></item>
<item><ref target="odds/odd2dtd.html">Conversion of ODD to DTD</ref></item>
<item><ref target="slides/teihtml-slides.html">Default conversion to HTML slides</ref></item>
<item><ref target="slides/teilatex-slides.html">Default conversion to LaTeX slides (using beamer)</ref></item>
</list>
</div>

<div xml:id="start-enrich">
  <head>Documentation of start points for ENRICH manuscript
  description customization</head>
<list>
<item><ref target="profiles/enrich/docx/to.html">ENRICH conversion to docx (OOXML)</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/enrich/fo/to.html">ENRICH conversion to XSL FO</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/enrich/html/to.html">ENRICH conversion to XHTML</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/enrich/latex/to.html">ENRICH conversion to LaTeX</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/enrich/docx/from.html">ENRICH conversion from docx (OOXML)</ref></item>
</list>
</div>

<div xml:id="start-iso">
  <head>Documentation of start points for ISO customization</head>
<list>
<item><ref target="profiles/iso/docx/to.html">ISO conversion to docx (OOXML)</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/iso/fo/to.html">ISO conversion to XSL FO</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/iso/html/to.html">ISO conversion to XHTML</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/iso/latex/to.html">ISO conversion to LaTeX</ref></item>
<item><ref target="profiles/iso/docx/from.html">ISO conversion from docx (OOXML)</ref></item>
</list>
</div>


<div><head>Customization</head>
<p>
  The TEI stylesheets are designed to be customized, and I will
  gladly add more parameterization in future. There are currently
  several hundred things you can set to change the output, described
  in the <ref target="customize.html">Customization Handbook</ref>.
  They are either XSLT variables, or named templates, so
  you need to understand a little of XSL syntax. If you know
  a  bit more, you can override any of the templates in the style files, 
  but then you are on your own.</p>

  <p>The <ref target="style.html">Stylebear</ref> web form
  will construct a XSL file for you, with all the variables configured. 
  </p>
  
</div>


<div>
<head>XSLT processors</head>
<p>
These stylesheets use XSLT 2.0, and have only been testd
Saxon (from <ptr target="http://saxon.sourceforge.net"/>). XSLT 1.0
stylesheets are also available, but will not be further maintained. It
is up to the user to find out how to run the XSLT processor! This may
be from within a Java program, from your editor, on the command-line,
or inside a web server.</p>
</div>

</body>
<back>
</back>
</text>
</TEI>


