<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="msdescription" xml:id="ACCMAT" ident="accMat">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>accompanying material</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">동봉 자료</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">伴隨資料</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">matériel d'accompagnement</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">material adicional</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">materiale allegato</gloss>
  <desc xml:id="accmat.desc">contains details of any significant additional
material which may be closely associated with the manuscript being
described, such as non-contemporaneous documents or fragments bound in
with the manuscript at some earlier historical period.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">기술하고 있는 원고와 밀접히 관련된 중요한 부가적 자료를 세밀하게 기술한다. 예를 들어, 어떤 이전 시기에 원고와 함께 제본된 비동시대의 문서  또는 문서 일부.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含可能與該手稿關係密切的重要附加資料之細節，例如非同時期的文件或是在早期與手稿裝訂一起的片段。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該手書き資料と関連する情
  報の詳細を記述するための要素．例えば，当該手書き資料が書かれた時代と
  は異なる時期の文書や断片についてについての詳細を示す．例えば，当該手
  書き資料が作成された以前に書かれた文書やその断片であったりするものに
  ついて．
</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">donne des détails sur tout matériel d'accompagnement
      étroitement associé au manuscrit, tel que documents non contemporains ou fragments reliés avec
      le manuscrit à une époque antérieure.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene eventuales detalles que conciernen a materiales añadidos estrechamente relacionados con el manuscrito examinado, p.ej. documentos no actuales o fragmentos cosidos junto al manuscrito en un período histórico precedente al actual.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene eventuali dettagli riguardanti maeriale aggiuntivo strettamente collegato al manoscritto in esame, per esempio documenti non attali o frammenti rilegati insieme al manoscritto in un periodo storico precedente a quello attuale</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="model.physDescPart"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.specialPara"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <accMat>A copy of a tax form from 1947 is included in the envelope
with the letter. It is not catalogued separately.</accMat>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <accMat>A copy of a tax form from 1947 is included in the envelope with the letter. It is
          not catalogued separately.</accMat>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <accMat>有張1947年的稅單一同與此信件放於信封裡，不單獨分類。</accMat>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#msadac"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
