<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="msdescription" xml:id="ADDITIONS" ident="additions">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">ajouts</gloss>
  <desc xml:id="additions.desc">contains a description of any significant additions found
within a manuscript, such as marginalia or other annotations. </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">방주 또는 기타 주석과 같이 원고 내의 중요한 부가정보의 기술을 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含手稿中任何重要增添文字的描述，例如旁註或其他註釋。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  当該手書き資料中にある，重要な付加物を示す．例えば，欄外の書き込みや
  注釈など．
  </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">contient la description des ajouts significatifs
      trouvés dans un manuscrit, tels que gloses marginales ou autres annotations.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una descripción de cualquier adición significativa encontrada al interno de un manuscrito como notas al márgen u otras anotaciones.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene un descrizione di qualsiasi aggiunta significativa trovata all'interno di un manoscritto come note a margine o altre annotazioni</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.physDescPart"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.specialPara"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <additions>
        <p>There are several marginalia in this manuscript. Some consist of
single characters and others are figurative. On 8v is to be found a drawing of
a mans head wearing a hat. At times sentences occurs: On 5v: 
<q xml:lang="is">Her er skrif andres isslendin</q>, 
on 19r: <q xml:lang="is">þeim go</q>, 
on 21r: <q xml:lang="is">amen med aund ok munn halla rei knar hofud summu all huad
batar þad mælgi ok mal</q>, 
On 21v: some runic letters and the sentence  <q xml:lang="la">aue maria gracia plena dominus</q>.</p>
      </additions>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <additions>
        <p>There are several marginalia in this manuscript. Some consist of single characters and
            others are figurative. On 8v is to be found a drawing of a mans head wearing a hat. At
            times sentences occurs: On 5v:<q xml:lang="is">Her er skrif andres isslendin</q>, on
            19r: <q xml:lang="is">þeim go</q>, on 21r: <q xml:lang="is">amen med aund ok munn halla
              rei knar hofud summu all huad batar þad mælgi ok mal</q>, On 21v: some runic letters
            and the sentence <q xml:lang="la">aue maria gracia plena dominus</q>.</p>
      </additions>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#msph2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
