<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="GLOBAL" type="atts" ident="att.global">
  <desc>provides attributes common to all elements in the TEI encoding scheme.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">TEI 부호화 스키마의 모든 요소에 공통 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供一組屬性，通用於TEI編碼標準中的所有元素。 </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> TEI符号化スキーム中の全要素に共通する属性を示す． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">fournit un jeu d'attributs communs à tous les éléments
    dans le système de codage TEI.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona un conjunto de atributos común a todos los
    elementos del esquema de codificación TEI.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">stabilisce un insieme di attributi comuni a tutti gli
    elementi dello schema di codifica TEI</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global.linking"/>
    <memberOf key="att.global.analytic"/>
    <memberOf key="att.global.facs"/>
    <memberOf key="att.global.change"/>
  </classes>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="xml:id" usage="opt">
      <gloss>identifier</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">확인소</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">identificador</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">identifiant</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">identificatore</gloss>
      <desc>provides a unique identifier for the element bearing the attribute.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">속성을 포함하는 요소에 대한 고유한 확인소를 제공한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供一個獨特識別符碼，識別帶有該屬性的元素。 </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該要素にユニークな識別子を示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">fournit un identifiant unique pour l'élément qui
        porte l'attribut</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona un identificador único para el elemento
        al cual se asocia el atributo.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna un identificatore unico all'elemento a cui è
        associato l'attributo</desc>
      <datatype>
        <data xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="ID"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any valid XML identifier.</valDesc>
      <valDesc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">tout identifiant XML valide.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>The <att>xml:id</att> attribute may be used to specify a canonical reference for an
          element; see section <ptr target="#CORS"/>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>L'attribut <att>xml:id</att> peut être employé pour indiquer une référence canonique pour
          un élément ; voir la section<ptr target="#CORS"/>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>El atributo <att>xml:id</att> se puede utilizar para especificar una referencia canónica
          para un elemento; ver la sección <ptr target="#CORS"/>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 当該属性<att>xml:id</att>は，属性の指示対象を示している．詳細 は<ptr target="#CORS"/>を参照のこと． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="n" usage="opt">
      <gloss>number</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">수</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">número</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">nombre</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">numero</gloss>
      <desc>gives a number (or other label) for an element, which is not necessarily unique within
        the document.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">요소의 번호(또는 다른 표지)를 제시하며, 문서 내에서 반드시 고유값일 필요는 없다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">將元素標上一個數字 (或其他標號)，該標號在文件中未必是獨特的。 </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 要素に数値やラベルを与える．これは当該文書中でユニークである必要 はない． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">donne un nombre (ou une autre étiquette) pour un
        élément, qui n'est pas nécessairement unique dans le document TEI.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona un número (u otra etiqueta) a un elemento
        que no es necesariamente único en el documento.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna un numero (o altra etichetta) a un elemento
        che non è necessariamente unico all'interno del documento</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="1">
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.text"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>the value consists of a single token which may however
      contain punctuation
      characters, whitespace or word
      separating characters. It need not be restricted to
      numbers.</valDesc>
      <valDesc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">toute chaîne de caractères ; souvent, mais pas
        nécessairement, numérique.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>The <att>n</att> attribute may be used to specify the numbering of chapters, sections,
          list items, etc.; it may also be used in the specification of a standard reference system
          for the text.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>L'attribut <att>n</att> peut être employé pour indiquer la numérotation de chapitres,
          sections, items de liste, etc. ; il peut également être employé dans les spécifications
          d'un système standard de référence pour le texte. </p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>El atributo <att>n</att> se puede utilizar para especificar la enumeración de los
          capítulos, de las secciones, de los items de una lista, etc.; puede también ser utilizado
          en la especificación de un sistema de referencia estándar para el texto.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 当該属性<att>n</att>は，章・節・リスト項目などの番号を特定する ために使われる．これは，テキストを指示する標準参照システムにお いも採用されている． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="xml:lang" usage="opt">
      <gloss>language</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">언어</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">lengua</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">langue</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">lingua</gloss>
      <desc>indicates the language of the element content using a <soCalled>tag</soCalled> generated
        according to <ref target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47</ref>
         </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko"><ref target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47</ref>에 따라 생성된
        <soCalled>tag</soCalled>를 사용하는 요소 내용의 언어를 나타낸다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">使用<ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3066.txt">RFC3066</ref>的代碼，指出該元素內容的使用語言 </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該要素の内容で使用されている言語を， <ref target="http://www.rfc-editor.org/rfc/bcp/bcp47.txt">BCP 47</ref>
        に準拠して作られた<soCalled>タグ</soCalled>で示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique la langue du contenu de l'élément en
        utilisant les codes du <ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3066.txt">RFC 3066</ref>
         </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la lengua del contenido del elemento
        utilizando los códigos extraídos de <ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3066.txt">RFC
          3066</ref>
         </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la lingua del contenuto dell'elemento
        utilizzando i codici tratti da <ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc3066.txt">RFC
        3066</ref>
         </desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.language"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>The value must conform to BCP 47. If the value is a
      private use code (i.e., starts with <val>x-</val> or contains
      <val>-x-</val>), a <gi>language</gi> element with a matching
      value for its <att>ident</att> attribute should be supplied in
      the TEI Header to document this value. Such documentation may
      also optionally be supplied for non-private-use codes, though
      these must remain consistent with their
      <choice><abbr>IETF</abbr><expan>Internet Engineering Task
      Force</expan></choice> definitions.</valDesc>
      <valDesc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">La valeur doit être conforme au BCP 47. Si la
        valeur est un code d'usage privé (c'est-à-dire commence par <code>x-</code> ou contient
      <code>-x-</code>),  il devrait correspondre à la valeur d'un attribut <att>ident</att> d'un élément <gi>language</gi> fourni dans l'en-tête TEI du document courant.</valDesc>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
	<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="en">
	  <p> … The consequences of
	  this rapid depopulation were the loss of the last
	  <foreign xml:lang="rap">ariki</foreign> or chief
	  (Routledge 1920:205,210) and their connections to
	  ancestral territorial organization.</p>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>the xml:lang value will be inherited from the immediately
enclosing element, or from its parent, and so on up the document hierarchy.
It is generally good practice to specify xml:lang at the highest
appropriate level, noticing that a different default may be needed for the
teiHeader from that needed for the associated resource element or elements,
and that a single TEI document may contain texts in many languages.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p> Si aucune valeur n'est indiquée pour <att>xml:lang</att>, la valeur de
            l'attribut<att>xml:lang</att> de l'élément immédiatement supérieur est héritée ; c'est
          pour cette raison qu'une valeur devrait toujours être attribuée à l'élément du plus haut
          niveau hiérarchique (<gi>TEI</gi>).</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>Si no se especifica ningún valor para <att>xml:lang</att>, el valor de <att>xml:lang</att> para el elemento inmediatamente englobado, se hereda; por esta razón, un valor
          se debe especificar siempre en el elemento exterior (<gi>TEI</gi>).</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 当該属性<att>xml:lang</att>に値がない場合には，親要素にある属 性値を継承する．従って，一番外側の要素(すなわち<gi>TEI</gi>)の
          属性値は常に継承されることになる． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>

    <attDef ident="rend" usage="opt">
      <gloss>rendition</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">번역</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">interpretación</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">interprétation</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">resa</gloss>
      <desc>indicates how the element in question was rendered or presented in the source text.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">문제의 요소가 원본 텍스트에 제시된 방법을 나타낸다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出該元素如何呈現於來源文件中 </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該要素が，元資料でどのように表示されていたかを示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique comment l'élément en question a été rendu ou
        présenté dans le texte source</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica cómo el elemento en cuestión ha sido dado o
        proporcionado en el texto fuente.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica come l'elemento in questione è stato reso o
        rappresentato nel testo originario</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.word"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>may contain any number of tokens, each of which may
      contain letters, punctuation marks, or symbols, but not whitespace or 
      word-separating characters.</valDesc>
      <valDesc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">toute chaîne de caractères ; si la restitution
        typographique d'un texte doit être systématiquement notée, un jeu systématique de
        valeurs pour l'attribut <att>rend</att> doit être défini.</valDesc>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)"><lb/>To The <lb/>Duchesse <lb/>of <lb/>Newcastle,
            <lb/>On Her <lb/><hi rend="case(mixed)">New Blazing-World</hi>. </head>
        </egXML>
        <!--    <p>
          <note type="cit">From the foreword by William Newcastle in
        Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of Newcastle's <title>The
        description of a new world, called the blazing-world</title>,
        WWP TR00253</note>
        </p>-->
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum versionDate="2010-02-26" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Belloy">
          <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">épître dédicatoire<lb/>à <lb/>Monsieur de Coucy <lb/>
                  <lb/>.</head>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>These Guidelines make no binding recommendations for the values of the <att>rend</att>
          attribute; the characteristics of visual presentation vary too much from text to text and
          the decision to record or ignore individual characteristics varies too much from project
          to project. Some potentially useful conventions are noted from time to time at appropriate
          points in the Guidelines. The values of the <att>rend</att> attribute are a set of 
	sequence-indeterminate individual tokens separated by whitespace.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Ces Principes directeurs ne font aucune recommandation contraignante pour les valeurs de
          l'attribut <att>rend</att>; les caractéristiques de la présentation visuelle changent trop
          d'un texte à l'autre et la décision d'enregistrer ou d'ignorer des caractéristiques
          individuelles est trop variable d'un projet à l'autre. Quelques conventions
          potentiellement utiles sont notées de temps en temps à des points appropriés dans ces
          Principes directeurs.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>Estas guías de consulta no hacen ninguna recomendación obligatoria para los valores del
          atributo <att>rend</att>; las características de la presentación visual varían demasiado
          de texto a texto y la decisión para registrar o para omitir características individuales
          varía demasiado de proyecto a proyecto. Observar algunas convenciones que puedan resultar
          útiles en los puntos indicados en las guías de consulta.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 本ガイドラインでは，当該属性<att>rend</att>の値として推奨するも のはない．活字表現の特徴は様々であり，それらのどれを採用するかは
          プロジェクトごとで異なるからである．当ガイドラインでは，有用な記 述法があれば，その都度示すことになっている． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
<attDef ident="style" usage="opt">
<desc>contains an expression in some formal style definition language
which defines the rendering or presentation
used for this element in the source text </desc>
<datatype maxOccurs="1">
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.text"/>
      </datatype>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <head style="text-align: center; font-variant: small-caps"><lb/>To The <lb/>Duchesse <lb/>of <lb/>Newcastle, <lb/>On Her
              <lb/><hi style="font-variant: normal">New Blazing-World</hi>. </head>
</egXML></exemplum>
<remarks><p>Unlike the attribute values of <att>rend</att>, the <att>style</att> attribute may contain whitespace. This attribute 
is intended for recording inline stylistic information concerning the source, not any particular output.</p></remarks>
</attDef>

    <attDef ident="rendition" usage="opt">
      <desc>points to a description of the rendering or presentation used for this element in the
        source text.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">원본 텍스트에서 이 요소에 대해 사용된 모양과 제시에 대한 기술을 가리킨다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">indica una descripción de la representación o de la
        presentación empleada para este elemento en el texto original.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該要素が示す表現が現れている，元資料のテキスト部分を示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">pointe vers une description du rendu ou de la
        présentation utilisés pour cet élément dans le texte source</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">indica una descrizione della resa o della
        presentazione utilizzate per tale elemento nel testo di partenza</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more URIs, separated by whitespace.</valDesc>
      <valDesc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">un ou plusieurs URIs, séparé par des blancs.</valDesc>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <head rendition="#ac #sc"><lb/>To The <lb/>Duchesse <lb/>of <lb/>Newcastle, <lb/>On Her
              <lb/><hi rendition="#no">New Blazing-World</hi>. </head>
          <!-- elsewhere... -->
          <rendition xml:id="sc" scheme="css">font-variant: small-caps</rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="no" scheme="css">font-variant: normal</rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="ac" scheme="css">text-align: center</rendition>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum versionDate="2010-02-26" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Belloy">
          <head rendition="#ac #sc"><lb/>épître dédicatoire <lb/>à <lb/>Monsieur de Coucy <lb/>
               </head>
          <rendition xml:id="fr_sc" scheme="css">font-variant: uppercase</rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="fr_ac" scheme="css">text-align: center</rendition>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>The <att>rendition</att> attribute is used in a very similar way to the <att>class</att>
          attribute defined for XHTML but with the important distinction that its function is to
          describe the appearance of the source text, not necessarily to determine how that text
          should be presented on screen or paper.</p>
        <p>Where both <att>rendition</att> and <att>rend</att> are supplied, the latter is
          understood to override or complement the former.</p>
        <p>Each URI provided should indicate a <gi>rendition</gi> element defining the intended
          rendition in terms of some appropriate style language, as indicated by the
          <att>scheme</att> attribute.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>L'attribut <att>rendition</att> est employé à peu près de la même manière que l'attribut
            <att>class</att> défini pour XHTML mais avec cette sérieuse différence que sa fonction
          est de décrire la présentation du texte source mais pas nécessairement de déterminer
          comment ce texte doit être représenté à l'écran ou sur le papier. </p>
        <p>Où <att>rendition</att> et <att>rend</att> sont donnés ensembles, il faut comprendre que
          le dernier remplace ou complète le premier.</p>
        <p> Chaque URI fourni doit indiquer un élément <gi>rendition</gi> définissant le rendu prévu
          dans les termes d'un langage approprié pour définir les styles, comme indiqué par
          l'attribut <att>scheme</att>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>El atributo <att>rendition</att> (interpretación) se utiliza en una manera muy similar al
          atributo <att>clase</att> definido por XHTML pero con una diferencia importante: que su
          función es describir el aspecto del texto original, no necesariamente para determinar la
          presentación visual de ese texto en la pantalla o el papel.</p>
        <p>Donde ambos <att>interpretación</att> y <att>rend</att> se dan, este último se emplea
          para reemplazar o para complementar el anterior.</p>
        <p>Cada URI proporcionado debe indicar al elemento <gi>interpretación</gi> que define la
          interpretación prevista en términos de cualquier lenguaje apropiado del estilo, según lo
          indicado por el atributo <att>esquema</att>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 属性<att>rendition</att>は，XHTMLの属性<att>class</att>と大変 似たように使用される．但し，重要な違いとして，当該属性は，元資
          料の表現を記述するものであり，スクリーン上または紙上でどう表示 されているかを示すものではない． </p>
        <p> 属性<att>rendition</att>と属性<att>rend</att>の両方が使用され ている場合，後者の値が前者の値を上書きする，または補うと判断さ れる． </p>
        <p> 当該属性値となるURIは，属性<att>scheme</att>で提示されているス タイル言語により，当該表現を定義する要素<gi>rendition</gi>を示
          すべきである． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="xml:base" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>provides a base URI reference with which applications can resolve relative URI
        references into absolute URI references.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">애플리케이션이 상대 URI 참조를 절대 URI 참조로 해결할 수 있게 해 주는 기본 URI
        참조를 제공한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供一個基礎統一資源識別符 (URI)
        參照，可將相對統一資源識別符參照轉變為絕對統一資源識別符參照。 </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 相対URIから絶対URIを構成する際に必要なベースURIを示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">donne une référence URI de base au moyen de laquelle
        les applications peuvent résoudre des références d'URI relatives en références d'URI
        absolues</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona una referencia URI de base gracias a la
        aplicación eventual de la cual pueden analizarse tanto referencias URI relativas como
        referencias URI absolutas.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna un riferimento URI di base grazie al quale
        eventuali applicazioni possono analizzare riferimenti URI relativi come riferimenti URI
        assoluti</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any syntactically valid URI reference.</valDesc>
      <valDesc versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">toute référence d'URI valide syntaxiquement.</valDesc>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <div type="bibl">
            <head>Bibliography</head>
            <listBibl xml:base="http://www.lib.ucdavis.edu/BWRP/Works/">
              <bibl n="   1">
                <author>
                  <name>Landon, Letitia Elizabeth</name>
                </author>
                <ref target="LandLVowOf.sgm">
                  <title>The Vow of the Peacock</title>
                </ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl n="   2">
                <author>
                  <name>Compton, Margaret Clephane</name>
                </author>
                <ref target="NortMIrene.sgm">
                  <title>Irene, a Poem in Six Cantos</title>
                </ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl n="   3">
                <author>
                  <name>Taylor, Jane</name>
                </author>
                <ref target="TaylJEssay.sgm">
                  <title>Essays in Rhyme on Morals and Manners</title>
                </ref>
              </bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </div>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum versionDate="2010-02-26" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Bibliog_Renaissance_Ital">
          <div type="bibl">
            <head>La Renaissance italienne, bibliographie sélective</head>
            <listBibl>
              <bibl n="1">
                <author>
                  <name> Michel Hochmann, ... </name>
                </author>
                <ref>
                  <title>L’Abcdaire de la Renaissance italienne</title>
                </ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl n="2">
                <author>
                  <name>Thames et Hudson,</name>
                </author>
                <ref>
                  <title>Dictionnaire de la Renaissance</title>
                </ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl n="3">
                <author>
                  <name> Hervé Loilier</name>
                </author>
                <ref>
                  <title>Florence : voyage dans la Renaissance italienne du XVe siècle</title>
                </ref>
              </bibl>
              <bibl n="3">
                <author>
                  <name>Linda Murray</name>
                  <title>La Haute Renaissance et le Maniérisme</title>
                </author>
              </bibl>
            </listBibl>
          </div>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="xml:space" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>signals an intention about how white space should be 
      managed by  applications. </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">signale que les applications doivent préserver
          l'espace blanc</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala la voluntad de hacer que el espaciado sea preservado por cualquier aplicación.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">segnala la volontà di far sì che la spaziatura sia mantenuta da qualsivoglia applicazione.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">空白文字類をアプリケーションがどう解釈するかを示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="default">
          <desc>signals that the application's default white-space processing modes are acceptable</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="preserve">
          <desc>indicates the intent that applications preserve all white space</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <remarks>
        <p>The <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#sec-white-space">XML
      specification</ref> provides further guidance on the use of this
      attribute. Note that many parsers may not handle xml:space correctly.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#STGA"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
