<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins-paderborn.tei-c.org/view/LingSIG/job/TEIP5-LingSIG-deadISOCat/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei"
  xml:id="DATCAT" type="atts" ident="att.datcat">
  <desc versionDate="2022-09-17" xml:lang="en">provides attributes that are used to align XML
    elements or attributes with the appropriate Data Categories (DCs) defined by an external 
    taxonomy, in this way establishing the identity of information containers and values, 
    and providing means of interpreting them.</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="ja" versionDate="2019-05-20"
    ><att>datacat</att>属性と<att>ValueDatacat</att>属性を提供する．これらがXML要素や属性を連携させる日付分類は、国際標準ISO
      12620:2009で定義されるものであり，<ptr target="http://www.isocat.org/"
    />にあるISOCatと呼ばれるWebリポジトリに格納されている．</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="datcat" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2022-09-17" xml:lang="en">provides a pointer to a definition of, and/or general
        information about, (a) an information container (element or attribute) or (b) a value of an
        information container (element content or attribute value), by referencing an external
        taxonomy or ontology. If <att>valueDatcat</att> is present in the immediate context, this attribute
        takes on role (a), while <att>valueDatcat</att> performs role (b).</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="ja" versionDate="2019-05-20"
        >指定された要素をISOcatの適切なデータカテゴリ（または複数のデータカテゴリ）と対応付けるPID（永続的識別子）を含む．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <dataRef key="teidata.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="valueDatcat" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2022-09-17" xml:lang="en">provides a definition of, and/or general
        information about a value of an information container (element content or attribute value),
        by reference to an external taxonomy or ontology. Used especially where a contrast with
        <att>datcat</att> is needed.</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="ja" versionDate="2019-05-20"
        >指定された要素の内容または指定された属性の値を，ISOcatの適切かつ単純なデータカテゴリ（または複数のデータカテゴリ）と対応付けるPID（永続的識別子）を含む．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <dataRef key="teidata.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="targetDatcat" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2022-09-17" xml:lang="en">provides a definition of, and/or general
        information about, information structure of an object referenced or modeled by the
        containing element, by reference to an external taxonomy or ontology. This attribute has the
        characteristics of the @datcat attribute, except that it addresses not its containing
        element, but an object that is being referenced or modeled by its containing element.</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <dataRef key="teidata.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>The below example presents the TEI encoding of the <ref
        target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Name%E2%80%93value_pair">name-value pair</ref>
        "<tag>part-of-speech, common-noun</tag>" (where the name/key is abbreviated as "POS",
      and the value is symbolized by "NN"). The <att>datcat</att> attribute relates the feature <hi
        rend="italic">name</hi> to the data category "part of speech", while the attribute
        <att>valueDatcat</att> relates the feature <hi rend="italic">value</hi> to the data category
      "common noun". Both these data categories should be defined in an external and preferably open
      reference taxonomy or ontology.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fs>
        <f name="POS" datcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-396_5a972b93-2294-ab5c-a541-7c344c5f26c3">
          <symbol valueDatcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-1256_7ec6083c-23d4-224d-6f94-eecbe6861545" value="NN"/>
        </f>
        <!-- ... -->
      </fs>
    </egXML>
    <p>"NN" is the symbol for common noun used e.g. in the <ref
        target="http://ucrel.lancaster.ac.uk/claws7tags.html">CLAWS-7 tagset</ref> defined by the
      University Centre for Computer Corpus Research on Language at the University of Lancaster. The
      very same data category used for tagging an early version of the British National Corpus, and
      coming from the so-called <ref target="http://www.natcorp.ox.ac.uk/docs/c5spec.html">BNC Basic
        (C5) tagset</ref>, uses the symbol "NN0" (rather than "NN"). Making these values semantically
      interoperable / interchangeable would be extremely difficult without a human expert if they
      were not anchored in a single point of an established reference taxonomy of morphosyntactic
      data categories. In the case at hand, the string "<ref
        target="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-1256_7ec6083c-23d4-224d-6f94-eecbe6861545"
        >http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-1256_7ec6083c-23d4-224d-6f94-eecbe6861545</ref>" is both
      a persistent identifier of the data category in question, as well as the address of the place where a shared definition
      of "common noun" is provided.</p>
    <p>While the symbols "NN", "NN0", and many others (often coming from languages other than
      English) are implicitly members of the container category "part of speech", it is sometimes
      useful not to rely on such an implicit relationship but rather use an explicit identifier
      for that data category, to distinguish it from other morphosyntactic data categories, such
      as "gender", "tense", etc. For that purpose, the above example uses the <att>datcat</att>
      attribute to reference a definition of "part of speech". The reference taxonomy in this example is the 
      <ref target="https://www.clarin.eu/content/clarin-concept-registry">CLARIN Concept
        Registry</ref>.</p>
    
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>If the feature structure markup exemplified above is to be repeated many times in a single
      document, it is much more efficient to gather the persistent identifiers in a single place and to
      only reference them, implicitly or directly, from feature structure markup. The following
      example is much more concise than the one above and relies on the concepts of feature structure declaration and
      feature value library, discussed in chapter <ptr target="#FS"/>.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fs>
        <f name="POS" fVal="#commonNoun"/>
        <!-- ... -->
      </fs>
    </egXML>
    <p>The assumption here is that the relevant feature values are collected in a place that the
      annotation document in question has access to -- preferably, a single document per linguistic
      resource, for example a <gi>fsdDecl</gi> that is XIncluded as a sibling of <gi>text</gi> or a
      child of <gi>encodingDesc</gi>; a <gi>taxonomy</gi> available resource-wide (e.g., in a shared
      header) is also an option. The example below presents a <gi>fvLib</gi> element that collects the
      relevant feature values (most of them omitted).</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>This example shows one way of encoding a <hi rend="bold">tagset</hi>, i.e., an established inventory of values of
      (in the case at hand) morphosyntactic categories.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fvLib n="POS values">
        <symbol xml:id="commonNoun" value="NN" datcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-396_5a972b93-2294-ab5c-a541-7c344c5f26c3"/>
        <symbol xml:id="properNoun" value="NP" datcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-1371_fbebd9ec-a7f4-9a36-d6e9-88ee16b944ae"/>
        <!-- ... -->
      </fvLib>
    </egXML>
    <p>Note that these Guidelines do not prescribe a specific choice between <att>datcat</att> and
        <att>valueDatcat</att> in such cases. The former is the generic way of referencing a data
      category, whereas the latter is more specific, in that it references a data category that
      represents a value. The choice between them comes into play where a single element -- or a
      tight element complex, such as the <gi>f</gi>/<gi>symbol</gi> complex illustrated above --
      make it necessary or useful to distinguish between the container data category and its
      value.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>In the context of dictionaries designed with semantic interoperability in mind, the following
      example ensures that the <gi>pos</gi> element is interpreted as the same information container
      as in the case of the example of <tag>f name="POS"</tag> above.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <gramGrp>
        <pos datcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-396_5a972b93-2294-ab5c-a541-7c344c5f26c3"
          valueDatcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-1256_7ec6083c-23d4-224d-6f94-eecbe6861545">NN</pos>
      </gramGrp>
    </egXML>
    <p>Again, the issue of efficiency and redundancy of this type of interoperable markup demands
      that the references to the particular data categories are provided either in the header of the
      dictionary or at the level of ODD, in the element <gi>equiv</gi> (child of <gi>elementSpec</gi>), which constitutes an
      equivalent of the <ident>att.datcat</ident> class.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>The <att>targetDatcat</att> attribute is reserved for feature structure declarations, and is
      analogous to the <att>targetLang</att> attribute of the <ident>att.pointing</ident> class, in that it describes the
      object that is being referenced, rather than the referencing object.</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fDecl name="POS" targetDatcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-396_5a972b93-2294-ab5c-a541-7c344c5f26c3">
        <fDescr>part of speech (morphosyntactic category)</fDescr>
        <vRange>
          <vAlt>
            <symbol value="NN" datcat="http://hdl.handle.net/11459/CCR_C-1256_7ec6083c-23d4-224d-6f94-eecbe6861545"/>
            <!-- ... -->
          </vAlt>
        </vRange>
      </fDecl>
    </egXML>
    <p>Above, the modeled feature uses <att>targetDatcat</att>, because if it used
        <att>datcat</att> then we would be saying that the <gi>fDecl</gi> is an instance of the part-of-speech container data category,
      whereas it is not -- the <gi>fDecl</gi> models a container (<gi>f</gi>) that encodes a part
      of speech. Note also that it is the <gi>f</gi> that is modeled above, not its values, which
      are used as direct references to data categories, hence the use of <att>datcat</att> in the
        <gi>symbol</gi> element.</p>
  </exemplum>
  
  <remarks versionDate="2022-09-17" xml:lang="en">
    <p>The TEI Abstract Model can be expressed as a hierarchy of attribute-value matrices (AVMs)
      of various types and of various levels of complexity, nested or grouped in various ways. At
      the most abstract level, an AVM consists of an information container and the value
      ('contents') of that container.</p>
    <p>A simple example of an XML serialization of such structures is, on the one hand, the opening
      and closing tags that delimit and name the container, and, on the other, the content enclosed
      by the two tags that constitues the value. An analogous example is an
      attribute name and the value of that attribute.</p>
    <p>In a TEI XML example of two equivalent serializations expressing the name-value pair
        <tag>part-of-speech,common-noun</tag>, namely <hi rend="mono"
        >&lt;pos>commonNoun&lt;/pos></hi> and <hi rend="mono">pos="common-noun"</hi>, one would
      classify the element <gi>pos</gi> and the attribute <att>pos</att> as containers (mapping onto
      the first member of the relevant name-value pair, while the <hi rend="mono">text()</hi>
      content of <gi>pos</gi> or the string/symbolic value of <att>pos</att> would be seen as
      mapping onto the second member of the pair.</p>
    <p>The <ident type="class">att.datcat</ident> class provides means of addressing the containers
      and their values, while at the same time providing a way to interpret them in the context of
      external taxonomies or ontologies. Aligning e.g. both the <gi>pos</gi> element and the
        <att>pos</att> attribute with the same value of an external reference point (i.e., an entry
      in an agreed taxonomy) affirms the identity of the concept behind both the element container
      and the attribute container, and optionally provides a definition of, in the case at hand,
      "part of speech".</p>
    <p>The value of the <ident type="class">att.datcat</ident> attributes should be a PID
      (persistent identifier) that points to a specific -- and, ideally, shared -- taxonomy or ontology. Among
      the resources that to a smaller or greater extent can be used as inventories of (more or less)
      standardized linguistic categories, are the GOLD ontology, CLARIN CCR, OLiA or termbase, and
      also the Universal Dependencies inventory, on the assumption that its URI are going to
      persist. Apart from these global resources, it is imaginable to address a project-specific
      taxonomy as well, if global interoperability is not the goal.</p>  
    <p>Historically, <att>datcat</att> and <att>valueDatcat</att> originate from (now obsolete) ISO
      12620:2009 standard, describing the data model and procedures for a Data Category Registry
      (DCR). The current version of the standard, ISO 12620-1, does not standardize the
      serialization of pointers, merely mentioning the TEI <ident type="class">att.datcat</ident> as
      an example.</p> 
    <p>Note that no constraint prevents the occurrence of a combination of att.datcat attributes:
      the <gi>fDecl</gi> element, which is a natural bearer of the <att>targetDatcat</att>
      attribute, is an instance of a specific modeling element, and, in principle, could be
      semantically "fixed" by an appropriate reference taxonomy of modeling devices.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja" versionDate="2019-06-16">
    <p>ISO
        12620:2009は、データ分類のレジストリ（DCR）に関するデータモデルと手続きについての国際標準である．データ分類は，一つの言語の構造における基本的な記述子として定義される。DCRのデータモデルでは、個々のデータ分類には、ユニークな永続的識別子（PID)、つまり、URIが割り当てられる．DCRからデータ分類を利用する言語資源，あるいは、できることならそのスキーマは、このPIDを用いて参照すべきである。TEI文書のようなXMLベースの資源(<ptr
        target="https://www.iso.org/standard/37243.html"/>にて参照可能)に関しては、ISO 12620:2009 付録
        Aに、<att>datcat</att>属性と<att>valueDatcat</att>属性を提供する小さなデータ分類参照のXML語彙がある。</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#DIMVLV"/>
    <ptr target="#FSSY"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>