<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- © TEI Consortium. Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licenses; see the file COPYING.txt for details. -->
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tagdocs" type="atts" ident="att.combinable">
  <desc versionDate="2010-05-11" xml:lang="en">provides attributes indicating how multiple
    references to the same object in a schema should be combined.</desc>
    <desc versionDate="2019-01-19" xml:lang="ja">あるスキーマにおける同一オブジェクトに対する複数の参照をどのように統合すべきか示す属性を提供する。</desc>
  <classes>
    
    <memberOf key="att.deprecated"/>
  </classes>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="mode" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2010-05-11" xml:lang="en">specifies the effect of this declaration on its
        parent object.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">그 부모 모듈에 이 선언의 효과를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標明該宣告在其來源模組中的作用。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">précise l'effet de cette déclaration sur son
        parent.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2019-01-19" xml:lang="ja">当該宣言が親要素に与える影響を示す。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica el efecto de esta declaración en el
        módulo del que obtiene el orígen (módulo padre)</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica l'effetto della dichiarazione sul modulo
        da cui trae origine</desc>
      <datatype>
        <dataRef key="teidata.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>add</defaultVal>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="add">
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="en">this declaration is part of the current definitions.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 선언은 현 정의에 추가된다.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">該宣告添加在現有定義中</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">esta declaración se agrega a las definiciones
            actuales</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2019-01-19" xml:lang="ja">当該宣言は現行定義に追加される。</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">cette déclaration s'ajoute aux définitions
            courantes.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="it">la dichiarazione fa parte alle definizioni
            correnti</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="delete">
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="en">the object with the same identifier (and namespace in the case of 
            an element or attribute) as the current one is no longer part of the current definitions</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 선언과 이 선언의 모든 자식들이 현 구성에서 제거된다.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">該宣告以及所有子宣告從現有的設定中被移除</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">esta declaración y todos sus hijos se
            suprimen de la disposición actual</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2019-01-19" xml:lang="ja">すでに存在する場合、当該宣言と当該以下の子要素は、現行の配置から外される。</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">cette déclaration et tous ses enfants sont
            retirés du système courant.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="it">l'oggetto con lo stesso nome (e namespace nel caso di un elemento
            o attributo) di quello corrente non fa più parte delle definizioni correnti.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="change">
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="en">this declaration changes the object of the same identifier (and namespace 
            in the case of an element or attribute) in the current definition</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 선언은 현 정의에서 동일 이름의 선언을 변경한다.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">該宣告改變在現有定義中名稱相同的宣告。</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">esta declaración cambia la declaración del
            mismo nombre en la definición actual</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2019-01-19" xml:lang="ja">当該宣言は、現行定義中の同名宣言を修正する。</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">cette déclaration modifie la déclaration de
            même nom dans la définition courante.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="it">la dichiarazione modifica l'oggetto con
            con lo stesso nome (e namespace nel caso di un elemento o attributo) nella definizione corrente.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="replace">
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="en">this declaration replaces the object with the same identifier (and 
            namespace in the case of an element or attribute) in the current definition.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 선언은 현 정의에서 동일 이름의 선언을 대체한다.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">該宣告代替在現有定義中名稱相同的宣告</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">esta declaración substituye la declaración
            del mismo nombre en la definición actual</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2019-01-19" xml:lang="ja">当該宣言は、現行定義中の同名宣言を置き換える。</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">cette déclaration remplace la déclaration de
            même nom dans la définition courante.</desc>
          <desc versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="it">la dichiarazione sostituisce l'oggetto
            con lo stesso nome (e namespace nel caso di un elemento o attributo) nella definizione corrente.</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="en">
    <p>An ODD processor should handle the values for <att>mode</att> as follows: <list type="gloss">
        <label>add</label>
      <item>the object should be created (processing any children in add mode); raise an error if the object has an identifier and 
        an object with the same identifier (and namespace in the case of an element or attribute) already exists.</item>
        <label>replace</label>
      <item>use this object in preference to any existing object with the same identifier (and namespace in the case of an element or attribute), 
        and ignore any children of that object; process any new children in replace mode</item>
        <label>delete</label>
      <item>do not process this object or any existing object with the same identifier (and namespace in the case of an element or attribute); 
        the element carrying this attribute must be empty: raise an error if there are any children</item>
        <label>change</label>
      <item>process this object and its children, replacing only those components of an existing object of the same type with the 
        same identifier (and namespace in case of an element or attribute) that are explicitly specified. This will change only 
        those existing attribute values and child elements that appear both in the original specification and in the new specification. 
        Other children from the original specification will be preserved.</item>
      </list>
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks versionDate="2022-04-12" xml:lang="it">
    <p>Un processore ODD dovrebbe considerare i valori dell'attributo <att>mode</att> in questo modo:
      <list type="gloss">
        <label>add</label>
        <item>l'oggetto dovrebbe essere creato, trattando tutti gli elementi figlio che hanno anch'essi il valore <val>add</val>.
          Se esistesse un oggetto con lo stesso nome (e namespace nel caso di un elemento o attributo) bisognerà dare un errore.
        </item>
        <label>replace</label>
        <item>utilizzare questo oggetto al posto di qualsiasi atro oggetto esistente con lo stesso nome (e namespace nel caso di un elemento o attributo),
          e ignorare gli elementi figlio di quell'oggetto; trattare tutti gli elementi che hanno anch'essi il valore <val>replace</val>.
        </item>
        <label>delete</label>
        <item>non trattare questo oggetto o qualsiasi altro oggetto con lo stesso nome (e namespace nel caso di un elemento o attributo);
          l'elemento con questo valore deve essere vuoto: dare un error nel caso in cui contenesse elementi figlio.
        </item>
        <label>change</label>
        <item>trattare questo oggetto e tutti i suoi elementi figlio, sustituendo solo i componenti di un oggetto già esistente e 
          direttamente specificato dello stesso tipo e con lo stesso nome (e namespace nel caso di un elemento o attributo).
          Questa operazione cambierà solamente i valori di attributi già esistenti ed elementi figlio che sono presenti sia nella specificazione originale
          che nella nuova specificazione. Gli altri elementi filgio che fanno parte della specificazione originale verranno mantenuti.</item>
      </list>
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">
    <p>La signification informelle des valeurs de l'attribut <att>mode</att> est la suivante :<list type="gloss">
        <label>add</label>
        <item>l'objet doit être créé (traitement de tout enfant dans le mode <val>add</val>) ;
          générer une erreur si un objet avec le même identifiant existe déjà.</item>
        <label>replace</label>
        <item>utiliser cet objet de préférence à tout autre portant le même identifiant et ignorer
          tout enfant de cet objet ; traiter tout nouvel enfant dans le mode <val>replace</val>. </item>
        <label>delete</label>
        <item>ne pas traiter cet objet ou aucun autre portant le même identifiant ; générer une
          erreur si de nouveaux enfants sont fournis.</item>
        <label>change</label>
        <item>traiter cet objet, et ses enfants, et ceux de n'importe quel objet portant le même
          identifiant, dans le mode <val>change</val>. </item>
      </list>
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks versionDate="2019-01-19" xml:lang="ja">
    <p>ODDプロセッサは<att>mode</att>属性値を次のように扱うべきである: <list type="gloss">
        <label>add</label>
        <item>オブジェクトを生成すべきである（子をすべて<val>add</val>モードで処理する）。同一の識別子を持つオブジェクトがすでに存在するばあいはエラーを発生させる。</item>
        <label>replace</label>
        <item>同一の識別子を持つ先んじて存在するすべてのオブジェクトよりも当該のオブジェクトを優先して使用し、それらのオブジェクトの子を無視する。新しい子はすべて<val>replace</val>モードで処理する。</item>
        <label>delete</label>
        <item>当該の、あるいは先んじて存在するすべてのオブジェクトを処理してはならない。子が与えられたときはエラーを発生させる。</item>
        <label>change</label>
        <item>当該のオブジェクトと子、また先んじて存在するすべてのオブジェクトの子を<val>change</val>モードで処理する。</item>
      </list></p>
  </remarks>
</classSpec>
