<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" predeclare="true" module="linking" xml:id="POINTER" type="atts" ident="att.pointing">
  <desc>defines a set of attributes used by all elements which point
  to other elements by means of one or more URI references.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce un insieme di attributi usati da tutti gli elementi che puntano ad altri elementi tramite uno o più URI</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>categorizes the pointer in some respect, using any
      convenient set of categories.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">fornisce una classificazione per il puntatore utilizzando una tassonomia funzionale</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該ポインタの種類を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.word"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>Any string of XML name characters. The type should
      indicate the intended function of the pointer, or the rhetorical
      relationship between its source and target.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="evaluate" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>specifies the intended meaning when the target of a
      pointer is itself a pointer.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il significato previsto quando la destinazione di un puntatore è essa stessa un puntatore</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該ポインタの参照先がポインタである場合，その意味を示す．</desc>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="all">
          <equiv/>
          <gloss>if the element pointed to is itself a pointer, then
	  the target of that pointer will be taken, and so on, until
	  an element is found which is not a pointer.</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">se l'elemento puntato è esso stesso un puntatore, allora sarà presa la destinazione di quel puntatore e così via fino a trovare un elemento che non è un puntatore</gloss>
          <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">(非ポインタにたどり着くまで，参照先を探す．)</gloss>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="one">
          <equiv/>
          <gloss>if the element pointed to is itself a pointer, then
	  its target (whether a pointer or not) is taken as the target
	  of this pointer.</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">se l'elemento puntato è esso stesso un puntatore, allora la sua destinazione (che sia un puntatore o meno) è presa come destinazione del puntatore</gloss>
          <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">(当該ポインタが参照するポインタの参照先を探す．)</gloss>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="none">
          <equiv/>
          <gloss>no further evaluation of targets is carried out
	  beyond that needed to find the element specified in the
	  pointer's target.</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">non viene condotta altra valutazione delle destinazioni se non quella necessaria a rintracciare l'elemento specificato nella destinazione del puntatore</gloss>
          <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">(当該ポインタが参照するポインタを探す．)</gloss>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <remarks>
        <p>If no value is given, the application program is
          responsible for deciding (possibly on the basis of user
          input) how far to trace a chain of pointers.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p/>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COXR"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
