<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" type="atts" xml:id="DATABLE" ident="att.datable">
  <desc>provides attributes for normalization of elements that contain
  dates, times, or datable events.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">날짜, 시간 또는 날짜 명기 사건을 포함하는 요소의 규격화에 대한 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供用於元素規格化的屬性，這些元素包含日期明確的事件。</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">用於紀錄時間規格化的屬性</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  日付や時間または時間事象を含む要素の正規化手法を示す属性を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs pour la normalisation d'
      éléments qui contiennent des mentions d'événements datables</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos para la normalización de elementos que contienen eventos datables.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">atributos para registrar expresiones temporales normalizadas.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna attributi per la normalizzazione di elementi che contengono eventi databili</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.datable.w3c"/>
    <memberOf key="att.datable.iso"/>
    <memberOf key="att.datable.custom"/>
  </classes>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="calendar" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates the system or calendar to which the date represented by the content of this
        element belongs.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">날짜 표현 시스템 또는 달력 표시 형식을 표시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指明該日期表示所使用的曆法計算系統。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該日付の歴システムを示す． </desc>
      <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">indique le système ou le calendrier auquel appartient
        la date exprimée dans le contenu de l'élément.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el sistema o calendario en que se muestra una
        fecha.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il sistema o calendario al quale la data
        appartiene.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">He was born on <date calendar="#Gregorian">Feb. 22, 1732</date> 
          (<date calendar="#Julian" when="1732-02-22"> Feb. 11, 1731/32, O.S.</date>).</egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Bouiller_Rapport"> L'année
          1960 fut, en vertu du calendrier grégorien, bissextile ; le 22 juin tomba ainsi le jour
          de l'été, le <date calendar="#Gregorian"> 22 juin</date>.
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="period" usage="opt">
      <desc>supplies a pointer to some location defining a named
        period of time within which the datable item is understood to
        have occurred.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">시간을 명시할 수 있는 항목이 일어난 시간의 기간명을 정의하는 특정 위치로의 포인터를 제공한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">suministra un indicador a una localización concreta que define un periodo de tiempo conocido dentro del cual el item datable se ha producido.</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
        時間事象の名前付き時間幅を定義する時点を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">fournit un pointeur vers un emplacement donné
        définissant une période de temps nommée pendant laquelle l'item datable
        s'inscrit.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">fornisce un puntatore a una data posizione definendo un determinato periodo di tempo entro il quale l'oggetto da datare è collocabile</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>This <soCalled>superclass</soCalled> provides attributes that
    can be used to provide normalized values of temporal information.
    By default, the attributes from the <ident type="class">att.datable.w3c</ident> class are provided. If the
    module for names &amp; dates is loaded, this class also provides
    attributes from the <ident type="class">att.datable.iso</ident> and
    <ident type="class">att.datable.custom</ident> classes. In general, the possible values of attributes restricted to
    the W3C datatypes form a subset of those values available via the
    ISO 8601 standard. However, the greater expressiveness of the ISO
    datatypes may not be needed, and there exists much greater
    software support for the W3C datatypes.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cette<soCalled>superclasse</soCalled> fournit des attributs qui peuvent être employés
                pour donner des valeurs normalisées à des informations relatives au temps. Par
                défaut, les attributs de la classse <ident type="class">att.datable.w3c</ident> sont
                fournis. Si le module pour les noms et les dates est chargé, cette classe fournit
                également des attributs de la classe<ident type="class">att.datable.iso</ident>. En
                général, les valeurs possibles des attributs limitées aux types de données W3C
                forment un sous-ensemble des valeurs que l'on trouve dans la norme ISO 8601.
                Cependant, il n'est peut-être pas nécessaire de recourir aux possibilités très
                étendues des types de données de l'ISO, il existe en effet une bien plus grande
                offre logicielle pour le traitement des types de données W3C.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Esta <soCalled>superclase</soCalled> proporciona atributos que pueden ser utilizados para proporcionar valores normalizados de información temporal.
    Por defecto, los atributos de la clase <ident type="class">att.datable.w3c</ident> son proporcionados. Si el módulo para los nombres y las fechas se acciona, esta clase también proporciona atributos de <ident type="class">att.datable.iso</ident>. En general, los valores posibles de los atributos son los restringidos por la forma de los datatypes de W3C, un subconjunto de esos valores disponibles vía el estándar de ISO 8601. Sin embargo, la mayoría de expresiones de los datatypes de ISO pueden no ser necesarios, y existe software de soporte para los datatypes de W3C.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    このいわゆる<soCalled>親クラス(スーパークラス)</soCalled>は，
    正規化された値を属性値として持つ，時間情報を示す属性になる．
    デフォルト値として，当該属性は，クラス<ident type="class">att.datable.w3c</ident>が付与されている．
    名前と日付に関するモジュールが使用される場合，当該クラスは，クラス
    <ident type="class">att.datable.iso</ident>から属性が与えられる．
    一般には，W3Cのデータ形式に従った属性値は，ITO8601に従った属性値の
    下位要素になっている．しかし，より強力な表現力を持つISOのデータ形
    式が必要になることはない．さらに強力な表現力をサポートするソフトウェ
    アも存在する．
    </p>
  </remarks>
</classSpec>
