<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" predeclare="true" module="linking" xml:id="CLLINK" type="atts" ident="att.global.linking">
  <desc>defines a set of attributes for hypertext and other linking,
which are enabled for all elements when the additional tag set for
linking is selected.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define un conjunto de atributos para hipertexto u otro vínculo habilitado para todos los elementos cuando se selecciona la etiqueta adicional para los enlaces.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce un insieme di attributi per ipertesto o altro legame abilitati per tutti gli elementi quando è selezionato il sottoinsieme di marcatori per i collegamenti</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="corresp" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points to elements that correspond to the current
      element in some way.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala los elementos que presentan una correspondencia con el elemento corriente.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">punta a elementi che hanno una qualche corrispondenza con l'elemento corrente</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素と対応する要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more URIs, separated by white space.</valDesc>
      <remarks/>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="synch" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points to elements that are synchronous with the current
      element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala los elementos que son sincrónicos con el elemento corriente.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">punta a elementi sincroni rispetto all'elemento corrente</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素と連動する要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more URIs, separated by white space.</valDesc>
      <remarks/>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="sameAs" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points to an element that is the same as the current
      element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala el elementos que se corresponde exactamente con el elemento corriente.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">punta a un elemento che corrisponde esattamente all'elemento corrente</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素と同一の要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a URI.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="copyOf" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points to an element of which the current element is a
	copy.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala un elemento del que el elemento corriente es una copia.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">punta a un elemento di cui l'elemento corrente è una copia</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素のコピー要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a URI.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Any content of the current element should be ignored. Its
	true content is that of the element being pointed at.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="next" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points to the next element of a virtual aggregate of which
      the current element is part.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">punta all'elemento seguente all'interno di unaggregazione virtuale di cui l'elemento corrente fa parte</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素の妹要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a URI.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="prev" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points to the previous element of a virtual aggregate of
      which the current element is part.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala al elemento precedente de una adición virtual, de la cual el elemento corriente forma parte.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">punta all'elemento precedente all'interno di unaggregazione virtuale di cui l'elemento corrente fa parte</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素の姉要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a URI.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="exclude" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>points to elements that are in exclusive alternation
      with the current element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">señala los elementos que estan en relación de alternancia exclusiva con el elemento corriente.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">punta a elementi in relazione di alternanza esclusiva con l'elemento corrente</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素の代替要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more URIs, separated by white space.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="select" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>selects one or more alternants; if one alternant is
      selected, the ambiguity or uncertainty is marked as resolved. If
      more than one alternant is selected, the degree of ambiguity or
      uncertainty is marked as reduced by the number of alternants not
      selected.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">selecciona una o más alternativas; si se selecciona una de las alternativas, la ambigüidad o la incerteza se indica como resuelta; si se selecciona más de una alternativa, el grado de ambigüidad o incerteza se indica como reducido del número de las alternativas no seleccionadas.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">seleziona una o più alternative; se viene selezionata una delle alternative, l'ambiguità o incertezza è indicata come risolta; se viene selezionata più di un'alternativa, il grado di ambiguità o incertezza è indicato come ridotto dal numero delle alternative non selezionate</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素の子要素として選択される要素を示す．</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more URIs, separated by white space.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>This attribute should be placed on an element which is
	superordinate to all of the alternants from which the
	selection is being made.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#SA"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
