<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- © TEI Consortium. Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licenses; see the file COPYING.txt for details. -->
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" type="atts" xml:id="class-attr-anchoring" ident="att.anchoring">
  <gloss versionDate="2021-01-28" xml:lang="en">anchoring</gloss>
  <desc versionDate="2021-01-28" xml:lang="en">provides attributes for use on annotations, e.g. notes and groups of notes
  describing the existence and position of an anchor for annotations.</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="anchored" usage="opt">
      <gloss versionDate="2017-06-25" xml:lang="en">anchored</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2017-06-25" xml:lang="de">verankert</gloss>
      <desc versionDate="2005-01-14" xml:lang="en">indicates whether the copy text shows the exact place of reference for the note.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">indique si l'exemplaire du texte montre l'emplacement
        de référence exact pour la note.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica si el texto de copia muestra el lugar exacto
        de referencia para una nota.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">說明來源文件是否指出附註的確切參照位置。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica se il testo copia mostra l'esatta posizione di
        riferimento della nota.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該注釈がある場所への参照は、正確にその場所を示しているかどうか。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2017-06-25" xml:lang="de">gibt an, ob eine Vorlage den exakten Referenzort der Anmerkung anzeigt.</desc>
      <datatype><dataRef key="teidata.truthValue"/></datatype>
      <defaultVal>true</defaultVal>
      <remarks versionDate="2007-04-22" xml:lang="en">
        <p>In modern texts, notes are usually anchored by means of explicit footnote or endnote
          symbols. An explicit indication of the phrase or line annotated may however be used
          instead (e.g. <q>page 218, lines 3–4</q>). The <att>anchored</att> attribute indicates
          whether any explicit location is given, whether by symbol or by prose cross-reference. The
          value <val>true</val> indicates that such an explicit location is indicated in the copy
          text; the value <val>false</val> indicates that the copy text does not indicate a specific
          place of attachment for the note. If the specific symbols used in the copy text at the
          location the note is anchored are to be recorded, use the <att>n</att> attribute.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Dans des textes modernes, les notes sont habituellement ancrées au moyen d’appels de
          notes explicites (pour des notes de bas de page ou des notes de fin de texte). A la place, une indication explicite de
          l'expression ou de la ligne annotée peut cependant être employée (par exemple <q>page 218,
            lignes 3–4</q>). L'attribut <att>anchored</att> indique si un emplacement est donné
          explicitement ou s'il est exprimé par un symbole ou par un renvoi. La valeur
          <val>true</val> indique qu'un endroit explicite est indiqué dans le texte ; la valeur
            <val>false</val> indique que le texte n'indique pas un endroit spécifique d'attachement
          pour la note. Si des symboles spécifiques utilisés dans le texte à l'endroit où la note
          est ancrée doivent être enregistrés, l'attribut <att>n</att> sera utilisé.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks versionDate="2017-06-25" xml:lang="de">
        <p>In modernen Texten wird auf Anmerkungen üblicherweise durch explizite Fuß- oder Endnotensymbole
          verwiesen. Stattdessen kann aber auch ein expliziter Hinweis auf die Phrase oder Zeile verwendet
          werden (z. B. <q>Seite 218, Zeile 3–4</q>). Das <att>anchored</att>-Attribut gibt an, ob ein
          expliziter Ort durch ein Symbol oder einen Querverweis angegeben ist. Der Wert <val>true</val>
          gibt an, dass ein expliziter Ort in der Vorlage angegeben ist; der Wert <val>false</val> gibt
          an, dass die Vorlage kein spezifisches Verweisziel für die Anmerkung angibt. Zur Verzeichnung
          von spezifischen Referenzzeichen, die in der Vorlage verwendet werden, wird das
          <att>n</att>-Attribut benutzt.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="targetEnd" usage="opt">
      <gloss versionDate="2020-12-20" xml:lang="en">target end</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2017-06-25" xml:lang="de">Bereichsende</gloss>
      <desc versionDate="2005-01-14" xml:lang="en">points to the end of the span to which the note is attached, if the note is not embedded
        in the text at that point.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">pointe vers la fin d'un passage auquel la note est
        attachée, si la note n'est pas enchâssée dans le texte à cet endroit.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el final de un periodo al cual una nota está
        enlazada, si la nota no está insertada en ese punto del texto.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">如果附註不是嵌在正文中，則用以標明附註所註段落的終點。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">rimanda alla fine della porzione di testo a cui la
        nota è allegata nel caso in cui la nota non sia inclusa nel testo in quel punto.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該注釈・コメントの終了点を示す。(当該注釈が注釈先の場所に埋め込 まれていない場合)</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2017-06-25" xml:lang="de">verweist auf das Ende eines Bereichs, dem das <gi>note</gi>-Element angefügt ist, es sei denn die
        Anmerkung ist in den Text an diesem Punkt bereits eingebettet.</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded"><dataRef key="teidata.pointer"/></datatype>
      <remarks versionDate="2009-01-23" xml:lang="en">
        <p>This attribute is retained for backwards compatibility; it may be removed at a subsequent
          release of the Guidelines. The recommended way of pointing to a span of elements is by
          means of the <ident>range</ident> function of XPointer, as further described in <ptr target="#SATSRN"/>. </p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Cet attribut est conservé pour assurer un arrière-plan compatible ; il sera supprimé dans la
          prochaine mise à jour des Recommandations. La procédure recommandée pour pointer en
          direction d'une expansion des éléments est de le faire au moyen de la fonction
            <ident>range</ident> de XPointer, telle que la description en est faite  à <ptr target="#SATSRN"/>. </p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks versionDate="2017-06-25" xml:lang="de">
        <p>Dieses Attribut wurde beibehalten, um eine Abwärtskompatibilität zu gewährleisten; bei einem
          zukünftigen Release der Guidelines kann es entfernt werden. Der empfohlene Weg, um auf einen
          Bereich zu verweisen, ist die Verwendung der <ident>range</ident>-Funktion von XPointer, wie in
          <ptr target="#SATSRN"/> beschrieben.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum versionDate="2021-01-28" xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="class-attr-anchoring-egXML-na" source="#SERAFIN2">
        <p>(...) tamen reuerendos dominos archiepiscopum et canonicos Leopolienses
              necnon episcopum in duplicibus Quatuortemporibus<anchor xml:id="A55234"/> totaliter expediui...</p>

        <!-- elsewhere in the document -->
            <noteGrp targetEnd="#A55234">
            <note xml:lang="en">
                Quatuor Tempora, so called dry fast days.
            </note>
            <note xml:lang="pl">
                Quatuor Tempora, tzw. Suche dni postne.
            </note>
            </noteGrp>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
</classSpec>
