<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" 
  xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xml:id="NAMES" type="atts" ident="att.naming">
  <desc>provides attributes common to elements which refer to named persons, places, organizations etc.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">사람, 장소, 조직 등의 이름을 지시하는 요소에 공통적 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供屬性，通用於參照到人物、地點、組織等的元素。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  名前，人物，場所，組織を示す要素に付与される属性を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs communs aux éléments qui font référence à des personnes, lieux, organismes, etc., nommés.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">identifica los atributos comunes a los elementos que se refieren a personas, lugares, organizaciones, etc. indicados por nombre</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">identifica degli attributi comuni a elementi che si riferiscono a persone, luoghi, organizzazioni, ecc. indicati per nome</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.canonical"/>
  </classes>
  <attList>

    <attDef ident="role" usage="opt">
<desc>may be used to specify further information about the entity referenced by
this name, for example the occupation of a person, or the status of a place. </desc>
<datatype>
<rng:ref name="data.enumerated"/>
</datatype>
    </attDef>

    <attDef ident="nymRef" usage="opt">
      <gloss>reference to the canonical name</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">표준 이름에 대한 참조</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">referencia al nombre canónico</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">référence au nom canonique</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">riferimento al nome canonico</gloss>
      <desc>provides a means of locating the canonical form
      (<term>nym</term>) of the names associated with the object
       named by
      the element bearing it.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">URI를 포함하는 요소에 의해 명명된 대상과 연관된 이름의 표준형식 (<term>nym</term>)의 위치를 가리키는 방법을 제공한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">proporciona los medios para localizar la forma canónica (<term>nym</term>) de los nombres asociados al objeto nombrado por el elemento que lo contiene.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該要素で名前が付与されている対象に関連する規範的な名前
    (<term>nym</term>)の場所を示す．
    </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">indique comment localiser la forme canonique
            (<term>nym</term>) des noms qui sont associés à l'objet nommé par l'élément qui le contient.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">indica un modo di localizzare la forma canonica (nym) dei nomi associati all'oggetto definito dall'elemento che lo contiene</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <remarks>
        <p>The value must point directly to one or more XML elements
        by means of one or more URIs, separated by whitespace. If more
        than one is supplied, the implication is that the name
        is associated with  several distinct canonical names.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>La valeur doit pointer directement vers un ou plusieurs
        éléments XML au moyen d'un ou plusieurs URIs, séparés par un
        espace blanc. Si plus d'un URI est fourni, alors le nom est
        associé à plusieurs noms canoniques distincts.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>El valor debe señalar directamente a uno o más elementos XML mediante uno o más URIs, separado por espacios en blanco.
        Si se suministra más de uno, la implicación es que el nombre está asociado a varios nombres canónicos distintos. </p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
        当該属性値は，当該文書またはURIで到達可能な場所にある，XML要素
        を直接指示するものでなくてはならない．
        </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CONARS"/>
    <ptr target="#NDNYM"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
