<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" type="atts" ident="att.internetMedia">
  <desc>provides attributes for specifying the type of a computer
  resource using a standard taxonomy.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">표준 분류법을 사용하는 컴퓨터 자원의 유형을 명시하는 속성을 제시한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  標準的な用語による計算機資源の種類を表す属性を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-05-27" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs pour spécifier le type de
ressource informatique selon une taxinomie normalisée.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">indica degli attributi che specificano il tipo di risorsa informatica utilizzando una tassonomia standard</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">atributos para registrar un periodo temporal normalizado</desc>
  <attList xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <attDef ident="mimeType" usage="opt">
      <gloss>MIME media type</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">MIME 매체 유형</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">Tipo de media del MIME</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">type de média MIME</gloss>
      <desc>specifies the applicable multimedia internet mail extension (MIME) media type</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">적용 가능한 다중매체 인터넷 메일 확장자(MIME) 매체 유형을 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該データのMIMEタイプ．</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">spécifie le type MIME (multipurpose internet mail extension) applicable.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">specifica il tipo MIME appropriato</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">El tipo de MIME</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-TW">MIME協定種類</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref name="data.word"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>The value should be a valid MIME media type</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr">La valeur doit être un type MIME valide.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>This attribute class provides attributes for describing a
    computer resource, typically available over the internet,
    according to standard taxonomies. At present only a single
    taxonomy is supported, the Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions
    Media Type system. This system of typology of media types is
    defined by the Internet Engineering Task Force in <ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt">RFC 2046</ref>. The
    <ref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">list of
    types</ref> is maintained by the Internet Assigned Numbers
    Authority.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cette classe d'attributs fournit des attributs pour décrire une ressource
                informatique, en général disponible sur internet, selon les taxinomies normalisées.
                Actuellement une seule taxinomie est reconnue : le système "Multipurpose Internet
                Mail Extensions Media Type". Ce système de typologie des types de média est définie
                par l'Internet Engineering Task Force dans<ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt">RFC 2046</ref>. La <ref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">liste des types</ref>
                est maintenue par l'Internet Assigned Numbers Authority. </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Esta clase de atributo proporciona los atributos para describir un recurso del ordenador, típicamente disponibles en Internet, según las taxonomías estándar. Solamente una única taxonomía se utiliza actualmente, el sistema Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions
    Media Type. Este sistema de tipología de los tipos de media es definido por el Internet Engineering Task Force <ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt">RFC 2046</ref>. 
    . La <ref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">lista de tipos</ref> es mantenida por el Internet Assigned Numbers Authority.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    当該属性クラスは，計算機資源を示すためのもので，一般には，インター
    ネット上にある資源を標準的な用語で示す．現時点では，MIMEタイプに従っ
    MIMEタイプについては，IETFの
    <ref target="http://www.ietf.org/rfc/rfc2046.txt">RFC 2046</ref>
    で規定されている．
    <ref target="http://www.iana.org/assignments/media-types/">
    使用できるタイプ名</ref>の管理は，IANAで行われている．
    </p>
  </remarks>
</classSpec>
