<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="spoken" predeclare="true" type="atts" ident="att.duration">
<!--desc>attributes for recording normalized temporal durations</desc-->
  <desc>provides attributes for normalization of elements that contain datable events.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">날짜를 정할 수 있는 사건을 포함하는 요소의 규격화를 위한 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供用於元素規格化的屬性，這些元素包含日期明確的事件。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  時間事象を含む要素の正規化手法を表す属性を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs pour la normalisation des
      éléments qui contiennent des mentions d'événements datables</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">indica degli attributi per la normalizzazione di elementi che contengono eventi databili</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos para la normalización de elementos que contienen eventos datables</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.duration.w3c"/>
    <memberOf key="att.duration.iso"/>
  </classes>
  <remarks>
    <p>This <soCalled>superclass</soCalled> provides attributes that
    can be used to provide normalized values of temporal information.
    By default, the attributes from the <ident type="class">att.duration.w3c</ident> class are provided. If the
    module for names &amp; dates is loaded, this class also provides
    attributes from the <ident type="class">att.duration.iso</ident>
    class. In general, the possible values of attributes restricted to
    the W3C datatypes form a subset of those values available via the
    ISO 8601 standard. However, the greater expressiveness of the ISO
    datatypes is rarely needed, and there exists much greater software
    support for the W3C datatypes.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cette<soCalled>superclasse</soCalled> fournit des attributs qui peuvent être employés
                pour fournir des valeurs normalisées d'information relative au temps. Par défaut,
                les attributs de la classe <ident type="class">att.duration.w3c</ident> sont
                fournis. Si le module pour les noms et dates est chargé, cette classe fournit
                également des attributs de la classe<ident type="class">att.duration.iso</ident>. En
                général, les valeurs possibles des attributs limitées aux types de données W3C
                forment un sous-ensemble des valeurs que l'on trouve dans la norme ISO 8601.
                Cependant, il est rarement nécessaire de recourir aux possibilités très étendues des
                types de données de l'ISO, il existe en effet une bien plus grande offre logicielle
                pour le traitement des types de données W3C.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Esta <soCalled>superclase</soCalled> proporciona atributos que se pueden utilizar para proporcionar los valores normalizados de la información temporal.
    Por defecto, los atributos de la clase <ident type="class">att.duration.w3c</ident> son proporcionados. Si el módulo para los nombres y las fechas se activa, esta clase también proporciona atributos para la clase <ident type="class">att.duration.iso</ident>
. En general, los valores posibles de los atributos son los restringidos por la forma de los datatypes de W3C, un subconjunto de esos valores disponibles vía el estándar de ISO 8601. Sin embargo, la mayoría de expresiones de los datatypes de ISO se necesitan raramente, y existe software de soporte para los datatypes de W3C.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    このいわゆる<soCalled>親クラス(スーパークラス)</soCalled>は，
    正規化された値を属性値として持つ，時間情報を示す属性になる．
    デフォルト値として，当該属性は，クラス
    <ident type="class">att.datable.w3c</ident>が付与されている．
    名前と日付に関するモジュールが使用される場合，当該クラスは，クラス
    <ident type="class">att.duration.iso</ident>から属性が与えられる．    
    一般には，W3Cのデータ形式に従った属性値は，ITO8601に従った属性値の
    下位要素になっている．しかし，より強力な表現力を持つISOのデータ形
    式が必要になることはない．さらに強力な表現力をサポートするソフトウェ
    アも存在する．        
    </p>
  </remarks>
</classSpec>
