<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="SPANNING" type="atts" ident="att.spanning">
  <desc>provides attributes for elements which delimit a span of text by pointing mechanisms rather than by enclosing it.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">포함보다는 포인터 메카니즘을 통하여 구분된 텍스트 구간을 나타내는 요소의 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供元素的屬性，這些元素使用參照機制來限定某一文字段，而非包含此文字段。
    </desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  テキスト幅の範囲を内容としてではなく参照機能を使って示す要素に付与さ
  れる属性を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">fournit des attributs pour les éléments qui délimitent un passage de texte par des mécanismes de pointage plutôt qu'en entourant le passage.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos para elementos que delimitan un fragmento de texto utilizando los señalizadores en lugar de cerrando el texto.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna degli attributi agli elementi che delimitano una porzione di testo utilizzando dei puntatori invece di racchiudere il testo stesso</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="spanTo" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates the end of a span initiated by the element
	bearing this attribute.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 속성을 포함하는 요소에 의해 시작된 구간의 끝을 나타낸다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出文字段的結尾，該文字段以帶有此屬性的元素開頭。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該要素が示す範囲の終点を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">indique la fin d'un passage introduit par l'élément portant cet attribut.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el final de un fragmento de texto iniciado con el elemento al cual es asignaado el atributo.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la fine della porzione di testo che ha inizio con l'elemento a cui è assegnato l'attributo</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>points to an element following this one in the current document. </valDesc>
      <valDesc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">pointe vers un élément qui suit celui présent dans le document courant.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>The span is defined as running in document order from the start
    of the content of the pointing element (if any) to the end of the
    content of the element pointed to by the spanTo attribute (if
    any). If no value is supplied for the attribute, the assumption is that the span is
    coextensive with the pointing element.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p> Le passage est défini comme courant depuis le début du contenu de l'élément pointeur (s'il y en a un) jusqu'à la fin du contenu de l'élément
      pointé par l'attribut <gi>spanTo </gi>(s'il y en a un), dans l'ordre du document. Si aucune valeur n'est fournie pour l'attribut, il est entendu
      que le passage est de même étendue que l'élément pointeur.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>El span se define como ejecutándose en la orden del documento des del comienzo del contenido del elemento indicado (si lo hay) al extremo del contenido del elemento señalado por el atributo del spanTo (si lo hay).
    Si no se suministra ningún valor para el atributo, la asunción es que el span es coextensivo con el elemento indicado.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    当該範囲は，当該文書中にある，(もしあれば)参照要素の内容の始点から，
    (もしあれば)属性spanToで示された要素の内容の終点までになる．
    当該属性に値がない場合，当該範囲は，当該参照要素と同じ範囲と想定す
    る．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#STECAT"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
