<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" module="linking" xml:id="PTRGROUP" type="atts" ident="att.pointing.group">
  <desc>defines a set of attributes common to all elements which
  enclose groups of pointer elements.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce un insieme di attributi comuni a tutti gli elementi che includono gruppi di puntatori</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.pointing"/>
  </classes>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="domains" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>optionally specifies the identifiers of the elements
      within which all elements indicated by the contents of this
      element lie.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">stabilisce facoltativamente gli identificatori di elementi all'interno dei quali si trovano tutti gli elementi indicati dai contenuti dell'elemento in questione</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該要素で参照される要素の識別子を示す．</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref name="data.name"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a list of at least two generic identifier names,
      separated by whitespace.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>If this attribute is supplied every element specified as a
	target must be contained within the element or elements
	named by it. An application may choose whether or not to
	report failures to satisfy this constraint as errors, but may
	not access an element of the right identifier but in the wrong
	context. If this attribute is not supplied, then target
	elements may appear anywhere within the target document.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="targFunc" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>describes the function of each of the values of the
      <att>targets</att> attribute of the enclosed <gi>link</gi>,
      <gi>join</gi> or <gi>alt</gi> tags.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">descrive la funzione di ognuno dei valori dell'attributo <att>targets</att> dei marcatori corrispondenti <gi>link</gi>,
      <gi>join</gi> o <gi>alt</gi></desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">属性targetsの属性値の働きを示す．</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref name="data.word"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a list of at least two valid names, separated by whitespace.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>The number of separate values must match the number of
        values in the <att>targets</att> attribute in the enclosed
        <gi>link</gi>, <gi>join</gi> or <gi>alt</gi> tags (an
        intermediate <gi>ptr</gi> element may be needed to accomplish
        this). It should also match the number of values in the
        <att>targType</att> and <att>domains</att> attributes of the
        current tag, if those have been specified.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks/>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#SA"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
