<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="NAMES" type="atts" ident="att.naming">
  <desc>provides attributes common to elements which refer to named persons, places, organizations etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">identifica los atributos comunes a los elementos que se refieren a personas, lugares, organizaciones, etc. indicados por nombre</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">identifica degli attributi comuni a elementi che si riferiscono a persone, luoghi, organizzazioni, ecc. indicati per nome</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="key" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>provides an external means
 of locating a full definition for the  entity being named, such as a database record key
      or other token.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona el modo de localizar una definición completa de la entidad en cuestión, como un campo clave de una voz de database </desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">stabilisce il modo di localizzare una definizione completa dell'entità in questione, come un campo chiave di una voce di database </desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">名前で特定できる実体の名前を示す．例えばデータベースにおけるレコードのキーやURI．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.key"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any string of Unicode characters</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>The value may be a unique identifier from a database, or
	any other externally-defined name for the referent. </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
<attDef ident="ref" usage="opt">
<equiv/>
      <desc>provides an explicit means
 of locating a full definition for the  entity being named by means of
 a URI.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any valid URI</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>The value must point directly to an XML element containing
	the corresponding information, located within the current
	document or elsewhere and acccessible by a URI. </p>
      </remarks></attDef>


    <attDef ident="nymRef" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>provides a means of locating the canonical form
      (<term>nym</term>) of the names associated with the object
       named by
      the element bearing it.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona el modo de localizar la forma canónica (<term>nym</term>) de los nombres asociados al objeto identificado mediante el atributo <att>key</att> y referido por el elemento que lo incluye.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any valid URI</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>The value must point directly to an XML element containing
	the corresponding information, located within the current
	document or elsewhere and acccessible by a URI. </p>
      </remarks></attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CONARS"/>
    <ptr target="#NDNYM"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
