<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" xml:id="TEIFORM" type="atts" ident="att.TEIform">
<gloss>TEI name form</gloss>
<desc>defines an attribute (<att>TEIform</att>) common to all tags in
the TEI scheme, and recommended for all user-defined extensions.</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="TEIform" usage="mwa">
	<equiv/>
	<desc>indicates the standard TEI name (generic identifier) for a given
element.</desc>
      <datatype><rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="NCName"/></datatype>
      <valDesc>must be a valid name;
by default, the canonical name of this element as defined in the TEI Guidelines.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>In the TEI DTDs, the default value for this attribute is
always the same as the generic identifier of the element.  If an element
is renamed using the techniques described in chapter <ptr target="#MD"/>,
the attribute declaration for <att>TEIform</att> will be left
undisturbed; the default value will thus still be the standard TEI name
for the element.  TEI-aware application programs can thus process
TEI-conformant documents which rename TEI elements, since by consulting
the <att>TEIform</att> attribute value the application can learn the
standard name for the element and process it accordingly.
 </p>
        <p>In the normal course of events, this attribute will never be
specified in a TEI-conformant document; all occurrences will have the
default value.  In some special circumstances, it can be useful to
specify a non-default value on some instances of an element; this allows
application programs to process correctly a locally defined element
which usually corresponds to one TEI element (which would be expressed
by the default value) but sometimes to another TEI element (which would
be expressed by explicit values attached to the element instance).
 </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>The attribute <att>TEIform</att>, though common to all tags
in the TEI encoding scheme, is not defined as part of the
<term>global</term> class for technical reasons.  Since its default
value must be specified separately for each element type, no elements
actually inherit the attribute from the element class
<term>TEIform</term>; each defines the attribute separately.
 </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#STGA"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
