<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" type="atts" ident="att.tableDecoration">
  <desc>provides attributes used to decorate rows or cells of a table.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">테이블의 행 또는 셀을 장식하는 속성을 제공한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供屬性，用以裝飾表格內的儲存格或列。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  表の行またはセルを修飾する属性を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">donne des attributs pour mettre en forme les lignes ou les cellules d'un tableau.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos usados para decorar filas o celdas de una tabla.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna degli attributi utilizzati per decorare righe e celle di una tabella</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="role" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <gloss version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">rôle</gloss>
      <desc>indicates the kind of information held in this cell or
in each cell of this row.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 셀에 또는 이 행의 각 셀에 나타난 정보의 종류를 제시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出此儲存格或列當中，各儲存格所包含的資訊類型。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該セル，または当該行中のセルにある情報の種類を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique le type d'informations contenues dans cette cellule ou dans chaque cellule de cette ligne.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica el tipo de información contenida en la celda en cuestión o en cada una de las celdas de la fila.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica il tipo di informazione contenuta nela cella in questione o in ciascuna delle celle della riga presa in esame</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>data</defaultVal>
      <valList type="semi">
        <valItem ident="label">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>labelling or descriptive information only.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">표지 또는 기술적 정보만 허용</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">僅為標號或描述性資訊。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">etiquetado o información descriptiva solamente.</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
          記述的情報またはラベルのみ．
          </desc>
          <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">uniquement des informations relatives au codage ou à la description</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">informazione esclusivamente descrittiva o del tipo etichetta</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="data">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>data values.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">데이터 값</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">數據值。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">valores de datos.</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
          日付情報．
          </desc>
          <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">valeurs de données</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">valori di dati</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <remarks>
        <p>When this attribute is specified on a row, its value is the
	default for all cells in this row. When specified on a cell,
	its value overrides any default specified by the
<att>role</att> attribute of the parent <gi>row</gi> element.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p> Quand cet attribut est appliqué à une ligne de tableau, sa valeur est
                        transmise comme valeur par défaut à toutes les cellules de cette ligne.
                        Quand il est spécifié sur une cellule, sa valeur annule et remplace toute
                        valeur spécifiée par défaut dans l'attribut <att>role</att> de l'élément
                        parent <gi>row</gi>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>Cuando este atributo se especifica en una fila, su valor es el valor por defecto para todas las celdas de esta fila. Cuando está especificado en una celda, su valor reemplaza cualquier valor por defecto especificado por
el atributo <att>papel</att> del elemento padre <gi>fila</gi>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
        当該属性が行に付与されている場合，当該属性値は当該行中の全セル
        のデフォルト値になる．当該属性がセルに付与されている場合，当該
        属性値は，親要素<gi>row</gi>の属性<att>role</att>にあるデフォ
        ルト値を上書きする．
      </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="rows" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <gloss version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">lignes</gloss>
      <desc>indicates the number of rows occupied by this cell or row.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 셀 또는 행에 의해 사용된 행의 수를 나타낸다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出此儲存格或列所占的列數。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該セルまたは行を含む行の数を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">indique le nombre de lignes occupées par la cellule ou la ligne en question.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el número de filas ocupado por una celda o por la fila en cuestión.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il numero di righe occupate dalla cella o riga in questione</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.count"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>1</defaultVal>
      <valDesc>A number; a value greater than one indicates that this
      cell (or row)
      spans several rows.</valDesc>
      <valDesc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">un nombre ; une valeur plus grande que un indique que cette cellule (ou cette ligne) occupe plusieurs lignes.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Where several cells span several rows, it may be more convenient
to use nested tables.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p> Lorsque plusieurs cellules s'étendent sur plusieurs lignes, il peut être plus pratique d'employer des tableaux inclus.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>Donde varias celdas atraviesan varias filas, puede ser más conveniente utilizar los vectores jerarquizados.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
        複数のセルが複数行に渡る場合には，入れ子の表を使った方が便利で
        ある．
        </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="cols" usage="opt">
      <gloss>columns</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">열</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">columnas</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">colonnes</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">colonne</gloss>
      <desc>indicates the number of columns occupied by this cell or
	row.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 셀 또는 행에 의해 사용된 열의 수를 나타낸다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出此儲存格或列所佔的欄位數。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該セルまたは行を含む列の数を示す．      
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique le nombre de colonnes occupées par cette cellule ou cette ligne.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el número de columnas que abraza una celda o fila.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il numero di colonne occupate dalla cella o riga</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.count"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>1</defaultVal>
      <valDesc>A number; a value greater than one indicates that this
      cell or row
      spans several columns.</valDesc>
      <valDesc version="2009-05-28" xml:lang="fr">un nombre ; une valeur plus grande que un indique que cette cellule (ou cette ligne)
        occupe plusieurs colonnes.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>Where an initial cell spans an entire row, it may be better treated as
a heading.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p> Lorsqu'une première cellule s'étend sur une ligne entière, il peut être préférable de la considérer comme un titre.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>Donde una celda inicial atraviesa una fila entera, puede ser tratada como título.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
        始めのセルが行全体である場合には，見出しとして扱った方がよい．
        </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#FT"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
