<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" predeclare="true" type="atts" ident="att.duration.w3c">
  <desc>attributes for recording normalized temporal durations.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">시간적 지속을 규격화한 녹음에 대한 속성</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">用於記錄時間長度規格化的屬性</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  正規化された時間幅を示す属性．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr"> attributs pour enregistrer des durées de temps
      normalisées</desc>
  <desc version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">attributi per la registrazione di durate temporali normalizzate</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">atributos para registrar un periodo temporal normalizado</desc>
  <attList xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <attDef ident="dur" usage="opt">
      <gloss>duration</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">지속</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">時間長度</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">durée</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">durata</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">duración</gloss>
      <desc>indicates the length of this element in time.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">시간선상에서 이 요소의 길이를 나타낸다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指明此元素的時間長度。
      </desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      時間幅を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique la longueur de cet élément dans le
        temps</desc>
      <desc version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">indica la durata nel tempo di tale elemento</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la longitud de este elemento en el tiempo.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref name="data.duration.w3c"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>If both <att>when</att> and <att>dur</att> are specified, the
    values should be interpreted as indicating a span of time by its
    starting time (or date) and duration. In order to represent a time
    range by a duration and its ending time the <att>when-iso</att>
    attribute must be used.</p>
    <p>In providing a <soCalled>regularized</soCalled> form, no claim
    is made that the form in the source text is incorrect; the
    regularized form is simply that chosen as the main form for
    purposes of unifying variant forms under a single heading.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p> Si <att>when</att> et <att>dur</att> sont indiqués en même temps, leurs valeurs
                doivent être interprétées comme indiquant un espace de temps à partir de son heure
                (ou date) de départ et de sa durée. Afin de représenter une fourchette de temps par
                une durée et sa fin, l'attribut <att>when-iso</att> doit être employé.</p>
    <p>En fournissant une forme <soCalled>regularized</soCalled>, il n'est rien affrimé sur
                la correction ou l'incorrection de la forme dans le texte source ; la forme
                régularisée est simplement celle qui est choisie comme forme principale afin
                d'unifier les variantes de forme sous une seule rubrique . </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Si ambos, <att>cuando</att> y <att>dur</att>, se especifican, los valores se deben interpretar como indicación de un intervalo de tiempo emtre su hora de salida (o fecha) y la duración. Para representar un intervalo de tiempo por su duración y su conlusión se debe emplear atributo <att>cuando-ISO</att>.
    el atributo debe ser utilizado.</p>
    <p>Para proporcionar una forma <soCalled>regularizada</soCalled>, no se hace ninguna declaración sobre que la forma en el texto original sea incorrecta; la forma regularizada es simplemente elegida como la forma principal con el fin de la unificación de las formas variables bajo el título.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    属性<att>when</att>と<att>dur</att>が指定されている場合，その属性
    値は，開始時間(開始日)と長さとで示される時間幅を示していると解釈さ
    れるべきである．時間幅とその終了時間を示す場合には，属性
    <att>when-iso</att>が使われる必要がある．
    </p>
    <p><soCalled>正規化</soCalled>形式ということで，元テキストにある形式
    が不正確であるということを含むものではない．
    ここでいう正規化形式とは，単に，ひとつの項目に同じ値を付与すること
    を目的とするものである．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CONADA"/>
    <ptr target="#NDDATE"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
