<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="DECLABL" type="atts" ident="att.declarable">
  <desc>provides attributes for those elements in the TEI Header which may be independently selected by means of  the specialpurpose <att>decls</att> attribute.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">provides attributes for those elements in the TEI Header which may be independently selected by means of  the special purpose <att>decls</att> attribute</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">individua attributi per gli elementi contenuti nell'intestazione che possono essere selezionati autonomamente grazie all'apposito attributo <att>decls</att></desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona atributos para los elementos contenidos en el encabezado que pueden ser seleccionados autónomamente mediante el atributo <att>decls</att> adecuado.</desc>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="default" usage="mwa">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates whether or not this element is selected by default when
its parent is selected.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">indicates whether or not this element is selected by default when
its parent is selected</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica se l'elemento è selezionato automaticamente quando è selezionato il genitore</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica si el elemento es seleccionado automáticamente o no  cuando es seleccionado el padre</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">親要素が選択された場合に，当該要素がデフォルトとして選択されるか
どうかを示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:data xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" type="boolean"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>false</defaultVal>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="true">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>This element is selected if its parent is selected</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">Este elemento es seleccionado si su padre es seleccionado.</desc>
          <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">(親要素が選択された場合，当該要素が選択される．)</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="false">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>This element can only be selected explicitly, unless it is the
only one of its kind, in which case it is selected if its parent is selected.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">Este elemento sólo puede ser seleccionado explícitamente, a menos que no sea el único de su género, ya  que en ese caso és seleccionado si es seleccionado el padre.</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <remarks>
    <p>The rules governing the association of declarable elements with
    individual parts of a TEI text are fully defined in chapter <ptr target="#CCAS"/>. Only one element of a particular type may have a
    <att>default</att> attribute with a value of <val>true</val>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CCAS"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
