<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- © TEI Consortium. Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licenses; see the file COPYING.txt for details. -->
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" predeclare="true" module="tei" type="atts" ident="att.global.rendition">
  <desc versionDate="2014-12-02" xml:lang="en">provides rendering attributes common to all elements in the TEI encoding scheme.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2019-07-21" xml:lang="ja">TEIの符号化スキーマにおけるすべての要素に共通するレンダリング属性を提供する。</desc>
  <classes/>
    
  
  <attList>
    
    
    
    <attDef ident="rend" usage="opt">
      <gloss versionDate="2007-07-02" xml:lang="en">rendition</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">번역</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">interpretación</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">interprétation</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">resa</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2019-07-21" xml:lang="ja">見た目の表示</gloss>
      <desc versionDate="2005-10-10" xml:lang="en">indicates how the element in question was rendered or presented in the source text.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">문제의 요소가 원본 텍스트에 제시된 방법을 나타낸다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出該元素如何呈現於來源文件中</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">当該要素が、元資料でどのように表示されていたかを示す。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique comment l'élément en question a été rendu ou
        présenté dans le texte source</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica cómo el elemento en cuestión ha sido dado o
        proporcionado en el texto fuente.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica come l'elemento in questione è stato reso o
        rappresentato nel testo originario</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded"><dataRef key="teidata.word"/></datatype>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)"><lb/>To The <lb/>Duchesse <lb/>of <lb/>Newcastle,
            <lb/>On Her <lb/><hi rend="case(mixed)">New Blazing-World</hi>. </head>
        </egXML>
        <!--    <p>
          <note type="cit">From the foreword by William Newcastle in
        Margaret Cavendish, Duchess of Newcastle's <title>The
        description of a new world, called the blazing-world</title>,
        WWP TR00253</note>
        </p>-->
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum versionDate="2010-02-26" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#fr-ex-Belloy">
          <head rend="align(center) case(allcaps)">épître dédicatoire<lb/>à <lb/>Monsieur de Coucy <lb/>
                  <lb/>.</head>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks versionDate="2012-10-24" xml:lang="en">
        <p>These Guidelines make no binding recommendations for the values of the <att>rend</att>
          attribute; the characteristics of visual presentation vary too much from text to text and
          the decision to record or ignore individual characteristics varies too much from project
          to project. Some potentially useful conventions are noted from time to time at appropriate
          points in the Guidelines. The values of the <att>rend</att> attribute are a set of 
	sequence-indeterminate individual tokens separated by whitespace.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2007-06-12">
        <p>Ces Principes directeurs ne font aucune recommandation contraignante pour les valeurs de
          l'attribut <att>rend</att>; les caractéristiques de la présentation visuelle changent trop
          d'un texte à l'autre et la décision d'enregistrer ou d'ignorer des caractéristiques
          individuelles est trop variable d'un projet à l'autre. Quelques conventions
          potentiellement utiles sont notées de temps en temps à des points appropriés dans ces
          Principes directeurs.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es" versionDate="2008-04-06">
        <p>Estas guías de consulta no hacen ninguna recomendación obligatoria para los valores del
          atributo <att>rend</att>; las características de la presentación visual varían demasiado
          de texto a texto y la decisión para registrar o para omitir características individuales
          varía demasiado de proyecto a proyecto. Observar algunas convenciones que puedan resultar
          útiles en los puntos indicados en las guías de consulta.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks versionDate="2019-07-21" xml:lang="ja"><p>本ガイドラインでは、当該属性<att>rend</att>の値として推奨するものはない。活字化の特徴は様々であり、それらのどれを採用するかはプロジェクトごとでおそろしく異なるからである。当ガイドラインでは、有用な記述法があれば、その都度示すことになっている。<att>rend</att>属性の値は、空白によって区切られる順序不定の個々のトークンの集合である。</p></remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="style" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2012-10-05" xml:lang="en">contains an expression in some formal style definition language
which defines the rendering or presentation
used for this element in the source text</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2022-05-09" xml:lang="ja">なんらかの形式的スタイル定義言語においてソーステキスト内の当該要素のレンダリングや表示を定義する際の表現を含む。</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="1"><dataRef key="teidata.text"/></datatype>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <head style="text-align: center; font-variant: small-caps"><lb/>To The <lb/>Duchesse <lb/>of <lb/>Newcastle, <lb/>On Her
              <lb/><hi style="font-variant: normal">New Blazing-World</hi>. </head>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks versionDate="2017-07-02" xml:lang="en">
        <p>Unlike the attribute values of <att>rend</att>, which uses whitespace as a separator, the <att>style</att> attribute may contain whitespace. This attribute is intended for recording inline stylistic information concerning the
source, not any particular output.</p>
        <p>The formal language in which values for this attribute are expressed may be specified using the <gi>styleDefDecl</gi> element in
the TEI header.</p>
        <p>If <att>style</att> and <att>rendition</att> are both present on an element, then
          <att>style</att> overrides or complements <att>rendition</att>. <att>style</att> should
          not be used in conjunction with <att>rend</att>, because the latter does not employ a
          formal style definition language.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks versionDate="2019-07-21" xml:lang="ja">
        <p>空白を区切り記号とする<att>rend</att>の属性値とは異なり、<att>style</att>属性は空白を含んでもよい。この属性は資料における行に埋め込まれたスタイル情報を記録するためのものであり、何らかの出力を対象とするものではない。</p>
        <p>この属性の値を表現する形式言語はTEIヘッダにおいて<gi>styleDefDecl</gi>要素を用いて指定されてもよい。</p>
        <p>もし<att>style</att>と<att>rendition</att>の両方が一つの要素に現れる場合、<att>style</att>は<att>rendition</att>を上書きもしくは補完する。<att>style</att>は<att>rend</att>と同時に用いられるべきではない。後者は形式的なスタイル定義言語を採用しているわけではないから。</p></remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="rendition" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2007-09-22" xml:lang="en">points to a description of the rendering or presentation used for this element in the
        source text.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">원본 텍스트에서 이 요소에 대해 사용된 모양과 제시에 대한 기술을 가리킨다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">indica una descripción de la representación o de la
        presentación empleada para este elemento en el texto original.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">当該要素が示す表現が現れている、元資料のテキスト部分を示す。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">pointe vers une description du rendu ou de la
        présentation utilisés pour cet élément dans le texte source</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">indica una descrizione della resa o della
        presentazione utilizzate per tale elemento nel testo di partenza</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded"><dataRef key="teidata.pointer"/></datatype>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <head rendition="#ac #sc"><lb/>To The <lb/>Duchesse <lb/>of <lb/>Newcastle, <lb/>On Her
              <lb/><hi rendition="#normal">New Blazing-World</hi>. </head>
          <!-- elsewhere... -->
          <rendition xml:id="sc" scheme="css">font-variant: small-caps</rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="normal" scheme="css">font-variant: normal</rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="ac" scheme="css">text-align: center</rendition>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum versionDate="2010-02-26" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#fr-ex-Belloy">
          <head rendition="#ac #sc"><lb/>épître dédicatoire <lb/>à <lb/>Monsieur de Coucy <lb/>
               </head>
          <rendition xml:id="fr_sc" scheme="css">font-variant: uppercase</rendition>
          <rendition xml:id="fr_ac" scheme="css">text-align: center</rendition>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks versionDate="2017-07-02" xml:lang="en">
        <p>The <att>rendition</att> attribute is used in a very similar way to the <att>class</att>
          attribute defined for XHTML but with the important distinction that its function is to
          describe the appearance of the source text, not necessarily to determine how that text
          should be presented on screen or paper.</p>
        <p>If <att>rendition</att> is used to refer to a style definition in a formal language like
          CSS, it is recommended that it not be used in conjunction with <att>rend</att>. 
          Where both <att>rendition</att> and <att>rend</att> are supplied, the latter is
          understood to override or complement the former.</p>
        <p>Each URI provided should indicate a <gi>rendition</gi> element defining the intended
          rendition in terms of some appropriate style language, as indicated by the
          <att>scheme</att> attribute.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks versionDate="2019-07-21" xml:lang="ja">
        <p>属性<att>rendition</att>は、XHTMLの属性<att>class</att>と大変 似たように使用される。但し、重要な違いとして、当該属性は、元資 料の表現を記述するものであり、スクリーン上または紙上でどう表示 されているかを示すものではない。</p>
        <p> もし<att>rendition</att>属性がCSSのような形式言語において定義されるスタイル定義を参照するのに用いられているなら、<att>rend</att>属性と同時に用いないことが推奨される。属性<att>rendition</att>と属性<att>rend</att>の両方が使用されている場合、後者の値が前者の値を上書きする、または補うと判断される。</p>
        <p> 当該属性値となるURIは、属性<att>scheme</att>で提示されているス タイル言語により、当該表現を定義する要素<gi>rendition</gi>を示すべきである。</p></remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2007-06-12">
        <p>L'attribut <att>rendition</att> est employé à peu près de la même manière que l'attribut
            <att>class</att> défini pour XHTML mais avec cette sérieuse différence que sa fonction
          est de décrire la présentation du texte source mais pas nécessairement de déterminer
          comment ce texte doit être représenté à l'écran ou sur le papier. </p>
        <p>Où <att>rendition</att> et <att>rend</att> sont donnés ensembles, il faut comprendre que
          le dernier remplace ou complète le premier.</p>
        <p> Chaque URI fourni doit indiquer un élément <gi>rendition</gi> définissant le rendu prévu
          dans les termes d'un langage approprié pour définir les styles, comme indiqué par
          l'attribut <att>scheme</att>.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es" versionDate="2008-04-06">
        <p>El atributo <att>rendition</att> (interpretación) se utiliza en una manera muy similar al
          atributo <att>clase</att> definido por XHTML pero con una diferencia importante: que su
          función es describir el aspecto del texto original, no necesariamente para determinar la
          presentación visual de ese texto en la pantalla o el papel.</p>
        <p>Donde ambos <att>interpretación</att> y <att>rend</att> se dan, este último se emplea
          para reemplazar o para complementar el anterior.</p>
        <p>Cada URI proporcionado debe indicar al elemento <gi>interpretación</gi> que define la
          interpretación prevista en términos de cualquier lenguaje apropiado del estilo, según lo
          indicado por el atributo <att>scheme</att> (esquema).</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    
    
  </attList>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#STGAre"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>