<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright TEI Consortium.
    Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
    See the file COPYING.txt for details
    $Date$
    $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="cb">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>column break</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">열 바꿈</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">分段</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">saut de colonne</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">cambio de columna</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">interruzione di colonna</gloss>
  <desc>marks the boundary between one column of a text and the next
        in a standard reference system.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">표준 참조 시스템에서 텍스트의 한 열과 다음 열 사이의 경계를 표지한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">用標準參照系統來標明文本段落之間的分界。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
        
        テキストの段と段の境界を，標準的な参照システムにより示す．
    </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">Dans un système de référence normalisé, marque dans un texte la frontière entre une colonne et la suivante.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la frontera entre una columna de un texto y la siguiente en un sistema de referencia estándard.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il limite tra una colonna di un testo e la successiva in un sistema di riferimento standard</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.milestoneLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.edition"/>
    <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
    <memberOf key="att.breaking"/>  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:empty xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>Markup of an early English dictionary printed in two columns:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#REF-cb-eg-1">
      <pb/>
      <cb n="1"/>
      <entryFree><form>Well</form>, <sense>a Pit to hold Spring-Water</sense>:
                <sense>In the Art of <hi rend="italic">War</hi>, a Depth the Miner
                    sinks into the Ground, to find out and disappoint the Enemies Mines,
                    or to prepare one</sense>.</entryFree>
      <entryFree>To <form>Welter</form>, <sense>to wallow</sense>, or
                <sense>lie groveling</sense>.</entryFree>
      <!-- remainder of column -->
      <cb n="2"/>
      <entryFree><form>Wey</form>, <sense>the greatest Measure for dry Things,
                    containing five Chaldron</sense>.</entryFree>
      <entryFree><form>Whale</form>, <sense>the greatest of
                    Sea-Fishes</sense>.</entryFree>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>On this element, the global <att>n</att> attribute indicates the number or other value associated with the column
            which follows the point of insertion of this <gi>cb</gi> element. Encoders should adopt a clear and consistent policy as to
            whether the numbers associated with column breaks relate to the physical
            sequence number of the column in the whole text, or whether columns are
            numbered within the page.
            By convention, the <gi>cb</gi> element is placed at the head of the
            column to which it refers.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>L'attribut global <att>n</att> donne un nouveau numéro ou une autre valeur à la
            colonne qui suit l'élément <gi>cb</gi>. Les encodeurs doivent faire un choix clair,
            et s'y tenir, entre l'option consistant à se fonder sur la séquence physique des
            colonnes dans le texte entier, et celle qui consiste à se fonder sur la numérotation
            des colonnes à l'intérieur de la page. Par convention, l'élément <gi>cb</gi>
            apparaît en haut de la colonne à laquelle il se rapporte.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
            当該要素にあるグローバル属性<att>n</att>は，当該要素<gi>cb</gi>が
            あるすぐ後にある段と関連する番号等を示す．符号化する人は，テキスト
            全体における物理的な段の並びから示された境界を示す番号であるか，ま
            たは当該ページ内で振られた番号であるのかなど，段境界に付与される番
            号付けには，明確で一貫した方針を採るべきである．
            一般的には，要素<gi>cb</gi>は，段落の始めに置かれる．
        </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CORS5" type="div3"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
