<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="certainty" ident="certainty">
  <desc>indicates the degree of certainty associated
  with some aspect of the text markup. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">텍스트 마크업의 어떤 특성과 관련된 확실성 또는 불확실성의 정도를 가리킨다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出標記文本某些部分的確定或不確定的程度。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  当該マークアップの確信度を示す．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">Indique le degré de certitude ou d'incertitude
      associé à certains aspects du balisage du texte.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">Indica el grado de certeza o incertidumbre asociado a algun aspecto del marcaje de texto.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il grado di certezza o incertezza associato a un determinato aspetto del la codifica del testo</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.certLike"/>
    <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
    <memberOf key="att.scoping"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <zeroOrMore xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <ref name="model.glossLike"/>
    </zeroOrMore>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="cert" usage="opt">
      <gloss>certainty</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">확실성</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">certeza</gloss>
      <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">certitude</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">certezza</gloss>
      <desc>signifies the degree of certainty associated with the object pointed to by the <gi>certainty</gi> element.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.certainty"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="locus" usage="req">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates more exactly the aspect concerning which
      certainty is being expressed: specifically, whether the markup
      is correctly located, whether the correct element or attribute
      name has been used, or whether the content of the element or
      attribute is correct,
	etc.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">요소의 적용가능성, 시작 및 종료 태그의 정확한 위치, 명시적 속성 값 등과 같이 마크업에서 불확실성을 유발하는 정확한 위치를 가리킨다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出不確定標記的確切位置：元素的應用性、開始標籤或結束標籤的確切位置、特定屬性的屬性值等。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該確信度が該当する場所の詳細を示す．例えば，要素全体，開始タグ
      または終了タグの正確な位置，特定属性の値，など．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">Indique le point précis sur lequel porte
          l'incertitude de balisage : pertinence de l'élément, position exacte de la balise de début
          ou de fin, valeur d'un attribut spécifique, etc.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la posición precisa de la incertidumbre en el marcaje: aplicabilidad del elemento, posición precisa del comienzo y del final de la etiqueta, valor de un atributo específico, etc.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la posizione dell'incertezza nella codifica: l'applicabilità dell'elemento, la precisa posizione del marcatore iniziale o finale, il valore di un singolo attributo, ecc.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="name">
          <desc>uncertainty concerns whether the name of the element
	  or attribute  used is correctly applied.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="start">
          <desc>uncertainty concerns whether the start of the element
	  is correctly identified.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="end">
          <desc>uncertainty concerns whether the end of the element
	  is correctly identified.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="location">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>uncertainty concerns both the start and the end of the
	  element.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="value">
          <desc>uncertainty concerns the content (for an element) or
	  the value (for an attribute)</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="assertedValue" usage="rec">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>provides an alternative value for the aspect of the markup in
question — an alternative generic identifier, transcription,
or attribute value, or the identifier of an <gi>anchor</gi> element (to
indicate an alternative starting or ending location).  If an
<att>assertedValue</att> is given, the confidence level specified by
<att>degree</att> applies to the alternative markup specified by
<att>assertedValue</att>; if none is given, it applies to the markup
in the text.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">문제의 마크업에 대한 대체가능한 값을 제공한다- 대체가능한 일반 확인소, 전사, 속성 값, 또는 (대체가능한 시작 또는 종료 위치를 지시하는) <gi>anchor</gi> 요소의 확인소. <att>assertedValue</att>가 제시된 경우, <att>degree</att>로 명시된 신뢰수준은 <att>assertedValue</att>에 의해 명시된 대체가능한 마크업에 적용된다; 만약 아무런 것도 제시되지 않는다면 텍스트의 마크업에 신뢰수준이 적용된다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供一個替代屬性值給指定標記部分—一個替代的類目識別符碼、轉錄、或屬性值，或是元素<gi>anchor</gi> (用來指出一個替代的開始或結束位置) 的識別符碼。若使用屬性<att>assertedValue</att>，則屬性<att>degree</att>中指出的確定程度適用於屬性<att>assertedValue</att>所指明的替代標記；若無使用，則確定程度適用於文本中的標記。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      懸案の部分に対する代替値を示す．例えば，共通識別子(GI)，転記，属
      性値，(他の開始・終了地点を示す)要素<gi>anchor</gi>の識別子，な
      ど．属性<att>assertedValue</att>がある場合，属性
      <att>degree</att>で定義された確信度は，属性
      <att>assertedValue</att>にある値への確信度を示す．
      何もない場合には，当該テキスト中の当該マークアップに該当する．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">fournit une valeur alternative pour l'aspect d'un
          balisage jugé incertain - un identifiant générique, une transcription ou une valeur
          d'attribut, ou l'identifiant d'un élément <gi>anchor</gi> (pour indiquer un
          emplacement alternatif de début ou de fin). Si un attribut <att>assertedValue</att> est
          présent, le degré de confiance spécifié par l'attribut <att>degree</att> s'applique au
          balisage alternatif précisé par la valeur d' <att>assertedValue</att>; s'il n'y a pas
          d'attribut <att>assertedValue</att>, ce degré de confiance s'applique au balisage du
          texte.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona un valor alternativo para
          el aspecto del marcaje en cuestion, un identificador
          genérico alternativo, transcripción, o valor de atributo, o
          de identificador de un elemento <gi>anchor</gi> (para
          indicar una posición de comienzo y fin alternativa). Si un
          <att>assertedValue</att> viene dado, el nivel de confianza
          especificado por <att>degree</att> se aplica al marcaje
          alternativo especificado por <att>assertedValue</att>; si no
          viene dado ninguno, se aplica al marcaje en el texto.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna un valore alternativo all'apetto della codifica in questione, un identificatore generico, una trascrizione, il valore di un attributo, o l'identificatore di un elemento <gi>anchor</gi> (per indicare una posizione di inizio o fine alternativa). Se viene fornito un attributo <att>assertedValue</att>, il livello di sicurezza specificato dall'attributo <att>degree</att> si applica alla codifica alternativa specificata dall'attributo <att>assertedValue</att>; se non viene fornito alcun attributo, si applica alla codifica del testo.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <choice xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <ref name="data.pointer"/>
          <ref name="data.name"/>
          <ref name="data.word"/>
        </choice>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>generic identifier, attribute value, location (e.g.
indicated by a reference to an <gi>anchor</gi> element or to an
<gi>ptr</gi> element), or other appropriate alternative
value.</valDesc>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <certainty target="#ESX" locus="name" assertedValue="placeName" cert="low">
            <desc>It is unlikely, but possible, that this refers to the place rather than the person.</desc>
          </certainty>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <certainty target="#fr_ESX" locus="name" assertedValue="place" degree="0.2"/>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum xml:lang="en">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <certainty match="parent::tei:gap/@reason" locus="value" cert="low"/>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>This attribute makes it possible to indicate the
degree of confidence in a specific alternative to some aspect
of the markup. In the example above the encoder is expressing
the likelihood (.2) that the generic identifier should be
<gi>placeName</gi> rather than <gi>persName</gi>, which is the coded
element.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Cet attribut permet
                        d'indiquer le degré de confiance dans une alternative spécifique à un aspect
                        du balisage. Dans l'exemple qui précède l'encodeur exprime la probabilité
                        qu'il faille un identifiant générique <gi>placeName</gi> plutôt que
                        <gi>persName</gi>, qui est l'élément encodé.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p>
	当該属性は，当該要素に対する代替値の確信度を示している．
	上の例では，符号化する人が当該可能性(.2)を示している．これは当
	該要素に使用される共通識別子は，<gi>persName</gi>ではなく
	<gi>placeName</gi>であるべき可能性の度合いを示している．
	</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="given" usage="rec">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates conditions assumed in the assignment of a degree
      of confidence.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">신뢰도 할당에서 추정된 조건을 표시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出在評估確定程度時所設想的情況。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      当該確信度が成立する条件を示す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">Indique les conditions présumées lors de
          l'attribution d'un degré de confiance.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica las condiciones asumidas en la asignación de un grado de confianza </desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica le condizioni presunte nell'assegnare un grado di certezza</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more pointers to element(s) characterizing the conditions which
      are assumed in the assignment of a degree of confidence.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>The envisioned typical value of this attribute would be the
	identifier of another <gi>certainty</gi> element or a list of
	such identifiers. It may thus be possible to construct
	probability networks by chaining <gi>certainty</gi> elements
	together. Such networks would ultimately be grounded in
	unconditional <gi>certainty</gi> elements (with no value for
	<att>given</att>). The semantics of this chaining would be
	understood in this way: if a <gi>certainty</gi> element is
	specified, via a reference, as the assumption, then it is not
	the attribution of uncertainty that is the assumption, but
	rather the assertion itself. For instance, in the example
	above, the first <gi>certainty</gi> element indicates that the
	confidence in the identification of the new scribe as
	<mentioned>msm</mentioned>. The second indicates the degree of
	confidence that <mentioned>Essex</mentioned> is a personal
	name, given that the new scribe is <mentioned>msm</mentioned>.
	Note that the given in the second <gi>certainty</gi> element
	is not the assertion that the likelihood that msm is the new
	scribe is 0.6, but simply the assertion that msm is the new
	scribe; this is a recommended convention to facilitate
	building networks.</p>
        <p>The ambitious encoder may wish to attempt complex networks
or probability assertions, experimenting with references to
other elements or prose assertions, and deploying feature
structure connectives such as <gi>alt</gi>, <gi>join</gi>, and
<gi>note</gi>.  However, we do not believe that the
<gi>certainty</gi> element gives, at this time, a comprehensive
ambiguity-free system for indicating certainty.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <!--<p> Un projet peut souhaiter utiliser un vocabulaire contrôlé pour cet attribut.</p>-->
        <p>La valeur typique à laquelle on pense pour cet attribut
        serait l'identifiant d'un autre élément <gi>certainty</gi> ou
        une liste comportant de tels identifiants. Il serait ainsi
        possible de construire des réseaux de probabilité en chaînant
        ensemble des éléments <gi>certainty</gi>. Ces réseaux seraient
        en définitive fondés sur des éléments <gi>certainty</gi>
        inconditionnels (sans attribut <att>given</att>). La
        sémantique de ce chaînage est à comprendre ainsi : si un
        élément <gi>certainty</gi> est spécifié comme postulat au
        moyen d'une référence (présence d'un attribut
        <att>given</att>), alors l'assertion même constitue le
        postulat, et non pas l'attribution d'un caractère
        d'incertitude. Ainsi, dans l'exemple ci-dessus, le premier
        élément <gi>certainty</gi> formule l'hypothèse que le nouveau
        scripteur est <mentioned>msm</mentioned>. Le second indique le
        degré de confiance dans le fait que
        <mentioned>Essex</mentioned> est un nom de personne, étant
        donné que le nouveau scripteur est
        <mentioned>msm</mentioned>. Notons que le postulat dans le
        deuxième élément <gi>certainty</gi> n'est pas que le degré de
        probabilité que msm soit le nouveau scripteur est de 0.6, mais
        simplement que msm est le nouveau scripteur ; il est
        recommandé d'utiliser cette convention pour faciliter la
        construction de réseaux.</p>
        <p>Les encodeurs ambitieux peuvent souhaiter construire des
        réseaux ou des assertions de probabilité complexes, en faisant
        référence à d'autres éléments ou à des assertions en texte
        libre, et en établissant des relations entre structures de
        traits, telles que <gi>alt</gi>, <gi>join</gi> et
        <gi>note</gi>. Toutefois nous ne pensons pas que l'élément
        <gi>certainty</gi> procure actuellement un système complet et
        sans ambiguïté pour indiquer le degré de certitude.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <!--<p>
	プロジェクトによっては，当該属性で使用される用語を管理したいだ
      ろう．
      </p>-->
        <p>
	当該属性値として考えられるものは，他の要素<gi>certainty</gi>の
      識別子またはそのリストである．従って，この要素<gi>certainty</gi>
      による連鎖は，確率ネットワークを作ることができる．この確率ネット
      ワークは，条件の付かない(属性<att>given</att>がない)要素
      <gi>certainty</gi>をベースに作られる．この要素の鎖は，以下のよう
      に解釈することができる．
      ある要素<gi>certainty</gi>を前提条件として参照している場合，
      属性にある確信度は，前提条件の内容ではなく，当該要素に関する記述
      を対象としたものである．例えば，上の例では，初めの要素
      <gi>certainty</gi>は，<mentioned>msm</mentioned>としてある新しい
      筆写者の識別子の確信度を示している．2番目のそれは，新しい筆写者
      が<mentioned>msm</mentioned>とすれば，
      <mentioned>Essex</mentioned>が個人名であるということの確信度を示
      している．この2番目の要素<gi>certainty</gi>にあるのは，msmが新し
      筆写者である確信度が0.6であるということではなく，msmは新しい筆写
      者であるとしていることに注意して欲しい．このように確率ネットワー
      クを作ることが推奨される．
      </p>
        <p>
	果敢な人は，他の要素や散文的記述を参照し，要素<gi>alt</gi>,
      <gi>join</gi>, <gi>not</gi>などの素性構造向け連結子を使い，
      複雑な確率ネットワークを作ろうとするかもしれない．しかし，当該要
      素<gi>certainty</gi>が，確信度を明瞭に示す包括的な解決策であると
      は，現時点では考えていない．
      </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="degree" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates the degree of confidence assigned to the aspect
of the markup named by the <att>locus</att> attribute.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko"><att>locus</att> 속성에 의해 명명된 마크업에 할당된 신뢰도를 표시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出屬性<att>locus</att>所指定的標記部分之確定程度。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
      属性<att>locus</att>で示された対象のに付与される確信度の程度を示
      す．
      </desc>
      <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">Indique le degré de confiance attribué à l'aspect
          du balisage que désigne l'attribut <att>locus</att>.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el grado de confianza asignado al aspecto del marcaje llamado por el atributo <att>locus</att>
			      </desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il grado di certezza assegnato ad un aspetto della codifica  indicato dall'attributo <att>locus</att>.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.probability"/>
      </datatype>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>(For discussion of this example, see section <ptr target="#CEconcon"/>)</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Ernest went to <anchor xml:id="A1"/> old
<persName xml:id="SYB">Saybrook</persName>.
<certainty xml:id="c1" target="#SYB" locus="name" degree="0.6"/>
			      <certainty target="#SYB" locus="start" given="#c1" degree="0.9"/>
			      <certainty xml:id="C-c2" target="#SYB" locus="name" assertedValue="persName" degree="0.4"/>
			      <certainty target="#SYB" locus="start" given="#C-c2" degree="0.5"/>
			      <certainty target="#SYB" locus="start" assertedValue="#a1" given="#c1" degree="0.5"/>
		    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <p xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">( Pour la discussion sur cet exemple, voir <ptr target="#CECECE"/>)</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Ernest est allé au <anchor xml:id="fr_A1"/> vieux
          <persName xml:id="fr_SYB">Saybrook</persName>.<certainty xml:id="fr_c1" target="#fr_SYB" locus="name" degree="0.6"/>
        <certainty target="#fr_SYB" locus="start" given="#c1" degree="0.9"/>
        <certainty xml:id="fr_C-c2" target="#fr_SYB" locus="name" assertedValue="persName" degree="0.4"/>
        <certainty target="#fr_SYB" locus="start" given="#C-c2" degree="0.5"/>
        <certainty target="#fr_SYB" locus="start" assertedValue="#a1" given="#c1" degree="0.5"/>
      </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      張先生去看<persName xml:id="zh-tw_JZZ">江子翠</persName>那邊有什麼活動。
      <certainty target="#zh-tw_JZZ" locus="name" degree="0.6"/>
         <certainty target="#zh-tw_JZZ" locus="name" assertedValue="placeName" degree="0.4"/>
      </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    王先生找到<anchor xml:id="zh-tw_A1"/>小<persName xml:id="zh-tw_lin">林</persName>，感動極了。
      <certainty xml:id="zh-tw_c1" target="#zh-tw_lin" locus="name" degree="0.8"/>
         <certainty target="#zh-tw_lin" given="#c1" locus="start" degree="0.9"/>      
         <certainty xml:id="zh-tw_c2" target="#zh-tw_lin" locus="name" assertedValue="placeName" degree="0.2"/>
         <certainty target="#zh-tw_lin" given="#c2" locus="start" degree="0.1"/>
         <certainty target="#zh-tw_lin" given="#c2" locus="start" assertedValue="#a1" degree="0.9"/>
      </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CECECE"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
