<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<macroSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" module="tei" type="dt" ident="data.temporal.w3c">
  <desc>defines the range of attribute values expressing a temporal
  expression such as a date, a time, or a combination of them, that
  conform to the W3C <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</title>
  specification. </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">날짜, 시간 또는 이들의 조합과 같은 시간 표현을 나타내는 속성 값 범위를 정의하며, 이는 W3C <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</title> 명시를 따른다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">定義表示時間的屬性值範圍，如日期、時間或兩者的結合，依照W3C<title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</title>specification標準所定義。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  日付や時間などの時間表現をとる属性値の範囲を定義する．これは，W3Cの
  <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</title>に従ったものになる．
 </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">définit la gamme des valeurs d'attributs propre à
      exprimer une valeur temporelle comme une date, une période, ou une combinaison des deux
      conformément aux spécifications <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</title>du W3C.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define la gama de valores de atributos que expresan un valor temporal del tipo fecha, hora, o combinación de ambas, de acuerdo con la especificación de W3C <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes</title>. </desc>
  <content>
    <rng:choice>
      <rng:data type="date"/>
      <rng:data type="gYear"/>
      <rng:data type="gMonth"/>
      <rng:data type="gDay"/>
      <rng:data type="gYearMonth"/>
      <rng:data type="gMonthDay"/>
      <rng:data type="time"/>
      <rng:data type="dateTime"/>
    </rng:choice>
  </content>
  <remarks>
    <p>If it is likely that the value used is to be compared with
    another, then a time zone indicator should always be included, and
    only the dateTime representation should be used.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p>
    当該属性値が他の値と比較される場合，時間帯は必ず示されるべきである．
    またはdateTimeを使うべきである(訳注：この文は修正されるかもしれな
    い)．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>S'il est probable que la valeur utilisée doive être comparée à 
      d’ autres, alors une indication de fuseau horaire sera  toujours être incluse, et 
      seule la représentation de dateTime sera employée.
    </p>
  </remarks>
</macroSpec>
