<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<macroSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  module="tei" type="dt" ident="data.enumerated">
  <desc>defines the range of attribute values expressed as a single XML name taken from a list of
    documented possibilities.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">기록된 확률의 목록으로부터 얻어진 단일 XML 이름으로 표현된 속성 값 범위를 정의한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">定義的屬性值範圍以單字或代號呈現，該單字或代號出自於一份紀錄所有可能性的列表</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 符号化されている記述にある，ひつとのXML名前を示す属性値の範囲を定義する． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">définit la gamme de valeurs d'attributs exprimées, comme
    un mot ou une occurence extraites d'une liste de possibilités documentées</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">define la gama de valores de atributos expresados como
    una única palabra o señal tomada de una lista de posibilidades documentadas.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">definisce la gamma di valori di attributi espressi come
    singola parola o token tratto da una lista di possibilità attestate</desc>
  <content>
    <rng:ref name="data.name"/>
  </content>
  <remarks>
    <p>Attributes using this datatype must contain a word which follows the rules defining a legal
      XML name (see <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#dt-name"/>): for example they cannot
      include whitespace or begin with digits. </p>
    <p>Typically, the list of documented possibilities will be provided (or exemplified) by a value
      list in the associated attribute specification, expressed with a <gi>valList</gi> element.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 当該データ型は，妥当なXML名前 (詳細は<ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#dt-name"/>
      を参照のこと)である単語でなくてはならない．例えば， 属性値として空白文字，または数値で始まる名前をとることはできない． </p>
    <p> 典型例は，可能な記述またはその例のリストが，要素<gi>valList</gi> 中に属性定義として示されている． </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks versionDate="2009-05-25" xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Les attributs utilisant ce type de données doivent contenir un mot qui suit les règles de
      définition d'un nom XML valide (voir <ptr target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#dt-name"/>):
      par exemple ils ne peuvent contenir des blancs ou commencer par des chiffres. </p>
    <p>Normalement, la liste des possiblités documentées est fournie (ou exemplifiée) par une liste
      de valeurs dans la spécification de l'attribut associé, exprimée par un élément
      <gi>valList</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
</macroSpec>
