<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="figures" ident="figDesc">
  <gloss>description of figure</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">그림 기술</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">圖表描述</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">description d'une figure</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">descripción de una figura</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">Descrizione di una figura</gloss>
  <desc>contains a brief prose description of the appearance or content
of a graphic figure, for use when documenting an image without
displaying it.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko"/>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含圖表內容的簡短文字描述，用於紀錄圖像但未呈現圖像的情況。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  図表の内容や現れ方について簡単な散文で解説を示す．当該図表を示さない
  で記録する場合に使用される．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">contient une brève description de l'apparence ou
			du contenu d'une représentation graphique, pour documenter une image sans avoir à
			l'afficher</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una breve descripción de la apariencia o del contenido de una figura gráfica, para utilizarla al documentar una imagen sin mostrarla.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una breve descrizione dell'aspetto o del contenuto di una figura, da utilizzare quando si vuole documentare un'immagine senza mostrarla.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.limitedContent"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <figure>
        <graphic url="emblem1.png"/>
        <head>Emblemi d'Amore</head>
        <figDesc>A pair of  naked winged cupids, each holding a
	flaming torch, in a rural setting.</figDesc>
      </figure>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p/>
    <p>This element is intended for use as an alternative to the
content of its parent <gi>figure</gi> element; for example, to display
when the image is required but the equipment in use cannot display
graphic images. It may also be used for indexing or documentary
purposes.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cet élément est prévu pour être utilisé comme alternative au contenu de son élément
                parent <gi>figure</gi>; par exemple, pour montrer que l'image est exigée mais que
               le matériel en service ne peut pas montrer des documents graphiques. Il peut également
                être employé pour l'indexation ou dans un but documentaire.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p/>
    <p>
    当該要素は，要素<gi>figure</gi>の内容の代わりに使用されるものであ
    る．例えば，当該図表を表示する際に，機器がその表示に対応していない
    場合に使用されるものである．また，索引や記録資料を作成するために使
    用されるかもしれない．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#FTGRA" type="div2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
