<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="header" xml:id="FILDESC" usage="req" ident="fileDesc">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>file description</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">File Description</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">descrizione del file</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">descripción del archivo.</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">ファイル記述</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="zh-tw">檔案描述</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr">description bibliographique du fichier</gloss>
  <desc>contains a full bibliographic description of an electronic
file.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una descrizione bibliografica completa di un file elettronico.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una descripción bibliográfica completa del archivo electrónico.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja"> コンピュータのファイルに関する書誌情報的な内容をま
とめる．</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="zh-tw">包含對電子檔案的完整書目敘述。</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="fr">L'élément Description bibliographique du fichier <gi>filedesc</gi> contient une description bibliographique complète du fichier électronique.</desc>
  <content xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <rng:group>
      <rng:ref name="macro.fileDescPart"/>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="sourceDesc"/>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The major source of information for those seeking to create
a catalogue entry or bibliographic citation for an electronic file. As
such, it provides a title and statements of responsibility together with
details of the publication or distribution of the file, of any series to
which it belongs, and detailed bibliographic notes for matters not
addressed elswhere in the header. It also contains a full bibliographic
description for the source or sources from which the electronic text was
derived.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cet élément est la source principale d'information pour ceux qui souhaitent créer une notice catalographique ou une citation bibliographique pour un fichier électronique. Il fournit le titre et les mentions de responsabilité, ainsi que des infomations sur la publication ou la distribution du fichier, sur  la collection à laquelle il appartient le cas échéant, et des notes détaillées sur des informations qui n'apparaissent pas ailleurs dans l'en-tête. Il contient également une description bibliographique complète de la ou des sources à partir desquelles le texte électronique a été dérivé.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#HD2"/>
    <ptr target="#HD11"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
