<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="msdescription" xml:id="FINALRUBRIC" ident="finalRubric">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">rubrique de fin</gloss>
  <desc xml:id="finalrubric.desc">contains the string of words that denotes the end of a text division, often with an assertion as to its author and title, usually set off from the text itself by red ink, by a different size or type of script, or by some other such visual device.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">종종 저자와 제목에 대한 언급을 하며, 적색의 잉크, 스크립트의 다양한 크기 또는 유형, 또는 어떤 시각적 도구로 표시된 텍스트로 시작되는 텍스트 부분의 끝을 표시하는 단어 열을 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含表示該文字區段結尾的字串，常有作者及標題的聲明，通常使用紅墨水、不同的字型與大小、或用其他不同視覺效果的圖案，來與文件本身作區別。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  テキスト部分の終わりを示す文字列を示す．その著者やタイトルを含むこと
  がある．一般には，テキスト中にある朱書きや，大きさや種類の異なる字体
  など，異なる視覚効果で示されている．
  </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">Contient les derniers mots d'une section de texte,
      qui incluent souvent la mention de son auteur et de son titre, et sont généralement
      différenciés du texte lui-même par l'utilisation d'une encre rouge, par une taille ou un style
      d'écriture particuliers, ou par tout autre moyen visuel.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una serie de palabras que señala el fin de una división textual; a menudo declara el autor y el título, y dicha serie normalmente es evidenciada del resto mediante tinta roja, un estilo distinto o una dimensión distinta de los caracteres, u otro rasgo gráfico visible. </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una stringa di parole che segnala la fine di una partizione testuale e spesso ne dichiara autore e titolo; tale stringa è solitamente evidenziata rispetto al resto tramite inchiostro rosso, diverso stile o diversa dimensione del carattere, o altro espediente grafico</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.msQuoteLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.phraseSeq"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="mul">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <finalRubric>Explicit le romans de la Rose ou l'art 
d'amours est toute enclose.</finalRubric>
      <finalRubric>ok lúkv ver þar Brennu-Nials savgv</finalRubric>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Roman-Rose">
      <finalRubric>Explicit le romans de la Rose ou l'art d'amours est toute enclose.</finalRubric>
      <finalRubric>Ci falt la geste que Turoldus declinet. </finalRubric>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#biblzh-tw_n42">
      <finalRubric>黃幼莘貢俚</finalRubric>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#mscoit"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
