<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="declarefs" xml:id="FSDECL" usage="mwa" ident="fsDecl">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>feature structure declaration</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">dichiarazione della struttura di tratti</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declaración de estructura de rasgo</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">素性構造宣言</gloss>
  <desc>declares one type of feature structure.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">dichiara un tipo di struttura di tratti</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declara un tipo de estructura de rasgo</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja"> 素性システムを宣言する．</desc>
  <content>
    <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:optional>
        <rng:ref name="fsDescr"/>
      </rng:optional>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="fDecl"/>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
      <rng:optional>
        <rng:ref name="fsConstraints"/>
      </rng:optional>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="req">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>gives a name for the type of feature structure being declared.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">fornisce il nome per il tipo di struttura di tratti che si sta dichiarando.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona un nombre para el tipo de estructura de rasgo que está siendo declarada.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該素性構造の種類を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>any convenient string of characters.</valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p/>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="baseTypes" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>gives the name of one or more typed feature structures
	from which this type inherits feature specifications and
	constraints; if this type includes a feature specification
	with the same name as that of any of those specified by this
	attribute, or if more than one specification of the same name
	is inherited, then the set of possible values is defined by
	unification. Similarly, the set of constraints applicable is
	derived by combining those specified explicitly within this
	element with those implied by the <att>baseTypes</att>
	attribute. When no <att>baseType</att> is specified, no
	feature specification or constraint is inherited.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">fornisce il nome ad una o più tipi di strutture di tratti dai quali il tipo eredita le specifiche e i vincoli dei tratti;
        se questo tipo include una specifica di tratti con lo stesso nome specificato da questo attributo, o se più di una specifica dello stesso nome è ereditata, allora l'insieme dei possibili valori è definito
        attraverso l'unificazione. In modo analogo, l'insieme dei vincoli applicabile deriva dalla combinazione di quelli specificati in modo esplicito all'interno dell'elemento con quelli sottintesi dall'attributo <att>baseTypes</att>
        Se nessun <att>baseTypes</att> è specificato, nessuna specificazione o vincolo di tratti è ereditata.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona el nombre de una o más estructura de rasgo dadas, de las cuales este tipo hereda especificaciones de rasgo y restricciones; si este tipo incluye una especificación de rasgo con el mismo nombre que las especificadas por este atributo, o si más de una especificación con el mismo nombre se hereda, entonces el conjunto de posibles valores se definen por la unión de estas. De la misma manera, el conjunto de restricciones aplicable se deriva de la combinación de las restricciones especificadas explícitamente dentro de este elemento con aquellas referidas por el atributo <att>baseTypes</att>. Cuando no se especifica ningún <att>baseType</att>, no se hereda ninguna especificación de rasgo o restricción.</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>one or more names as defined by the <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#dt-name">W3C XML
      Specification</ref></valDesc>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>Inheritance is defined here as a monotonous relation.</p>
        <p>The process of combining constraints
	may result in a contradiction, for example if two
	specifications for the same feature
	specify disjoint ranges of values, and at least one such
	specification is mandatory. In such a case, there is
	no valid representative for the type being defined. </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#FD"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
