<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="gaiji" xml:id="GLYPHNAME" ident="glyphName">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>character glyph name</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">그림문자명</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">字體名稱</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">nom du glyphe d'un caractère</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">nombre del pictograma</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">nome del glifo</gloss>
  <desc>contains the name of a glyph, expressed following Unicode conventions for character names. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">문자명에 대한 유니코드 방식에 따라 표현된 그림 문자명을 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含一字體名稱，其表示法根據統一碼協定 (Unicode)。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> ユニコードに従った文字名で，グリフを示す． </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">contient le nom d'un glyphe, exprimé selon les
    conventions de l'Unicode pour les noms de caractère</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene el nombre de un pictograma, expresado según las
    convenciones Unicode para los nombres de carácteres.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene il nome di un glifo, espresso secondo le
    convenzioni Unicode per i nome dei caratteri.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <text xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="und">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <glyphName>CIRCLED IDEOGRAPH 4EBA</glyphName>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <glyphName>IDEOGRAMME ENCADRE 4EBA</glyphName>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>For characters of non-ideographic scripts, a name following the conventions for Unicode names
      should be chosen. For ideographic scripts, an <term>Ideographic Description Sequence</term>
      (IDS) as described in Chapter 10.1 of the Unicode Standard is recommended where possible.
      Projects working in similar fields are recommended to coordinate and publish their list of
        <gi>glyphName</gi>s to facilitate data exchange.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Le nom du glyphe doit respecter les conventions Unicode pour le nommage des caractères dans
      les écritures non idéographiques. Dans le cas des écritures idéographiques, il est recommandé
      de saisir, si possible, une <term>séquence de description idéographique</term> (SDI) décrite
      dans le chapitre 10.1 du standard Unicode. Il est recommandé, pour les projets portant sur des
      champs similaires, de coordonner et de publier leur liste d'éléments <gi>glyphName</gi> pour
      faciliter l'échange de données.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 非表意文字の場合，ユニコードの名前付与規則に従った名前が選択される べきである．表意文字の場合，ユニコード規格の10.1節にある <term>表意文字記述列(IDS)</term>
      が推奨される．似た分野を扱うプロジェ クト間では，データ交換のために，要素<gi>glyphName</gi>は調整され，公 開されることが勧告されている． </p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
