<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="dictionaries" xml:id="GRAM" usage="opt" ident="gram">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>grammatical information</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">informazioni grammaticali</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">información gramatical</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">文法情報</gloss>
  <desc>within an entry in a dictionary or a terminological data file, contains grammatical
        information relating to a term, word, or form.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">all'interno di una voce in un dizionario o di un file terminologico, contiene informazioni relative a un termine, una parola o una forma.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">dentro de una entrada de un diccionario, o en un archivo de datos terminológicos, contiene información gramatical relativa al término, palabra o forma. </desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja"> 当該項目に関連する文法情報を示す．</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.morphLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.lexicographic"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.paraContent"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>classifies the grammatical information given according to
      some conve
nient typology
                — in the case of terminological information, preferably the dictionary of
                data element types specified in ISO WD 12 620.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">classifies the grammatical information given according to some convenient
                    typology — in the case of terminological information, preferably the dictionary
                    of data element types specified in ISO WD 12 620.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">classifica le informazioni grammaticali secondo un'appropriata tipologia - nel caso di informazioni terminologiche, preferibilmente il dizionario di degli elementi specificati in ISO WD 12 620.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">clasifica la información gramatical dada de acuerdo a una tipología funcional  — en el caso de información terminológica, preferiblemente el diccionario de tipos de elemento de datos se especifica en ISO WD 12 620.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該文法情報の分類を示す．用語を示す場合，ISO WD 12 620に従うこと
が望ましい．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valList type="open">
        <valItem ident="pos">
          <gloss>part of speech</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">part of speech (any of the word classes to which a word may be
                            assigned in a given language, based on form, meaning, or a combination
                            of features, e.g. noun, verb, adjective, etc.)</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">parte del discorso (una qualsiasi delle classi a cui una parola può essere assegnata in una data lingua, basata sulla forma, il significato o una combinazione di tratti, ad esempio nome, verbo, aggettivo, ecc.)</gloss>
          <gloss xml:lang="es">parte del discurso</gloss>
          <desc>any of the word classes to which a word may be
          assigned in a given language, based on form, meaning, or a
          combination of features, e.g. noun, verb, adjective,
          etc.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">indicates the part of speech assigned to a dictionary headword (noun, verb, adjective,
            etc.)</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la parte del discorso assegnata a un lemma (nome, verbo, aggettivo, ecc.)</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">cualquiera de las
          categorías de palabras que se puede encontrar en una lengua
          dada, basándose en la forma, significado, o combinación de
          rasgos, p.ej. nombre, verbo, adjetivo, etc.</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="gen">
          <gloss>gender</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">gender (formal classification by which nouns and pronouns, and often
                            accompanying modifiers, are grouped and inflected, or changed in form,
                            so as to control certain syntactic relationships)</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">genere (classificazione formale secondo cui i nomi e i pronomi, e spesso i modificatori che li accompagnano, sono raggruppati e flessi, o cambiati di forma in modo da controllarne alcune relazioni sintattiche)</gloss>
          <gloss xml:lang="es">género</gloss>
          <desc>formal classification by which nouns and pronouns, and
          often accompanying modifiers, are grouped and inflected, or
          changed in form, so as to control certain syntactic
          relationships</desc>
          <desc version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">identifies the morphological gender of a lexical item, as given in the dictionary.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">identifica il genere morfologico di un'unità lessicale, secondo la modalità del dizionario.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">&gt;clasificación formal para nombres
          y pronombres, y a menudo para modificadores que los
          acompañan, aparecen agrupados y flexionan o cambian de forma
          del mismo modo, y permiten controlar las relaciones
          sintácticas</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="num">
          <gloss>number</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-08-25" xml:lang="it">number (e.g. singular, plural, dual, ...)</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">numero (ad esempio singolare, plurale, duale, ecc.)</gloss>
          <gloss xml:lang="es">número</gloss>
          <desc>grammatical number, e.g. singular, plural, dual, …</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">p.ej. individual, plural, dual, …</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="animate">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>animate or inanimate</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">animado o inanimado</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="proper">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>proper noun or common noun</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">nombre común o nombre propio</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>A much fuller list of values for the <att>type</att> attribute may be generated
                    from the dictionary of data element types under preparation as ISO TC 37/SC 3/WD
                    12 620, Computational Aids in Terminology. See ISO 12 620 for fuller details.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <entry>
        <form>
          <orth>pamplemousse</orth>
        </form>
        <gramGrp>
          <gram type="pos">noun</gram>
          <gram type="gen">masculine</gram>
        </gramGrp>
      </entry>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>In terminological data, the <gi>gram</gi> element usually refers to the most recently
            specified <gi>term</gi> or <gi>otherForm</gi> element. In flat term entries, the
            <att>group</att> and <att>depend</att> attributes may be used to indicate exceptions to
            this general rule. In dictionaries, the element typically relates to the form or forms
            with which it is grouped in a <gi>form</gi> or other grouping element.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#DITPGR" type="div1"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
