<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="textstructure" ident="group">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">groupe</gloss>
  <desc>contains the body of a composite text, grouping together a sequence of distinct texts (or
    groups of such texts) which are regarded as a unit for some purpose, for example the collected
    works of an author, a sequence of prose essays, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">어떤 목적의 단위로 간주되는 일련의 서로 다른 텍스트(또는 그러한 텍스트군)를 모아 놓은 혼합 텍스트의
    본문을 포함한다. 예를 들어, 한 작가의 선집, 일련의 수필 등. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含複合文本的正文，所匯集的一連串單一文件 (或文件群組)
    ，因為某特殊目的被視為一個整體，例如一個作者的作品集合、一連串的散文集等。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> ある単位として独立している個別テキストをまとめた複合テキストを示す． 例えば，ある著者の作品集やエッセイ集など． </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">contient le corps d’un texte composite qui regroupe une
    suite de textes distincts (ou des groupes de textes de ce type), considérés comme formant une
    unité dans un but quelconque, par exemple pour présenter les œuvres complètes d’un auteur, une
    suite d’essais en prose, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-18" xml:lang="de">enthält den Kerntext eines aus mehreren Einzeltexten
    bestehenden Textes, (oder eine Reihe solcher Texte), die zusammen als Einheit gesehen werden,
    zum Beispiel die gesammelten Werke eines Autors, eine Reihe von Prosastücken etc. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene el cuerpo de un texto compuesto, es decir, que
    agrupa un conjunto de textos distintos (o grupos de textos) considerados como una unidad por
    criterios determinados, por ejemplo la obra completa de un autor, una serie de ensayos, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene il corpo di un testo composito, che raggruppa
    cioè un insieme di testi distinti (o più insiemi di testi) considerati come unità per
    determinati scopi, per esempio l'opera completa di un autore, una serie di saggi, ecc.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.declaring"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="model.divTop"/>
          <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>
      <rng:group>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="text"/>
          <rng:ref name="group"/>
        </rng:choice>
        <rng:zeroOrMore>
          <rng:choice>
            <rng:ref name="text"/>
            <rng:ref name="group"/>
            <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
          </rng:choice>
        </rng:zeroOrMore>
      </rng:group>
      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="model.divBottom"/>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible">
      <text>
        <!-- Section on Alexander Pope starts -->
        <front>
          <!-- biographical notice by editor -->
        </front>
        <group>
          <text>
            <!-- first poem -->
          </text>
          <text>
            <!-- second poem -->
          </text>
        </group>
      </text>
      <!-- end of Pope section-->
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#DS"/>
    <ptr target="#DSGRP"/>
    <ptr target="#CCDEF"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
