<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" xml:id="HEAD" usage="rwa" ident="head">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>heading</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">titolo</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">encabezamiento</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">標題</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">表題</gloss>
  <desc>contains any type of heading, for example the title of a section,
or the heading of a list, glossary, manuscript description, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene qualsiasi tipo di titolo, per esempio il titolo di una sezione, di una lista, di un glossario, di una descrizione di manoscritto, ecc.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene cualquier tipo de encabezamiento, por ejemplo el título de una sección o el encabezado de una lista, glosario, descripción de un manuscrito, etc.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">包含任何種類的標題，像是章節名稱、或是列表、詞彙表、手稿等的標題。</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja"> 章・節や，リスト，用語集，手書きもの等の見出し．</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.headLike"/>
    <memberOf key="model.pLike.front"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.paraContent"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>categorizes the heading in any way meaningful 
         to the encoder. </desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">fornisce la categoria del titolo in modo significativo per il codificatore</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">clasifica el encabezamiento de cualquier manera significativa para el codificador.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">標記者可自行用任何方法將標題分類。</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該表題の分類．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>A set of user-defined keywords may be employed. Their
            significance should be documented in the header.
        </valDesc>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <p>The most common use for the <gi>head</gi> element
is to mark the headings of sections.  In older writings, the
headings or <term>incipits</term> may be rather longer than
usual in modern works.	If a section has an explicit ending as
well as a heading, it should be marked as a <gi>trailer</gi>, as
in this example:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div1 n="I" type="book">
        <head>In the name of Christ here begins
the first book of the ecclesiastical history of Georgius
Florentinus, known as Gregory, Bishop of Tours.</head>
        <list>
          <head>Chapter-Headings</head>
        </list>
        <div2 type="section">
          <head>In the name of Christ here begins Book I of the
history.</head>
          <p>Proposing as I do ...</p>
          <p>From the Passion of our Lord until the death of Saint Martin
four hundred and twelve years passed.</p>
          <trailer>Here ends the first Book, which covers five thousand,
 five hundred and ninety-six years from the beginning of the
 world down to the death of Saint Martin.</trailer>
        </div2>
      </div1>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum>
    <p>The <gi>head</gi> tag is also used to mark headings
of other units, such as lists:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">With a few exceptions, connectives are equally useful in
all kinds of discourse:  description, narration, exposition,
argument.
<list type="simple"><head>Connectives</head><item>above</item><item>accordingly</item><item>across from</item><item>adjacent to</item><item>again</item><item><!-- ... --></item></list></egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The <gi>head</gi> element is used for headings at all
levels; software which treats (e.g.) chapter headings,
section headings, and list titles differently must determine the
proper processing of a <gi>head</gi> element based on its
structural position.  A <gi>head</gi> occurring as the first
element of a list is the title of that list; one occurring as
the first element of a <gi>div1</gi> is the title of that
chapter or section.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COLI" type="div2"/>
    <ptr target="#DSDTB" type="div2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
