<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright TEI Consortium. Licensed under the GNU General Public License. See the file COPYING.txt for details $Date$ $Id$ -->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="linking" ident="join">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss version="2009-10-06" xml:lang="fr">jointure</gloss>
  <desc>identifies a possibly fragmented segment of text, by pointing at the possibly discontiguous elements which compose it.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">텍스트를 구성하고 있는 비연소적 요소를 가리킴으로 텍스트의 파편화된 분절을 식별한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標明文本中可能的不完整分割，指向構成此不完整分割的可能不連接元素。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> バラバラにあるテキスト部分を参照し，ひとつのテキスト部分を指定する． </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">identifie un segment de texte, qui peut être fragmenté, en pointant vers les éléments éventuellement dispersés qui le composent.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">identifica un segmento o fragmento de texto señalando eventuales elementos no contiguos que lo componen.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">identifica un segmento o frammento di testo puntando ad eventuali elementi non contigui che lo compongono</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.pointing"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <zeroOrMore xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <ref name="model.glossLike"/>
    </zeroOrMore>
  </content>
  <constraintSpec ident="joinTargets1" scheme="isoschematron">
    <constraint>
      <report xmlns="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" test="@target and @targets">You may not supply both 
	@target and @targets</report>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <constraintSpec ident="joinTargets2" scheme="isoschematron">
    <constraint>
      <report xmlns="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" test="not(@target) and not(@targets)">You must
	supply either @target or @targets</report>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <constraintSpec ident="joinTargets3" scheme="isoschematron">
    <constraint>
      <assert xmlns="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" test="contains(@target,' ')">You must supply at least two
values for @target</assert>
    </constraint>
  </constraintSpec>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="targets" usage="opt" status="deprecated">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>specifies the identifiers of the elements or passages to be joined into a virtual element.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">가상 요소로 결합될 수 있는 요소 또는 단락의 확인소를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標明與一個虛擬元素相連結的元素或段落識別符碼。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 仮想要素へとまとめられる要素または一節の識別子を示す． </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">spécifie les identifiants des éléments ou des passages qui doivent être réunis dans un élément virtuel.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica los identificadores de los elementos o fragmentos de texto a enlazar en un elemento virtual.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica gli identificatori degli elementi o porzioni di testo da collegare in un elemento virtuale</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="2" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>two or more pointers (URIs), separated by whitespace</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr" version="2009-10-05">deux pointeurs ou plus (URI), séparés par des espaces.</valDesc>
      <remarks>
        <p>This attribute is deprecated. It is retained for backward compatibility
only; the attribute <att>target</att> should be used for
preference. It is an error to supply both attributes, but one or the
other must be present.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="result" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>specifies the name of an element which this aggregation may be understood to represent.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">이 집합체의 표상으로 이해될 수 있는 요소의 이름을 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出一個推斷該元素集合所代表的元素名稱。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該要素によりまとめられる要素名を示す． </desc>
      <desc version="2009-10-06" xml:lang="fr">spécifie le nom de l'élément que cette agrégation est censée former.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el nombre del elemento representado por el conjunto de identificadores en cuestión.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il nome dell'elemento rappresentato dall'insieme di identificatori in questione</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>The generic identifier of an element in the current DTD.</valDesc>
      <valDesc xml:lang="fr" version="2009-10-05">L'identificateur générique d'un élément dans le modèle XML utilisé.</valDesc>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="scope" usage="rec">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates whether the targets to be joined include the entire element indicated (the entire subtree including its root), or just the children of the target (the branches of the subtree).</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">결합된 대상이 제시된 전체 요소(그 뿌리를 포함하는 전체 하부수형도) 또는 대상의 자식노드(하부수형도의 가지)의 포함 여부를 제시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出被連結的目標是否包含所指元素的完整部份 (完整樹狀圖包含根節點) ，或僅包含該目標的子元素 (樹狀分支部份) 。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> まとめられる対象が，要素全体(すなわち当該要素をルートとする部分 木全体)，またはその子要素(すなわち部分木の枝)であるかどうかを示 す． </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique si les cibles à réunir incluent l'intégralité de l'élément indiqué (le sous-arbre entier y compris sa racine) ou seulement les enfants de la cible (les branches du sous-arbre).</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica si las metas a enlazar incluyen el elemento entero indicado (el árbol entero con la raíz inclusive) o sólo los elementos que tienen como padre la misma meta (las ramas del árbol).</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica se le destinazioni da collegare includono l'intero elemento indicato (l'intero albero compresa la radice) oppure solo gli elementi che hanno come genitore la stessa destinazione (i rami dell'albero)</desc>
      <defaultVal>root</defaultVal>
      <valList type="closed">
        <valItem ident="root">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>the rooted subtrees indicated by the targets attribute are joined, each subtree become a child of the virtual element created by the join</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">대상 속성에 의해 지시된 한 뿌리에 대한 하부수형도가 결합되고, 각 하부수형도는 결합에 의해 생성된 실제 요소의 자식 노드가 된다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">由屬性target所指明、具根節點的樹狀圖彼此連結，每個樹狀圖成為該連結所產生之虛擬元素的子元素。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">las subárboles arraigados indicados por los atributos targets</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 属性で示された根付き部分木がまとめられ，各部分木は，当該要素 で作られた仮想要素の子となる． </desc>
          <desc version="2009-10-06" xml:lang="fr">les sous-arbres dotés de leur racine qui sont désignés par l'attribut <att>targets</att> sont joints ; chaque sous-arbre devient un fils de l'élément virtuel créé par la jointure. </desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">gli alberi dotati di radice e indicati dall'attributo delle destinazioni sono collegati e ogni albero diventa un discendente dell'elemento virtuale ottenuto dal collegamento</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="branches">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>the children of the subtrees indicated by the targets attribute become the children of the virtual element (i.e. the roots of the subtrees are discarded)</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">대상 속성에 의해 지시된 하부수형도의 자식은 실제 요소의 자식이 된다.(즉, 하부수형도의 뿌리는 없어진다)</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">由屬性target所指明的樹狀圖的子元素成為虛擬元素的子元素 (例如捨去樹狀圖的根節點) 。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">los hijos de los sub-árboles indicados por el atributo de los target se inician con los hijos del elemento virtual (es decir, las raíces de los sub-árboles se desechan)</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 属性で示された部分木の子は，仮想要素の子となる(すなわち，当 該部分木の根は捨てられる． </desc>
          <desc version="2009-10-06" xml:lang="fr">les fils des sous-arbres désignés par l'attribut <att>targets</att> deviennent les fils de l'élément virtuel (c'est-à-dire que les racines des sous-arbres disparaissent).</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">i discendenti degli alberi indicati dall'attributo delle destinazioni diventano i discendenti dell'elemento virtuale (cioè vengono rimosse le radici dei vari alberi)</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>The following example is discussed in section <ptr target="#SAAG"/>:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <sp>
        <speaker>Hughie</speaker>
        <p>How does it go? <q><l xml:id="frog_x1">da-da-da</l><l xml:id="frog_l2">gets a new frog</l><l>...</l></q> 
            </p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker>Louie</speaker>
        <p>
          <q>
            <l xml:id="frog_l1">When the old pond</l>
            <l>...</l>
          </q>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker>Dewey</speaker>
        <p>
          <q>... <l xml:id="frog_l3">It's a new pond.</l> 
               </q>
        </p>
        <join target="#frog_l1 #frog_l2 #frog_l3" result="lg" scope="root"/>
      </sp>
    </egXML>
    <!-- a famous haiku by Bashoo, in an eccentric translation -->
    <p>The <gi>join</gi> element here identifies a linegroup (<gi>lg</gi>) comprising the three lines indicated by the <att>target</att> attribute. The value <code>root</code> for the <att>scope</att> attribute indicates that the resulting virtual element contains the three <gi>l</gi> elements linked to at #frog_l1 #frog_l2 #frog_l3, rather than their character data content.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <p xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">The following example is discussed in section <ptr target="#SAAG"/>:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <sp>
        <speaker>Hughie</speaker>
        <p>How does it go? <q><l xml:id="fr_frog_x1">da-da-da</l><l xml:id="fr_frog_l2">gets a new frog</l><l>...</l></q>
            </p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker>Louie</speaker>
        <p>
          <q>
            <l xml:id="fr_frog_l1">When the old pond</l>
            <l>...</l>
          </q>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker>Dewey</speaker>
        <p>
          <q>... <l xml:id="fr_frog_l3">It's a new pond.</l>
               </q>
        </p>
        <join target="#fr_frog_l1 #fr_frog_l2 #fr_frog_l3" result="lg" scope="root"/>
      </sp>
    </egXML>
    <p xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">The <gi>join</gi> element here identifies a linegroup (<gi>lg</gi>) comprising the three
        lines indicated by the <att>target</att> attribute. The value <code>root</code> for
          the<att>scope</att> attribute indicates that the resulting virtual element contains the
        three <gi>l</gi> elements linked to at #frog_l1 #frog_l2 #frog_l3, rather than their
        character data content.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <p xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">In this example, the attribute <att>scope</att> is specified with the value of
          <code>branches</code> to indicate that the virtual list being constructed is to be made by
        taking the lists indicated by the <att>target</att> attribute of the <gi>join</gi> element,
        discarding the <gi>list</gi> tags which enclose them, and combining the items contained
        within the lists into a single virtual list:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>Southern dialect (my own variety, at least) has only <list xml:id="fr_LP1"><item><s>I done gone</s></item><item><s>I done went</s></item></list> whereas Negro Non-Standard basilect has both these and <list xml:id="fr_LP2"><item><s>I done go</s></item></list>.</p>
      <p>White Southern dialect also has <list xml:id="fr_LP3"><item><s>I've done gone</s></item><item><s>I've done went</s></item></list> which, when they occur in Negro dialect, should probably be considered as
          borrowings from other varieties of English.</p>
      <join result="list" xml:id="fr_LST1" target="#fr_LP1 #fr_LP2 #fr_LP3" scope="branches">
        <desc>Sample sentences in Southern speech</desc>
      </join>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <sp>
        <speaker>休</speaker>
        <p>怎麼樣了？<q><l xml:id="zh-tw_frog_x1">呱、呱、呱</l><l xml:id="zh-tw_frog_l2">有新來的青蛙</l><l>...</l></q> 
            </p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker>路易</speaker>
        <p>
          <q>
            <l xml:id="zh-tw_frog_l1">以前的池塘</l>
            <l>...</l>
          </q>
        </p>
      </sp>
      <sp>
        <speaker>迪威</speaker>
        <p>
          <q>... <l xml:id="zh-tw_frog_l3">有新的池塘</l> 
               </q>
        </p>
        <join target="#zh-tw_frog_l1 #zh-tw_frog_l2 #zh-tw_frog_l3" result="lg" scope="root"/>
      </sp>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>台灣譯為<list xml:id="zh-tw_LP1"><item><s>艾蜜莉的異想世界</s></item></list> ；香港譯作<list xml:id="zh-tw_LP2"><item><s>天使愛美麗</s></item></list>。</p>
      <p>中國大陸則名為<list xml:id="zh-tw_LP3"><item><s>阿梅麗的奇妙命運</s></item></list>。</p>
      <join result="list" xml:id="zh-tw_LST1" target="#zh-tw_LP1 #zh-tw_LP2 #zh-tw_LP3" scope="branches">
        <desc>電影Le Fabuleux Destin d'Amélie Poulain的中港台譯名</desc>
      </join>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>In this example, the attribute <att>scope</att> is specified with the value of <code>branches</code> to indicate that the virtual list being constructed is to be made by taking the lists indicated by the <att>target</att> attribute of the <gi>join</gi> element, discarding the <gi>list</gi> tags which enclose them, and combining the items contained within the lists into a single virtual list:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>Southern dialect (my own variety, at least) has only <list xml:id="LP1"><item><s>I done gone</s></item><item><s>I done went</s></item></list> whereas Negro Non-Standard basilect has both these and <list xml:id="LP2"><item><s>I done go</s></item></list>.</p>
      <p>White Southern dialect also has <list xml:id="LP3"><item><s>I've done gone</s></item><item><s>I've done went</s></item></list> which, when they occur in Negro dialect, should probably be considered as borrowings from other varieties of English.</p>
      <join result="list" xml:id="LST1" target="#LP1 #LP2 #LP3" scope="branches">
        <desc>Sample sentences in Southern speech</desc>
      </join>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#SAAG" type="div2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
