<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright TEI Consortium.
    Licensed under the GNU General Public License.
    See the file COPYING.txt for details
    $Date$
    $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" xml:id="LINEBR" usage="opt"
    ident="lb">
    <equiv/>
    <gloss>line break</gloss>
    <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">행 바꿈</gloss>
    <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">分行</gloss>
    <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
    <gloss version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">saut de ligne</gloss>
    <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">salto de línea</gloss>
    <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">interruzione di riga</gloss>
    <desc>marks the start of a new (typographic) line in some edition or version of a text.</desc>
    <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">텍스트의 편집 또는 버전에서 새로운 (인쇄상의) 행 시작을 표지한다.</desc>
    <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">標記某版本文本裡 (在印刷上) 的新起行。</desc>
    <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> ある版における新しい(印刷上の)行の始まりを示す． </desc>
    <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">marque le début d'une nouvelle ligne (typographique)
        dans une édition ou version donnée d'un texte</desc>
    <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">marca el comienzo de una nueva línea (topográfica) en
        alguna edición o versión del texto.</desc>
    <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">segna l'inizio di una nuova riga (tipografica) in
        qualche edizione o versione di un testo.</desc>
    <classes>
        <memberOf key="model.milestoneLike"/>
        <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
        <rng:empty xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
    </content>
    <attList>
        <attDef ident="ed" usage="rec">
            <gloss>edition</gloss>
            <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">판</gloss>
            <gloss version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">edición</gloss>
            <gloss version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">édition</gloss>
            <gloss version="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">edizione</gloss>
            <desc>indicates the edition or version in which the line break is located at this point</desc>
            <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="kr">이 지점에 행 바꿈 위치 판 또는 버전을 나타낸다.</desc>
            <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-tw">指出該分行位於哪一個版本</desc>
            <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該改行が行われた版を示す． </desc>
            <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">indique l'édition ou la version dans laquelle
                le saut de ligne est localisé à ce point précis</desc>
            <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la edición o la versión del texto en la
                cual el cambio de línea se situa en ese punto. </desc>
            <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica l'edizione o la versione in cui
                l'interruzione di riga è situata in questo punto</desc>
            <datatype>
                <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.code"/>
            </datatype>
            <valDesc>Any string of characters; usually a siglum conventionally used for the
            edition.</valDesc>
        </attDef>
    </attList>
    <exemplum>
        <p>Indicating typographical line breaks within metrical lines, where they occur at different
            places in different editions:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <l>Of Mans First Disobedience,<lb ed="e2"/> and<lb ed="e1"/> the Fruit</l>
            <l>Of that Forbidden Tree, whose<lb ed="e1 e2"/> mortal tast</l>
            <l>Brought Death into the World,<lb ed="e1"/> and all<lb ed="e2"/> our woe,</l>
        </egXML>
    </exemplum>
    <exemplum>
        <p>Indicating line structure of title page, display text, etc.:</p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <docTitle>
                <titlePart type="main">
                    <lb/>THE <lb/>Pilgrim's Progress <lb/>FROM <lb/>THIS WORLD, <lb/>TO <lb/>That
                    which is to come: </titlePart>
                <!-- etc. -->
            </docTitle>
        </egXML>
    </exemplum>
    <remarks>
        <p>By convention, <gi>lb</gi> elements should appear at the point in the text where a new
            line starts. The <att>n</att> attribute, if used, indicates the number or other value
            associated with the text between this point and the next <gi>lb</gi> element, typically
            the sequence number of the line within the page, or other appropriate unit. This element
            is intended to be used for marking actual line breaks on a manuscript or printed page,
            at the point where they occur; it should not be used to tag structural units such as
            lines of verse (for which the <gi>l</gi> element is available) except in circumstances
            where structural units cannot otherwise be marked. </p>
        <p>The <att>type</att> attribute may be used to characterize the linebreak in any respect,
            for example as word-breaking or not. </p>
    </remarks>
    <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>L'attribut global <att>n</att> affecte un nouveau numéro ou une autre valeur à la ligne
            qui suit l'élément <gi>lb</gi>. Les encodeurs doivent faire un choix clair, et s'y
            tenir, entre l'option consistant à se fonder sur la séquence physique des lignes dans la
            page, et celle consistant à se fonder sur un aspect de la structure logique du texte.
            Par convention, l'élément <gi>lb</gi> apparaît au début de la ligne à laquelle il se
            rapporte.</p>
        <p>La balise <gi>lb</gi> sert à faire des retours à la ligne typographiques dans les textes
            en prose. Elle doit être bien distinguée de l'élément <gi>l</gi>, qui est utilisé pour
            baliser des lignes de vers.</p>
    </remarks>
    <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 当該要素にあるグローバル属性<att>n</att>は，要素<gi>lb</gi>に続く 行と関連する数値を示す．符号化する人は，改行を示す当該数値が，ペー
            ジ内にある物理的行数またはテキストの論理構造と関連するかについて， 明確で一貫した方針を採るべきである．
            一般には，要素<gi>lb</gi>は，参照する行の開始地点にあるべきである． </p>
        <p> 要素<gi>lb</gi>は，散文中における印刷上の行を示すためのものである． 韻文中の行を示す要素<gi>l</gi>とは注意して使い分けるべきである． </p>
    </remarks>
    <listRef>
        <ptr target="#CORS5" type="div3"/>
        <ptr target="#DRPAL" type="div3"/>
    </listRef>
</elementSpec>
