<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright TEI Consortium.
    Licensed under the GNU General Public License.
    See the file COPYING.txt for details
    $Date$
    $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="lb">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>line break</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">행 바꿈</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">分行</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">saut de ligne</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">salto de línea</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">interruzione di riga</gloss>
  <desc>marks the start of a new (typographic) line in some edition or version of a text.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">텍스트의 편집 또는 버전에서 새로운 (인쇄상의) 행 시작을 표지한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標記某版本文本裡 (在印刷上) 的新起行。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> ある版における新しい(印刷上の)行の始まりを示す． </desc>
  <desc version="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">marque le début d'une nouvelle ligne (typographique) dans
    une édition ou dans une version d'un texte.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">marca el comienzo de una nueva línea (topográfica) en
    alguna edición o versión del texto.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">segna l'inizio di una nuova riga (tipografica) in qualche
    edizione o versione di un testo.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.milestoneLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.sourced"/>
    <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
    <memberOf key="att.breaking"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:empty xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>This example shows typographical line breaks within metrical lines, where they occur at different
      places in different editions:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <l>Of Mans First Disobedience,<lb ed="1674"/> and<lb ed="1667"/> the Fruit</l>
      <l>Of that Forbidden Tree, whose<lb ed="1667 1674"/> mortal tast</l>
      <l>Brought Death into the World,<lb ed="1667"/> and all<lb ed="1674"/> our woe,</l>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>This example encodes typographical line breaks as a means of
preserving the visual appearance of a title page. The <att>break</att>
attribute is used to show that the line break does not (as elsewhere)
mark the start of a new word.  </p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="fr" corresp="#rab3">
      <titlePart rend="italic"><lb/>L'auteur susdict supplie les Lecteurs
<lb/>benevoles, soy reserver à rire au 
soi-<lb break="no"/>xante &amp; dixhuytiesme livre.
</titlePart>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>By convention, <gi>lb</gi> elements should appear at the point in the text where a new line
      starts. The <att>n</att> attribute, if used, indicates the number or other value associated
      with the text between this point and the next <gi>lb</gi> element, typically the sequence
      number of the line within the page, or other appropriate unit. This element is intended to be
      used for marking actual line breaks on a manuscript or printed page, at the point where they
      occur; it should not be used to tag structural units such as lines of verse (for which the
        <gi>l</gi> element is available) except in circumstances where structural units cannot
      otherwise be marked. </p>
    <p>The <att>type</att> attribute may be used to characterize the
    line break in any respect. The more specialised attributes
    <att>break</att> and <att>ed</att> should be preferred when the
    intent is to indicate whether or not the line
    break is word-breaking, or to note the source from which it
    derives.  </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p> Par convention, l'élément <gi>lb</gi> apparaît à l’endroit du texte où commence une nouvelle
      ligne. L'attribut <att>n</att>, s’il est utilisé, donne un nombre ou une autre valeur associée
      au texte entre ce point et l’élément suivant <gi>lb</gi>, spécifiquement le numéro de la ligne
      dans la page, ou une autre unité de mesure appropriée. Cet élément est prévu pour être employé
      pour marquer un saut de ligne sur un manuscrit ou sur une page imprimée, à l’endroit où il se
      survient; on n’utilisera pas de balisage structurel comme une succession de vers (pour lequel
      l’élément <gi>l</gi> est disponible) sauf dans le cas où des blocs structurés ne peuvent pas
      être marqués autrement. </p>
    <p> L'attribut <att>type</att> sera employé pour caractériser toute espèce de caractéristiques
      du saut de ligne, sauf la coupure des mots (indique par
    l'attribut <att>break</att>) ou la source concernée. </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 当該要素にあるグローバル属性<att>n</att>は，要素<gi>lb</gi>に続く 行と関連する数値を示す．符号化する人は，改行を示す当該数値が，ペー
      ジ内にある物理的行数またはテキストの論理構造と関連するかについて， 明確で一貫した方針を採るべきである． 一般には，要素<gi>lb</gi>は，参照する行の開始地点にあるべきである． </p>
    <p> 要素<gi>lb</gi>は，散文中における印刷上の行を示すためのものである． 韻文中の行を示す要素<gi>l</gi>とは注意して使い分けるべきである． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CORS5" type="div3"/>
    <ptr target="#DRPAL" type="div3"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
