<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
  Copyright TEI Consortium. 
  Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
  See the file COPYING.txt for details
  $Date$
  $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="list">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>list</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr">liste</gloss>
  <desc>contains any sequence of items organized as a list.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">목록의 형태로 정리된 항목을 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含以列表方式呈現的任何連續項目。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> リストのような，項目列を示す． </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">contient une suite d'items ordonnés dans une liste.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene cualquier secuencia de ítems o elementos
    organizados en una lista.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una qualsiasi sequenza di voci organizzate in
    una lista.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.sortable"/>
    <memberOf key="model.listLike"/>
  </classes>
  <!-- 	    <rng:zeroOrMore>
              <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
              </rng:zeroOrMore> -->
  <!-- The removal of this component (and the same one after <headItem> is-->
  <!-- wrong, and breaks the content model. The right thing to do, IMHO,-->
  <!-- is to leave these in, and either-->
  <!-- * improve the ODD -> DTD process so that it does the right thing-->
  <!--   (which would probably be very hard)-->
  <!-- * require the user to fix the content model if & when she removes-->
  <!--   <headItem> or <headLabel>-->
  <!-- I haven't fixed this particular instance yet, because we hope to-->
  <!-- completely revamp the content of <list>, anyway, hopefully-->
  <!-- removing the special-purpose <headItem> and <headLabel>. -Syd -->
  <content>
    <group xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <zeroOrMore>
        <choice>
          <group>
            <ref name="model.divTop"/>
          </group>
          <group>
            <ref name="model.global"/>
          </group>
        </choice>
      </zeroOrMore>
      <choice>
        <oneOrMore>
          <ref name="item"/>
          <zeroOrMore>
            <ref name="model.global"/>
          </zeroOrMore>
        </oneOrMore>
        <group>
          <optional>
            <ref name="headLabel"/>
          </optional>
          <optional>
            <ref name="headItem"/>
          </optional>
          <oneOrMore>
            <ref name="label"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
              <ref name="model.global"/>
            </zeroOrMore>
            <ref name="item"/>
            <zeroOrMore>
              <ref name="model.global"/>
            </zeroOrMore>
          </oneOrMore>
        </group>
      </choice>
      <zeroOrMore>
        <group>
          <group>
            <ref name="model.divBottom"/>
          </group>
          <zeroOrMore>
            <ref name="model.global"/>
          </zeroOrMore>
        </group>
      </zeroOrMore>
    </group>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>describes the form of the list.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">목록의 형식을 기술한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">描述列表的形式。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該リストの形式を示す． </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">décrit la forme de la liste.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">describe la composición de una lista.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">descrive la forma della lista</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>simple</defaultVal>
      <valList type="semi">
        <valItem ident="ordered">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>list items are numbered or lettered. </desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">목록의 각 항목은 숫자순 또는 문자순으로 정렬되어 있다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">列表項目以數字或字母依順序排列。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">los elementos de la lista se numeran (con números
            o letras). </desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> リストの項目は番号付けまたは文字付けされている． </desc>
          <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">le classement des items de la liste est
            alphanumérique</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">le voci della lista sono in ordine numerico o
            alfabetico</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="bulleted">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>list items are marked with a bullet or other typographic device. </desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">목록의 각 항목은 글머리표 또는 부호로 표지되어 있다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">列表項目以黑點或其他印刷符號排列。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">los items de la lista se marcan con ul punto
            negro o con cualquier otro caracter tipográfico. </desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> リスト項目は，中黒または他の印刷可能な印で示されている． </desc>
          <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">les items de la liste sont marqués par une puce
            ou avec un autre signe typographique.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">le voci della lista sono contraddistinte da un
            punto o altro </desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="simple">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>list items are not numbered or bulleted. </desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">목록의 각 항목이 숫자 또는 글머리표로 표지되어 있지 않다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">列表項目的排列沒有用數字或任何其他符號作標記。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">los items de la lista no son numerados o
            punteados. </desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> リスト項目は，番号付けまたは中黒付けがされていない． </desc>
          <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">les items de la liste ne sont pas numérotés ni
            précédés d'une puce.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">le voci della lista sono sono ordinate</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="gloss">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>each list item glosses some term or concept, which is given by a label element
            preceding the list item.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">목록의 각 항목은 선행하는 요소에서 제시된 용어 또는 개념에 대한 설명이다.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">各列表項目為一些字詞或概念下註解，每個項目之前並帶有標籤元素。</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">cada item de la lista glosa algun término o
            concepto de los que han sido dados por un elemento de la lista de la etiqueta que
            precede.</desc>
          <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> リスト項目は，当該リスト項目に先行してあるラベル要素で示され
            たある用語や意義をまとめたものである． </desc>
          <desc version="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">chaque item de la liste commente un terme ou
            concept qui est donné par un élément <gi>label</gi>précédant l'item de la liste.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">ogni voce dell'elenco è la glossa di un termine o
            concetto dato da un elemento legenda che precede la voce stessa</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <remarks>
        <p>The formal syntax of the element declarations allows <gi>label</gi> tags to be omitted
          from lists tagged <tag>list type="gloss"</tag>; this is however a semantic error.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>La syntaxe formelle des déclarations d'élément permet d'omettre les étiquettes de balises
          des listes balisées par <tag>list type="gloss"</tag> mais c'est une erreur sémantique.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 当該要素の宣言では，要素<gi>label</gi>は，タグ<tag>list type="gloss"</tag>中で省略することができることになっているが，
          これは意味上のエラーになる． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <list type="ordered">
        <item>a butcher</item>
        <item>a baker</item>
        <item>a candlestick maker, with <list type="bullets"><item>rings on his fingers</item><item>bells on his toes</item></list>
            </item>
      </list>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Perec-vie">
      <list type="unordered">
        <item>Thé sans sucre et sans lait </item>
        <item>Un jus d'ananas</item>
        <item>Un yaourt</item>
        <item>Trois biscuits de seigle </item>
        <item>Carottes râpées</item>
        <item>Côtelettes d'agneau (deux)</item>
        <item>Courgettes</item>
        <item>Chèvre frais </item>
        <item>Coings</item>
      </list>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Perec-vie">
      <div>
        <p> Selon des critères qui n'appartiennent qu'à lui, Rémi Plassaert a classé ses buvards
            en huit tas respectivement surmontés par :</p>
        <list type="bullets">
          <item>un toréador chantant (dentifrice émail Diamant)</item>
          <item>un tapis d'Orient du XVIIe siècle, provenant d'une basilique de Transylvanie
              (Kalium-Sedaph, soluté de propionate de potassium)</item>
          <item>Le Renard et la Cicogne (sic), gravure de Jean-Baptiste Oudry (Papeteries
              Marquaize, Stencyl, Reprographie)</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Perec-vie">
      <div>
        <p> [...] et tout autour, la longue cohorte de ses personnages, avec leur histoire, leur
            passé, leurs légendes :</p>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item> 1 Pélage vainqueur d'Alkhamah se faisant couronner à Covadonga </item>
          <item> 2 La cantatrice exilée de Russie suivant Schönberg à Amsterdam</item>
          <item> 3 Le petit chat sourd aux yeux vairons vivant au dernier étage</item>
          <item>4 Le crétin chef d'îlot faisant préparer des tonneaux de sable</item>
        </list>
      </div>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <list type="ordered">
        <item>一個屠夫</item>
        <item>一個糕點師父</item>
        <item>一個燭台工人<list type="bullets"><item>手上戴了戒指</item><item>腳趾上有鈴鐺</item></list>
            </item>
      </list>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#biblzh-tw_n11">
      <div1 type="section">
        <head>青年守則</head>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item n="1">守則一至五條包括八德：<list type="ordered"><item n="1.1">一、忠勇為愛國之本 。</item><item n="1.2">二、服從為負責之本。</item><item n="1.3">三、孝順為齊家之本。</item><item n="1.4">四、勤儉為服務之本。</item><item n="1.5">五、仁愛為接物之本。</item></list>
               </item>
          <item n="2">六至九條意指四維：<list type="ordered"><item n="2.1">六、整潔為強身之本。</item><item n="2.2">七、信義為立業之本。</item><item n="2.3">八、助人為快樂之本。</item><item n="2.4">九、和平為處世之本</item></list>
               </item>
          <item n="3">十至十二條就是三達德：<list type="ordered"><item n="3.1">十、學問為濟世之本。</item><item n="3.2">十一、禮節為治事之本。</item><item n="3.3">十二、有恆為成功之本。</item></list>
               </item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#biblzh-tw_n12">
      <p>我們二人謹定于2008年7月3日正午十二時，在台北舉行結婚典禮，寫下海誓山盟，終身遵守，在婚姻路上，共同經營，災難病情，互相扶持，永不分離。并就下列事項，立下承諾，即令滄海化為桑田，桑田再變為滄海，也要攜手共進，相親相愛，直到白頭。<list type="simple"><item>我們宣誓：從結婚這一天開始，不但成為夫妻，互相敬愛，分擔對方的快樂和憂愁，也同時成為朋友，而且是諍友，互相勉勵，互相規勸，互相批評。</item><item>我們領悟：愉快的共同生活，全靠心靈溝通，所以，我們一定善用言語，不僅表達愛心、關心，也使彼此藉語言加深了解，一起成長。絕不粗聲叱責，絕不用肢體代替言語，絕不允許發生婚姻暴力。 </item><item>我們認知：家庭與事業是夫妻共同經營的果實，夫妻對家庭的貢獻等值，在家庭內或社會上，價值完全相同，社會工作薪俸無論多少，家務工作的薪俸都與其相同。</item><item>我們同意：將來我們有子女，管教上如果有不同的意見，甚至尖銳對立的意見，一定要克制自己，去請教專家，絕不把孩子當成實現自己希望的工具，也絕不用孩子來炫耀自己。 </item><item>我們認為：一夫一妻制，是社會安定的磐石，是孩子們成長最安全的溫床，我們喜愛并尊重這種制度，并用事實和行動，維護它的尊嚴。</item><item>我們警惕：婚姻生活并不多彩多姿，它不但平凡，而且瑣碎，如果不滋養珍惜，容易使生命憔悴，心靈粗俗，所以生活之中，我們一定保持適度的假期，與孩子一起長大。</item><item>我們謹記：我們孝敬自己的父母，也孝敬對方的父母，不僅是回報養育之恩，也是培養自己人格的完整，為我們的下一代立下榜樣。 </item><item>我們了解：我們將來會老，所以，我們從結婚這一天，就培養專業之外的其它藝朮興趣，如書、畫、音樂，使我們生命永遠充實燦爛。 </item></list>
         </p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <p>The following example treats the short numbered clauses of Anglo-Saxon legal codes as lists
      of items. The text is from an ordinance of King Athelstan (924–939):</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div1 type="section">
        <head>Athelstan's Ordinance</head>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item n="1">Concerning thieves. First, that no thief is to be spared who is caught with
            the stolen goods, [if he is] over twelve years and [if the value of the goods is] over
            eightpence. <list type="ordered"><item n="1.1">And if anyone does spare one, he is to pay for the thief with his
                wergild — and the thief is to be no nearer a settlement on that account — or to
                clear himself by an oath of that amount.</item><item n="1.2">If, however, he [the thief] wishes to defend himself or to escape, he is
                not to be spared [whether younger or older than twelve].</item><item n="1.3">If a thief is put into prison, he is to be in prison 40 days, and he may
                then be redeemed with 120 shillings; and the kindred are to stand surety for him
                that he will desist for ever.</item><item n="1.4">And if he steals after that, they are to pay for him with his wergild,
                or to bring him back there.</item><item n="1.5">And if he steals after that, they are to pay for him with his wergild,
                whether to the king or to him to whom it rightly belongs; and everyone of those who
                supported him is to pay 120 shillings to the king as a fine.</item></list>
               </item>
          <item n="2">Concerning lordless men. And we pronounced about these lordless men, from whom
            no justice can be obtained, that one should order their kindred to fetch back such a
            person to justice and to find him a lord in public meeting. <list type="ordered"><item n="2.1">And if they then will not, or cannot, produce him on that appointed day,
                he is then to be a fugitive afterwards, and he who encounters him is to strike him
                down as a thief.</item><item n="2.2">And he who harbours him after that, is to pay for him with his wergild
                or to clear himself by an oath of that amount.</item></list>
               </item>
          <item n="3">Concerning the refusal of justice. The lord who refuses justice and upholds
            his guilty man, so that the king is appealed to, is to repay the value of the goods and
            120 shillings to the king; and he who appeals to the king before he demands justice as
            often as he ought, is to pay the same fine as the other would have done, if he had
            refused him justice. <list type="ordered"><item n="3.1">And the lord who is an accessory to a theft by his slave, and it becomes
                known about him, is to forfeit the slave and be liable to his wergild on the first
                occasionp if he does it more often, he is to be liable to pay all that he owns.</item><item n="3.2">And likewise any of the king's treasurers or of our reeves, who has been
                an accessory of thieves who have committed theft, is to liable to the same.</item></list>
               </item>
          <item n="4">Concerning treachery to a lord. And we have pronounced concerning treachery to
            a lord, that he [who is accused] is to forfeit his life if he cannot deny it or is
            afterwards convicted at the three-fold ordeal.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </egXML>
    <p>Note that nested lists have been used so the tagging mirrors the structure indicated by the
      two-level numbering of the clauses. The clauses could have been treated as a one-level list
      with irregular numbering, if desired.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>These decrees, most blessed Pope Hadrian, we propounded in the public council ... and they
        confirmed them in our hand in your stead with the sign of the Holy Cross, and afterwards
        inscribed with a careful pen on the paper of this page, affixing thus the sign of the Holy
        Cross. <list type="simple"><item>I, Eanbald, by the grace of God archbishop of the holy church of York, have
            subscribed to the pious and catholic validity of this document with the sign of the Holy
            Cross.</item><item>I, Ælfwold, king of the people across the Humber, consenting have subscribed with
            the sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Tilberht, prelate of the church of Hexham, rejoicing have subscribed with the
            sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Higbald, bishop of the church of Lindisfarne, obeying have subscribed with the
            sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Ethelbert, bishop of Candida Casa, suppliant, have subscribed with thef sign of
            the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Ealdwulf, bishop of the church of Mayo, have subscribed with devout will.</item><item>I, Æthelwine, bishop, have subscribed through delegates.</item><item>I, Sicga, patrician, have subscribed with serene mind with the sign of the Holy
            Cross.</item></list>
         </p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p rend="dataDesc">May contain an optional heading followed by a series of items, or a series of
      label and item pairs, the latter being optionally preceded by one or two specialized
    headings.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p rend="dataDesc">Peut contenir un titre facultatif suivi d'une succession d'items ou d'une
      succession de couples constitués d'une étiquette et d'un item, ce dernier type pouvant être
      précédé par un ou deux titres spécifiques.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p rend="dataDesc"> 一連の項目またはラベルと項目の組の前に，選択的にヘダーをとることが ある．一連のラベルと項目の組の場合，選択的に，ひとつ以上のヘダーが
      先行することがある． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COLI" type="div2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
