<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" xml:id="LIST" usage="rwa" ident="list">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss/>
  <desc>contains any sequence of items organized as a list.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene cualquier secuencia de ítems o elementos organizados en una lista.</desc>
  <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">包含以列表方式呈現的任何連續項目。</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">リスト構造のような，一連の項目を持つもの．</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.listLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
    <rng:group>
      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:group>
            <rng:ref name="model.divTop"/>
          </rng:group>
          <rng:group>
            <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
          </rng:group>
        </rng:choice>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>
      <rng:choice>
        <rng:oneOrMore>
          <rng:ref name="item"/>
          <rng:zeroOrMore>
            <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
          </rng:zeroOrMore>
        </rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:group>
          <rng:optional>
            <rng:ref name="headLabel"/>
<!-- 	    <rng:zeroOrMore>
	      <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
	    </rng:zeroOrMore> -->
<!-- The removal of this component (and the same one after <headItem> is-->
<!-- wrong, and breaks the content model. The right thing to do, IMHO,-->
<!-- is to leave these in, and either-->
<!-- * improve the ODD -> DTD process so that it does the right thing-->
<!--   (which would probably be very hard)-->
<!-- * require the user to fix the content model if & when she removes-->
<!--   <headItem> or <headLabel>-->
<!-- I haven't fixed this particular instance yet, because we hope to-->
<!-- completely revamp the content of <list>, anyway, hopefully-->
<!-- removing the special-purpose <headItem> and <headLabel>. -Syd -->
          </rng:optional>
          <rng:optional>
            <rng:ref name="headItem"/>
<!--	    <rng:zeroOrMore>
	      <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
	    </rng:zeroOrMore> -->
          </rng:optional>
          <rng:oneOrMore>
            <rng:ref name="label"/>
            <rng:zeroOrMore>
              <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
            </rng:zeroOrMore>
            <rng:ref name="item"/>
            <rng:zeroOrMore>
              <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
            </rng:zeroOrMore>
          </rng:oneOrMore>
        </rng:group>
      </rng:choice>
      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:group>
	  <rng:group>
	    <rng:ref name="model.divBottom"/>
	  </rng:group>
          <rng:zeroOrMore>
            <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
          </rng:zeroOrMore>
        </rng:group>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="opt">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>describes the form of the list.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">describe la composición de una lista.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">描述列表的形式。</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該リストの形を示す．</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>simple</defaultVal>
      <valList type="semi">
        <valItem ident="ordered">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>list items are numbered or lettered.
    </desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">ítems de lista numerados.</desc>
          <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">列表項目以數字或字母依順序排列。</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="bulleted">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>list items are marked with a
bullet or other typographic device.
    </desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">los ítems de la lista están marcados con un punto u otro recurso tipográfico.</desc>
          <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">列表項目以黑點或其他印刷符號排列。</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="simple">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>list items are not numbered or bulleted.
    </desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">los ítems de la lista no están ni numerados ni introducidos por un recurso tipográfico.</desc>
          <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">列表項目的排列沒有用數字或任何其他符號作標記。</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="gloss">
          <equiv/>
          <desc>each list item glosses some term or
concept, which is given by a label element preceding
the list item.</desc>
          <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">cada ítem de la lista glosa algún término o concepto que ha sido dado por un elemento que precede la lista.</desc>
          <desc version="2006-06-05" xml:lang="zh-tw">各列表項目為一個字詞下註解，每個項目之前並帶有標籤元素。</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>The formal syntax of the element declarations allows
<gi>label</gi> tags to be omitted from lists tagged <tag>list
type="gloss"</tag>; this is however a semantic error.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <list type="ordered">
        <item>a butcher</item>
        <item>a baker</item>
        <item>a candlestick maker, with
<list type="bullets"><item>rings on his fingers</item><item>bells on his toes</item></list>
   </item>
      </list>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum>
    <p>The following example treats the short numbered clauses of
Anglo-Saxon legal codes as lists of items.  The text is from an
ordinance of King Athelstan (924–939):</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <div1 type="section">
        <head>Athelstan's Ordinance</head>
        <list type="ordered">
          <item n="1">Concerning thieves.  First, that no thief is to be
     spared who is caught with the stolen goods, [if he is] over
     twelve years and [if the value of the goods is] over eightpence.
    <list type="ordered"><item n="1.1">And if anyone does spare one, he is to pay for the
      thief with his wergild — and the thief is to be no nearer a
      settlement on that account — or to clear himself by an oath of
      that amount.</item><item n="1.2">If, however, he [the thief] wishes to defend himself
      or to escape, he is not to be spared [whether younger or older
      than twelve].</item><item n="1.3">If a thief is put into prison, he is to be in prison
      40 days, and he may then be redeemed with 120 shillings; and the
      kindred are to stand surety for him that he will desist for ever.</item><item n="1.4">And if he steals after that, they are to pay for him
      with his wergild, or to bring him back there.</item><item n="1.5">And if he steals after that, they are to pay
      for him with his wergild, whether to the king or to him
      to whom it rightly belongs; and everyone of those who
      supported  him is to pay 120 shillings to  the king as a fine.</item></list></item>
          <item n="2">Concerning lordless men.  And we pronounced about these
   lordless men, from whom no justice can be obtained, that one
   should order their kindred to fetch back such a person to justice
   and to find him a lord in public meeting.
   <list type="ordered"><item n="2.1">And if they then will not, or cannot, produce him on
      that appointed day, he is then to be a fugitive afterwards, and
      he who encounters him is to strike him down as a thief.</item><item n="2.2">And he who harbours him after that, is to pay for him
      with his wergild or to clear himself by an oath of that amount.</item></list></item>
          <item n="3">Concerning the refusal of justice.  The lord who
    refuses justice and upholds his guilty man, so that the king is
    appealed to, is to repay the value of the goods and 120 shillings
    to the king; and he who appeals to the king before he demands
    justice as often as he ought, is to pay the same fine as the
    other would have done, if he had refused him justice.
    <list type="ordered"><item n="3.1">And the lord who is an accessory to a theft by his
      slave, and it becomes known about him, is to forfeit the slave
      and be liable to his wergild on the first occasionp if he does it
      more often, he is to be liable to pay all that he owns.</item><item n="3.2">And likewise any of the king's treasurers or of our
      reeves, who has been an accessory of thieves who have committed
      theft, is to liable to the same.</item></list></item>
          <item n="4">Concerning treachery to a lord.  And we have pronounced
   concerning treachery to a lord, that he [who is accused] is to
   forfeit his life if he cannot deny it or is afterwards convicted
   at the three-fold ordeal.</item>
        </list>
      </div1>
    </egXML>
    <p>Note that nested lists have been used so the tagging mirrors the
structure indicated by the two-level numbering of the clauses.
The clauses could have been treated as a one-level list with
irregular numbering, if desired.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p>These decrees, most blessed Pope Hadrian, we propounded in the
public council ... and they confirmed them in our hand in your
stead with the sign of the Holy Cross, and afterwards inscribed
with a careful pen on the paper of this page, affixing thus the
sign of the Holy Cross.
<list type="simple"><item>I, Eanbald, by the grace of God archbishop of the holy
church of York, have subscribed to the pious and catholic
validity of this document with the sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Ælfwold, king of the people across the Humber,
consenting have subscribed with the sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Tilberht, prelate of the church of Hexham, rejoicing
have subscribed with the sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Higbald, bishop of the church of Lindisfarne, obeying
have subscribed with the sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Ethelbert, bishop of Candida Casa, suppliant, have
subscribed with thef sign of the Holy Cross.</item><item>I, Ealdwulf, bishop of the church of Mayo, have subscribed
with devout will.</item><item>I, Æthelwine, bishop, have subscribed through
delegates.</item><item>I, Sicga, patrician, have subscribed with serene mind
with the sign of the Holy Cross.</item></list>
</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p rend="dataDesc">May contain an optional heading followed by a series of
items, or a series of label and item pairs, the latter being optionally
preceded by one or two specialized headings.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COLI" type="div2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
