<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="verse" xml:id="METDECL" usage="rec" ident="metDecl">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>metrical notation declaration</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="zh-tw">韻律宣告</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr">déclaration métrique</gloss>
  <desc>documents the notation employed to represent a metrical
  pattern when this is specified as the value of a <att>met</att>,
  <att>real</att>, or <att>rhyme</att> attribute on any structural
  element of a metrical text (e.g. <gi>lg</gi>, <gi>l</gi>, or
  <gi>seg</gi>).</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">documenta l'annotazione adottata nella rappresentazione di uno schema metrico, specificato come valore di un attributo <att>met</att>, <att>real</att>, o <att>rhyme</att> su un qualsiasi elemento strutturale di un testo metrico (ad esempio <gi>lg</gi>, <gi>l</gi>, or <gi>seg</gi>).</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">documenta la notación empleada para representar un patrón métrico cuando éste se especifica como el valor de un atributo <att>met</att>, <att>real</att>, o <att>rhyme</att> en cualquier elemento estructural de un texto métrico (p.ej. <gi>lg</gi>, <gi>l</gi>, or <gi>seg</gi>).</desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">韻律パタンの表記法を示す．</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="zh-tw">在標記韻文所用到的結構性元素(例：<gi>行組</gi>、<gi>詩行</gi>、或
    <gi>強制分割</gi>)當中使用<att>格律</att>、<att>實行</att>、或
    <att>押韻</att>等屬性，來表示文章的韻律模式時，則在此解釋該屬性屬性
    值標記韻律模式的方法。</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="fr"> L’élément Déclaration métrique <gi>metDecl</gi>
  décrit la méthode employée pour noter un modèle métrique lorsque
  celui-ci est spécifié par les attributs <att>met </att>,
  <att>real</att>, ou <att>rhyme</att>, qui s’appliquent à tout
  élément de la structure d’un texte versifié (par exemple
  <gi>lg</gi>, <gi>l</gi>, ou <gi>seg</gi>).</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.encodingPart"/>
    <memberOf key="att.declarable"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:choice xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="model.pLike"/>
          <rng:ref name="model.noteLike"/>
        </rng:choice>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="metSym"/>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
    </rng:choice>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="type" usage="mwa">
      <equiv/>
      <desc>indicates whether the notation conveys the abstract
      metrical form, its actual prosodic realization, or the rhyme
      scheme, or some combination thereof.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica se l'annotazione fornisce la forma metrica estratta, la sua realizzazione prosodica,lo schema delle rime o un loro combinazione</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica si la notación indica la forma métrica abstracta, su realización prosódica real,  el esquema rítmico o alguna combinación de todo ello.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該表記法が，抽象的韻律
      形式，実際に出現する韻律形，押韻規則，これらの組み合わせなのかを
      示す．</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="fr">indique si la notation traduit la forme
      métrique abstraite, sa réalisation prosodique, le schéma de
      rime, ou une combinaison de ces différents éléments.</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="3">
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>met real</defaultVal>
      <valList>
        <valItem ident="met">
          <gloss><att>met</att> attribute</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">atributo <att>met</att></gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-06-14" xml:lang="es"><att>rhyme</att> attribute</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">atributo <att>rhyme (rima)</att></gloss>
          <desc>declaration applies to the abstract metrical form
	  recorded on the <att>met</att> attribute</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="real">
          <gloss><att>real</att> attribute</gloss>
          <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">atributo <att>real</att></gloss>
          <desc>declaration applies to the actual realization of the
	  conventional metrical structure recorded on the
	  <att>real</att> attribute</desc>
        </valItem>
        <valItem ident="rhyme">
          <gloss><att>rhyme</att> attribute</gloss>
          <desc>declaration applies to the rhyme scheme
	  recorded on the <att>rhyme</att> attribute</desc>
        </valItem>
      </valList>
      <exemplum>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>By default, the <gi>metDecl</gi> element documents the
        notation used for metrical pattern and realization. It may
        also be used to document the notation used for rhyme scheme
        information; if not otherwise documented, the rhyme scheme
        notation defaults to the traditional <q>abab</q> notation.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Par défaut, l'élément <gi>metDecl</gi> documente la notation utilisée pour le modèle métrique et sa réalisation. Il peut aussi être utilisé pour la notation du schéma de rime ; s'il n'est pas documenté d'une autre manière, la notation du schéma de rime pourra l'être par défaut sous la forme traditionnelle <q>abab</q>.
        </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="pattern" usage="opt">
      <gloss>regular expression pattern</gloss>
      <desc>specifies a regular expression defining any value that
	is legal for this notation.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica un'espressione regolare che definisce qualsiasi valore legale per l'annotazione</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica una expresión regular que define cualquier valor válido para esta notación.</desc>
      <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">当該表記法に叶う値を正規表現で示す．</desc>
      <desc xml:lang="fr">indique une expression régulière définissant toute valeur permise dans cette notation.</desc>
      <datatype>
        <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pattern"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>the value must be a valid regular expression per the
      World Wide Web Consortium's <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes
      Second Edition</title>, <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/#regexs">Appendix
      F</ref></valDesc>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <metDecl xml:id="ip" type="met" pattern="((SU|US)USUSUSUS/)">
        <metSym value="S">stressed syllable</metSym>
        <metSym value="U">unstressed syllable</metSym>
        <metSym value="/">metrical line boundary</metSym>
      </metDecl>
    </egXML>
    <p>This example is intended for the far more restricted case
    typified by the Shakespearean iambic pentameter. Only metrical
    patterns containing exactly ten syllables, alternately stressed
    and unstressed, (except for the first two which may be in either
    order) to each metrical line can be expressed using this
    notation.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <metDecl xml:id="ip-fr" pattern="((SU|US)USUSUSUS/)">
        <metSym value="S">syllabe accentuée</metSym>
        <metSym value="U">syllabe non accentuée</metSym>
        <metSym value="/">frontière de vers métrique</metSym>
      </metDecl>
    </egXML>
    <p>Cet exemple s'entend dans un cas beaucoup plus restreint dont l'exemple typique est le pentamètre iambique shakespearien. Seuls les modèles métriques contenant exactement dix syllabes, alternativement accentuées ou non accentuées, (à l'exception des deux premières qui peuvent être l'une ou l'autre) à chaque vers peuvent être exprimés en utilisant cette notation.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p rend="dataDesc">The encoder may choose whether to define the
    notation formally or informally. However, the two methods may not
    be mixed. That is, <gi>metDecl</gi> may contain either a sequence
    of <gi>metSym</gi> elements or, alternately, a series of
    paragraphs or other components. If the <att>pattern</att>
    attribute is specified and <gi>metSym</gi> elements are used, then
    all the codes appearing within the <att>pattern</att> attribute
    should be documented.</p>
    <p>Only usable within the header if the verse module is used.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p rend="dataDesc">contient ou une suite d'éléments <gi>metSym</gi> ou des paragraphes. Si un seul élément <gi>metSym</gi> est défini, tous les codes apparaissant dans l'attribut <att>pattern</att> doivent être documentés, si ce dernier est renseigné.</p>
    <p>L'encodeur peut choisir de définir la notation formellement ou non. Toutefois, les deux méthodes ne peuvent être combinées.</p>
    <p>Ne peut être utilisé dans l'en-tête que si le jeu d'éléments pour la poésie est activé.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#HDMN"/>
    <ptr target="#VEME"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
