<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="milestone">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">balise de bornage</gloss>
  <desc>marks a boundary point separating any kind of section of a text, typically but not
    necessarily indicating a point at which some part of a standard reference system changes, where
    the change is not represented by a structural element.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">텍스트의 절을 분할하는 경계점을 표지한다. 이는 표준 참조 시스템에서의 변화로 표시되며, 구조적 요소에
    의해서는 표시되지 않는다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">標明文本中由標準參照系統變更所指示的任何區塊分界點，並且該章節未以任何結構性元素標記。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 当該セクションが，構造要素により表現することができない場合に，標準的
    な参照機能により，テキストの各種セクション間にある境界点を示す． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2009-01-06" xml:lang="fr">marque un point séparant n'importe quelle section d'un
    texte qui indique, habituellement mais pas nécessairement, un endroit à partir duquel une
    certaine partie d'un système standard de référence change et que ce changement n'est pas
    représenté par un élément structurel.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">marca un punto de frontera que separa cada tipo de
    sección de un texto, indicado por cambios en el sistema de referencia estándard, donde la
    sección no es representada por un elemento estructural.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">segnala il limite che separa ogni tipo di sezione di un
    testo, come indicato da cambiamenti nel sistema di riferimento standard, qualora la sezione non
    sia rappresentata da un elemento strutturale.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.milestoneLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.milestoneUnit"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.edition"/>
    <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
    <memberOf key="att.breaking"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <empty xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
<!-- MDH 2012-07-15: Attribute @unit moved to att.milestoneUnit; milestone and refState are now members of 
     that attribute class. This centralizes the definition of the attribute and its suggested values. 
     SF ticket http://purl.org/tei/bugs/3537452. -->
  
  <exemplum xml:lang="mul">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><milestone n="23" ed="La" unit="Dreissiger"/>
      ... <milestone n="24" ed="AV" unit="verse"/> ...</egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><milestone n="23" ed="La" unit="Dreissiger"/> ... <milestone n="24" ed="AV" unit="verse"/>
        ...</egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><milestone n="23" ed="拉丁文版本" unit="三十"/> ...
        <milestone n="24" ed="聖經欽定版本" unit="韻文"/> ...</egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>For this element, the global <att>n</att> attribute indicates the new number or other value
      for the unit which changes at this milestone. The special value
      <mentioned>unnumbered</mentioned> should be used in passages which fall outside the normal
      numbering scheme, such as chapter or other headings, poem numbers or titles, etc.</p>
    <p>The order in which milestone elements are given at a given point is not normally significant.
      <!--Milestones for page and column should precede
milestones for line numbers. -->
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Pour cet élément, l'attribut global <att>n</att> affecte un nouveau numéro ou une autre
      valeur à l'unité qui change à partir de l'élément <gi>milestone</gi>. La valeur
        <mentioned>unnumbered</mentioned> doit être utilisée pour les passages qui sortent du
      système normal de numérotation (par ex. titres de chapitres, numéros ou titres de poèmes, ou
      noms des personnages qui prennent la parole dans une pièce de théâtre).</p>
    <p>L'ordre dans lequel apparaissent les éléments <gi>milestone</gi> à un endroit donné n'est en
      principe pas signifiant.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 当該要素にあるグローバル属性<att>n</att>は，当該標石要素が示す変化 の単位の，他の値を示す．特別な値<mentioned>unnumbered</mentioned>
      は，一般的な番号付けスキームから外れている一節中で使用されるべきで ある(例えば，章見出し，詩の番号やタイトル，詩劇における話し手の属 性など)． </p>
    <p> 標石要素の順番は，一般には重要ではない．
      <!--Milestones for page and column should precede milestones for
    line numbers. -->
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#CORS5" type="div3"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
