<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<classSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tei" xml:id="PHRASE" type="model"
  ident="model.phrase">
  <desc>groups elements which can occur at the level of individual words or phrases.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">개별 단어 또는 구 층위에서 나타날 수 있는 요소를 모아 놓는다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">匯集的元素可出現於個人字詞層次上。 </desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 独立した語句レベルに出現する要素をまとめる． </desc>
  <desc version="2009-10-06" xml:lang="fr">regroupe des éléments qui apparaissent au niveau de
    mots isolés ou de groupes de mots.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">agrupa los elementos que pueden aparecer en el nivel de
    palabras o sintagmas.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">raggruppa gli elementi che appaiono a livello di singole
    parole o sintagmi</desc>
  <remarks>
    <p>This class of elements can occur only within larger elements of the class <term>inter</term>
      or <term>chunk</term>. In prose, this means these elements can occur within paragraphs, list
      items, lines of verse, etc.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cette classe d'éléments ne peut se trouver qu'à l'intérieur d'éléments plus vastes de la
      classe intermédiaire (<term>inter</term>) ou fragment (<term>chunk</term>). Pour les textes en
      prose, cela signifie que ces éléments peuvent se trouver dans des paragraphes, des entrées de
      listes, des vers, etc.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Esta clase de elementos puede darse solamente dentro de elementos más grandes de la clase
        <term>inter</term> o <term>fragmento</term>. En prosa significa que estos elementos pueden
      aparecer dentro de párrafos, en los elementos de una lista, en las líneas de verso, etc.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 当該要素クラスは，クラス<term>inter</term>にある大きめの要素，すな わち<term>塊</term>の中で出現可能である．散文においては，当該要素
      は，段落，リスト項目，韻文行などの中で出現可能である． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#STEC"/>
  </listRef>
</classSpec>
