<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- © TEI Consortium. Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licenses; see the file COPYING.txt for details. -->
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="namesdates" ident="object">
  <desc versionDate="2018-07-15" xml:lang="en">contains a description of a single identifiable physical object.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2019-01-22" xml:lang="de">enthält die Beschreibung eines einzelnen identifizierbaren physischen Objekts.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="att.sortable"/>
    <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
    <memberOf key="att.declaring"/>
    <memberOf key="att.docStatus"/>
    <memberOf key="att.canonical"/>
    <memberOf key="model.objectLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <sequence>
      <elementRef key="objectIdentifier" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
      <classRef key="model.headLike" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
      <!--
          The desired content model for the following is
            ( pLike | ( msContents? & physDesc? & history? & additional? ) )
          but of course we can't use interleave, as DTDs (and maybe XSD)
          will not support that. See https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2214.
        -->
      <alternate>
        <classRef key="model.pLike" minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
        <!-- Cannot use maxOccurs=4 because resulting content model is ambiguous -->
        <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
          <elementRef key="msContents"/>
          <elementRef key="physDesc"/>
          <elementRef key="history"/>
          <elementRef key="additional"/>
        </alternate>
      </alternate>
      <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <classRef key="model.noteLike"/>
        <classRef key="model.biblLike"/>
        <elementRef key="linkGrp"/>
        <elementRef key="link"/>
      </alternate>
      <elementRef key="object" minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded"/>
    </sequence>
  </content>
    <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <listObject>
        <object xml:id="Alfred_Jewel">
          <objectIdentifier>
            <country>United Kingdom</country>
            <region>Oxfordshire</region>
            <settlement>Oxford</settlement>
            <institution>University of Oxford</institution>
            <repository>Ashmolean Museum</repository>
            <collection>English Treasures</collection>
            <idno type="ashmolean">AN1836p.135.371</idno>
            <idno type="wikipedia">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alfred_Jewel</idno>
            <objectName>Alfred Jewel</objectName>
          </objectIdentifier>
          <physDesc>
            <p> The Alfred Jewel is about 6.4 cm in length and is made of combination of filigreed <material>gold</material>
              surrounding a polished teardrop shaped piece of transparent <material>quartz</material>. Underneath the rock
              crystal is a cloisonné enamel image of a man with ecclesiastical symbols. The sides of the jewel holding the
              crystal in place contain an openwork inscription saying "AELFRED MEC HEHT GEWYRCAN", meaning 'Alfred ordered
              me made'. </p>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>It is generally accepted that the Alfred Jewel dates from the <origDate>late 9th Century</origDate> and
              was most likely made in <origPlace>England</origPlace>. </origin>
            <provenance when="1693">The jewel was discovered in 1693 at Petherton Park, North Petherton in the English
              county of Somerset, on land owned by Sir Thomas Wroth. North Petherton is about 8 miles away from Athelney,
              where King Alfred founded a monastery. </provenance>
            <provenance when="1698">A description of the Alfred Jewel was first published in 1698, in the Philosophical
              Transactions of the Royal Society.</provenance>
            <acquisition> It was bequeathed to Oxford University by Colonel Nathaniel Palmer (c. 1661-1718) and today is in
              the Ashmolean Museum in Oxford. </acquisition>
          </history>
        </object>
        
      </listObject>
      
      <!-- Elsewhere in document -->
      <p> The <objectName ref="#MinsterLovellJewel">Minster Lovell Jewel</objectName> is probably the most similar to the
        <objectName ref="#Alfred_Jewel">Alfred Jewel</objectName> and was found in <placeName ref="#MinsterLovell">Minster
          Lovell</placeName> in <placeName ref="#Oxfordshire">Oxfordshire</placeName> and is kept at the <orgName
            ref="#AshmoleanMuseum">Ashmolean Museum</orgName>. 
      </p>
      
      
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <listObject>
        <object xml:id="MaskOfTutankhamun">
          <objectIdentifier>
            <objectName xml:lang="en">Mask of Tutankhamun</objectName>
            <idno type="carter">256a</idno>
            <idno type="JournalD'Entrée">60672</idno>
            <idno type="exhibition">220</idno>
            <institution>Museum of Egyptian Antiquities</institution>
            <address>
              <street>15 Meret Basha</street>
              <district>Ismailia</district>
              <settlement>Cairo</settlement>
              <country>Egypt</country>
              <location>
                <geo>30.047778 31.233333</geo>
              </location>
            </address>
          </objectIdentifier>
          <msContents>
            <p>The back and shoulders of the mask is inscribed with a protective spell in Egyptian hieroglyphs formed of ten
              vertical and horizontal lines. This spell first appeared on masks in the Middle Kingdom at least 500 years
              before Tutankhamun, and comes from chapter 151 of the <title>Book of the Dead</title>.</p>
          </msContents>
          <physDesc>
            <p> The mask of Tutankhamun is 54cm x 39.3cm x 49cm. It is constructed from two layers of high-karat gold that
              varies in thickness from 1.5-3mm. It weighs approximately 10.23kg and x-ray crystallography shows that it is
              composed of two alloys of gold with a lighter 18.4 karat shade being used for the face and neck while a heavier
              22.5 karat gold was used for the rest of the mask.</p>
            <p>In the mask Tutankhamun wears a nemes headcloth which has the royal insignia of a cobra (Wadjet) and vulture
              (Nekhbet) on it. These are thought respectively to symbolize Tutankhamun's rule of both Lower Egypt and Upper
              Egypt. His ears are pierced for earrings. The mask has rich inlays of coloured glass and gemstones, including
              lapis lazuli surrounding the eye and eyebrows, quartz for the eyes, obsidian for the pupils. The broad collar is
              made up of carnelian, feldspar, turquoise, amazonite, faience and other stones.</p>
          </physDesc>
          <history>
            <origin>
              <p>The mask of Tutankhamun was created in <origPlace>Egypt</origPlace> around <origDate when="-1323"
                type="circa">1323 BC</origDate>. It is a death mask of the 18th-dynasty ancient Egyptian Pharaoh Tutankhamun
                who reigned 1332–1323 BC. </p>
            </origin>
            <provenance>
              <p>The mask of Tutankhamun was found in his burial chamber at Theban Necropolis in the Valley of the Kings in
                1922. On 28 October 1925 the excavation team led by English archaeologist Howard Carter opened the heavy
                sarcophagus and three coffins and were the first people in around 3,250 years to see the mask of Tutankhamun.
                Carter wrote in his diary: <quote> The pins removed, the lid was raised. The penultimate scene was disclosed –
                  a very neatly wrapped mummy of the young king, with golden mask of sad but tranquil expression, symbolizing
                  Osiris … the mask bears that god's attributes, but the likeness is that of Tut.Ankh.Amen – placid and
                  beautiful, with the same features as we find upon his statues and coffins. The mask has fallen slightly
                  back, thus its gaze is straight up to the heavens. </quote>
              </p>
            </provenance>
            <acquisition> In December 1925, the mask was removed from the tomb, placed in a crate and transported 635
              kilometres (395 mi) to the Egyptian Museum in Cairo, where it remains on public display. </acquisition>
          </history>
          <additional>
            <adminInfo>
              <custodialHist>
                <custEvent when="1944">When it was discovered in 1925, the 2.5kg narrow gold beard was no longer attached to
                  the mask and was reattached to the chin by use of a wooden dowel in 1944.</custEvent>
                <custEvent when="2014-08"> In August 2014 when the mask was removed from its display case for cleaning, the
                  beard fell off again. Those working in the museum unadvisedly used a quick-drying epoxy to attempt to fix
                  it, but left the beard off-centre. </custEvent>
                <custEvent when="2015-01">The damage was noticed and repaired in January 2015 by a German-Egyptian team who
                  used beeswax, a material known to be used as adhesives by the ancient Egyptians.</custEvent>
              </custodialHist>
            </adminInfo>
          </additional>
        </object>
      </listObject>
    </egXML>
    
  </exemplum>
<remarks versionDate="2019-12-27" xml:lang="en">
        <p>
        <!--JC: Remove warnings of version number after a couple of releases.  -->
        The <gi>object</gi> element is a recent addition to the TEI P5 Guidelines as of version 3.5.0 and as such may
        be more prone to further revision in the next few releases as its use develops. This may be particularly evident where its 
        contents have been borrowed from <gi>msDesc</gi> and have yet to be generalized from their use in the context of manuscript descriptions.  
        </p>
  
  <p>The <gi>object</gi> element may be used for describing any object, text-bearing or not, though where the textuality of the object is the 
    primary concern or a collection is mostly composed of manuscripts, encoders may prefer the <gi>msDesc</gi> element (a more specific form of <gi>object</gi>) which may be used not only to
    describe manuscripts but any form of text-bearing objects such as early printed books.    
  </p>
  
</remarks> 
  
<remarks versionDate="2019-01-22" xml:lang="de">
  <p>
    Das <gi>object</gi>-Element ist eine Neuerung zu den TEI P5 Guidelines ab Version 3.5.0 und kann daher in den nächsten Releases noch weiter überarbeitet werden. 
    Dies kann besonders dann vorkommen, wenn der Inhalt von <gi>msDesc</gi> übernommen wurde und durch seine spezifische Verwendung im Rahmen von Manuskriptbeschreibungen 
      noch verallgemeinert werden muss.
  </p>
</remarks>  
  
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#NDOBJ"/>
  </listRef>
 </elementSpec>
