<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
    Copyright TEI Consortium.
    Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
    See the file COPYING.txt for details
    $Date$
    $Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="core" ident="said">
  <gloss>speech or thought</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">대화 또는 사고</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">parlamento, discurso o pensamiento</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">Parole ou pensée.</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">parlato o pensiero</gloss>
  <desc>indicates passages thought or spoken aloud, whether explicitly indicated in the source or
    not, whether directly or indirectly reported, whether by real people or fictional characters.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">원본에 명시적으로 표시되었든지 않았든지, 직접적으로 또는 간접적으로 보고되었든지 않았든지, 그리고 실제
    인물 또는 가공의 인물에 의해 생성되었는지 간에, 생각 혹은 소리 내어 말한 단락을 표시한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">indica los pasajes pensados o hablados en voz alta, si
    está indicado explícitamente en la fuente o no, si señalado directamente o indirectamente, sean
    de gente real o de personajes ficticios.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 考えたり声に出されたりした一節を示す．元資料中に明示されているかどう
    か，間接的な伝聞かどうか，実在の人物に依るものかどうか，などは問わな い． </desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">indique que les passages sont pensés ou qu'ils sont
    prononcés à haute voix, que cela soit indiqué explicitement ou non dans la source , que ces
    passages soient directement ou indirectement rapportés par des personnages réels ou fictifs.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">indica brani pensati o pronunciati, siano essi
    esplicitamente indicati nella fonte o meno, in discorso diretto o indiretto e attribuibili a
    persone realmente esistenti o personaggi di fantasia</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.qLike"/>
    <memberOf key="att.ascribed"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.specialPara"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="aloud" usage="opt">
      <desc>may be used to indicate whether the quoted matter is regarded as having been vocalized
        or signed.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">인용부가 발화된 것으로 또는 신호된 것으로 볼 수 있는지를 표시할 때 사용할 수 있다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">puede ser utilizado para indicar si el material
        marcado ha sido verbalizado o firmado.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 引用内容が言語または記号化されているかどうかを示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">peut être utilisé pour indiquer si l'on estime que
        l'objet cité est dit oralement ou par signes.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">può essere utilizzato per indicare se la citazione in
        questione è stata pronunciata o firmata</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.xTruthValue"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>unknown</defaultVal>
      <remarks>
        <p>The value <val>true</val> indicates the encoded passage was expressed outwardly (whether
          spoken, signed, sung, screamed, chanted, etc.); the value <val>false</val> indicates that
          the encoded passage was thought, but not outwardly expressed.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>La valeur <val>true</val> indique que le passage encodé a été prononcé de manière
          explicite (qu'il ait été dit, exprimé par geste, chanté, crié, déclamé etc.) ; la valeur
            <val>false</val> indique que le passage encodé a été pensé, mais pas prononcé.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>El valor <val>verdad</val> indica que el pasaje codificado fue expresado exteriormente
          (si fue hablado, cantado, gritado, etc.); el valor <val>falso</val> indica que el pasaje
          codificado era un pensamiento, pero no expresado exteriormente.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 属性値<val>true</val>は，符号化されている一節が，外見上(発話，記号， 歌，叫び，詠唱など)表現されていることを示す．属性値
          <val>false</val>は，符号化されている一節が，考えられてはいるが， 外見上は表現されていないことを示す． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="direct" usage="opt">
      <desc>may be used to indicate whether the quoted matter is regarded as direct or indirect
        speech.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">인용부가 직접 대화로 또는 간접 대화로 간주할 수 있는지를 표시할 때 사용할 수 있다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">puede ser utilizado para indicar si el material
        marcado está considerado como discurso directo o indirecto.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 引用内容が，直接または間接的な話(法)かどうかを示す． </desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">peut être utilisé pour indiquer si le sujet cité est
        à considérer comme comme étant du discours direct ou du discours indirect.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">può essere utilizzato per indicare se la citazione in
        questione è considerata come discorso diretto o indiretto</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.xTruthValue"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>true</defaultVal>
      <remarks>
        <p>The value <val>true</val> indicates the speech or thought is represented directly; the
          value <val>false</val> that speech or thought is represented indirectly, e.g. by use of a
          marked verbal aspect.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>La valeur <val>true</val> indique que la parole ou la pensée est représentée directement
          ; la valeur <val>false</val>,  qu'elle est représentée indirectement , par exemple marquée
          par une forme verbale.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="es">
        <p>El valor <val>verdad</val> indica que el discurso o el pensamiento está representado
          directamente; el valor <val>falso</val> que el discurso o el pensamiento está representado
          indirectamente, p.ej. por medio de un aspecto verbal marcado.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> 属性値<val>true</val>は，話や考えは，直接的に示されていることを示 す．属性値<val>false</val>は，話や考えは，間接的に示されていること
          示す．例えば，動詞アスペクト指標により示されている． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COHQQ-eg-34">
      <p><said>Our minstrel here will warm the old man's heart with song, dazzle him with jewels and
          gold</said>, a troublemaker simpered. <said>He'll trample on the Duke's camellias, spill
          his wine, and blunt his sword, and say his name begins with X, and in the end the Duke
          will say, <said>Take Saralinda, with my blessing, O lordly Prince of Rags and Tags, O
            rider of the sun!</said>
            </said></p>
    </egXML>
    <!-- Thurber: The 13 Clocks, near end of chapter I -->
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Flaubert_Sal">
      <p>Ils l'entendaient murmurer : <said> Morts ! Tous morts ! Vous ne viendrez plus obéissant
            à ma voix, quand, assise sur le bord du lac, je vous jetais dans la gueule des pépins de
            pastèques ! Le mystère de Tanit roulait au fond de vos yeux, plus limpides que les
            globules des fleuves.</said> Et elle les appelait par leurs noms, qui étaient les noms
          des mois.<said>Siv ! Sivan ! Tammouz, Eloul, Tischri, Schebar ! Ah ! pitié pour moi,
            Déesse ! </said>
        </p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#fr-ex-Balzac_Vie">
      <p><said aloud="true" rend="pre(“) post(”)">On veut donc plaire à sa petite fille ?...
          </said>, dit Caroline en mettant sa tête sur l'épaule d'Adolphe, qui la baise au front en
          pensant : <said aloud="false">Dieu merci, je la tiens! </said>.</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#biblzh-tw_n20">
      <p><said>一路下去，慢慢我發覺我和王一生之間，既開始有互相的信任和基於經驗的同情，又有各自的疑問。</said>
            他總是問我與他認識之前是怎麼生活的，尤其是父母死後的兩年是怎麼混的。<said>我大略地告訴他，可他又特別在一些細節上詳細地打聽，主要是關於吃。例如講到有一次我一天沒有吃到東西，他就問：<said>
            「一點兒都沒吃到嗎？」</said>
            </said>
         </p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="zh-TW">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <p><said aloud="true" rend="pre(“) post(”)">嗯，</said>他耳邊傳來小小的聲音說： <said aloud="true" rend="pre(“) post(”)">有點難以決定，非常困難。 很有勇氣、頭腦也不錯、有天份。喔！我的天啊！沒錯— 還有熱切證明自我的渴望，這真的很有趣。…
          我應該把你分發到哪呢？</said>
         </p>
      <p>哈利抓緊分類帽的邊緣想著：<said aloud="false" rend="italic">不要是史來哲林，千萬不要</said>。</p>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COHQQ-eg-35">
      <p><said aloud="true" rend="pre(“) post(”)">Hmmm</said>, said a small voice in his ear. <said aloud="true" rend="pre(“) post(”)">Difficult. Very difficult. Plenty of courage, I see.
          Not a bad mind either. there's talent, oh my goodness, yes — and a nice thirst to prove
          yourself, now that's interesting. … So where shall I put you?</said></p>
      <p>Harry gripped the edges of the stool and thought, <said aloud="false" rend="italic">Not
          Slytherin, not Slytherin</said>.</p>
    </egXML>
    <!-- Rowling: Harry Potter and the Sorcerer's Stone,
            chapter 7 "The Sorting Hat"; p. 121 of the first
            Scholastic trade paperback edition -->
  </exemplum>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#COHQQ"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
