<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$
$Author$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="header" xml:id="SAMPDECL" usage="opt" ident="samplingDecl">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>sampling declaration</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">dichiarazione di campionatura</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declaración de muestra</gloss>
  <gloss version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja">標本</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="zh-tw">取樣宣告</gloss>
  <gloss xml:lang="fr">Déclaration d'échantillonage</gloss>
  <desc>contains a prose description of the rationale and methods used
in sampling texts in the creation of a corpus or collection.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una descrizione dei metodi e dei principi usati nella campionatura dei testi nella creazione o raccolta del corpus.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una descripción en prosa sobre los fundamentos y métodos usados en textos de muestra en la creación de un corpus o una selección de textos. </desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-28" xml:lang="ja"> コーパス等を作成する際に抽出された標本テキストを作成した方
法や方針を，散文で示す．</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="zh-tw">以篇章描述的方式說明建立文集或文選時文件取樣的原理與方法。</desc>
  <desc xml:lang="fr">L’élément Déclaration d’échantillonnage <gi>samplingDecl</gi> contient une description en prose suivie de la logique et des méthodes utilisées pour l'échantillonnage des textes dans la création d’un corpus ou d’une collection.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="model.encodingPart"/>
    <memberOf key="att.declarable"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:ref name="model.pLike"/>
    </rng:oneOrMore>
  </content>
  <exemplum>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"/>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>This element records all information about systematic
inclusion or omission of portions of the text, whether a reflection
of sampling procedures in the pure sense or of systematic
omission of material deemed either too difficult to transcribe
or not of sufficient interest.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cet élément rassemble toute information sur l'inclusion ou l'omission systématique de portions du texte, quel que soit le résultat de procédures d'échantillonnage au sens strict, ou de l'omission systématique d'éléments jugés soit trop difficiles à transcrire, soit sans intérêt.</p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#HD52"/>
    <ptr target="#HD5"/>
    <ptr target="#CCAS2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
