<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="header" ident="samplingDecl">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>sampling declaration</gloss>
  <gloss version="2009-01-05" xml:lang="fr">déclaration d'échantillonnage</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">표본 추출 선언</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">取樣宣告</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2006-10-18" xml:lang="de">Beschreibung des Auswahlverfahrens</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declaración de muestra</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">dichiarazione di campionatura</gloss>
  <desc>contains a prose description of the rationale and methods used in sampling texts in the
    creation of a corpus or collection.</desc>
  <desc version="2009-01-05" xml:lang="fr"> contient une description en texte libre du raisonnement
    et des méthodes utilisés pour l'échantillonnage des textes dans la création d’un corpus ou
    d’une collection.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">코퍼스 또는 텍스트 집단 구축에서 표본 추출에 사용된 원리와 방법에 대한 산문체 기술을 포함한다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">以篇章描述的方式說明建立文集或文選時文件取樣的原理與方法。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> コーパス等を作成する際，テキストを標本化する原理や手法に関する，散文 による解説を含む． </desc>
  <desc version="2006-10-18" xml:lang="de">enthält eine Beschreibung der Kriterien und Methoden,
    nach denen die Textsamples für ein Korpus oder eine Sammlung ausgewählt wurden. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene una descripción en prosa sobre los fundamentos y
    métodos usados en textos de muestra en la creación de un corpus o una selección de textos. </desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una descrizione dei metodi e dei principi usati
    nella campionatura dei testi nella creazione o raccolta del corpus.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.encodingDescPart"/>
    <memberOf key="att.declarable"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:ref name="model.pLike"/>
    </rng:oneOrMore>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <samplingDecl>
        <p>Samples of up to 2000 words taken at random from the beginning, middle, or end of each
          text identified as relevant by respondents.</p>
      </samplingDecl>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>This element records all information about systematic inclusion or omission of portions of
      the text, whether a reflection of sampling procedures in the pure sense or of systematic
      omission of material deemed either too difficult to transcribe or not of sufficient
    interest.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>Cet élément rassemble toute information sur l'inclusion ou l'omission systématique de
      segments du texte, quel que soit le résultat des procédures d'échantillonnage au sens strict,
      ou de l'omission systématique d'éléments jugés soit trop difficiles à transcrire, soit sans
      intérêt.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="es">
    <p>Este elemento registra toda la información sobre la inclusión sistemática o la omisión de
      fragmentos de texto, si los procedimientos de muestra en el sentido estricto o la omisión
      sistemática del material se consideran demasiado difíciles de transcribir o no de suficiente
      interés.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 純粋な意味での標本化過程または体系的な資料の省略が，難しすぎて転記 できない，または充分な関心が得られていないと考えられているにしても， 当該要
      素は，テキスト部分の体系的な取捨選択に関する情報の全てを 記録する． </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#HD52"/>
    <ptr target="#HD5"/>
    <ptr target="#CCAS2"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
