<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- © TEI Consortium. Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licenses; see the file COPYING.txt for details. -->
<?xml-model href="https://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:sch="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron" xmlns:teix="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" module="tagdocs" xml:id="SCHEMASPEC" ident="schemaSpec">
  <gloss versionDate="2007-07-04" xml:lang="en">schema specification</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">스키마 명시</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">especificación de esquema</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">spécification de schéma</gloss>
  <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">specifica dello schema</gloss>
  <desc versionDate="2005-01-14" xml:lang="en">generates a TEI-conformant schema and documentation for it.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">TEI 구조 스키마 및 문서를 생성한다.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">建立一個符合TEI標準的模型以及該模型文件。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">TEI準拠のスキーマや文書を示す。</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">génère un schéma conforme à la TEI et la
                        documentation qui l'accompagne.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">genera un esquema TEI-conforme y la documentación relativa.</desc>
  <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">genera uno schema TEI-conforme e la relativa documentazione</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.frontPart"/>
    <memberOf key="model.encodingDescPart"/>
    <memberOf key="model.frontPart"/>
    <memberOf key="att.identified"/>
    <memberOf key="att.namespaceable"/>
    <memberOf key="att.docStatus"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <sequence>
      <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <classRef key="model.identEquiv"/>
        <classRef key="model.descLike"/>
      </alternate>
      <alternate minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <classRef key="model.oddRef"/>
        <classRef key="model.oddDecl"/>
	<elementRef key="listRef"/>
      </alternate>      
    </sequence>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="start" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2010-05-14" xml:lang="en">specifies entry points to the schema, i.e. which patterns
      may be used as the root of documents conforming to
      it.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">스키마에서 표제 항목 지점을 명시한다. 즉, 어떤 요소가 해당 문서의 뿌리로 사용되는 것이 허용되었는지를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出該模型的初步條件，例如在符合該模型標準的文件中，那些元素可做為文件的根元素。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">当該スキーマの開始点を示す。すなわち、TEI準拠文書の根要素となる
      要素を示す。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">précise les points d'accès au schéma,
                                        i.e. quels sont les éléments permis comme racine des documents XML qui se
                                        conforment à ce schéma.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica los puntos de acceso al esquema, es decir, qué elementos son los permitidos para ser usados como raíz de los documentos conforme al esquema mismo.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">specifica i punti di accesso allo schema, cioè quali elementi sono consentiti come radice dei documenti conformi allo schema stesso</desc>
      <datatype maxOccurs="unbounded"><dataRef key="teidata.name"/></datatype>
      <defaultVal>TEI</defaultVal>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="prefix" usage="opt">
      <desc versionDate="2013-01-11" xml:lang="en">specifies a default prefix which will be prepended to all
      patterns relating to TEI elements, unless otherwise stated.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">TEI 요소와 관련된 모든 유형에 첨가될 접두사를 명시한다. 이는 TEI로서 동일 이름의 요소를 갖는 외부 스키마가 혼용되는 것을 허용한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指明一個附加在所有和TEI元素相關的模式中的前綴。這使得外部模型可以和TEI結合，這些外部模型具有和TEI元素名稱相同的元素。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">TEI要素の全パタンに対応する接頭辞を示す。これにより、TEIと同じ名
      前を持つ外部スキーマを混在させることができる。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">précise un préfixe qui sera ajouté à tous
                                        les modèles de définition des éléments de la TEI. Cela autorise l'introduction
                                        des schémas externes ayant des éléments de même nom que ceux de la TEI</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">especifica un prefijo que será antepuesto a todos los patrones relativos a los elementos TEI.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica un prefisso che sarà anteposto a tutti i pattern relativi a elementi TEI; questo consente</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="0">
        <dataRef key="teidata.xmlName"/>
      </datatype>
      <remarks versionDate="2013-05-06" xml:lang="en">
        <p>Use of this attribute allows an external schema which
           has an element with the same local name as a TEI element to
           be mixed in.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2007-06-12">
        <p>Les deux-points, bien qu'ils soient permis à l'intérieur de
        la valeur, provoqueront la génération d'un schéma invalide.
        </p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja" versionDate="2008-04-05">
        <p>
          コロンは、値としては認められるが、スキーマ中では使用できない。
        </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="targetLang" usage="opt">
      <gloss versionDate="2007-07-04" xml:lang="en">target language</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">목적 언어</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">lengua meta</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">langue cible</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">lingua di arrivo</gloss>
      <desc versionDate="2012-04-25" xml:lang="en">specifies which language to use when creating
      the objects in a schema if names for elements or attributes are available in more
      than one language</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">요소 또는 속성의 이름을 만들기 위해 여러 언어에서 사용가능한 경우, 스키마에서 대상을 만들 때 사용하는 언어를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">若元素或屬性名稱所使用的語言有一種以上，說明建立文件模型時要使用那一種語言。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">要素や属性の名前が複数言語である場合には、スキーマ中の対象を作成
      する際に使用される言語を特定する。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">lorsque des noms pour un élément ou pour
                                        un attribut sont disponibles en plusieurs langues, précise quelle langue
                                        utiliser lors de la création d'objets dans un schéma .</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la lengua que se utiliza para la creación de objetos en el esquema en el caso en que los nombres de elementos o atributos esten disponibles en otras lenguas.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la lingua da utilizzare per la creazione di oggetti nello schema nel caso in cui i nomi di elementi o attributi siano disponibili in più lingue</desc>
      <datatype><dataRef key="teidata.language"/></datatype>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="docLang" usage="opt">
      <gloss versionDate="2007-07-04" xml:lang="en">documentation language</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">문서화 언어</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-04-06" xml:lang="es">lengua de la documentación</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2008-03-30" xml:lang="fr">langue de documentation</gloss>
      <gloss versionDate="2007-11-06" xml:lang="it">lingua della documentazione</gloss>
      <desc versionDate="2012-04-25" xml:lang="en">specifies which
      languages to use when creating documentation if the description
      for an element, attribute, class or macro is available in more
      than one language</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">요소, 속성, 부류 또는 매크로에 대한 기술이 여러 언어에서 사용 가능한 경우, 문서를 만들 때 사용하는 언어를 명시한다.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">若元素、屬性、元素集或巨集指令描述所使用的語言有一種以上，說明建立文件時要使用那一種語言。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">要素、属性、クラス、マクロの解説が複数言語で可能な場合、解説の言
      語を特定する。</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">lorsque la description pour un élément,
                                        un attribut, une classe ou une macro est disponible en plusieurs langues,
                                        précise quelle langue utiliser lors de la création de la documentation.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica la lengua que se ha de utilizar para la creación de la documentación en el caso en que las descripciones de elementos, atributos, clases o macros esten disponibles en más lenguas.</desc>
      <desc versionDate="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica la lingua da utilizzare per la creazione della documentazione nel caso in cui le descrizioni di elementi, attributi, classi o macro siano disponibili in più lingue</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded"><dataRef key="teidata.language"/></datatype>
      <remarks xml:lang="en" versionDate="2022-04-04">
        <p>Although multiple languages may be specified, the current
        TEI ODD processor is only capable of handling one.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="defaultExceptions" usage="rec">
      <gloss versionDate="2016-11-20" xml:lang="en">default namespace
      exclusions</gloss>
      <desc versionDate="2016-11-20" xml:lang="en">provides a list of namespaces and/or prefixed element names to be excluded by default from anyName in RELAX NG schemas</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <dataRef key="teidata.namespaceOrName"/>
      </datatype>
      <defaultVal>http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0 teix:egXML</defaultVal>
      <remarks versionDate="2017-05-11" xml:lang="en">
        <p>Specifies defaults for the <att>except</att> attribute of <gi>anyElement</gi>. RELAX NG validation (unless DTD Compatibility Mode is turned off) requires that any elements which may take an <att>xml:id</att> be excluded from the content of <ident>anyName</ident> name classes. For normal TEI purposes, this includes anything in the TEI namespace and the <gi>egXML</gi> element. The <att>defaultExceptions</att> attribute sets the global defaults for these exclusions. Element prefixes must be declared using a namespace declaration on the parent or an ancestor element.</p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="und">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#UND">
      <schemaSpec prefix="TEI_" ident="testsvg" start="TEI svg">
        <moduleRef source="tei:current" key="header"/>
        <moduleRef key="core"/>
        <moduleRef key="drama"/>
        <moduleRef url="svg11.rng"/>
      </schemaSpec>
    </egXML>
    <p>This schema combines elements from the current versions of the drama and core
    modules,  the current release version of the header module, and elements
    from an existing RELAX NG schema available from the URL indicated.</p>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="und">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#UND">
      <schemaSpec ident="Bare-plus" source="tei_bare.compiled.odd" start="TEI">
        <moduleRef key="tei"/>
        <moduleRef key="header"/>
        <elementRef key="q" source="tei:3.0.0"/>
        <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
      </schemaSpec>
    </egXML>
    <p>This schema starts with a pre-existing customization of the TEI
    called TEI Bare (a customization with a minimal selection of
    elements). The <gi>q</gi> element is not available in TEI Bare,
    but it can be brought back. In this case, we will get the version
    defined in TEI P5 release 3.0.0 </p>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks versionDate="2021-02-02" xml:lang="en">
    <!--
        oddRef:
        classRef, dataRef, elementRef, macroRef, and moduleRef

        oddDecl:
        classSpec, constraintSpec, dataSpec, elementSpec, listRef,
        macroSpec, moduleSpec, outputRendition, specGrp, and specGrpRef
    -->
    <p>A <gi>schemaSpec</gi> combines references to modules,
    individual element or macro declarations, and specification groups
    together to form a unified schema.</p>
    <p>The processing of the <gi>schemaSpec</gi> element must resolve
    any conflicts amongst the declarations it either contains or
    refers to. Different ODD processors may generate schemas and
    documentation using different concrete syntaxes.</p>
    <!-- note: moved from removed att.readFrom -->
    <p>The source may be specified (on the <att>source</att>
    attribute) in the form of a private URI, for which the recommended
    format is <code>tei:x.y.z</code>, where <code>x.y.z</code>
    indicates the version number, e.g. <code>tei:1.5.1</code> for
    1.5.1 release of TEI P5 or (as a special case)
    <code>tei:current</code> for whatever is the latest release. The
    source indicated must provide a set of TEI-conformant
    specifications in a form directly usable by an ODD processor. By
    default, this will be the location of the current release of the
    TEI Guidelines.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr" versionDate="2007-06-12">
    <p>Un schéma combine des références aux modules ou aux groupes de
    spécifications avec d'autres déclarations atomiques. Le traitement
    d'un élément de schéma doit résoudre tous les conflits entre les
    déclarations qu'il contient ou les références. Des processeurs ODD
    différents peuvent générer des schémas et une documentation en
    utilisant différentes syntaxes concrètes.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja" versionDate="2008-04-05">
    <p>
      スキーマは、モジュールまたは規定集への参照と、他の原子的宣言とを関
      連づける。スキーマ要素は、関連する宣言間の齟齬を調整しなければなら
      ない。ODDソフトウェアは、その種類によって、異なるスキーマや文書を
      生成するかもしれない。
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#HD5"/>
    <ptr target="#TDmodules"/>
    <ptr target="#IM-unified"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
