<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="tagdocs" xml:id="SPECDESC" ident="specDesc">
  <gloss>specification description</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">명시 기술</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">元素或元素集描述</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">specification description</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">descripción de elemento o clase.</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">descrizione di elemento o classe</gloss>
  <desc>indicates that a description of the specified element or class should be included at this
    point within a document.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">명시된 요소 또는 부류에 대한 기술이 문서 내 이 지점에 포함되었음을 나타낸다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">指出指定元素或元素集的描述應在此包括在文件中。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 特定された要素またはクラスの解説は，文書中のこの場所にあるべきである ことを示す． </desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">indique qu'une description de l'élément particulier ou de
    la classe particulière doit être incluse à ce point dans un document.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">indica el punto del documento en el que debe inserirse la
    descripción de un elemento dado o de una clase dada.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica il punto del documento nel quale deve essere
    inserita la descrizione di un dato elemento o di una data classe</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.specDescLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <empty xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
  </content>
  <attList>
    <attDef ident="key" usage="opt">
      <gloss>identifier</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">확인소</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">識別符碼</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">identifiant</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">identificador</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">identificatore</gloss>
      <desc>supplies the identifier of the documentary element or class for which a description is
        to be obtained.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">기술이 얻어진 문서 요소 또는 부류에 대한 확인소를 제시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供文件元素或元素集的識別符碼。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 解説が表される，記録用の要素またはクラスの識別子を示す． </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">donne l'identifiant de l'élément ou de la classe
        documentaire pour lequels la description est à faire.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">adscribe un identificador al elemento o a la clase
        que se está describiendo.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">assegna un identificatore all'elemento o alla classe
        per i quali deve essere fornita una descrizione</desc>
      <datatype>
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"/>
      </datatype>
      <exemplum xml:lang="und">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <specDesc key="emph"/>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <specDesc key="emph"/>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
    </attDef>
    <attDef ident="atts" usage="rec">
      <gloss>attributes</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">속성</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">屬性</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">attributs</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">atributo</gloss>
      <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">attributi</gloss>
      <desc>supplies attribute names for which descriptions should additionally be obtained.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">기술이 부가적으로 얻어진 속성명을 제시한다.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">提供其屬性描述應另外包含的屬性名稱。</desc>
      <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"> 解説が付加的に表される属性名を示す． </desc>
      <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">donne les noms des attributs dont il faut une
        description supplémentaire.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">proporciona nombres de atributo pera los que se debe
        proporcionar una descripción.</desc>
      <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">indica dei nomi di attributi per i quali devono
        essere fornite delle descrizioni</desc>
      <datatype minOccurs="0" maxOccurs="unbounded">
        <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"/>
      </datatype>
      <valDesc>a whitespace-separated list of attribute names</valDesc>
      <exemplum xml:lang="und">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <specDesc key="foreign" atts="usage xml:lang"/>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <specDesc key="foreign" atts="usage xml:lang"/>
        </egXML>
      </exemplum>
      <remarks>
        <p>The attribute names listed may include both attributes inherited from a class and those
          defined explicitly for the associated element. If the <att>atts</att> attribute is not
          supplied, then descriptions for all non-inherited attributes are listed, along with
          references to any classes. If an empty string is supplied as the value for the
          <att>atts</att> attribute, then no description should be displayed.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="fr">
        <p>Les noms d'attribut listés peuvent inclure à la fois des attributs hérités d'une classe
          et ceux qui sont définis explicitement pour l'élément associé. Si l'attribut <att>atts</att> n'est
          pas fourni, il faut lister et décrire tous les attributs non hérités, avec référence aux
          classes éventuelles. Si une chaîne vide est indiquée comme valeur pour l'attribut
            <att>atts</att>, on ne devrait pas afficher de description.</p>
      </remarks>
      <remarks xml:lang="ja">
        <p> リスト中の属性名には，クラスから継承した属性や，また関連する要 素で明示的に定義されている属性を含むかもしれない．
          属性<att>atts</att>がない場合，継承されない属性がリスト化され， 各クラスへの参照が示される．属性<att>atts</att>の値に空文字が
          付与されている場合，解説は表示されないべきである． </p>
      </remarks>
    </attDef>
  </attList>
  <exemplum xml:lang="und">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <specDesc key="orth"/>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum version="2008-04-06" xml:lang="fr">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <specDesc key="orth"/>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="und">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <specDesc key="emph"/>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <exemplum xml:lang="und">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <specDesc key="foreign" atts="usage xml:lang"/>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p>The description is usually displayed as a label and an item, with any list of values defined
      for the attribute as an embedded glossary list, No selection among the values is possible. The
      list of attributes may include some which are inherited by virtue of an element's class
      membership; descriptions for such attributes may also be retrieved using another
      <gi>specDesc</gi>, this time pointing at the relevant class.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p>La description est habituellement affichée sous la forme d'une étiquette et d'un contenu,
      avec toutes les listes de valeurs définies pour l'attribut, comme une liste de glossaire imbriquée.
     Aucune sélection parmi ces valeurs n'est possible. La liste d'attributs peut inclure des
      attributs hérités en vertu de leur appartenance à une classe d'éléments ; les descriptions de
      ces attributs peuvent également être récupérées en utilisant un autre élément
      <gi>specDesc</gi> qui pointe cette fois vers la classe pertinente.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p> 当該解説は，一般には，属性として定義される値のリストとして，ラベル と各項目で示される．その値から更に選択することはできない．属性
      のリストには，要素クラスから継承したものもある．このような属性の解 説は，他の要素<gi>specDesc</gi>を使い示されるかもしれない．この場
      合，関連するクラスを指示することになる． </p>
  </remarks>
</elementSpec>
