<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="iso-fs" ident="vDefault">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>value default</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">기본 값</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">기준값</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">預設值</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">valeur par défaut</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">valor predeterminado</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">valore predefinito</gloss>
  <desc>declares the default value to be supplied when a feature structure
does not contain an instance of <gi>f</gi> for this name; if
unconditional, it is specified as one (or, depending on the value of
the <att>org</att> attribute of the enclosing <gi>fDecl</gi>) more
<gi>fs</gi> elements or primitive values;
if conditional, it is specified as
one or more <gi>if</gi> elements; if no default is specified, or no
condition matches, the value <val>none</val> is assumed.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">자질 구조가 이 이름에 대한 자질의 예를 포함하지 않는다면 제시된 기본값을 선언한다. 조건이 미명시되었을 때 하나 이상의 자질구조 요소 또는 원형 값(또는 fDecl의 org 속성 값의 의존하는 값)으로 명시된다; 만약 조건이 명시될 때, 하나 이상의 요소로 명시된다; 만약 기본 값이 명시되지 않는다면 또는 일치하는 조건이 없다면, none 값이 상정된다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-12-20" xml:lang="ko">어떤 자질 구조가 이 이름에 대한 f의 실례를 포함하고 있지 않을 때, 제공된 기본값을 선언한다; 만약 특별한 조건이 없다면, 하나 이상의 fs 요소나 원형 값으로 (또는 FDecl에 둘러싸인 org 속성의 값에 의존하여) 명시된다.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">在功能結構不包含元素<gi>f</gi>以提供名稱的情況下，宣告使用預設值；若無條件限制，預設值會被指明為一個 (或，取決於所包含的元素<gi>fDecl</gi>中屬性<att>org</att>的屬性值) 多個元素<gi>fs</gi>或原始值；若有條件限制，則被指明為一個或多個元素<gi> if</gi>；若無任何預設值、或無條件符合，則採用屬性值 <val>none</val>。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  素性構造が要素<gi>f</gi>を持たないときのデフォルト値を宣言する．条件
  的でない場合，要素<gi>fs</gi>または値がもうひとつ(または，要素
  <gi>fDecl</gi>にある属性orgの値に依存する数だけ)付与される．条件的な
  場合，要素であればひとつ以上が付与される．デフォルト値が指定されてい
  ない場合，または条件が成立しない場合は，値noneをとるする．
  </desc>
  <desc version="2009-04-16" xml:lang="fr">déclare la valeur par défaut à fournir quand une
      structure de traits ne contient aucun cas de <gi>f</gi> pour ce nom ; si elle est inconditionnelle,
      on l'indique comme un élément <gi>fs</gi> (ou plusieurs, selon la valeur de l'attribut <att>org</att> du <gi>fDecl</gi>
      englobant) ; si elle est conditionnelle, on l'indique comme un ou plusieurs éléments <gi>if</gi> ; si
      aucune valeur par défaut n'est précisée ou si aucune condition ne correspond, la valeur nulle
      est retenue.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">declara el valor predeterminado que se aplica cuando una estructura de rasgo no contiene un valor de f para este nombre; si es incondicional, se especifica como uno (según el valor del atributo org de la fDecl) o más elementos fs o como valores primitivos; si es condicional, se especifica como uno o más elementos; si no hay un valor predeterminado, o no hay ninguna condición combinada, no se asume ningún valor.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">dichiara il valore predefinito da fornire quando una struttura di tratti non contiene una occorrenza di f per questo nome; se non condizionato, è specificato come uno o (a seconda del valore
      dell'attributo org del fDecl accluso) più elementi fs di valori primitivi; se condizionato, è specificato come uno o più elementi if; se non è specificto alcun valore predefinito, o nessuna condizione corrisponde, viene assunto il valore nessuno.</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:choice xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="model.featureVal"/>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="if"/>
      </rng:oneOrMore>
    </rng:choice>
  </content>
  <exemplum xml:lang="en">
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
      <fDecl name="INV">
        <fDescr>inverted sentence</fDescr>
        <vRange>
          <vAlt>
            <binary value="true"/>
            <binary value="false"/>
          </vAlt>
        </vRange>
        <vDefault>
          <binary value="false"/>
        </vDefault>
      </fDecl>
    </egXML>
  </exemplum>
  <remarks>
    <p rend="dataDesc">May contain a legal feature value, or a series of <gi>if</gi>
elements.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="fr">
    <p rend="dataDesc">Peut contenir une valeur de trait admise ou une série d'éléments
                    <gi>if</gi>.</p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p rend="dataDesc">
    正しい素性値，または一連の要素<gi>if</gi>をとる．
    </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#FD"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
