<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details
$Date$

$Id$
-->
<elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="textcrit" ident="witList">
  <equiv/>
  <gloss>witness list</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">版本列表</gloss>
  <gloss version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja"/>
  <gloss version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">liste de témoins</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">lista de testimonios</gloss>
  <gloss version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">lista dei testimoni</gloss>
  <desc>lists definitions for all the witnesses referred to by a critical
  apparatus, optionally grouped hierarchically.</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-02" xml:lang="zh-TW">包含一份所有版本的列表，這些版本在學術編輯註解中的元素<gi>wit</gi>或屬性<att>wit</att>內指明。</desc>
  <desc version="2008-04-05" xml:lang="ja">
  校勘資料中で参照される全文献の定義リストを示す．構造化されていること
  もある．
</desc>
  <desc version="2007-06-12" xml:lang="fr">cet élément décrit sous la forme d'une liste tous
			les témoins auxquels fait référence un apparat critique ; ces descriptions peuvent être
			groupées de façon hiérarchisée</desc>
  <desc version="2007-05-04" xml:lang="es">contiene la lista con todos los testimonios a los cuales se hace referencia en los elementos y atributos relativos a los testimonios en el aparato crítico</desc>
  <desc version="2007-01-21" xml:lang="it">contiene una lista di tutti i testimoni a cui si fa riferimento negli elementi e attributi relativi ai testimoni nell'apparato critico</desc>
  <classes>
    <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    <memberOf key="model.listLike"/>
  </classes>
  <content>
    <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
      <!--      <rng:zeroOrMore>
        <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
      </rng:zeroOrMore>-->
      <rng:optional>
        <rng:ref name="model.headLike"/>
      </rng:optional>
      <rng:oneOrMore>
        <rng:choice>
          <rng:ref name="witness"/>
          <rng:ref name="witList"/>
        </rng:choice>
        <!--        <rng:zeroOrMore>
          <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
        </rng:zeroOrMore>-->
      </rng:oneOrMore>
    </rng:group>
  </content>
  <remarks>
    <p rend="dataDesc">May contain
a series of <gi>witness</gi>  or <gi>witList</gi> elements.
</p>
    <p>The provision of a <gi>witList</gi> element simplifies
the automatic processing of the apparatus, e.g. the reconstruction
of the readings for all witnesses from an exhaustive apparatus.</p>
    <p>Situations commonly arise where there are many more or less
fragmentary witnesses, such that there may be quite distinct groups
of witnesses for different parts of a text or collection of
texts. Such groups may be given separately, or nested within a single
<gi>witList</gi> element at the beginning of the file listing all the
witnesses, partial and complete, for the text, with the attestation
of fragmentary witnesses indicated within the apparatus by use of the
<gi>witStart</gi> and <gi>witEnd</gi> elements described in section
<ptr target="#TCAPMI"/>.</p>
    <p>Note however that a given witness can only be defined once, and can
therefore only appear within a single <gi>witList</gi> element. </p>
  </remarks>
  <remarks xml:lang="ja">
    <p rend="dataDesc">
    一連の要素<gi>witness</gi>や<gi>witList</gi>を含むかもしれない．
    </p>
    <p>
    当該要素<gi>witList</gi>により，校勘資料の自動処理が可能になる．例
    えば，全校勘資料から全文献の解釈を再構成する処理である．
    </p>
    <p>
    文献が断片的であるのはよくあることで，この場合，テキストの部分毎に
    文献をまとめることがあるかもしれない．このようなグループは，独立し
    ているかもしれないし，または，全文献のリストを持つファイルの冒頭に
    あるにあるいち要素<gi>witList</gi>の中に入れ子化され，要素
    <gi>witStart</gi>や<gi>witEnd</gi>が，当該文献中で示されている断片
    的な文献を示すかもしれない．詳細は，<ptr target="#TCAPMI"/>を参照
    のこと．
    </p>
    <p>
    しかし，文献は一度だけ定義され，要素<gi>witList</gi>の中にのみ出現
    することに注意すること．
     </p>
  </remarks>
  <listRef>
    <ptr target="#TCAPLL"/>
  </listRef>
</elementSpec>
