<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:ge="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">An Encoding Model for Genetic Editions</title>
            <author>Fotis Jannidis, Elena Pierazzo, Malte Rehbein</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="2">Draft</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>TEI MS SIG, Genetic Edition Workgroup</authority>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born Digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
            <date>08 May 2009</date>
            <desc>Conversion from MS Word</desc>
         </change>
         <change>
            <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
            <date>01 August 2009</date>
            <desc>Major update following Paris' Workshop</desc>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <divGen type="toc"/>
         <pb/>
         <div>
<head>About this Document</head>
<p>This document contains the <hi rend="bold">draft</hi> of an
encoding model for Genetic Editions and Genetic Editing. The Document
is the product of a Workgroup on Genetic Editions (chair: Fotis
Jannidis), which is part of the TEI MS SIG (chairs: Elena Pierazzo,
Malte Rehbein, Amanda Galley). </p>
<p>The purpose of this workgroup is to try to elaborate an <hi rend="bold">Application
      Profile</hi> able to encode genetic editions and, in general, genetic phenomena.
   The application profile will discuss how to use existing TEI elements in a genetic
   framework, presenting, where necessary, new elements and will take the form of a TEI
   extension. </p>
<p>Respect the <hi rend="italic">TEI P5 Guidelines</hi>, the present document aims to
   integrate Chapter 11. <hi rend="italic">Representation of Primary Sources</hi> and
   Chapter 12. <hi rend="italic">Critical Apparatus</hi>. It might be the case that it
   will, at the end of the process described in the following section, constitute a self
   standing new <title>Guidelines</title> chapter, but this decision will be taken later
   on.</p>
<p>The current state of this document reflects the discussion held in three different
   meetings:</p>
<list type="bulleted">
   <item>MS SIG meeting held in London during the annual members’ TEI meeting (November
      2008); the minutes of the meeting can be found here: <ptr
         target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Minutes_London_2008"/>.</item>
   <item>Genetic Edition workgroup held in London (March 2009); minutes can be found
      here: <ptr target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Minutes_London_03-2009"/>. </item>
   <item>Workshop "Genetic Editions in a Digital Framework", held in Paris, 14/15 May
      2009, and following discussion; programme of the workshop can be found here: <ptr
         target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/GeneticEditionsWorkshopParis"/></item>
</list>
<p>The working group has made a large use of the <title>HNML. HyperNietzsche Markup
      Language</title> and following versions (<title>GML Genetic Markup
   Language</title>) written by Paolo D'Iorio and collaborators for the HyperNietzsche
   project. We would like to thank Paolo D'Iorio for his invaluable contribution in the
   early stages of the work. </p>
<div>
   <head>Methodology</head>
   <p>Te stages we will follow to complete the present encoding model are the following:</p>
   <list type="bulleted">
      <item>In the beginning we will work on a pseudo-encoding which is tightly bound to
         our own terminology <hi rend="italic">[Stage completed on July 2009]</hi>.</item>
      <item>In a second step we will try to map this pseudo-encoding to the actual TEI
         encoding framework, in cooperation with Lou Burnard. The result will be
         presented at TEI' Members Meeting 2009.</item>
      <item>The same step-by-step approach shall be taken for the standardisation
         process: <list type="bulleted">
 <item>First we develop an application profile a.k.a. a well-documented TEI
    customisation.</item>
 <item>This will be presented to te TEI Council as a global proposal for
    modify the TEI</item>
 <item>If the TEI Council approves it, we will then possibly rework it into a
    separate chapter for the TEI <title>Guidelines</title> or as integrations
    to existing Chapters.</item>
         </list></item>
   </list>
   <p>All versions of the draft will be publicly available for discussions and feedback
      from the community. Versions will be hosted on the TEI Wiki as PDF documents,
      while the XML source will be stored in the TEI SVN repository.</p>
</div>
<div>
   <head>Conventions used</head>
   <p>Although the entire document is a draft and therefore susceptible of changes, some
      sections are less stable than others. In particular, when a section or a
      particular element requires further discussion or is considered an open problem,
      such a section or element is marked by a * mark.</p>
   <p>All newly introduced elements are marked by the namespace prefix <hi rend="bold"
         >ge:</hi>, while TEI elements are marked by a <hi rend="bold">tei:</hi>
      namespace prefix.</p>
</div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
<head>Theoretical Framework</head>
<p>The encoding model will present how to handle both <hi rend="bold">Genetic
      Transcription</hi> (a transcription of a single document), how to reconstruct a
      <hi rend="bold">Genetic Dossier</hi>, meaning how to describe genetic relations
   amongst multiple witnesses, and how to prepare a <hi rend="bold">Genetic Edition</hi>
   based on a single or multiple witnesses . In this latter case the model can be used
   both in the case of a full transcription of all extant witnesses, and in the case of
   the full transcription of only one base-text, with the others witnesses
   reconstructible via collation. </p>
<p>The model aims to be independent of presuppositions made by any particular
   theoretical framework; therefore a couple of typical dichotomies in editorial theory
   have to be recognised and discussed.</p>
<div>
   <head>Fact (or record) vs. Interpretation</head>
   <p>In German editorial theory there is a well known opposition between what is there
      on the source document, the record, and the interpretation of this phenomenon
         (<emph>Befund und Deutung</emph>). This seems to imply that there is a way to
      talk about the record without any interpretation, but this is certainly not
      entirely correct, because everything we say about a text is based on
      interpretation (using a not very strict meaning of the word), in particular in the
      realm of genetic criticism.<note place="foot">See also the TEI’s (implicit)
         position on this point: “we define markup, or (synonymously) encoding, as any
         means of making explicit an <hi rend="italic">interpretation</hi> of a text”
         (TEI Guidelines: <emph>v. A Gentle Introduction to XML</emph>, <ptr
 target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SG.html"/>). See
         also reference to Robinson and Solopova 1993/1997: 21: “Any primary textual
         source… has its own semiotic system within it.[…] The two semiotic system are
         materially distinct, in that text written by hand is not the same as the text
         on the computer screen” (quoted in Robinson 2009:44-45).</note> On the other
      hand this truism cannot conceal the fact that there is an obvious difference
      between the interpretation that some trace of ink is indeed a specific letter and
      the assumption that a change in a manuscript at the first line has been made at
      the same time as the change in the next line because it adjusts the text to the
      new rhyme word introduced by the first change. Therefore we propose to talk about
      differing levels of interpretation as we might not be able to clearly
      differentiate between “what’s there” (document/fact) and “how does it relate”
      (text/interpretation).</p>
</div>
<div>
   <head>Document vs. Text</head>
   <p>In any branch of Manuscript Studies (Editing, Codicology, Palaeography, Art
      History, History) the first level of enquiry is always the document, the physical
      support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes. </p>
   <p>To understand the text that is contained in the manuscript, a deep study of the
      manuscript itself is fundamental: the layout, the type of script, the type of
      writing support, the binding and many other aspects are able to tell us about
      when, where and why this particular text was composed. The text therefore
      represents the second level of enquiry, not the first. In the case of modern draft
      manuscripts scholars must give detailed consideration to the layout, the different
      stratifications of writing and the disposition of these in the physical space; all
      of these, together with the understanding of the text, are required to gain
      insight about the composition, time of revisions, and flow of the text.
      Furthermore, for some kind of texts we know that the kind of physical support used
      to record them is not only influencing but also determining the text itself. For
      instance, the content and the length of letters are often determined from the size
      and quantity of paper available to the writer. </p>
   <p>Despite all of this, the TEI’s approach forces scholars to consider the text
      first. Of the two main hierarchies (text and document), the TEI privileges the
      text (hence <hi rend="italic">Text</hi> Encoding Initiative) and relegates
      topological description to empty elements (<gi>tei:pb/</gi>, <gi>tei:lb/</gi>,
         <gi>tei:cb/</gi>) or attributes (<gi>tei:add place=""</gi>, <gi>tei:note
         place=""</gi>). The TEI does not say that documents are not relevant, but that
      they are less relevant than texts; to use a bibliographical metaphor, texts are
         <soCalled>substantial</soCalled> while documents are
      <soCalled>accidental</soCalled>. </p>
   <p>The TEI does not handle the document level very well but for genetic editions this
      level is crucial. We should therefore offer two possible encoding: Document and
      Text.</p>
   <p>We should then clarify the way we will use the following words:</p>
   <list type="bulleted">
      <item><label>Document</label> the physical object, the manuscript or other primary
         source</item>
      <item><label>Text</label> the content of the document, the words written in their
         logical (non physical) sequence</item>
      <item><label>Facsimile</label> a surrogate representation (non necessarily
         digital) of the document (a photograph, a microfilm, a digital image)</item>
      <item><label>Document level</label> transcription of the content of a document
         according to its physical layout</item>
      <item><label>Text level</label> transcription of the content of a document
         according to its logical, semantic meaning </item>
      <item><label>Text stage</label> a reconstructible and possible timed stage of
         evolution of a text, represented by a document or by a revision campaign within
         one or more documents. </item>
   </list>
</div>
         </div>
         <div>
<head>Aspects of Genetic Editions</head>
<p>Modern genetic editions encode the genetic process within one manuscript and over the
   course of two or more manuscripts; in this latter case quite often they also offer a
   view on each of the manuscripts as an integral and self-contained object. This is
   because the manuscript view provides the material basis for the relationships
   established by the inter-manuscript relationship. Therefore we propose to
   differentiate between the following aspects of a genetic edition:</p>
<list type="bulleted">
   <item>
      <label>Document level</label>
      <list type="bulleted">
         <item>
 <label>The topological description</label> description of the layout of the
 text and the basis for a rendition of a text as a diplomatic transcription.</item>
         <item>
 <label>Alterations</label> like additions, deletions, substitutions.</item>
         <item>
 <label>Grouping Revisions</label> allows to group changes at different
 locations of one document, in order to create sets which express the
 editorial assumption that these changes have been undertaken in one
         stage.</item>
      </list>
   </item>
   <item>
      <label>Dossier level</label>
      <list type="bulleted">
         <item>
 <label>Genetic Grouping</label> allows to group phenomena in more than one
 document, in order to describe editorial assumption that these phenomena are
 related in some way.</item>
         <item>
 <label>Genetic Relations</label> allows to express the genetic relation
 between different parts of a text, and/or across several documents, as a
 series of steps on a path.</item>
         <item>
 <label>Collation and Critical Apparatus</label> allows to express the
 differences between texts as the result of a comparison between
         documents.</item>
      </list>
   </item>
   <item>
      <label>Manuscript and Dossier levels</label>
      <list type="bulleted">
         <item>
 <label>Chronology, Date and Time</label> the encoding of the chronology of
 the text or parts of it in absolute or relative time.</item>
         <item>
 <label>Documenting Editorial Decisions</label> allows to document the
 arguments which are the basis for editorial decisions to encode the text in
 a specific way including ways to express uncertainty and
         alternatives.</item>
      </list>
   </item>
</list>
<div>
   <head>Document level</head>
   <div>
      <head>Topological Description: the Document</head>
      <p>The topological description includes 4 hierarchically organised levels: <list
 type="bulleted">
 <item>Document<list type="bulleted">
       <item>Writing Surface (page, double page, folium, etc.) <list
 type="bulleted">
 <item>Zone <list type="bulleted">
       <item>Line (or <gi>tei:p</gi> or other block
       elements)</item>
    </list></item>
          </list></item>
    </list></item>
         </list>
         <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <document xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
    <writingSurface type="page">
       <docZone type="top-border" lrx="150" lry="228" ulx="0" uly="265">
          <line>here a line</line>
       </docZone>
       <docZone type="main-body" lrx="150" lry="0" ulx="0" uly="292">
          <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">here a paragraph</p>
       </docZone>
    </writingSurface>
 </document>
         </egXML>
      </p>
      <p><gi>ge:docZone</gi>s can be nest and grouped, can overlap and have a depth
         level (i.e belong to a <ref target="#text-stage">text stage</ref>). Their
         positioning respect the <gi>ge:docZone</gi> element is defined by cartesian
         coordinates, similar to the one used by the <gi>tei:zone</gi> element, with the
         difference that such coordinates should refer to the document and not to the
         facsimile. The element carries an <att>orientation</att> attribute which
         describes (in degrees) the orientation of the writing respect the main
         orientation of the writing surface as defined by the <gi>tei:msDesc</gi>.</p>
      <p>Zones are arbitrarily defined by the editors according to the layout of the
         writing surface (<gi>ge:writingSurface</gi>) and can make use of a standardised
         vocabulary (e.g. the top margin); zaones can also be defined according to
         semantic aspects (e.g. a semantically coherent group of text, a datable
         revision or addition). Their content can be: <list>
 <item><gi>ge:line</gi>: a sequence of lines of text</item>
 <item><gi>tei:p</gi> and other block paragraph-like elements</item>
 <item>a graphic/image </item>
         </list></p>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head xml:id="altrations">*Alterations</head>
      <p>Alterations occurs within a single manuscript, but it is an open question
         whether we can consider a sort of <soCalled>alteration</soCalled> also
         discrepancies amongst versions preserved by different manuscripts (dossier
         level). For instance, if by comparing (collating) two versions preserved by two
         witnesses we note a word has been added or deleted, shell we encode it with
 <gi>tei:add</gi> and <gi>tei:del</gi> as we would do when transcribing a
         single manuscript? Or do we need a complete new set of elements to do it? True
         is that in a genetic process it is totally arbitrary when an author stops
         revising the text within a given document and decides to move to a new document
         (i.e. copy it anew), so the two are indeed closely related. On the other hand
         we need to be able to differentiate somehow the two phenomena as the one within
         a single document are explicitly marked by the author, while the one detected
         by comparison are only implicitly so (and it may also happen that those
         implicit alteration were perhaps marked in a lost intermediate version). This
         remains an open problem (see <ref target="#collation">also</ref>).</p>
      <p>The following discussion relates to the alterations occurred at document level:
         for a discussion later whether to use them at dossier level also <ref
 target="#collation">see</ref>.</p>
      <div>
         <head>Additions</head>
         <p>Beside “normal” additions (see for instance the TEI definition of the
    <gi>tei:add</gi> element: “contains letters, words, or phrases inserted
 in the text by an author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.”), we have
 outlined some other special set of additions:</p>
         <list type="bulleted">
 <item><label>Repetitions</label> for which we have introduced a <gi
       xml:id="repe">ge:repetition type=""</gi> element. Repetitions can be
    of two main types:<list type="bulleted">
       <item>
          <label>Fixation</label> which results from authors fixing a text
          passage by overwriting it (e.g. a pencilled passage fixed with
          ink).</item>
       <item>
          <label>Clarification</label> a word is badly written and the author
          rewrites it to clarify. </item>
    </list></item>
 <item><label>*Alternatives</label> when an author proposes more alternative
    readings for a segment without deciding which is the best. For those
    cases the TEI already offers a system (<gi>tei:alt/</gi>) that might be
    adapted (i.e. semantically broadened or have attributes added). </item>
 <item xml:id="mm">
    <label>Meta-marks</label> (<gi>ge:metaMark</gi>): marginal notes and
    other additions to the text have to be differentiated from meta-marks
    commanding an alteration (e.g. “move this passage over there”) or the
    date of the beginning of a manuscript or a revision, which represent a
    sort of processing instruction of the document.</item>
         </list>
         <p>
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <add xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
       <metaMark xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
       >add</metaMark> is <metaMark
          xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
       >here</metaMark>
    </add>
 </egXML>
         </p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Deletions</head>
         <p>Beside “normal” deletions (see for instance the TEI definition for
    <gi>tei:del</gi>: “contains a letter, word, or passage deleted, marked as
 deleted, or otherwise indicated as superfluous or spurious in the copy text
 by an author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.”), we have outlined some
 other special set of deletions: </p>
         <list type="bulleted">
 <item><label>Marked as used </label>passages that happen to be stroked
    through, where the strike marks the passage as used/copied at another
    location/another manuscript. We have created two elements
    <gi>ge:used</gi> and <gi>ge:usedSpan/</gi> for that purpose.</item>
 <item><label>Overwriting</label> is a particular case of a deletion, unless
    it is a case of repetition (<ref target="#repe">see</ref>) or a false
    start (<ref target="#false-start">see</ref>).</item>
         </list>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Transpositions</head>
         <p>By transposition we mean words of blocks that are moved by the author in a
 different position by using arrows, asterisks or numbers. A possible
 approach (used, for instance by the <title>HNML</title>) would be to encode
 it as a substitution (i.e. considering the segment previous the
 transposition as deleted, substituted by the one after the transposition)
 but this will not work for transposition of blocks. </p>
         <list type="unordered">
 <item>A new encoding should be envisaged: <list type="bulleted">
       <item>First: make the segment to be transposed addressable, either via
          an identifiable empty element (<gi>ge:trSpan/</gi>) or via a
          “cross-cutting” <gi>tei:seg</gi> or similar.</item>
       <item>Secondly: markup meta-marks which might be in the text (e.g. a
          super linear “add <emph>is</emph> here” or numbers “3 2 4 1” or
          asterisks), with an element <gi>ge:metaMark</gi>.</item>
       <item>Relate the functional mark to the identified passages, either by
          referring to the passage added via attributes or implicitly because
          the <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> is contained in an <gi>tei:add</gi> or
 <gi>tei:del</gi>, as in the following example:</item>
    </list></item>
         </list>
         <p>
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <metaMark type="callout" function="#transp1"
       xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">2.</metaMark>
    <trSpan id="thisbird"
       xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"/>
    <line xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">This <del
          type="immediate" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">animal</del>
       bird is a species found in <undo target="#del2"
          xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
          <del id="del2" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"> dense </del>
       </undo> vegetation such as</line>
    <line xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"> reeds,
       bushes and thick undergrowth.</line>
    <trSpan spanTo="#thisbird"
       xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"/>
    <metaMark type="callout" function="#transp1"
       xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">1.</metaMark>
    <trSpan id="fivetosixeggs"
       xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"/>
    <line xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">5-6 eggs
       are laid in a nest in a low tree.</line>
    <trSpan spanTo="#fivetosixeggs"
       xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"/>
 </egXML>
         </p>
         <p>The re-alignment of the transposed blocks or segments can be supplied via a
 stand-off mechanism, to be used, for instance, within the
    <gi>tei:teiHeader</gi>:<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <profileDesc xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
       <transpositions
          xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
          <transposition id="transp1">
 <ptr target="#fivetosixeggs" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"/>
 <ptr target="#thisbird" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"/>
          </transposition>
       </transpositions>
    </profileDesc>
 </egXML>
         </p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>*Substitution</head>
         <p>The current TEI encoding consider a substitution as a mere couple of
 deletion/addition. Nevertheless there are cases in which the substitution
 include more material. The current <gi>tei:subst</gi> might therefore need a
 revision to allow more loose substitution like to following: <egXML
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">indisputably <subst><del>&amp;
 evidently</del> become
       <del>much</del><add>considerably</add></subst> worse</p>
 </egXML></p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>*Instant corrections and *false starts</head>
         <p>To distinguish instant correction from other kind of alterations is
 important for establishing the timing of a specific revisions and the whole
 genetic process. The information might be supplied as a specific attribute
 of <gi>tei:add/</gi>, <gi>tei:del/</gi>, <gi>tei:subst</gi> etc., called
    <att>*timing</att> (or <att>*instant</att> or similar).</p>
         <p>A specific subset of instant correction is represented by <hi rend="bold"
    xml:id="false-start">false starts</hi>, which are parts of a word that
 are overwritten by another (or stroked through), meaning that the author
 started to write a word, then changed his/her mind and overwrote all o part
 of what already written to fit the new word. This is an open problem: how to
 encode the partial word? Which is the scope of the correction? just the
 parts of the word that have been altered or all of it, even the one not
 actually written? In case it is possible to understand the word partially
 written how to encode it? Will <gi>tei:supplied</gi> a good candidate for
 that?</p>
         <p>Probably, in this latter case a new element should be added, called, perhaps
    <gi>ge:fStart</gi>, provided by a <att>scope</att>
    (<val>part</val>|<val>full</val>) and <att>method</att>
    (<val>overwrite</val>|<val>stroked</val> et simil.) attribute.<note
    place="foot"><hi rend="bold">EP</hi>: I think we should suggest a
       <att>method</att> attribute for <gi>tei:del</gi> as well, more
    specific than <att>rend</att>.</note></p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>Undoing alterations</head>
         <p>In some case authors take back alterations, e.g. a stroked through passage
 being restored via a dotted underlining, or a text that is firstly
 underlined, then the underline is deleted by a waving line. </p>
         <p>An element <gi>tei:restore</gi> already exists in TEI for undoing a
 deletion, but we need a more general approach, for instance to delete
 underling or a transposition. We have introduced an element <gi>ge:undo</gi>
 for that purpose provided by at attribute <att>target</att> pointing at the
 element to be undone: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <undo target="#und1"
       xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
       <hi rend="underline" id="und1" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
          >underline</hi>
    </undo>
 </egXML>
         </p>
         <p>Normally the element <gi>ge:undo</gi> would contain the element to be
 undone, a part in the cases of partial undoing as in the following example:
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <del id="del1" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"><ge:undo
          target="#del1" rev="#thirdRev"
          xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
       >is</ge:undo> nomadic</del>
 </egXML></p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head xml:id="text-stage">Grouping Revisions </head>
      <p>In some cases revisions can be attributed to a single campaign of revision (or
 <soCalled>text-stage</soCalled>), meaning we can say that a set of
         alterations (deletion, addition, substitution, transposition, etc.) are
         interrelated (i.e. one is a consequence of the other, they happened at the same
         time, etc.). To document this we need:<list type="bulleted">
 <item>A system to attribute an alteration or any other phenomena occurring
    at document level to a particular revision campaign/text-stage</item>
 <item>A way to describe a revision campaign/text-stage</item>
         </list></p>
      <p>For the former purpose ('attribute an alteration to a revision campaign') we
         have introduced a global attribute <att>ge:rev</att> that points to an
 <att>xml:id</att> attribute within an element describing a specific
         text-stage; the element provided for that purpose is <gi>ge:revDesc</gi> which
         can occur within the <gi>tei:teiHeader</gi> and groups the editorial reasons
         for stating that some alteration belong to a text-stage. Element
         <gi>ge:revDesc</gi> contains a sequence of <gi xml:id="revNote"
         >ge:revNote</gi>, each of them describing a single text-stage. Typically, a
 <gi>ge:revNote</gi> will contain several references to <gi>ge:edJust</gi>
         elements (see <ref target="#edjust">below</ref>) and to other annotations
         contained within the <gi>tei:Header</gi>.</p>
      <p>In many cases it is necessary to scope a portion of text in which one or more
         alteration occurs, in order to give the necessary context for any editorial
         discussion. For that purpose we have introduced an element
         <gi>ge:revision</gi>, which occurs within a <gi>ge:line</gi> or a
         <gi>tei:p</gi> or any block and phrasal level elements. As the element is
         likely to overlap with other hierarchies (in particular it is very likely to
         overlap with <gi>ge:line</gi> in case the editor has chosen to encode the
         document level), we also provide a <gi>ge:revSpan/</gi> empty element.</p>
   </div>
</div>
<div>
   <head>Dossier Level</head>
   <div>
      <head>*Genetic Grouping </head>
      <!--<p>Forming change-sets is necessary to group alterations of different text
         passages, all of which form one revision. This can be implemented either via a
         wrapping element (e.g. &lt;revision/&gt;) or via a stand-off mechanism for
         spatially disparate changes. </p>-->
      <p>Alterations, revisions and other compositional phenomena may need to be grouped
         at dossier level: it might in fact occur that authors correct two versions at a
 time,<note place="foot">Several examples available: Manzoni, for instance,
 was used to modify an old draft to see how a new variant fit with the
 context before coping it into a new draft.</note>or we might need to express
         that two or more documents are related in other ways; for instance, one can be
         the sequel of the other, they might have been drafted at the same time, or one
         might contain some other kind of analogy, like a newspaper article that inspire
         some kind of reflection contained in a given work. </p>
      <p>In those cases such a grouping can be encoded within a <gi>gi:geneticGrp</gi>
 element.<note place="foot"><hi rend="bold">EP</hi>: Sorry, but I don't like
 the name <gi>ge:textGroup</gi>, it is not clear enough. I appreciate we need
 a generic name, but we are not grouping texts, we are grouping: a)
 revisions; b) blocks (for instance when we want reorder chapters, as for
 Fotis' Kafka example; c) ???. I think <gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi> is
         clearer.</note> As the element <gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi> can be used more
         generally for any kind of genetic grouping, a <att>type</att> attribute is also
         provided. <gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi> contains a sequence of <gi
 xml:id="geneticNote">ge:geneticNote</gi> which <att>targets</att> attribute
         can refer to several <gi>ge:revNote</gi> of specific documents or to other
         annotations and editorial statements.</p>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head>Genetic Relations</head>
      <p>With <soCalled>genetic relations</soCalled> we intend the possibility of
         ordering different text-stages contained within a single document, or more
         probably, across different document into an ideal line of development, going,
         for instance from a version <hi rend="bold">A</hi> to a version <hi rend="bold"
 >B</hi> (that can be represented by a different document or by an
         editorially reconstructed text-stage), to a version <hi rend="bold">C</hi>,
         etc.</p>
      <p>To do so, we have introduced the concepts of <soCalled>steps</soCalled> and
 <soCalled>paths</soCalled> fro which we took inspiration from
         <title>HNML</title>.</p>
      <div>
         <head>Steps and Paths </head>
         <p>A <soCalled>step</soCalled> connects two versions (represented by two
 documents or by two reconstructed text-stages within the same document),
 while a <soCalled>path</soCalled> connects two or more steps.</p>
         <list type="bulleted">
 <item>
    <gi>ge:step</gi> embeds a <att>relation</att> attribute which points to
    description of a specific type of relation as defined by
       <gi>ge:geneticRel</gi> element (<ref target="#genRel">see</ref>); an
    attribute <att>cert</att> signifies the degree of certainty associated
    with the interpretation. Each <gi>ge:step</gi> element contains:<note
       place="foot"><hi rend="bold">EP</hi>: we need to clarify well the
       difference between a <gi>ge:step</gi> and a <gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi>, I
       am still not clear if we need both or only one
       (<gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi>, that is).</note><list type="bulleted">
       <item><gi xml:id="stepNote">ge:stepNote</gi>: an editorial declaration
          which describes the arguments to asses such a step.</item>
       <item><gi>ge:stepLink targets=""/</gi>: a pointer to the two textual
          versions that compose a step.</item>
       <item>
          <gi>ge:stepAlteration</gi>
          <note place="foot"><hi rend="bold">EP</hi>: guys I forgot why we
 need this!</note>
       </item>
    </list></item>
 <item>
    <gi>ge:path</gi> in the same way as <gi>ge:step</gi>, it embeds a
       <att>relation</att> attribute which points to description of a
    specific type of relation as defined by <gi>ge:geneticRel</gi> element
       (<ref target="#genRel">see</ref>); an attribute <att>cert</att>
    signifies the degree of certainty associated with the interpretation. A
       <gi>ge:path</gi> contains:<list type="bulleted">
       <item><gi xml:id="pathNote">ge:pathNote</gi>: an editorial declaration
          which presents the arguments for the assessment of such a path.</item>
       <item><gi>ge:pathLink targets=""</gi>: a pointer to the
          <gi>ge:step</gi> that compose the path.</item>
       <item><gi>ge:pathAlt</gi>: in some cases path can include alternatives
          routes, for instance when a specific connection is not sure, or
          when from a specific witness two or more (authorial) copies are
          derived. In this case the <gi>ge:pathAlt</gi> will include two or
          more <gi>ge:path</gi> elements and a <gi>gi:pathNote</gi>
          explaining the reasons for the bifurcation.</item>
    </list></item>
         </list>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>*Relationships</head>
         <p>The type of connections existing between two or more textual variants (a
 step) or two or more steps (a path) need to be declared and described in
 order to be used. We have therefore introduced the element <gi
    xml:id="genRel">ge:geneticRel</gi> to be used within the
    <gi>tei:profileDesc</gi>. A relation is defined in two ways: by a label
 (within a <gi>tei:label</gi>) and via attributes defining different
 properties, such as:</p>
         <list type="bulleted">
 <item><att>*transitivity</att>: the relation is transferable to all
    components of the group </item>
 <item><att>*symmetry</att>: the relation between A and B is equal to the
    relation there is between B and A<note place="foot"><hi rend="bold"
       >EP:</hi> In how much depth shall we define a relationship? How many
       characteristics should we include? Can relationships be defined within
       the TEI or, for instance, by advising the use of other graph-oriented
       markup languages like RDF/XML?</note></item>
         </list>
         <p>Examples of relations are:<list type="bulleted">
    <item><label>Time</label> one document or textual version follows or
       precede another</item>
    <item><label>Evolutionary</label> one document or textual version
       represent the evolution or the development of another</item>
    <item><label>Thematic</label> two or more documents concern the same
       topic </item>
    <item><label>Conceptual</label> two or more documents are connected in
       some logical way</item>
 </list></p>
      </div>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head xml:id="collation">*Collation and Critical Apparatus</head>
      <p>AS we already discussed (<ref target="#altrations">see</ref>), the moment in
         which the author decides to stop editing a draft and move to another draft is
         arbitrary, therefore alterations within a given document and alterations which
         results from the collation of different drafts of the same text are more
         conceptually connected than readings characterising different witnesses as a
         result of a scribal copy.</p>
      <p>For instance, if we have two draft documents of the same text, A and B, if a
         deletion occurs within A or B we would probably mark it with a <gi>tei:del</gi>
         element. On the other hand, when by comparing A and B we see a passage has been
         suppressed, we would also probably mark is as such. Whether we need another set
         of editorial elements or we should use the same set that are used for
         transcription is still an open problem. </p>
      <p>We can imagine at least two different scenarios:<list type="bulleted">
 <item>Only one document has been entirely transcribed (perhaps the first or
    the last version), while the others are only reconstructible via
    collation, which can be stored within the same document or in a separate
    one.</item>
 <item>All documents composing a dossier have been transcribed and the
    collation is stored in a separate document</item>
         </list></p>
      <div>
         <head>One document is transcribed</head>
         <p>If, beside the base-text which is fully transcribed, all extant witnesses
 have to be reconstruct via collation, it is mandatory to be able to
 distinguish alterations that happen within them and between witnesses. For
 instance, using the existing tag set we could possibly encode as follows:
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <app xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
       <rdg wit="#A" id="rdg1">here is a passage in A</rdg>
       <rdg wit="#B">
          <del>
 <ptr target="#A #rdg1"/>
          </del>
       </rdg>
    </app>
 </egXML></p>
         <p>Nevertheless, this might force the intended usage of <gi>tei:del</gi> and
 might imply that there is a deletion on B, which is not the case. This might
 be solved perhaps using the <att xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 >type</att> attribute or another attribute or creating a new element (say
    <gi>ge:interDel</gi>) for deletions deducted via collation, reserving
    <gi>tei:del</gi> for deletions that happen at document level.</p>
      </div>
      <div>
         <head>All documents are transcribed</head>
         <p>In this case we can assume that all alterations occurring at document level
 are already encoded within each transcription, therefore the collation will
 only need to point to passages within the separate files classifying the
 types of readings resulting from the collation: <egXML
    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <app xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
       <rdg wit="#A" from="#v34" to="#v36"/>
       <rdg wit="#B" from="#v33" type="suppressed"/>
    </app>
 </egXML>
         </p>
         <p>The exemplified encoding implies that attributes <att>from</att> and
 <att>to</att> are added for the <gi>tei:rdg</gi> element. </p>
      </div>
   </div>
</div>
<div>
   <head>Manuscript and Dossier Levels</head>
   <div>
      <head>Chronology, Date and Time</head>
      <p>We want to express chronology as <hi rend="bold">absolute</hi> and <hi
 rend="bold">relative</hi> measures. Absolute time is the unambiguous
         reference to a calendar and time schema, while relative timing is express
         events as happened <hi rend="italic">before</hi> and/or <hi rend="italic"
         >after</hi> another event. Relative time can also be expressed by the relation
         to the (known or unknown) creation of another document or text. Dating can be
         justified by prose and/or by reference to a characteristic of a manuscript
         (e.g. hand, ink, etc.). The outlining of a chronology for a document or dossier
         can then be used as an argument to determine the existence of a text-stage.</p>
      <p>We might be able to express <hi rend="bold">absolute time</hi> by adapting
         existing element/attributes (<gi>tei:timeline/</gi> is a likely candidate), but
         more probably we need to create another element.</p>
      <p>For absolute timing we envisage two cases that can occur separately or in
         combination:</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
         <item>The dating of a witness (a manuscript part of a dossier) or of a zone may
 not be directly documented within its content, i.e. it can be deduced from
 external facts and documents. The editorial date attribution should be
 included in the <gi>tei:teiHeader</gi>. </item>
         <item>Dates can be found in the document as added by the author as sort of
 metadata (for instance the date of the beginning/ending of writing on aa
 specific document, or the date of a revision campaign); those should be
 encoded without necessarily adding them in the <gi>tei:teiHeader</gi> (they
 can be considered a type of <hi rend="bold">meta-mark</hi>: see <ref
    target="#mm">below</ref>)</item>
      </list>
      <p>We might express <hi rend="bold">relative time</hi> as
         predecessor/successor-relationships</p>
      <list type="bulleted">
         <item>It might be a direct relationship: <att>next</att>, <att>previous</att>,
    <att>sync</att>.</item>
         <item>It might be a “sorting” relationship: <att>before</att>,
 <att>after</att>.</item>
         <item>Temporal relative relationships may also be expressed via a numbering
 scheme (<val>0</val>, <val>1</val>, <val>2</val>, …) within a
 <att>*relTime</att> ('relative time') attribute. In this case we assume a
    <hi rend="bold">default</hi> timeline (the time of writing and of the
    <ref target="#instCor">instant corrections</ref>) which is represented by
    <val>0</val>, and successive revision-times (<val>1</val>, <val>2</val>,
 etc.)</item>
      </list>
      <p>Information about absolute or relative time can be given on all levels of a
         text or document. </p>
   </div>
   <div>
      <head>Documenting Editorial Decisions</head>
      <p>As genetic editions and genetic editing are essentially interpretative,
         documenting editorial decisions has a fundamental and central role. </p>
      <p>Different forms of documentation have been discussed before on several of the
         previous sections: <list type="bulleted">
 <item><gi>ge:revNote</gi>: documents the constitution of a text-stage (<ref
       target="#revNote">see</ref>) </item>
 <item><gi>ge:geneticNote</gi>: documents the constitution of a genetic group
       (<ref target="#geneticNote">see</ref>)</item>
 <item><gi>ge:stepNote</gi>: arguments the assessment of a connection between
    to text-stages (a step, <ref target="#stepNote">see</ref>)</item>
 <item><gi>ge:pathNote</gi>: discuss the arguments for the creation of a
    connection between two or more steps (<ref target="#pathNote"
 >see</ref>)</item>
         </list>All these elements embed a <att>cert</att> attribute to declare the
         level of certainty; all of them should make a large use of <att>xml:id</att> to
         be pointed from many somewhere in the text.</p>
      <p>But annotations can also occurs in-line (i.e. close to a textual fragment they
         relate to) and for that reasons we created the <gi xml:id="edjust"
         >ge:edJust</gi> global element which should always be used with an
         <att>xml:id</att> attribute as the other types of annotations seen above are
         very likely to refer to specific points in the text within a more complex
         argumentation. The <att>target</att> attribute points to the element to be
         annotated, while the <att>locus</att> attribute points to the concept to be
         justified. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <edJust target="#origDate" locus="suppliedContent"  xmlns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
    <p  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The diary entry <ref target="#apr1date"> is dated</ref>. The entry
       precedes the <ref type="edjust" target="#samaria"> other text on the
          witness</ref> by 22 years, as the <ref type="edjust"
          target="#inkanalysis"> ink analysis </ref> shows. </p>
 </edJust>
         </egXML></p>
   </div>
</div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
<head>ODD</head>
<p>TEI Extension for Genetic Editions&#xD;&#xD; preliminary version</p>
<schemaSpec ident="geneticTEI" docLang="en" prefix="tei_" start="TEI" xml:lang="en"
   targetLang="en">
   <moduleRef key="core"/>
   <moduleRef key="tei"/>
   <moduleRef key="header"/>
   <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
   <moduleRef key="certainty"/>
   <moduleRef key="analysis"/>
   <moduleRef key="drama"/>
   <moduleRef key="iso-fs"/>
   <moduleRef key="linking"/>
   <moduleRef key="msdescription"/>
   <moduleRef key="nets"/>
   <moduleRef key="textcrit"/>
   <moduleRef key="transcr"/>
   <moduleRef key="verse"/>
   <moduleRef key="gaiji"/>
   <!-- topographical document structure -->
   <elementSpec ident="document" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>Document-centric description of a primary source, containing topographical
         information as well as a transcriptions</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.resourceLike"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:ref name="writingSurface"/>
         </rng:oneOrMore>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="writingSurface" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc> A surface on which text is written. </desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:ref name="docZone"/>
         </rng:oneOrMore>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <classSpec ident="att.coordinated" type="atts" mode="change" module="tei">
      <attList>
         <attDef ident="orient" mode="add">
 <desc>(orientation) The orientation of the coordinate system in which the
    parameters ulx, uly, lrx, lry are given. In arc degrees. The rotation is
    clockwise.</desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.numerical"/>
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
      </attList>
   </classSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="docZone" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc> A zone or block of text that is constituted by its graphical shape or by
         any other criterion.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
         <memberOf key="att.coordinated"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <!-- is such a model possible in ODD?
 
 <rng:optional xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
     <rng:choice>
         <rng:group>
 <rng:attribute name="x"> </rng:attribute>
 <rng:attribute name="y"/>
 <rng:attribute name="width"/>
 <rng:attribute name="height"/>
 <rng:attribute name="coordSys"/>
         </rng:group>
         <rng:attribute name="ref"/>
     </rng:choice>
 </rng:optional>
 <rng:optional xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
     <rng:attribute name="depth"/>
 </rng:optional>
 -->
         <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:choice>
    <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
    <rng:ref name="line"/>
    <rng:ref name="docZone"/>
 </rng:choice>
         </rng:zeroOrMore>
      </content>
      <attList>
         <!-- using existing att.coordinated instead
     
           <attDef ident="x">
     <desc> The x coordinate of the upper left corner of the rectangular
         zone, expressed in the specified coordinate system</desc>
     <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 name="data.numeric"/>
     </datatype>
 </attDef>

 <attDef ident="y">
     <desc> The y coordinate of the upper left corner of the rectangular
         zone, expressed in the specified coordinate system</desc>
     <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 name="data.numeric"/>
     </datatype>
 </attDef>

 <attDef ident="width">
     <desc> The width of the rectangular zone, expressed in the specified
         coordinate system</desc>
     <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 name="data.numeric"/>
     </datatype>
 </attDef>

 <attDef ident="height">
     <desc> The height of the rectangular zone, expressed in the specified
         coordinate system</desc>
     <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 name="data.numeric"/>
     </datatype>
 </attDef>
 -->
         <attDef ident="ref">
 <desc> A reference to an arbitrary object that describes the placement and
    extent of the zone (such as an SVG element in an external file). The use
    of this attribute is exclusive of giving x/y-coordinates directly. </desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
       name="data.pointer"/>
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
         <attDef ident="depth">
 <desc> Establishes an order on sets of zones in respect to their overlay.
    Greater depth signifies that a zone lies under another zone with lesser
    depth, i.e. was brought to paper earlier.</desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
       name="data.pointer"/>
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
      </attList>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="line">
      <desc>Marks a topographic line in the source document</desc>
      <content>
         <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"
 xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <!-- editorial justification -->
   <elementSpec ident="edJust" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>(editorial justification) An editorial justification of any part of
         the&#xD; edited text.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.global"/>
         <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
         <memberOf key="model.headerPart"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="model.pLike"/>
      </content>
      <attList>
         <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
 <desc>Points to the element to be justified.</desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
       name="data.pointer"/>
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
         <attDef ident="locus" mode="add">
 <desc>The location of the content to be justified.</desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"
    />
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
      </attList>
   </elementSpec>
   <!-- authorial changes -->
   <elementSpec ident="revDesc" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>(revision description) A description of the various revisions that occurred
         in the text&#xD; genesis.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.headerPart"/>
      </classes>
      <content xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
         <rng:choice xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:oneOrMore>
    <rng:ref name="tei_model.pLike"/>
 </rng:oneOrMore>
 <rng:group>
    <rng:optional>
       <rng:ref name="tei_summary"/>
    </rng:optional>
    <rng:oneOrMore>
       <rng:ref name="tei_revNote"/>
    </rng:oneOrMore>
 </rng:group>
         </rng:choice>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="revNote" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>Describes a revision in the text genesis.</desc>
      <classes/>
      <content>
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 name="macro.specialPara"/>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="revision">
      <desc>Groups contained changes in the document to one revision. Changes are those
         indicated by add, del and other elements of model.pPart.transcriptional, as
         well as the undo, repetition and transposition elements.The rev attribute
         points to a description of the revision.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:choice>
    <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
    <rng:ref name="line"/>
    <rng:ref name="docZone"/>
 </rng:choice>
         </rng:zeroOrMore>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="metaMark" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>(meta mark) A textual or graphical element in a manuscript that is
         functional but not part of the text. Could transform the text, like a
         strikethrough, or provide meta-information, like a date.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
         <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.specialPara"/>
      </content>
      <attList>
         <attDef ident="function" mode="add">
 <desc>Points to the function (e.g. add, delete) of the mark.</desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
       name="data.pointer"/>
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
      </attList>
   </elementSpec>
   <classSpec ident="att.global" type="atts" mode="change" module="tei">
      <attList>
         <attDef ident="rev" mode="add">
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
      </attList>
   </classSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="used" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>In many cases, authors mark portions of text as having been used, usually
         meaning the text has been transcribed to a fair copy. The mark is often a
         strikethrough, but can be any author-specific mark.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:choice>
    <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
    <rng:ref name="line"/>
    <rng:ref name="docZone"/>
 </rng:choice>
         </rng:zeroOrMore>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="undo" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>Marks up an action represented by an element to be undone.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 name="macro.specialPara"/>
      </content>
      <attList>
         <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
 <desc>The element representing the action to be undone.</desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
       name="data.pointer"/>
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
      </attList>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="subst" module="transcr" mode="change">
      <attList>
         <attDef ident="type" mode="add">
 <desc>The type of substitution.</desc>
 <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"
    />
 </datatype>
         </attDef>
      </attList>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="repetition" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>A clarification of already written text.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.global"/>
         <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
         <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 name="macro.specialPara"/>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="unclear" module="core" mode="change">
      <classes mode="replace">
         <memberOf key="model.choicePart" mode="add"/>
         <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional" mode="add"/>
         <memberOf key="att.editLike" mode="add"/>
         <memberOf key="att.typed" mode="add"/>
      </classes>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="transpositions" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc> Describes the textual transpositions.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.profileDescPart"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:ref name="transposition"/>
         </rng:oneOrMore>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="transposition" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc> Describes a textual transposition. Contains a list of pointers that
         specifies the new order of the text fragments. </desc>
      <content>
         <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
 <rng:ref name="ptr"/>
         </rng:oneOrMore>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <!-- authorial changes: spanning -->
   <elementSpec ident="revisionSpan">
      <desc>Groups contained changes in the document to one revision. Changes are those
         indicated by add, del and other elements of model.pPart.transcriptional, as
         well as the undo, repetition and transposition elements.The rev attribute
         points to a description of the revision.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
         <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
      </classes>
      <content> </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="usedSpan" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>In many cases, authors mark portions of text as having been used, usually
         meaning the text has been transcribed to a fair copy. The mark is often a
         strikethrough, but can be any author-specific mark.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
         <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <empty xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="trSpan" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" mode="add">
      <desc>(transposition) A part of the text that has been moved to a different
         location.</desc>
      <classes>
         <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
         <memberOf key="model.global"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
         <empty xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <!-- genetic relations -->
   <elementSpec ident="node" module="nets" mode="change">
      <classes mode="change">
         <memberOf mode="add" key="attribute.pointing"/>
      </classes>
      <attList>
         <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
 <desc> A link to the element or passage represented by the node.</desc>
 <datatype>
    <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
       name="data.pointing"/>
 </datatype>
 </attDef>
      </attList>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="arc" module="nets" mode="change">
      <classes mode="change">
 <memberOf mode="add" key="att.typed"/>
      </classes>
   </elementSpec>
   <!-- spanning text structure -->
   <elementSpec ident="divSpan" module="textstructure" mode="add">
      <desc>(text division) contains a subdivision of the front, body, or back of a
 text.</desc>
      <classes>
 <memberOf mode="add" key="model.divLike"/>
 <memberOf mode="add" key="att.spanning"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
 <empty xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
   <elementSpec ident="pSpan" module="core" mode="add">
      <desc>(paragraph) marks paragraphs in prose.</desc>
      <classes>
 <memberOf mode="add" key="model.pLike"/>
 <memberOf mode="add" key="att.spanning"/>
      </classes>
      <content>
 <empty xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
      </content>
   </elementSpec>
</schemaSpec>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
