<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
 xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
 xmlns:ge="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">An Encoding Model for Genetic Editions</title>
            <author>Fotis Jannidis, Elena Pierazzo, Malte Rehbein</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="2">Draft</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>TEI MS SIG, Genetic Edition Workgroup</authority>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born Digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
            <date>08 May 2009</date>
            <desc>Conversion from MS Word</desc>
         </change>
         <change>
            <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
            <date>01 August 2009</date>
            <desc>Major update following Paris' Workshop</desc>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <divGen type="toc"/>
         <pb/>
         <div>
            <head>About this Document</head>
            <p>This document contains the <hi rend="bold">draft</hi> of an encoding model for
               Genetic Editions and Genetic Editing. The document is the product of a Workgroup on
               Genetic Editions (chair: Fotis Jannidis), which is part of the TEI MS SIG (chairs:
               Elena Pierazzo, Malte Rehbein, Amanda Galley). </p>
            <p>The purpose of this workgroup is to try to elaborate an <hi rend="bold">Application
                  Profile</hi> able to encode genetic editions and, in general, genetic phenomena.
               The application profile will discuss how to use existing TEI elements in a genetic
               framework, presenting, where necessary, new elements and will take the form of a TEI
               extension. </p>
            <p>With respect to the <title>TEI P5 Guidelines</title>, the present document aims to
               integrate Chapter 11. <title>Representation of Primary Sources</title> and Chapter
               12. <title>Critical Apparatus</title>. It might be the case that it will, at the end
               of the process described in the following section, constitute a self standing new
                  <title>Guidelines</title> chapter, but this decision will be taken later on.</p>
            <p>The current state of this document reflects the discussion held in three different
               meetings:</p>
            <list >
               <item>MS SIG meeting held in London during the annual members’ TEI meeting (November
                  2008); the minutes of the meeting can be found here: <ptr
                     target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Minutes_London_2008"/>.</item>
               <item>Genetic Edition workgroup held in London (March 2009); minutes can be found
                  here: <ptr target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Minutes_London_03-2009"/>. </item>
               <item>Workshop "Genetic Editions in a Digital Framework", held in Paris, 14/15 May
                  2009, and following discussion; programme of the workshop can be found here: <ptr
                     target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/GeneticEditionsWorkshopParis"/></item>
            </list>
            <p>The working group has made a large use of the <title>HNML. HyperNietzsche Markup
                  Language</title> and following versions (<title>GML Genetic Markup
                  Language</title>) written by Paolo D'Iorio and collaborators for the
               HyperNietzsche project. We would like to thank Paolo D'Iorio for his invaluable
               contribution in the early stages of the work. </p>
            <div>
               <head>Methodology</head>
               <p>The stages we will follow to complete the present encoding model are the
                  following:</p>
               <list >
                  <item>Initially, we will work on a pseudo-encoding which is tightly bound to our
                     own terminology <hi rend="italic">[Stage completed on July 2009]</hi>.</item>
                  <item>In a second step we will try to map this pseudo-encoding to the actual TEI
                     encoding framework, in cooperation with Lou Burnard. The result will be
                     presented at TEI' Members Meeting 2009.</item>
                  <item>The same step-by-step approach will be taken for the standardisation
                     process: <list >
                        <item>First we develop an application profile, that is, a well-documented
                           TEI customisation.</item>
                        <item>This will be presented to te TEI Council as a proposed modification of
                           the TEI</item>
                        <item>If the TEI Council approves it, the Council will also decide how it
                           should be integrated into the current <title>Guidelines</title>.</item>
                     </list></item>
               </list>
<p>All versions of the draft will be publicly available for discussions and feedback
    from the community. Versions will be hosted on the TEI Wiki as PDF documents,
    while the XML source will be stored in the TEI SVN repository.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
 <head>Conventions used</head>
 <p>Although the entire document is a draft and therefore susceptible of changes, some
    sections are less stable than others. In particular, when a section or a
    particular element requires further discussion or is considered an open problem,
    such a section or element is marked by a * mark.</p>
 <p>All newly introduced elements are marked by the namespace prefix <hi rend="bold"
       >ge:</hi>, while TEI elements are not marked by any namespace prefix.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Theoretical Framework</head>
            <p>The genetic approach differentiates from a more traditional text study approach
 because it is not only interested on 'what is on the page', but also to reconstruct
 the <hi rend="bold">process</hi> necessary to produce 'what is on the page'.</p>
            <p>The encoding model will present how to handle <hi rend="bold">Genetic
    Transcription</hi> (a transcription of a single document), how to reconstruct a
    <hi rend="bold">Genetic Dossier</hi>, meaning how to describe genetic relations
 amongst multiple witnesses, and how to prepare a <hi rend="bold">Genetic Edition</hi>
 based on a single or multiple witnesses. In this latter case the model can be used
 both in the case of a full transcription of all extant witnesses, and in the case of
 the full transcription of only one base-text, with the others witnesses
 reconstructable via collation. </p>
            <p>The model aims to be independent of presuppositions made by any particular
 theoretical framework; therefore a couple of typical dichotomies in editorial theory
 have to be recognised and discussed.</p>
            <div>
 <head>Fact (or record) vs. Interpretation</head>
 <p>In German editorial theory there is a well known opposition between what is there
    on the source document, the record (<foreign>Befund</foreign>), and the
    interpretation of this phenomenon (<foreign>Deutung</foreign>). This seems to
    imply that there is a way to talk about the record without any interpretation, but
    this is certainly not entirely correct, because everything we say about a text is
    based on interpretation (using a not very strict meaning of the word), in
    particular in the realm of genetic criticism.<note place="foot">See also the TEI’s
       (implicit) position on this point: <q>we define markup, or (synonymously)
          encoding, as any means of making explicit an <hi rend="italic"
             >interpretation</hi> of a text</q> (TEI Guidelines: <ref
          target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SG.html">v. A
          Gentle Introduction to XML</ref>). See also reference to Robinson and
       Solopova 1993/1997: 21: <q>Any primary textual source… has its own semiotic
          system within it.[…] The two semiotic system are materially distinct, in
          that text written by hand is not the same as the text on the computer
          screen</q>.</note> On the other hand this truism cannot conceal the fact
    that there is an obvious difference between the interpretation that some trace of
    ink is indeed a specific letter and the assumption that a change in a manuscript
    at the first line has been made at the same time as the change in the next line
    because it adjusts the text to the new rhyme word introduced by the first change.
    Therefore we propose to talk about differing levels of interpretation as we might
    not be able to clearly differentiate between “what’s there” (document/fact) and
    “how does it relate” (text/interpretation).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
 <head>Document vs. Text</head>
 <p>In every branch of Manuscript Studies (Editing, Codicology, Palaeography, Art
    History, History) the first level of enquiry is always the document, the physical
    support that lies in front of the scholar’s eyes. </p>
 <p>To understand the text that is contained in the manuscript, a deep study of the
    manuscript itself is fundamental: the layout, the type of script, the type of
    writing support, the binding and many other aspects are able to tell us about
    when, where and why this particular text was composed. The text therefore
    represents the second level of enquiry, not the first. In the case of modern draft
    manuscripts scholars must give detailed consideration to the layout, the different
    stratifications of writing and the disposition of these in the physical space; all
    of these, together with the understanding of the text, are required to gain
    insight about the composition, time of revisions, and flow of the text.
    Furthermore, for some kind of texts we know that the kind of physical support used
    to record them not only influences but may actually determine the text itself. For
    instance, the content and the length of letters are often determined by the size
    and quantity of paper available to the writer. </p>
 <p>The TEI has traditionally prioritised the text level. Of the two possible main hierarchies
    potentially available to someone transcribing a primary source (text and
    document), the TEI privileges the text (hence <hi rend="italic">Text</hi> Encoding
    Initiative) and relegates physical, topographical layout to empty elements
       (<gi>pb/</gi>, <gi>lb/</gi>, <gi>cb/</gi>) or attributes (<gi>add
    place=""</gi>, <gi>note place=""</gi>). The TEI does not say that documents are
    not relevant, but that they are less relevant than texts; to use a bibliographical
    metaphor, texts are <soCalled>substantial</soCalled> while documents are
       <soCalled>accidental</soCalled>. </p>
 <p>However, for genetic editions a focus on the document is  crucial. In many cases, 
    the only way to reconstruct the process of writing and re-writing
    which leads to a new text is to examine a
    specific document. We therefore propose to complement the existing
    text-focussed approach with a new encoding
    scheme focussed instead on the document.</p>
 <p>We should then clarify the way we will use the following words:</p>
 <list >
    <item><label>Document</label> the physical object, the manuscript or other primary
       source</item>
    <item><label>Text</label> the content of the document, the words written in their
       logical (non physical) sequence</item>
    <item><label>Facsimile</label> a surrogate representation (non necessarily
       digital) of the document (a photograph, a microfilm, a digital image)</item>
    <item><label>Document level</label> transcription of the content of a document
       according to its physical layout</item>
    <item><label>Text level</label> transcription of the content of a document
       according to its logical, semantic meaning </item>
    <item><label>Text stage</label> a reconstructible and possible timed stage of
       evolution of a text, represented by a document or by a revision campaign within
       one or more documents. </item>
 </list>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Aspects of Genetic Editions</head>
            <p>Modern genetic editions encode the genetic process within one manuscript and over the
 course of two or more manuscripts; in this latter case quite often they also offer a
 view of each of the manuscripts as a single self-contained object. This is because
 the manuscript view provides the material basis for the relationships established by
 the inter-manuscript relationship. Therefore we propose to differentiate between the
 following aspects of a genetic edition:</p>
            <list >
 <item>
    <label>Document level</label>
    <list >
       <item>
          <label>The topological description</label> description of the layout of the
          text and the basis for a rendition of a text as a diplomatic
          transcription.</item>
       <item>
          <label>Textual Alterations</label> like additions, deletions,
          substitutions.</item>
       <item>
          <label>Grouping Modifications</label> groups of changes at different
          locations of one document, used to create sets which express the editorial
          assumption that these changes have been undertaken in one stage.</item>
    </list>
 </item>
 <item>
    <label>Dossier level</label>
    <list >
       <item>
          <label>Comparison</label> (Collation) expresses the differences between
          texts as the result of a comparison between documents.</item>
       <item>
          <label>Genetic Grouping</label> groups phenomena in more than one document,
          in order to describe editorial assumption that these phenomena are related
          in some way.</item>
       <item>
          <label>Genetic Relations</label> describes the genetic relation between
          different parts of a text,<note place="foot">As in the case where a document
             describes the ordering of parts of a text contained in another document.
             It is the case, for instance of Beckett's <title>That Time</title> where
             the speeches of A, B and C are obsessively first subdivided and
             subsequently shuffled and reshuffled by the means of sequences of letters
             and numbers contained in a number of documents.</note> and/or across
          several documents, as a series of steps on a path.</item>
    </list>
 </item>
 <item>
    <label>Document and Dossier levels</label>
    <list >
       <item>
          <label>Chronology, Date and Time</label> the encoding of the chronology of
          the text or parts of it in absolute or relative time.</item>
       <item>
          <label>Documenting Editorial Decisions</label> documents the arguments which
          are the basis for editorial decisions to encode the text in a specific way
          including ways to express uncertainty and alternatives.</item>
    </list>
 </item>
            </list>
            <div>
 <head>Document level</head>
 <div>
    <head>The Document-based Transcription </head>
    <p>The document-based transcription includes 4 hierarchically organised levels:
          <list >
          <item>Document<list >
  <item>Writing Surface (page, double page, folium, etc.) <list
        >
        <item>zone <list >
              <item>Line (or <gi>p</gi> or other block elements)</item>
           </list></item>
     </list></item>
             </list></item>
       </list></p>
    <p>We propose to use introduce a new element, <gi>ge:document</gi> to encode a
       document-based transcription, as an alternative to <gi>text</gi>, and to use a
       modified version of <gi>surface</gi> and <gi>div</gi>.</p>
    <p>A <gi>ge:document</gi> contains a sequence of <gi>surface</gi> elements. The
          <gi>surface</gi> element has been added a <att>type</att> attribute which
       suggested values are <val>page</val>, <val>leaf</val>, and similar. The
       orientation of the writing surface is defined either by a set of cartesian
       coordinates (measured from the top left corner) or implicitly stated by width
       and height of the page recorded within <gi>msDesc</gi> (namely within
          <gi>dimension</gi> or <gi>measure</gi> within <gi>objectDesc</gi>). </p>
    <p>The <gi>surface</gi> element contains a sequence of
    <gi>zone</gi> elements.
       <gi>zone</gi>s can be nested and grouped, can overlap and have a sequence level
       (i.e belong to a <ref target="#text-stage">text stage</ref>), expressed by the
          <att>seq</att> attribute. Their positioning with respect to the
          <gi>surface</gi> element is defined by cartesian coordinates, measured from
       the top left corner. The element carries an <att>sOrient</att> attribute which
       describes (in degrees) the orientation that the surface has taken to enable the
       content (writing, images) in that <gi>div</gi>, with respect to the normal
       orientation of the <gi>surface</gi>. Note that the mechanism aims to describes
       the process by which the content of a specific <gi>div</gi> has been supplied
       (i.e. the author has physically rotate the writing surface) more that the
       orientation of the writing.</p>
    <p>Zones are arbitrarily defined by the editors according to the layout of the
       writing surface and can make use of a standardised vocabulary (e.g. the top
       margin). In some cases they represents physical divisions, like when patches
       are pinned or glued to the main surface. Their content can be: <list>
          <item><gi>ge:line</gi>: a sequence of lines of text</item>
          <item>a <gi>p</gi> or other block paragraph-like elements</item>
          <item>a graphic/image </item>
       </list></p>
    <p>In the following we can easily detect two main areas of writing, the diary
       entry (black ink) and another (supposedly later) annotation in blue ink. <figure>
          <graphic url="constr_example/D1-thumb.png"/>
       </figure>In order to add the annotation in the blue ink, the diary page has
       been rotated 90° clockwise by the author. The page can be transcribed as
       follows (transcription line by line):</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
       <ge:document>
          <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
             <zone seq="0" ulx="10" uly="43" lrx="185" lry="84" sOrient="0" unit="mm">
  <ge:line>
     <date xml:id="apr1date" rend="right">1 April 2009 </date>
  </ge:line>
  <ge:line>Fed Birds in the park today.</ge:line>
  <ge:line>Might write an article about </ge:line>
  <ge:line>the Thick-billed Warbler. </ge:line>
             </zone>
             <zone seq="1" ulx="9" uly="20" lrx="70" lry="60" sOrient="90" unit="mm">
  <ge:line>Samaria is a Greek </ge:line>
  <ge:line>brand of water that</ge:line>
  <ge:line>comes from the natural</ge:line>
  <ge:line>springs of Stilos, in </ge:line>
  <ge:line>Crete </ge:line>
             </zone>
          </surface>
       </ge:document>
    </egXML>
    <p>Second option (textual transcription within a document-based transcription)</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
       <ge:document>
          <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
             <zone seq="0" ulx="10" uly="43" lrx="185" lry="84" sOrient="0" unit="mm">
  <dateline>
     <date rend="right"> 1 April 2009 </date>
  </dateline>
  <p>Fed Birds in the park today.<lb/> Might write an article about
     <lb/> the Thick-billed Warbler. </p>
             </zone>
             <zone seq="1" ulx="9" uly="20" lrx="70" lry="60" sOrient="90" unit="mm">
  <p>Samaria is a Greek <lb/> brand of water that <lb/> comes from the
     natural <lb/> springs of Stilos, in <lb/> Crete</p>
             </zone>
          </surface>
       </ge:document>
    </egXML>
    <p>A document-based transcription, which is done page-by-page and possibly
       line-by-line, is very likely to generate overlapping with all block level
       elements. We have therefore introduced a new class of elements called
       model.spanning which groups all elements that can be eventually spanned across
       pages and lines. All those elements have been provided with an
          <att>spanTo</att> attribute: when such an attribute is in use, the element
       must be empty. See the previous example encoded with spanned elements:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
       <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
          <zone seq="0" ulx="10" uly="43" lrx="185" lry="84" sOrient="0" unit="mm">
             <zone spanTo="#end"/>
             <dateline>
  <date rend="right"> 1 April 2009 </date>
             </dateline>
             <p xml:id="p1" spanTo="#p2"/> Fed Birds in the park today.<lb/> Might
             write an article about <lb/> the Thick-billed Warbler. </zone>
          <zone seq="1" ulx="9" uly="20" lrx="70" lry="60" sOrient="90" unit="mm">
             <p xml:id="p2" spanTo="end"/> Samaria is a Greek <lb/> brand of water
             that <lb/> comes from the natural <lb/> springs of Stilos, in <lb/> Crete
  <anchor xml:id="end"/>
          </zone>
       </surface>
    </egXML>
<!-- treat patches as something else not zones -->
    <p>In case of glued/pinned patches, the <gi>zone</gi> can make use of the attribute
          <att>patch</att> which value will be a description of the kind of patch
       (e.g.: <val>flipping</val>, <val>attached</val>, <val>detached</val>, etc.) and
       by the attribute <att>binder</att> describe the method by which it is connected
       to the main surface (e.g.: <val>glue</val>, <val>pins</val>,
       <val>staples</val>, etc.); dimensions can also be provided using
          <att>height</att> and <att>width</att> (please notice that they have to be
       expressed in the same unit given by <att>unit</att> attribute).</p>
    <p>An example of patches can be seen in one of the first draft of the poem
       eventually titled <title>The Sleeper</title> by Walt Whitman (see <ptr
          target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/duk.00258.001.jpg"
       />), which could be encoded as follows:</p>
    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
       <surface>
          <div>
             <head>Poem</head>
             <l>As in Visions...</l>
          </div>
          <div seq="0" patch="attached" binder="glue" heigth="40" width="90" unit="mm"
             ulx="23" uly="62" lrx="113" lry="102"> [first patch] </div>
          <div seq="0" patch="attached" binder="glue" heigth="35" width="90" unit="mm"
             ulx="25" uly="64" lrx="115" lry="99"> [second patch] </div>
       </surface>
    </egXML>
 </div>
 <div xml:id="alterations">
    <head>*Textual Alterations</head>
    <p>Alterations occurs within a single manuscript, but it is an open question
       whether we can consider discrepancies amongst versions preserved by different
       manuscripts (dossier level) also as a sort of <soCalled>alteration</soCalled>.
       For instance, if by comparing (collating) two versions preserved by two
       witnesses we note a word has been added or deleted, should we encode it, within
       a collation, with <gi>add</gi> or <gi>del</gi> as we would when transcribing a
       single manuscript? Or do we need a completely new set of elements to do it? In
       a genetic process, at any point the author can decide to stop revising the text
       within a given document and decide to move to a new document (i.e. copy it
       anew), so the two phenomena (alterations at document level and alterations at
       dossier level) are indeed closely related. On the other hand we need to
       differentiate them because the one within a single document is explicitly
       marked by the author, while the one detected by comparison is only implicit. It
       may also happen that implicit alterations were perhaps marked in a lost
       intermediate version. This remains an open problem (see <ref
          target="#collation">also</ref>).</p>
    <p>The following discussion relates to the alterations at document level: for a
       discussion of their use at dossier level also <ref target="#collation"
          >see</ref> below.</p>
    <div>
       <head>Additions</head>
       <p>Beside “normal” additions (see for instance the TEI definition of the
             <gi>add</gi> element: <q>contains letters, words, or phrases inserted in
             the text by an author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.</q>), we have
          outlined some other special kinds of additions, where text is added to the
          document but not to the text:</p>
       <list >
          <item><label>Repetitions</label> which can be of two main types:<list
  >
  <item>
     <label>Fixation</label> which results from authors fixing a text
     passage by overwriting it (e.g. a pencilled passage fixed with
     ink). Fixation can affect large potions of text, therefore it seems
     unpractical to transcribe the same text twice (as we would do in
     case we used <gi>add</gi>); furthermore it often happens that
     authors, while fixating a text, the decide to apply some
     modification on the underlying text. Therefore we need an element
     that imply a repetition (without providing it) and in the mean time
     is distinguished by <soCalled>real</soCalled> additions and for
     this reason we have introduced a <gi>ge:repetition</gi> element.
     See, for instance the following example of such a practise taken
     from page 70 of Jane austen's <title>Sanditon</title> (notice that
     the scope of such a fixation is of a page and a half):<figure>
        <graphic url="constr_example/AusSand70.png"/>
     </figure>
     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <ge:repetition type="fixation" hand="ja2" seq="1">Now, if we
           could get <subst seq="1">
              <del>but</del>
              <add status="duplicate">get</add>
           </subst>
           <del seq="1">get</del> a young Heiress</ge:repetition>
     </egXML> In the example, some corrections belong to the fixation
     stage, as Austen see in the fixation an opportunity to manipulate
     the text previously written. This fact has been marked via the
        <att>seq</att> attribute, assigning to all the alteration
     belonging to the repetition phase the same value (for the
        <att>seq</att> attribute, se <ref target="#seq"
     >below</ref>).</item>
  <item>
     <label>Clarification</label> a word is badly written and the author
     rewrites it to clarify. In this case the TEI <gi>add
        status="duplicate"</gi> element could be used. An example of
     that can be see at <ptr
        target="http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms.html"/>, where the
     first example, where we have two lost chars overwritten by 'er',
     then overwritten again, could be encoded as follows: <egXML
        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <ge:line>Bæg<del>
              <gap extent="2" unit="chars"/>
           </del><add rend="overwritten" place="inline">er</add>
           <add status="duplicate" type="clarification" place="inline"
              >er</add>klang</ge:line>
     </egXML></item>
             </list></item>
          <item><label>*Alternatives</label> when an author proposes several
             alternative readings for a segment without deciding which is the best.
             For those cases the TEI already offers a system (<gi>alt/</gi>) can be
             adapted. An example of that can be found in Vetter and McDonald
  2003,<note place="foot">
  <bibl>
     <author>Lara Vetter and Jarom McDonald</author>
     <title level="a">Witnessing Dickinson's Witnesses</title>
     <title level="j">Literary Linguistic Computing</title>
     <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
     <biblScope type="pp">151-165</biblScope>
     <date>2003</date>
     <ptr
        target="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/18/2/151?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;fulltext=vetter&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT"
     />
  </bibl>
             </note> where in the poem <title>The inundation of the Spring</title> by
             Emily Dickinson we found, amongst other, that the word
  <mentioned>estranged</mentioned> can be alternated with
  <mentioned>alarmed</mentioned> (written in-line, aster
  <mentioned>estranged</mentioned>) and <mentioned>submerged</mentioned>
             written at the bottom of the page; as <mentioned>estranged</mentioned> is
             underlined, the editors assume that this is the selected alternative (see
             pp. 155-162). Such case can be encoded as follows: <egXML
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <div type="body">
     <l> + <hi rend="underlined" xml:id="alt1">estranged<alt
              targets="#alt1 #alt2
              #alt3"
              mode="excl" weights="1 0 0"/></hi> - + <add
           type="alternative" xml:id="alt2" place="inline">alarmed</add>
     </l>
  </div>
  <div type="margin-bottom"> + <add type="alternative" xml:id="alt3"
        >submerged</add> - </div>
             </egXML></item>
          <item xml:id="mm">
             <label>Meta-marks</label> (<gi>ge:metaMark</gi>): marginal notes and
             other additions to the text should be differentiated from meta-marks
             commanding an alteration (e.g. “move this passage over there”) or the
             date of the beginning of a manuscript or a revision, which represent a
             sort of processing instruction in the document. The element carries a
  <att>function</att> attribute which specify which is the function of
             the meta-mark and a <att>target</att> attribute which points to the
             element which the function refers. An example can be seen in the Emily
             Dickinson poem just shown, where the <mentioned>+</mentioned> sign marks
             that the word that follows is or has alternatives, so the example above
             could be re-encoded as follows: <egXML
  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <div>
     <l>
        <ge:metaMark function="alternative" targets="#alt01">+<alt
              targets="#alt01 #alt02 #alt03" mode="excl" weights="1 0 0"
           /></ge:metaMark>
        <hi rend="underlined" xml:id="alt01">estranged</hi> -
           <ge:metaMark function="alternative" targets="#alt2"
           >+</ge:metaMark>
        <add type="alternative" xml:id="alt02" place="inline"
           >alarmed</add>
     </l>
  </div>
  <div>
     <ge:metaMark function="alternative" targets="#alt03">+</ge:metaMark>
     <add type="alternative" xml:id="alt03">submerged</add> - </div>
             </egXML> Other examples of <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> can be represented by
             proofs' markup, like the ones that can be seen in several pages of Walt
             Whitman (see, for instance: <ptr
  target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/loc.00295.jpg"
             />).</item>
       </list>
    </div>
    <div>
       <head>Deletions</head>
       <p>Beside “normal” deletions (see for instance the TEI definition for
             <gi>del</gi>: “contains a letter, word, or passage deleted, marked as
          deleted, or otherwise indicated as superfluous or spurious in the copy text
          by an author, scribe, annotator, or corrector.”), we have outlined some
          other special kinds of deletion: </p>
       <list >
          <item><label>Marked as used</label> passages that happen to be struck
             through, where the strike marks the passage as used/copied at another
             location/another manuscript. In this case the author does not intend to
             suppress the content, but only to mark that it has been transferred or
             reused. We have created the <gi>ge:used</gi> element for this purpose. As
             the portions that are marked as used are normally full pages or large
             portions of pages, <gi>ge:used</gi> can contains <gi>div</gi>s or can be
             used within them. See an example of this in Walt Whitman (<ptr
  target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/20051105_0650.jpg"
             />) <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <surface>
     <ge:used rend="cross">
        <div>
           <lg><head rend="underline">The Poet</head><l><del
      rend="striketrhough">I think</del> His sight is
   the</l> [...] </lg>
        </div>
     </ge:used>
  </surface>
             </egXML>
          </item>
          <item><label>Overwriting</label> is a particular case of a deletion, unless
             it is a case of repetition (<gi>ge:repetition</gi>) or a false start (see
  <ref target="#false-start">below</ref>).</item>
       </list>
    </div>
    <div>
       <head>Transpositions</head>
       <p>By transposition we mean words or blocks that are moved by the author to a
          different position using arrows, asterisks or numbers. A possible approach
          (used, for instance in <title>HNML</title>) would be to encode this as a
          substitution (i.e. to consider the segment previous to the transposition as
          deleted, and substituted by the one after the transposition) but this will
          not work for transposition of blocks. The encoding of such passages should
          take into account several steps:</p>
       <list type="ordered">
          <item>Make the segment to be transposed addressable, via a “cross-cutting”
             element (<gi>ge:tr</gi>) which could also be used as an empty
             element.</item>
          <item>Markup meta-marks which might be in the text (e.g. a super linear or
             marginal list of numbers “3 2 4 1” or asterisks), with an element
  <gi>ge:metaMark</gi>. </item>
          <item>Relate the <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> to the passages to be transposed,
             either via attributes or implicitly because the <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> is
             contained in an <gi>add</gi> or <gi>del</gi>.</item>
          <item>Reorder the passages according to the instructions contained by the
  <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> elements.</item>
       </list>
       <p>For instance, if we consider the first example from Ibsen manuscripts
          retrievable at <ptr target="http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms.html"/> we
          could encode as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <div>
  <ge:line><ge:tr xml:id="ib1">bör</ge:tr><ge:metaMark rend="underline"
        function="transposition" targets="#ib1" place="above"
        >2.</ge:metaMark> og <ge:tr xml:id="ib2">hör</ge:tr><ge:metaMark
        rend="underline" function="transposition" targets="#ib2"
        place="above">1.</ge:metaMark></ge:line>
             </div>
          </egXML> In Example 1 at <ptr
             target="http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms3.html"/>, Ibsen transposes a
          full block, in this cases it might be more convenient to use <gi>ge:tr</gi>
          as an empty element: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <l><ge:metaMark function="transposition" place="margin-left"
     targets="#ib3">2.)</ge:metaMark><ge:tr spanTo="#ib3"/>thi da er du
  med Himmelen i Pagt; –<anchor xml:id="ib3"/></l>
             <l><ge:metaMark function="transposition" place="margin-left"
     targets="#ib4">1.)</ge:metaMark><ge:tr spanTo="#ib4"/>da kan du
  Folkets Jøkelhjerter tine;<anchor xml:id="ib4"/></l>
          </egXML></p>
       <p>The re-alignment of the transposed blocks or segments can be supplied via a
          stand-off mechanism, to be used, for instance, within <gi>profileDesc</gi>,
          or elsewhere in the document:<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <profileDesc>
  <ge:transpositions>
     <ge:transposition xml:id="transp1">
        <ptr target="#ib2"/>
        <ptr target="#ib1"/>
     </ge:transposition>
     <ge:transposition xml:id="transp2">
        <ptr target="#ib4"/>
        <ptr target="#ib3"/>
     </ge:transposition>
  </ge:transpositions>
             </profileDesc>
          </egXML>
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <ge:line><ge:tr xml:id="ib01">bör</ge:tr><ge:metaMark rend="underline"
     function="transposition" targets="#ib1" place="above"
     >2.</ge:metaMark> og <ge:tr xml:id="ib02">hör</ge:tr><ge:metaMark
     rend="underline" function="transposition" targets="#ib02"
     place="above">1.</ge:metaMark>
  <ge:transpositions>
     <ge:transposition>
        <ptr target="#ib02"/>
        <ptr target="#ib01"/>
     </ge:transposition>
  </ge:transpositions></ge:line>
          </egXML>
       </p>
    </div>
    <div>
       <head>*Substitution</head>
       <p>The current TEI encoding considers a substitution as a combination of
          deletion/addition. Nevertheless there are cases in which a substitution
          includes more material. The current <gi>subst</gi> might therefore need a
          revision to allow more loose substitutions. An example of this can be seen
          in The following example taken from Thomas More's <title>Lalla Rooke</title>
          <figure>
             <graphic url="constr_example/MooreRooke.png"/>
          </figure> which encoding could be: <egXML
             xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <ge:line>While <subst><del>pondering</del> thus <add>she
     mus'd</add></subst>, her pinions fann'd</ge:line>
          </egXML></p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="false-start">
       <head>*Instant corrections and *false starts</head>
       <p>Distinguishing instant correction from other kinds of alteration is
          important when establishing the timing of a specific revisions and in the
          whole genetic process. The information might be supplied as a specific
          attribute of <gi>add/</gi>, <gi>del/</gi>, <gi>subst</gi> etc., called
             <att>*timing</att> (or <att>*instant</att> or similar).<note place="foot"
  ><hi rend="bold">EP</hi>: I would avoid to use <att>type</att> as it
             my be useful for other things and I would rather prefer to have an
             attribute that express a temporal semantics.</note></p>
       <p>A specific subset of instant correction is represented by <hi rend="bold"
             >false starts</hi>, which are parts of a word that are overwritten by
          another (or struck through), meaning that the author started to write a
          word, then changed his/her mind and overwrote all or part of what was
          already written to fit the new word. This is an open problem: how to encode
          the partial word? Which is the scope of the correction? just the parts of
          the word that have been altered or all of it, even if this was not actually
          written? If it is possible to understand the word partially written, how
          should it be encoded? </p>
       <p> An example of false start can be seen in one of the many version of Walt
          Whitman's <title>The Sleepers</title> (available at <ptr
             target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/uva.00256.001.jpg"
          />) where the beginning of the third block could be encoded as follows:
             <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <ge:line><del type="false-start" rend="overstrike" scope="part">T</del>
  <subst>
     <del rend="overstrike">The</del>
     <add place="above">
        <del rend="overstrike">His</del>
     </add>
  </subst>
  <subst>
     <del rend="overwritten">i</del>
     <add place="superimposed">I</add>
  </subst>ron necklace</ge:line>
          </egXML>
          <note place="foot"><hi rend="bold">EP</hi>: I think we should suggest a
  <att>method</att> attribute for <gi>del</gi>, more specific than
  <att>rend</att>.</note> False starts are by nature constituted by word
          fragments, normally the beginning of a word (hence false <hi rend="italic"
             >start</hi>), so no encoding is provided to mark that the deletion
          affects a partial word. In case the editor is able and wishes to provide the
          unwritten missing part of the word (for searching or any other analytical
          purposes, for instance) the <gi xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
             >supplied</gi> element could be used, perhaps together with a
             <att>type</att> attribute (possibly redundant is already used for the
             <gi>del</gi> element).</p>
    </div>
    <div>
       <head>Undoing alterations</head>
       <p>In some case authors undo alterations, e.g. a struck through passage may be
          restored via a dotted underlining, or the underlining of a passage may be
          deleted by a wavy line. </p>
       <p>An element <gi>restore</gi> already exists in TEI for undoing a deletion,
          but we need a more general approach, for instance to delete underlining or
          transposition. We have introduced an element <gi>ge:undo</gi> for that
          purpose provided with at attribute <att>target</att> pointing at the element
          to be undone. Normally the element <gi>ge:undo</gi> would contain the
          element to be undone, except in the case of partial undoing as in the
          following example taken from Giacomo Leopardi's <title>Zibaldone</title> (p.
          3595) <figure>
             <graphic url="constr_example/LeoZib.png"/>
          </figure>Which could be encoded as follows:<egXML
             xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <ge:line> che e’ <hi rend="underline" xml:id="uline1"><ge:undo
        target="#uline1">si</ge:undo> rechi a’</hi>
  <del rend="overstrike">dotti</del>
  <hi rend="underline">denti</hi> l’un d’essi cibi</ge:line>
          </egXML></p>
    </div>
 </div>
 <div xml:id="text-stage">
    <head>Grouping Modifications (Document level)</head>
    <p>In some cases modifications can be attributed to a single campaign of revision
       (or <soCalled>text-stage</soCalled>), meaning we can say that a set of
       alterations (deletion, addition, substitution, transposition, etc.) are
       interrelated (i.e. one is a consequence of the other, they happened at the same
       time, etc.). To document this we need:<list >
          <item>A system to attribute an alteration or any other phenomena occurring
             at document level to a particular revision campaign/text-stage</item>
          <item>A way to describe a revision campaign/text-stage</item>
       </list></p>
    <p>For the former purpose ('attribute an alteration to a revision campaign') we
       have introduced a global attribute <att>mod</att> that points to an
          <att>xml:id</att> attribute within an element describing a specific
       text-stage; the element provided for that purpose is <gi>ge:modGrp</gi>
       ('modification group') which can occur within <gi>creation</gi> in the
          <gi>teiHeader</gi> and groups the editorial reasons for stating that some
       alteration belong to a text-stage. Element <gi>ge:modGroup</gi> contains a
       sequence of <gi xml:id="revNote">ge:modNote</gi>, each of them describing a
       single text-stage. Typically, a <gi>ge:modNote</gi> will contain several
       references to <gi>ge:edJust</gi> elements (see <ref target="#edjust"
          >below</ref>) and to other annotations contained within the
          <gi>teiHeader</gi> or in the document. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <profileDesc>
             <creation>
  <date notAfter="1816-07-18"/>
  <ge:modGroup>
     <ge:modNote xml:id="mod1">The first draft of
           <title>Persuasion</title> is completed by the <date>July 16
           1816</date> written after the word <q>Finis</q> at <ref
           target="#pers-30">page 30</ref>. </ge:modNote>
     <ge:modNote xml:id="mod2"> After the <date>16th of July</date>
        Austen starts revision of the two final chapters, by rewriting
        the end and adding a new block (<ref target="#transp-1">pages
           32-35</ref>) to be inserted at <ref target="#insertion-p1"
           >page 19</ref>. This stage is documented by the deletion of
        the date (<date>July 16 1816</date>) at <ref target="#pers-30"
           >page 30</ref>, and the addition of more text and of a new
        date (<date>July 18. 1816</date>) at <ref target="#pers-31">page
           31</ref>
     </ge:modNote>
     <ge:modNote>Before publication, after <date>July 18th, 1816</date>
        chapters 10-11 were broken into three chapters, 10, 11, 12, as
        witnessed by the print</ge:modNote>
  </ge:modGroup>
             </creation>
          </profileDesc>
       </egXML></p>
    <p>In many cases it is necessary to scope a portion of text in which one or more
       alteration occurs, in order to give the necessary context for any editorial
       discussion. For that purpose we have introduced an element <gi>ge:mod</gi>,
       which occurs within a <gi>ge:line</gi> or a <gi>p</gi> or any block and phrasal
       level elements. As the element is likely to overlap with other hierarchies (in
       particular it is very likely to overlap with <gi>ge:line</gi> in case the
       editor has chosen to encode the document level), the element can also used as
       empty (provided it carries a <att>spanTo</att> attribute). <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <ge:line>her face) – <ge:mod spanTo="#ch10-06-23" mod="#mod1"/>But <subst>
  <del rend="overstriked">I do not</del>
  <add place="above">you have not</add>
             </subst> see much</ge:line>
          <ge:line>the Look of it <del rend="overstriked">in your
             Countenance."</del></ge:line>
          <ge:line><add place="above">as Grave as a little Judge."</add>,<anchor
  xml:id="ch10-06-23"/> – Anne blushed. – Aye, aye, that</ge:line>
       </egXML></p>
 </div>
            </div>
            <div>
 <head>Dossier Level</head>
 <p>In terms of encoding, a dossier will be represented by a <gi>teiCorpus</gi>, which
    will allow us to have a <gi>teiHeader</gi> at dossier level, where to describe all
    the phenomena that will be described below and a <gi>teiHeader</gi> for each of
    the documents forming the dossier.</p>
 <p>It might be convenient to include documents within the dossier (corpus) via a
    XInclude mechanism, in order to keep each document in a separate file and yet to
    be included in the main dossier.</p>
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
       xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
       xmlns:ge="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
       <teiHeader> [..] </teiHeader>
       <![CDATA[<xi:include href="document1.xml"/>
       <xi:include href="document2.xml"/>
       <xi:include href="document3.xml"/>]]>
    </teiCorpus>
 </egXML>
 <div>
    <head>*Genetic Grouping </head>
    <p>Alterations, revisions and other compositional phenomena may need to be grouped
       at dossier level: it might in fact occur that authors correct two versions at a
          time,<note place="foot">Manzoni, for instance, used to modify an old draft
          to see how a new variant fitted with the context before copying it into a
          new draft.</note>or we might need to express that two or more documents are
       related in other ways; for instance, one can be the sequel of the other, they
       might have been drafted at the same time, or one might contain some other kind
       of analogy, like a newspaper article that inspired some kind of reflection
       contained in a given work. </p>
    <p>Such groupings can be encoded within a <gi>gi:geneticGrp</gi> element.<note
          place="foot"><hi rend="bold">EP</hi>: Sorry, but I don't like the name
             <gi>ge:textGroup</gi>, it is not clear enough. I appreciate we need a
          generic name, but we are not grouping texts, we are grouping: a) revisions;
          b) blocks (for instance when we want reorder chapters, as for Fotis' Kafka
          example; c) ???. I think <gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi> is clearer.</note> As the
       element <gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi> can be used more generally for any kind of
       genetic grouping, a <att>type</att> attribute is also provided.
          <gi>ge:geneticGrp</gi> contains a sequence of <gi xml:id="geneticNote"
          >ge:geneticNote</gi> whose <att>targets</att> attribute can refer to several
          <gi>ge:modNote</gi> of specific documents or to other annotations and
       editorial statements.</p>
    <p>An example of Genetic Grouping can be considered the overview done by Kenneth
       Price and Brett Barney on the genesis of a Walt Whitman poem eventually titled
          <title>The Sleepers</title> which can be seen at <ptr
          target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/sleepers.html"/>.
       In this example we have 15 witnesses composed over 30 years, some of which
       contains just vague thematic resemblances with the poem (see witnesses 1-2, for
       instance), others are more strongly related.</p>
    <p>In this case we could create several kind of grouping, for instance: <list
          >
          <item>thematic: group texts that speak about night visions which the editors
             think are related to the poem</item>
          <item>evolutionary: group text for which the genetic connection is
             stronger</item>
          <item>type of document: group text that come form the same type of document
             (printed, notebook, etc.)</item>
       </list></p>
    <p>The first case could be encoded as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <profileDesc>
             <ge:geneticGrp>
  <ge:geneticNote type="thematic">
     <linkGrp>
        <link targets="#poem #sweet_flag"/>
     </linkGrp>
     <p>Groups the witnesses that contains ideas and suggestions that
        may have a connection to the poem</p>
  </ge:geneticNote>
             </ge:geneticGrp>
          </profileDesc>
       </egXML></p>
 </div>
 <div>
    <head>Genetic Relations</head>
    <p>By <soCalled>genetic relations</soCalled> we mean the possibility of ordering
       different text-stages contained within a single document, or more probably,
       across different document into an ideal line of development, going, for
       instance from a version <hi rend="bold">A</hi> to a version <hi rend="bold"
          >B</hi> (that can be represented by a different document or by an
       editorially reconstructed text-stage), to a version <hi rend="bold">C</hi>,
       etc.</p>
    <p>While a <gi>ge:geneticNote</gi> would describe what a group of witnesses have
       in common, a genetic relation will try to align those witnesses in an ideal
       genetic/evolutionary line.</p>
    <p>To do so, we have adapted the concepts of <soCalled>node</soCalled>,
          <soCalled>arcs</soCalled> and <soCalled>graph</soCalled>.</p>
    <div>
       <head>Nodes and Arcs </head>
       <p>A node represent one version or a text that is somehow involved in the
          genetic process of a specific work; an arc connects two nodes (i.e. two
          version, two witnesses) and the set of the arcs generate a graph, i.e. the
          ideal line from the first to the last version of a work.</p>
       <list >
          <item>
             <gi>node</gi> represent a version of a text, or a text stage, or any
             related document. The element need to carry an <att>xml:id</att>
             attribute (to be used by arcs) and a <att>target</att> attribute which
             points to a file, in case of a document, or to a <gi>ge:modNote</gi>, in
             case of a text stage.</item>
          <item>
             <gi>arc</gi> embeds a <att>rel</att> attribute which points to
             description of a specific type of relation as defined by a
  <gi>relation</gi> element (see <ref target="#genRel">below</ref>); an
             attribute <att>cert</att> signifies the degree of certainty associated
             with the interpretation; attribute <att>from</att> and <att>to</att>
             point to nodes, respectively to the beginning end ending points of the
             arc. Each <gi>arc</gi> element contains a <gi>label</gi> which give a
             title to the arc, and by an optional <gi>ge:edJust</gi>, which contains
             some sort of editorial statement about the arc. </item>
          <item>
             <gi>graph</gi> contains the full path from the first to the last version
             of a given work, in terms of a sequence of <gi>node</gi> and <gi>arc</gi>
             elements. A <gi>label</gi> element gives the title to the graph, while a
  <gi>ge:edJust</gi> element can be used to contain editorial statements
             about the constitution of a such path. </item>
       </list>
       <p>The overview done by Kenneth Price and Brett Barney on the genesis of a Walt
          Whitman poem eventually titled <title>The Sleepers</title> which can be seen
          at <ptr
             target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/sleepers.html"/>
          can be used as a test case to demonstrate how the genetic relations can be
          build and documented.<note place="foot">All editorial statements are taken
             from the aforementioned website.</note></p>
       <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <graph type="genetic">
             <label>The Sleepers</label>
             <ge:edJust>
  <p>Tracing the development of the poem eventually titled "The
     Sleepers" involves over 100 images of both handwritten and printed
     material produced across a 30-year period.</p>
             </ge:edJust>
             <node xml:id="A" target="#poem"/>
             <node xml:id="B" target="#sweet_flag"/>
             <node xml:id="C" target="#curse1"/>
             <node xml:id="D" target="#efflux"/>
             <node xml:id="E" target="#shroud"/>
             <node xml:id="F" target="#curse2"/>
             <node xml:id="G" target="#topple_down"/>
             <node xml:id="H" target="#black_lucifer"/>
             <node xml:id="Z" target="#Leaves81-82"/>
             <arc from="#A" to="#C" rel="#thematic" cert="low">
  <label>Night Visions</label>
  <ge:edJust>
     <p>Notes for a poem about night "visions," possibly related to the
        untitled 1855 poem that Whitman eventually titled "The
        Sleepers."</p>
  </ge:edJust>
             </arc>
             <arc from="#B" to="#C" rel="#thematic" cert="medium">
  <label>List of Ideas</label>
  <ge:edJust>
     <p>In this early manuscript, Whitman's lists contain ideas related
        to both "Song of Myself" and "The Sleepers." </p>
  </ge:edJust>
             </arc>
             <arc from="#C" to="#F" rel="#evolution">
  <label>I am a curse</label>
  <ge:edJust>
     <p>An early manuscript draft of the "Lucifer" section of the poem
        that likely lead to the 1855 printed version. </p>
  </ge:edJust>
             </arc>
             <arc from="#F" to="#G" rel="#evolution">
  <label>Black Lucifer</label>
  <ge:edJust>
     <p>The second notebook, "No doubt the efflux of the soul," is a
        longer one (24 leaves) that lays out the philosophical ideas
        that generate the poem and produces some of the key images in
        the first section of the poem ("Cache! And Cache again! All over
        the earth, and in the heavens that swathe the earth, and in the
        waters of the sea.—They do their jobs well; those journeymen
        divine. Only from the Poet they can hide nothing and would not
        if they could"). The key point here is that Whitman was
        generating different parts of his poem in at least three
        different notebooks—working out in one notebook the imagery in
        trial poetic lines, and working out in the other two the main
        ideas in prose.</p>
  </ge:edJust>
             </arc>
             <arc from="#G" to="#H" rel="#evolution">
  <label>Lucifer</label>
             </arc>
             <arc from="#D" to="#Z" rel="#evolution">
  <label>First section</label>
             </arc>
             <arc from="#E" to="#Z" rel="#evolution">
  <label>Central section</label>
  <ge:edJust>
     <p>A manuscript containing approximately seven lines, lightly
        revised, of the poem eventually titled "The Sleepers."</p>
  </ge:edJust>
             </arc>
             <arc from="#H" to="#Z" rel="#evolution">
  <label>Lucifer</label>
             </arc>
          </graph>
       </egXML>
       <p>The graph can them be represented as follows:<figure>
             <graphic url="constr_example/geneticRel.png"/>
          </figure></p>
    </div>
    <div>
       <head>*Relationships</head>
       <p>The type of connections existing between two or more textual variants (an
          arc) or two or more steps (a graph) need to be declared and described in
          order to be used. For that purpose a slightly modified version of the
          element <gi xml:id="genRel">relation</gi> could be used within the
             <gi>profileDesc</gi>. A relation is defined in two ways: by a name
          (within a <att>name</att> attribute) and via attributes defining different
          properties, <note place="foot"><hi rend="bold">EP:</hi> Not sure how much to
             modify <gi>relation</gi>, Lou, I think this is worthy a
          disucssion</note></p>
       <p>Examples of relations are:<list >
             <item><label>Time</label> one document or textual version follows or
  precede another</item>
             <item><label>Evolutionary</label> one document or textual version
  represent the evolution or the development of another</item>
             <item><label>Thematic</label> two or more documents concern the same
  topic </item>
             <item><label>Conceptual</label> two or more documents are connected in
  some logical way</item>
          </list></p>
       <p>For the previous example relations could have been defined as follows:
             <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <profileDesc>
  <relation name="Thematic" xml:id="thematic">
     <desc>Relates witnesses that share themes and topic</desc>
  </relation>
  <relation name="Evolutionary" xml:id="evolution">
     <desc>Relates witnesses that are connected from a evolutionary
        point of view</desc>
  </relation>
             </profileDesc>
          </egXML>
       </p>
    </div>
 </div>
 <div xml:id="collation">
    <head>*Collation and Critical Apparatus</head>
    <p>As previously discussed (see <ref target="#alteration">above</ref>), at any
       time of the creation process the author can decide to stop editing a draft and
       move to another draft. Therefore alterations within a given document and
       alterations which result from the collation of different drafts of the same
       text are more conceptually connected than readings characterising different
       witnesses as a result of a scribal copy.</p>
    <p>For instance, if we have two draft documents of the same text, A and B, if a
       deletion occurs within A or B we would probably mark it with a <gi>del</gi>
       element. On the other hand, if when comparing A and B, we see a passage has
       been suppressed, we would also probably mark it as a deletion of some sort.</p>
    <p>At present the TEI uses an argument <foreign xml:lang="lat">e
          silentio</foreign>, meaning that is something is missing from a witness, the
       absence of the portion can be deducted by comparing different readings, but no
       element is used to qualify such absence. For instance comparing <title>Leaves
          of Grass</title>of the 1856 with the version of 1881-82at line 22 (of the
       1881-82 edition, see <ptr
          target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/sleepers.html"/>),
       we notice that some words have been added: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <l n="22">And the enraged and treacherous dispositions<app>
  <lem wit="#Leaves81-82">, all, all</lem>
  <rdg wit="#Leaves56"/>
             </app> sleep</l>
       </egXML>
    </p>
    <p>The usage of elements such <gi>add</gi> or <gi>del</gi> within a reading
       normally will mean that something has been added or deleted within that
       particular witness.</p>
    <p>The addition (or deletion) of a segment from a version is normally a deliberate
       act of the author and we would like to be able to record that in positive way;
       whether we need another set of editorial elements or we should use the same set
       that are used for transcription is still an open problem. </p>
    <p>For a critical genetic edition we can imagine at least two different
          scenarios:<list >
          <item>Only one document has been entirely transcribed (perhaps the first or
             the last version), while the others are only reconstructable via
             collation, which can be stored within the same document or in a separate
             one.</item>
          <item>All documents composing a dossier have been transcribed and the
             collation is stored in a separate document</item>
       </list></p>
    <div>
       <head>One document is transcribed</head>
       <p>If, beside the base-text which is fully transcribed, all extant witnesses
          have to be reconstructed via collation, it is mandatory to be able to
          distinguish alterations that happen within them and between witnesses. For
          instance, using the existing tag set we could possibly encode as follows:
             <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <l n="22">And the enraged and treacherous dispositions<app>
     <lem wit="#Leaves81-82">
        <add>, all, all</add>
     </lem>
     <rdg wit="#Leaves56"/>
  </app> sleep</l>
          </egXML></p>
       <p>Nevertheless, this might force the intended usage of <gi>add</gi> as it
          might imply that there is an addition (interlinear, marginal or wherever) on
          the edition 1881-82 (a problem which will certainly be magnified with
          manuscripts) which is not the case. This might be solved perhaps using the
             <att xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">type</att> attribute or another
          attribute or creating a new element (say <gi>ge:interAdd</gi>) for addition
          implied by collation, reserving <gi>add</gi> for deletions that happen at
          the document level.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
       <head>All documents are transcribed</head>
       <p>In this case we can assume that all alterations occurring at document level
          are already encoded within each transcription, therefore the collation will
          only need to point to passages within the separate files and classify the
          types of readings resulting from the collation: <egXML
             xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <app xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <rdg wit="#Leaves81-82" from="#v22-5" to="#v22-8" type="added"/>
  <rdg wit="#Leaves56" from="#v22-5"/>
             </app>
          </egXML>
       </p>
       <p>The example encoding implies that attributes <att>from</att> and
             <att>to</att> are added to the <gi>rdg</gi> element.<note place="foot">I
             have not added those attributes as I think we have to discuss this
             further.</note></p>
    </div>
 </div>
            </div>
            <div>
 <head>Manuscript and Dossier Levels</head>
 <div>
    <head>Chronology, Date and Time</head>
    <p>Absolute time is the unambiguous reference to a calendar and time schema, while
       relative timing expresses events as happening <hi rend="italic">before</hi>
       and/or <hi rend="italic">after</hi> other events. Relative time can also be
       expressed by the relation to the (known or unknown) creation of another
       document or text. Dating can be justified by prose and/or by reference to a
       characteristic of a manuscript (e.g. hand, ink, etc.). The outlining of a
       chronology for a document or dossier can then be used as an argument to
       determine the existence of a text-stage.</p>
    <div>
       <head>Absolute Time</head>
       <p>For absolute timing we envisage two cases that can occur separately or in
          combination:</p>
       <list >
          <item>The dating of a witness (a manuscript part of a dossier) or of a
             division is not be directly documented within its content, i.e. it can be
             deduced from external facts and documents. The editorial date attribution
             should be included in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, within the
  <gi>creation</gi> element. </item>
          <item>Dates can be found in the document added by the author as a kind of
             metadata (for instance the date of the beginning/ending of writing on a
             specific document, or the date of a revision campaign); those should be
             encoded without necessarily adding them in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> (they
             can be considered a type of <hi rend="bold">meta-mark</hi>: see <ref
  target="#mm">below</ref>)</item>
       </list>
       <p>For expressing both cases we can use a slightly revised version of the
             <gi>timeline</gi> element. As we need to be able to express alternatives
          and uncertainty, the content model of <gi>timeline</gi> has been enlarged to
          accept a <gi>choice</gi> element; <gi>timelene</gi> can then also be used
          within <gi>choice</gi>. The <gi>when</gi> element has been modified to
          include editorial attributes like <att>cert</att>, <att>resp</att>,
             <att>evidence</att> and <att>source</att>, therefore in case of a date
          written in the manuscript by the author, like for Austen's
             <title>Persuasion</title>, we will have: <egXML
             xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <when target="#pers-1" absolute="1816-07-08" evidence="internal"
  cert="high" source="#date-1"/>
          </egXML> Otherwise, in case of a conjectural date discussed in several parts
          of the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, we will have: <egXML
             xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <when target="#t2" absolute="1922" precision="low" evidence="conjecture"
  cert="medium" source="#inkanalysis"/>
          </egXML>
       </p>
       <p>As an example, let's consider again the analysis provided by Kenneth Price
          and Brett Barney on Whitman's <title>The Sleepers</title> (<ptr
             target="http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/sleepers.html"
          />), and let's assume that the order in which the witnesses are presented in
          the website is a chronological order; let's also assume that the chronology
          of two witnesses (the one titled <title>[become a shroud]</title> and the
          one titled <title>[I am a curse]</title>) is uncertain, the encoding could
          be as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
             <timeline origin="#poem" desc="dossier timeline">
  <when target="#poem"/>
  <when target="#sweet_flag"/>
  <when target="#curse1"/>
  <when target="#efflux"/>
  <choice>
     <timeline origin="#shroud" weights="0.8">
        <when target="#shroud"/>
        <when target="#curse2"/>
     </timeline>
     <timeline origin="#curse2" weights="0.8">
        <when target="#shroud"/>
        <when target="#curse2"/>
     </timeline>
  </choice>
  <when target="#topple_down"/>
  <when target="#black_lucifer"/>
  <!-- more -->
  <when target="#Leaves81-82" absolute="1881" evidence="internal"/>
             </timeline>
          </egXML>
       </p>
       <p>The example show how to order witnesses within a dossier, but the same model
          can be used to order text stages or variants within a section.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
       <head>Relative Time</head>
       <p>Relative time can be expressed in various ways: </p>
       <list >
          <item>In the easies case it might be a direct relationship: <att>next</att>,
  <att>previous</att>, <att>sync</att>, or as a “sorting” relationship:
  <att>before</att>, <att>after</att>.</item>
          <item>In some cases one may be able to express the relative timing of a
             section or a passage marked by the <gi>ge:mod</gi> element. This can be
             expressed via a numbering scheme (<val>0</val>, <val>1</val>,
  <val>2</val>, …) within a <att>seq</att> attribute. In this case we
             assume a <hi rend="bold">default</hi> time-line (the time of writing and
             of the <ref target="#instCor">instant corrections</ref>) which is
             represented by <val>0</val>, and successive revision-times (<val>1</val>,
  <val>2</val>, etc.)</item>
          <item>More complex situation could be expressed via the <gi>timeline</gi>
             element, as seen before. In this cases, when the attribute
  <att>absolute</att> is present, an absolute time is assumed, when
             absent, a relative time is assumed; in this way absolute and relative
             time can be used together. In case it is necessary to express
             simultaneity, the attributes <att>interval</att> and <gi>since</gi> could
             be used as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <when xml:id="t1" target="#poem"/>
  <when xml:id="t2" interval="0" since="#t1" target="#sweet_flag"/>
             </egXML>
          </item>
       </list>
       <p>Information about absolute or relative time can be given on all levels of a
          text or document. </p>
    </div>
 </div>
 <div>
    <head>Documenting Editorial Decisions</head>
    <p>As genetic editions and genetic editing are essentially interpretative,
       documenting editorial decisions has a fundamental role. </p>
    <p>Different forms of documentation have been discussed before in several previous
       sections: <list >
          <item><gi>ge:modNote</gi>: documents the constitution of a text-stage (<ref
  target="#modNote">see</ref>) </item>
          <item><gi>ge:geneticNote</gi>: documents the constitution of a genetic group
  (<ref target="#geneticNote">see</ref>)</item>
       </list>All these elements carry a <att>cert</att> attribute to declare the
       level of certainty, and a <att>resp</att> attribute to declare the editorial
       responsibility of an annotation; all of them should use <att>xml:id</att> to be
       pointed at from many places in the text.</p>
    <p>But annotations can also occur in-line (i.e. close to a textual fragment they
       relate to) and for that reasons we created the <gi xml:id="edjust"
          >ge:edJust</gi> global element. This should always be used with an
          <att>xml:id</att> attribute as the other types of annotations seen above are
       very likely to refer to specific points in the text within a more complex
       argument. The <att>target</att> attribute points to the element to be
       annotated, while a <att>cert</att> attribute indicates the level of confidence
       assigned to a specific editorial argument. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <arc xml:id="a-1" from="#A" to="#C" rel="#thematic" cert="low">
             <label>Night Visions</label>
             <ge:edJust target="#a-1" cert="medium" evidence="conjecture">
  <p>Notes for a poem about night "visions," possibly related to the
     untitled 1855 poem that Whitman eventually titled "The
     Sleepers."</p>
             </ge:edJust>
          </arc>
       </egXML></p>
 </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
            <head>ODD</head>
            <p>TEI Extension for Genetic Editions -- preliminary version</p>
            <schemaSpec ident="geneticTEI" docLang="en" prefix="tei_" start="teiCorpus TEI"
 xml:lang="en" targetLang="en">
 <moduleRef key="core"/>
 <moduleRef key="tei"/>
 <moduleRef key="header"/>
 <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
 <moduleRef key="certainty"/>
 <moduleRef key="analysis"/>
 <moduleRef key="drama"/>
 <moduleRef key="linking"/>
 <moduleRef key="msdescription"/>
 <moduleRef key="nets"/>
 <moduleRef key="textcrit"/>
 <moduleRef key="transcr"/>
 <moduleRef key="gaiji"/>
 <moduleRef key="namesdates"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="analytic" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="biblItem" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="biblStruct" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="binaryObject" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="broadcast" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="analysis" ident="cl" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="analysis" ident="c" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div1"/>
 <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div2"/>
 <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div3"/>
 <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div4"/>
 <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div5"/>
 <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div6"/>
 <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div7"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="equipment" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="equiv" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="fsdDecl" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="headItem" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="headLabel" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="meeting" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="metDecl" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="metSym" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="monogr" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="postBox" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="postCode" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="recording" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="recordingStmt" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="state" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="stdVals" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="street" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="tagsDecl" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="analysis" ident="w" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="tagUsage" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="core" ident="imprint" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="rendition" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="header" ident="namespace" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="addName" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="age" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="birth" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="bloc" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="death" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="district" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="education" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="event" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="faith" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="floruit" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="forename" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="genName" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="geo" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="geogFeat" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="geogName" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="langKnowledge" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="langKnown" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="lisEvent" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="lystNym" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="listOrg" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="listPerson" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="listPlace" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="location" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="nameLink" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="nationality" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="nym" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="occupation" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="offset" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="org" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="orgName" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="person" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="personGrp" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="place" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="population" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="region" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="residence" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="roleName" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="sex" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="socecStatus" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="surname" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="terrain" mode="delete"/>
 <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="trait" mode="delete"/>
 <!-- classes -->
 <classSpec type="model" ident="model.spanning" mode="add">
    <desc>Contains elements that can be spanned across hierarchies. </desc>
    <remarks>
       <p> When <att>spanTo</att> is used, the element must be empty. </p>
    </remarks>
 </classSpec>

 <classSpec ident="att.global" type="atts" mode="change" module="tei">
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="mod" mode="add">
          <desc>Points to a <gi>modNote</gi> which contains a description of a
             text-stage to which the editors think the alteration marked by the
  <att>mod</att> attribute belongs.</desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
             <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </classSpec>

 <!-- topographical document structure -->

 <elementSpec ident="document" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>Document-centric container of a transcription of a primary source,
       containing topographical information as well as a transcriptions</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.resourceLike"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="surface"/>
       </rng:oneOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>

 <elementSpec ident="surface" mode="change">
    <classes mode="change">
       <memberOf key="att.typed" mode="add"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:choice>
          <rng:zeroOrMore>
             <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
          </rng:zeroOrMore>
          <rng:zeroOrMore>
             <rng:ref name="model.glossLike"/>
          </rng:zeroOrMore>
          <rng:zeroOrMore>
             <rng:ref name="model.graphicLike"/>
          </rng:zeroOrMore>
          <rng:zeroOrMore>
             <rng:ref name="model.divLike"/>
          </rng:zeroOrMore>
       </rng:choice>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>

 <elementSpec ident="zone" mode="change">
    <classes mode="change">
       <memberOf key="att.spanning" mode="add"/>
       <memberOf key="att.coordinated" mode="add"/>
       <memberOf key="att.transcriptional" mode="add"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
  <rng:zeroOrMore>
     <rng:text/>
     <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
  </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="ref" mode="add">
          <desc> A reference to an arbitrary object that describes the placement and
             extent of the division (such as an SVG element in an external file). The
             use of this attribute is exclusive of giving x/y-coordinates directly. </desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  name="data.pointer"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="sOrient" mode="add">
          <desc>(surface orientation) The orientation that the surface has taken to
             enable the content (writing, images) in that division, with respect to
             the normal orientation of the <gi>surface</gi> as assumed by the
             dimensions given in the <gi>msDesc</gi> section or by the coordinates of
             the <gi>surface</gi> itself. The orientation is expressed in arc degrees.
             The rotation is clockwise.</desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
             <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.numerical"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="patch" mode="add">
          <desc>Describe the type of patch</desc>
          <datatype>
             <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.word"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="binder" mode="add">
          <desc>Describe the method by which a patch is connected to the main
             surface</desc>
          <datatype>
             <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.word"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="heigth">
          <desc>The height of the patch</desc>
          <datatype>
             <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.numerical"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="width">
          <desc>The width of the patch</desc>
          <datatype>
             <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.numerical"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="line" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
    <desc>Contains the transcription of a topographic line in the source
       document</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="model.divPart"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"
          xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <!-- editorial justification -->
 <elementSpec ident="edJust" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>(editorial justification) An editorial justification of any part of
       the&#xD; edited text.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.global"/>
       <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
       <memberOf key="model.headerPart"/>
       <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="model.pLike"/>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
          <desc>Points to the element to be justified.</desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  name="data.pointer"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="creation" mode="change">
    <content>
       <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="macro.phraseSeq.limited"/>
       </rng:zeroOrMore>
       <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="modGroup"/>
       </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="modGroup" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>(modification group) groups and describes the various modifications that
       occurred in the text's genesis within a document.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    </classes>
    <content xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
       <rng:choice xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:oneOrMore>
             <rng:ref name="model.pLike"/>
          </rng:oneOrMore>
          <rng:group>
             <rng:optional>
  <rng:ref name="summary"/>
             </rng:optional>
             <rng:oneOrMore>
  <rng:ref name="modNote"/>
             </rng:oneOrMore>
          </rng:group>
       </rng:choice>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="modNote" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>Describes a revision in the text genesis.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
          name="macro.specialPara"/>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="mod" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>Scope an area in the document containing several alteration which are
       interrelated to each others; Can also be used to segment the text in order to
       give a meaningful semantic context to an alteration. </desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="model.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:choice>
             <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
             <rng:ref name="line"/>
          </rng:choice>
       </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <!-- authorial changes -->
 <elementSpec ident="metaMark" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>(meta mark) A textual or graphical element in a manuscript that is
       functional but not part of the text. Could transform the text, like a
       strikethrough, or provide meta-information, like a date.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="model.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="att.placement"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="macro.specialPara"/>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="function" mode="add">
          <desc>Describe to the function (e.g. add, delete, alternate) of the
             mark.</desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1">
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.word"
             />
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="targets">
          <desc>Points to the element(s) to which the function of the meta-mark
             refers. Pointers are separated by a white space</desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1">
             <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.pointer"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="used" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>In many cases, authors mark portions of text as having been used, usually
       meaning the text has been transcribed to a fair copy. The mark is often a
       strikethrough, but can be any author-specific mark.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="model.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="model.global"/>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:choice>
             <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
             <rng:ref name="line"/>
             <rng:ref name="model.divLike"/>
          </rng:choice>
       </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="undo" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>Marks up an action represented by an element to be undone.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="model.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
          name="macro.specialPara"/>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
          <desc>The element representing the action to be undone.</desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  name="data.pointer"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="subst" module="transcr" mode="change">
    <content>
       <rng:group xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:group>
             <rng:ref name="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
          </rng:group>
          <rng:oneOrMore>
             <rng:choice>
  <rng:text/>
  <rng:ref name="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
             </rng:choice>
          </rng:oneOrMore>
       </rng:group>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="type" mode="add">
          <desc>The type of substitution.</desc>
          <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.name"
             />
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="repetition" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>A repetition of already written text.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
       <memberOf key="model.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.placement"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
          name="macro.specialPara"/>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="reason">
          <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.word"
             />
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="unclear" module="core" mode="change">
    <classes mode="replace">
       <memberOf key="model.choicePart" mode="add"/>
       <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional" mode="add"/>
       <memberOf key="att.editLike" mode="add"/>
       <memberOf key="att.typed" mode="add"/>
    </classes>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="transpositions"
    ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions" mode="add">
    <desc> Describes the textual transpositions.</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.profileDescPart"/>
       <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="transposition"/>
       </rng:oneOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="transposition"
    ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions" mode="add">
    <desc> Describes a textual transposition. Contains a list of pointers that
       specifies the new order of the text fragments. </desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="ptr"/>
       </rng:oneOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="tr" ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions"
    mode="add">
    <desc>Mark a section to be transposed</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
       <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="model.spanning"/>
       <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
          name="macro.specialPara"/>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <!-- genetic groups -->
 <elementSpec ident="geneticGrp" mode="add"
    ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
    <desc>Group texts and document which are somehow related in a genetic
       process</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="model.profileDescPart"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="geneticNote"/>
       </rng:oneOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="geneticNote" mode="add"
    ns="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Genetic_Editions">
    <desc>Contains the links to the text or documents that are connected within a
       genetic group as well as the description of single genetic group</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="att.global"/>
       <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
       <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="linkGrp"/>
       </rng:oneOrMore>
       <rng:zeroOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="model.pLike"/>
       </rng:zeroOrMore>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <!-- genetic relations -->
 <elementSpec ident="node" module="nets" mode="change">
    <classes mode="change">
       <memberOf mode="add" key="attribute.pointing"/>
    </classes>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
          <desc> A link to the element or passage represented by the node.</desc>
          <datatype>
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  name="data.pointing"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="arc" module="nets" mode="change">
    <classes mode="change">
       <memberOf mode="add" key="att.typed"/>
       <memberOf mode="add" key="att.editLike"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:optional xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="label"/>
          <rng:optional>
             <rng:ref name="label"/>
          </rng:optional>
       </rng:optional>
       <rng:optional xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="edJust"/>
       </rng:optional>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="rel" mode="add">
          <desc>Points to a <gi>relation</gi></desc>
          <datatype>
             <rng:ref xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
  name="data.pointing"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="relation" mode="change">
    <classes>
       <memberOf mode="add" key="model.profileDescPart"/>
    </classes>
 </elementSpec>
 <!-- timeline -->
 <elementSpec ident="timeline" mode="change">
    <classes mode="change">
       <memberOf key="model.choicePart" mode="add"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:oneOrMore xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <rng:ref name="when"/>
          <rng:zeroOrMore>
             <rng:ref name="choice"/>
          </rng:zeroOrMore>
       </rng:oneOrMore>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="weights">
          <datatype>
             <rng:ref name="data.probability"
  xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec ident="when" mode="change">
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
    </classes>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
          <datatype>
             <rng:ref name="data.pointer"
  xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="unit" mode="delete"/>
       <attDef ident="interval" mode="replace">
          <datatype>
             <rng:choice xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
  <rng:ref name="data.numeric"/>
  <rng:value>unknown</rng:value>
             </rng:choice>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <!-- spanning text structure -->
 <elementSpec ident="p" mode="change">
    <classes mode="change">
       <memberOf mode="add" key="att.spanning"/>
       <memberOf mode="add" key="model.spanning"/>
       <memberOf mode="add" key="model.global"/>
    </classes>
 </elementSpec>
 <!-- XInclude -->
 <elementSpec xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ident="include"
    ns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" mode="add">
    <desc>The W3C XInclude element</desc>
    <classes>
       <memberOf key="model.common"/>
       <memberOf key="model.headerPart"/>
    </classes>
    <content>
       <rng:optional>
          <rng:ref name="fallback"/>
       </rng:optional>
    </content>
    <attList>
       <attDef ident="href">
          <desc>pointer to the resource being included</desc>
          <datatype>
             <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="parse" usage="opt">
          <defaultVal>xml</defaultVal>
          <valList type="closed">
             <valItem ident="xml"/>
             <valItem ident="text"/>
          </valList>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="xpointer" usage="opt">
          <datatype>
             <rng:text/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="encoding" usage="opt">
          <datatype>
             <rng:text/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="accept" usage="opt">
          <datatype>
             <rng:text/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="accept-charset" usage="opt">
          <datatype>
             <rng:text/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
       <attDef ident="accept-language" usage="opt">
          <datatype>
             <rng:text/>
          </datatype>
       </attDef>
    </attList>
 </elementSpec>
 <elementSpec xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" ident="fallback"
    ns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" mode="add">
    <desc>Wrapper for fallback elements if an XInclude fails</desc>
    <content>
       <rng:ref name="AnyThing"/>
    </content>
 </elementSpec>
 <macroSpec type="pe" ident="AnyThing" mode="add">
    <desc>Matches any element</desc>
    <content>
       <zeroOrMore xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
          <choice>
             <element>
  <anyName/>
  <zeroOrMore>
     <attribute>
        <anyName>
           <except>
              <name>xml:id</name>
              <name>xml:lang</name>
           </except>
        </anyName>
     </attribute>
  </zeroOrMore>
  <ref name="AnyThing"/>
             </element>
             <text/>
          </choice>
       </zeroOrMore>
    </content>
 </macroSpec>
            </schemaSpec>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
