<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"
   xmlns:ge="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title type="main">An Encoding Model for Genetic Editions</title>
            <author>Lou Burnard, Fotis Jannidis, Elena Pierazzo, Malte Rehbein</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition n="3">Revised Draft</edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <authority>TEI MS SIG, Genetic Edition Workgroup</authority>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <p>Born Digital</p>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
	<change when="2010-10-03">
	  <name>Syd Bauman</name>
	  <desc>Typos</desc>
	</change>
         <change when="2010-04-05">
            <name>Gregor Middell</name>
            <date>5 April 2010</date>
            <desc>Extended theoretical part; writing acts vs. textual stages</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-04-03">
            <name>Gregor Middell</name>
            <date>3 April 2010</date>
            <desc>Reworked chapter "The dossier level"; added graph-based encoding of genetic
               aspects</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-04-03">
            <name>Gregor Middell</name>
            <date>3 April 2010</date>
            <desc>Chapter "Revision campaigns" revamped; added examples/ updated schema</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-04-02">
            <name>Moritz Wissenbach</name>
            <date>2 April 2010</date>
            <desc>Chapter "Revision campaigns" extended</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-04-01">
            <name>Gregor Middell</name>
            <date>1 April 2010</date>
            <desc>updated schema</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-04-01">
            <name>Gregor Middell</name>
            <date>1 April 2010</date>
            <desc>Extracted examples into separate files, added test suite</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-04-01">
            <name>Malte Rehbein</name>
            <date>1 April 2010</date>
            <desc>Chapter Undoing alterations extended</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2010-03-11">
            <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
            <date>11-03-2010</date>
            <desc>Implementation of the decisions made 25/26 of February</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2009-09-10">
            <name>Lou Burnard</name>
            <date>28-30 Oct 09</date>
            <desc>Further revision campaign</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2009-09-10">
            <name>Lou Burnard</name>
            <date>9-11 Sept 09</date>
            <desc>Further revision campaign</desc>
         </change>
         <change when="2009-08-28">
            <name>Lou Burnard</name>
            <date>27-28 Aug 09</date>
            <desc>Major revisions after discussion with Elena</desc>
         </change>
         <change>
            <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
            <date>08 May 2009</date>
            <desc>Conversion from MS Word</desc>
         </change>
         <change>
            <name>Elena Pierazzo</name>
            <date>01 August 2009</date>
            <desc>Major update following Paris' Workshop</desc>
         </change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <front>
         <divGen type="toc"/>
         <pb/>
         <div>
            <head>About this Document</head>
            <p>This document describes a <hi rend="bold">draft</hi> encoding model for Genetic
               Editions and Genetic Editing. The document is the product of a Workgroup on Genetic
               Editions (chair: Fotis Jannidis), which is part of the TEI MS SIG (chairs: Elena
               Pierazzo, Malte Rehbein, Amanda Galley). </p>
            <p>The workgroup's goal was to develop an Application Profile for the encoding of
               genetic editions and, in general, genetic phenomena. It is expressed as a TEI P5
               conformant customization, integrating material from the existing TEI Guidelines,
               chiefly Chapter 11. <title>Representation of Primary Sources</title> and Chapter 12.
                  <title>Critical Apparatus</title>, together with additional new material. It may
               eventually, at the end of the process described in the following section, constitute
               a free-standing new chapter of the <title>Guidelines</title> or remain a set of
               recommendations for how to customize the Guidelines, but that is a decision for the
               TEI Council.</p>
            <p>The document reflects discussions held at a number of different meetings:</p>
            <list>
               <item>MS SIG meeting held in London during the annual members’ TEI meeting (November
                  2008); the minutes of the meeting can be found here: <ptr
                     target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Minutes_London_2008"/>.</item>
               <item>Genetic Edition workgroup held in London (March 2009); minutes can be found
                  here: <ptr target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Minutes_London_03-2009"/>. </item>
               <item>Workshop "Genetic Editions in a Digital Framework", held in Paris, 14/15 May
                  2009, and following discussion; programme of the workshop can be found here: <ptr
                     target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/GeneticEditionsWorkshopParis"/></item>
               <item>Genetic Edition workgroup held in Würzburg (September 2009)</item>
            </list>
<p>The document was subsequently extensively revised by Elena Pierazzo and Lou Burnard, for
                  presentation at a panel held at the Annual TEI Members Meeting in November
                  2009; at a 
               Genetic Edition workgroup held in Oxford (February
	       2010); at a Genetic Edition workgroup held in Würzburg
	       (March 2010); and finally in Oxford in April of the
	       same year for
	       presentation to the TEI Council meeting in Dublin.</p>
            <p>The work group was initially inspired by HMNL, the 
	    <soCalled>HyperNietzsche Markup
                  Language</soCalled> and following versions (<title>GML Genetic Markup
                  Language</title>) produced by Paolo D'Iorio and colleagues from the HyperNietzsche
               project. We would like to thank Paolo D'Iorio for his invaluable contribution in the
               early stages of the work. </p>
<p>Major contributors to this document, in addition to those already
cited, include Gregor Middel and Moritz Wissenbach, from the
Faustprojekt at the University of Wuerzburg. </p>
            <div>
               <head>Work Plan</head>
               <p>The planned evolution of this document and the encoding model it describes may be
                  summarized as follows:</p>
               <list>
                  <item>Initially, we worked on a pseudo-encoding model, expressed using our own
                     terminology. This stage was completed by July 2009. <!-- reference ? --></item>
                  <item>This pseudo-encoding model was re-expressed using the TEI P5 encoding
                     framework and revised extensively. </item>
                  <item>The same step-by-step approach will be taken for the standardisation
                     process: <list>
                        <item>First we develop an application profile, that is, a well-documented
                           TEI customisation.</item>
                        <item>This will be presented to the TEI Council as a proposed modification
                           of the TEI</item>
                        <item>If the TEI Council approves it, the Council will decide how it should
                           be integrated into the current <title>Guidelines</title>.</item>
                     </list></item>
               </list>
               <p>This draft document is publicly available for discussion and feedback from the
                  community. The document source is maintained in the TEI subversion repository at
                     <ptr target="http://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/tei/trunk/genetic/"/>;
                  background information about the development of the proposals and associated
                  materials, is hosted on the TEI Wiki at <ptr
                     target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/Category:Genetic_Editions"/>. </p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Conventions used</head>
               <p>Although the entire document is a draft and therefore susceptible of changes, some
                  sections are less stable than others. In particular, when a section or a
                  particular element requires further discussion or is considered an open problem,
                  such a section or element is marked by a * mark.</p>
               <p>As required for TEI conformance, non-TEI elements are defined in a distinct
                  non-TEI namespace. In the usage examples and throughout this document that
                  namespace is mapped to the prefix <hi rend="bold">ge:</hi>, while TEI elements are
                  not marked by any namespace prefix.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div>
            <head>Theoretical Framework</head>
            <p>The genetic approach differs from other approaches to the study of texts because it
               aims not only to identify <q>what is on the page</q>, but also to reconstruct the
                  <emph rend="bold">process</emph> necessary to produce <q>what is on the
               page</q>.</p>
            <p>The encoding model for Genetic Editing must therefore handle:- <list>
                  <item>Genetic <term>transcription</term> of a single document in such a way as to
                     trace its evolution; </item>
                  <item>Genetic <term>reconstruction</term>: that is, creation of a <term>Genetic
                        Dossier</term> assembling multiple related documents, and description of the
                     genetic relations amongst them;</item>
                  <item>Genetic <term>editing</term>, the goal of which is preparation of a
                        <term>Genetic Edition</term> whether derived from a single or multiple
                     witnesses.</item>
               </list> A Genetic Edition may be prepared by producing a full transcription of all
               extant witnesses, or by combining a full transcription of only one document (a
                  <term>base-text</term>) with information derived from other witnesses by means of
               automatic collation.</p>
            <p>Because our model aims to be independent of presuppositions associated with any
               particular theoretical framework, we begin by reviewing some typical dichotomies in
               editorial theory.</p>
            <div xml:id="deutung">
               <head>Fact vs. Interpretation</head>
               <p>In German editorial theory there is a well known opposition between what is there
                  in the source document, the <term>record</term> (<foreign xml:lang="deu" rend="it"
                     >Befund</foreign>), and the interpretation of this phenomenon (<foreign
                     xml:lang="deu" rend="it">Deutung</foreign>). This opposition implies that there
                  is a way to talk about the record without any interpretation. Yet at some possibly
                  simplistic level, everything we say about a text is based on interpretation,
                  particularly in the realm of genetic criticism.<note place="foot">See also the
                  TEI’s (implicit) position on this point: <q>we define markup, or (synonymously)
                        encoding, as any means of making explicit an <hi rend="italic"
                           >interpretation</hi> of a text</q> (TEI Guidelines: <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/SG.html">v. A
                        Gentle Introduction to XML</ref>). See also reference to Robinson and
                     Solopova 1993/1997: 21: <q>Any primary textual source… has its own semiotic
                        system within it.[…] The two semiotic system are materially distinct, in
                        that text written by hand is not the same as the text on the computer
                        screen</q>.</note> At the same time, there is an obvious difference between
                  the interpretation that some trace of ink is indeed a specific letter and the
                  assumption that a change in one line of a manuscript must have been made at the
                  same time as a change in another line because their effects are textually related
                  (for example, the first change was to a rhyming word, which necessitated the
                  second change). Therefore we propose to talk about differing <term>levels</term>
                  of interpretation, thus differentiating between <soCalled>what’s there</soCalled>
                  (document/fact) and <soCalled>how does it relate</soCalled>
                  (text/interpretation).</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Status vs. Process</head>
               <p>When a scholar examines a written text, especially a manuscript, the object of the
                  investigation is usually to discover the final result of that writing and
                  rewriting process. The examination can take various forms: it can be approached
                  from a codicological or documentary point of view, <soCalled>photographing</soCalled> the resulting
                  product, from a textual point of view, or from a genetic point of view, by trying
                  to describe the flow of authoring.</p>
               <p>The present proposal addresses both approaches: sections <ptr target="#document"/>
                  and <ptr target="#alterations"/> are presented from
		  the codicological or documentary point of view,
                  while the other sections investigate the process of writing and re-writing of the
                  text, thus constituting the purely genetic parts of the present proposal.</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Document vs. Text</head>
               <p>In Manuscript Studies (Editing, Codicology, Palaeography, Art History, History)
                  the first level of enquiry is always the document, the physical support that lies
                  in front of the scholar’s eyes. </p>
               <p>To understand the text that is contained in the manuscript, a deep study of the
                  manuscript itself is fundamental: the layout, the type of script, the type of
                  support, the binding, and many other aspects are able to tell us about
                  when, where, and why this particular text was composed. The text however
                  represents a different level of enquiry: it is a construct, derived from the
                  reading of the documents.</p>
               <p>In the case of modern draft manuscripts scholars must give detailed consideration
                  to the layout, the different stratifications of writing and the disposition of
                  these in the physical space; all of these, together with an understanding of the
                  text, are required to gain insight about the composition, time of revisions, and
                  flow (<foreign xml:lang="fr">flux</foreign>) of the text. Furthermore, in some
                  cases, we know that the kind of physical support used to record it not only
                  influences but may also actually determine the text itself. For instance, the
                  content and the length of letters are often determined by the size and quantity of
                  the paper available to the writer; even more so for items such as postcards. </p>
               <p>The TEI has traditionally prioritised the text level. Of the two possible views
                  available to someone transcribing a primary source (text and document), the TEI
                  privileges the text (hence <hi rend="italic">Text</hi> Encoding Initiative). Such
                  physical or topographical information as a typical TEI encoding provides is
                  subordinate to the main structural encoding, whether because it is represented by
                  empty elements (<gi>pb/</gi>, <gi>lb/</gi>, <gi>cb/</gi>) or attributes (<gi>add
                     place=""</gi>, <gi>note place=""</gi>, or <att>rend</att>). The TEI thus
                  reflects the not uncommon view that, while relevant, documents are somehow less
                  relevant than the texts they embody; to use a bibliographical metaphor, texts are
                     <soCalled>substantial</soCalled> while documents are
                     <soCalled>accidental</soCalled>. </p>
               <p>However, for genetic editions, a focus on the document is crucial. In
                  many cases, the only way to reconstruct the process of writing and re-writing
                  which leads to a new text is to examine a specific document. We therefore propose
                  to complement the existing text-focussed approach with a new encoding scheme
                  focussed instead on the document.</p>
               <p>We should then clarify the way we will use the following words:</p>
               <list>
                  <item><label>Document</label> the physical object, the manuscript or other primary
                     source, comprising one or more written surfaces</item>
                  <item><label>Text</label> the intellectual content of the document, the words
                     written in their logical (non physical) sequence</item>
                  <item><label>Facsimile</label> a surrogate representation (not necessarily
                     digital) of the document (a photograph, a microfilm, a digital image)</item>
                  <item><label>Document level</label> transcription of the content of a document
                     according to its physical layout</item>
                  <item><label>Text level</label> transcription of the content of a document
                     according to its logical, semantic meaning </item>
               </list>
            </div>
            <div xml:id="act_vs_state">
               <head>Writing Acts vs. Text Stages</head>
               <p>As noted in the previous section, the focus on purely
	       documentary aspects in a genetic edition often serves to reconstruct the writing
                  process, which in turn enables allow the editor to justify a genetic analysis,
                  for example to identify which text passage has been altered first or which textual variant predates
                  another. The encoding of the writing process, it
		  must be observed, is not simply a different point of
		  view about the text in hand, but rather regards as a
		  relevant a set of
	       information fundamentally different from that
	       captured by a purely textual encoding.</p>
               <p>When talking about alterations on a textual level,
	       it is
	       the <emph>stages</emph> of the text which vare of major
	       interest. These stages are the results of various alterations
                  applied to the draft; each addition, deletion, substitution etc. is viewed from the perspective
                  of the possibly new text state it yields. For example the following substitution is
                  well-defined from this perspective:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <subst>
                     <del>landscape</del>
                     <add>scenery</add>
                  </subst>
               </egXML>
               <p>When considering the  writing process however, a
	       number of different possible writing acts can
                  be imagined leading to the same change of state. For
		  example: <egXML
                     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <p>
                        <del rend="strikethrough">landsca</del>pe <handShift new="#new_material"
                        />scenery </p>
                  </egXML>
               </p>
               <p>This example stresses the writing process and
	       provides two additional pieces of information: firstly
	       the fact that the author did not strike through the
	       whole of the first word and secondly that
                  a change in writing material happened just before
		  the word <mentioned>scenery</mentioned> was written.
                  In current encoding practice, which tends to favour the textual view, the two
                  perspectives are often integrated, subordinating aspects of the writing process to
                  their textual outcome  or regularizing them so they do not interfere with
                  a text-driven evaluation of the encoding.</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <subst>
                     <del><hi rend="strikethrough">landsca</hi>pe</del>
                     <add hand="#new_material">scenery</add>
                  </subst>
               </egXML>
               <p>As the example shows, this integrative approach can be a viable one in many cases,
                  but taking this pragmatic shortcut  blurs a specific editorial
                  distinction, maybe exactly the distinction one wants to emphasize (e.g. to
                  separate <foreign>Befund</foreign> from
		  <foreign>Deutung</foreign>). Furthermore, it makes it particularly hard to be as precise about the
                     <emph>documentation</emph> of <soCalled>what’s
		     there</soCalled> as one is about the
                     <emph>interpretation</emph> of <soCalled>what’s the possible outcome</soCalled>. Ideally in a
                  genetic edition the editor would prefer to encode the two perspectives
                  separately and align them later on instead of trying to integrate them right away,
                  and thereby potentially neglect  information of
	       importance in their genetic analysis.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Aspects of Genetic Editions</head>
            <p>Modern genetic editions describe the genetic process within one manuscript and over
               the course of two or more manuscripts, which are said to form part of a
                  <term>dossier</term>, that is, the set of documents which a genetic editor
               considers as having contributed to the evolution of a particular text, including
               associated diaries, letters, etc. Usually a view of a manuscript as a single
               self-contained object is also offered. This is because the manuscript view provides
               the material basis for the relationships established by the inter-manuscript
               relationship. Therefore we propose to differentiate between the following aspects of
               a genetic edition:</p>
            <list type="gloss">
                  <label>Document level</label>
               <item>
                  <list type="gloss">
                        <label>topological description</label>                     <item>
 description of the layout of the
                        text and the basis for a rendition of a text as a diplomatic
                        transcription.</item>
<label>Textual Alterations</label>                     <item>
                         like additions, deletions,
                        substitutions.</item>
<label>Grouping Modifications</label>                     <item>
                         groups of changes at different
                        locations of one document, used to create sets which express the editorial
                        assumption that these changes have been undertaken in one stage.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>

                  <label>Dossier level</label>
               <item>                  <list type="gloss">

                        <label>Genetic Grouping</label>                      <item>groups phenomena in more than one document,
                        in order to describe editorial assumption that these phenomena are related
                        in some way.</item>
<label>Genetic Relation</label>                      <item>
                        describes the genetic relation between
                        different parts of a text,<note place="foot">As in the case where a document
                           describes the ordering of parts of a text contained in another document.
                           It is the case, for instance of Beckett's <title>That Time</title> where
                           the speeches of A, B and C are obsessively first subdivided and
                           subsequently shuffled and reshuffled by the means of sequences of letters
                           and numbers contained in a number of documents.</note> or across
                        several documents, as a series of steps on a path.</item>
<label>Comparison or Collation</label>                       <item>
                        expresses the differences between
                        texts as the result of a comparison between documents.</item>
                     <!-- will need revision -->
                  </list>
               </item>
                  <label>Document and Dossier levels</label>
               <item>
                  <list type="gloss">

                        <label>Chronology, Date and Time</label>                      <item>the encoding of the chronology of
                        the text or parts of it in absolute or relative time.</item>

                        <label>Documenting Editorial Decisions</label>                      <item>documents the arguments which
                        are the basis for editorial decisions to encode the text in a specific way
                        including ways to express uncertainty and alternatives.</item>
<label>Text Stage</label>                      <item>a reconstructable stage in the evolution of a
                        text, represented by a document or by a revision campaign within one or more
                        documents, possibly assigned to a specific point in time. </item>
                  </list>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The document level</head>
            <div xml:id="document">
               <head>Transcription of a document </head>
               <p>A document-based transcription is hierarchically organised in the following way: <list>
                     <item>document<list>
                           <item>Writing Surface (page, double page, folium, etc.) <list>
                                 <item>zone <list>
                                       <item>Text, lines or tables</item>
                                    </list></item>
                              </list></item>
                        </list></item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>We propose to introduce a new element, <gi>ge:document</gi> to encode a
                  document-based transcription, at the same level as the existing TEI <gi>text</gi>
                  element. A full TEI document may thus comprise: <list>
                     <item>a TEI Header, containing metadata</item>
                     <item>a TEI <gi>facsimile</gi> element, containing and describing visual
                        representations of a document</item>
                     <item>a <gi>ge:document</gi> element, containing a genetic transcription of a
                        document</item>
                     <item>a TEI <gi>text</gi> element, containing an encoded version of the text
                        constructed from the document.</item>
                  </list>The header and at least one of the other three components must be present.
                  We do not discuss <gi>facsimile</gi> or <gi>text</gi> elements here; for these
                  refer to the published TEI Guidelines. </p>
               <p>In the simplest case, a document contains one or more written surfaces, of various
                  types (pages, for example). Each surface may contain one or more distinct written
                  zones of writing, each comprising one or more identifiable topographic lines. The
                  following elements are used to represent these basic components: <specList>
                     <specDesc key="document"/>
                     <specDesc key="surface" atts="type"/>
                     <specDesc key="zone" atts="rotate stage"/>
                     <specDesc key="line" atts="type"/>
                     <specDesc key="table"/>
                  </specList></p>
               <!-- remove @rotate? add something to describe writing orientation,
using SVG description of baseline; added to any zone, line 
simple case writing orientation on zone, or line;
or link to something in SVG for complex case

distinguish  writing direction; svg for shape and for baseline

moritz will write on wiki soon

-->
               <p>Like a <gi>facsimile</gi>, a <gi>ge:document</gi> contains information about the
                  written surfaces constituting a document. Because of this similarity, we would
                  like to use the same elements (<gi>surface</gi> and <gi>zone</gi>) as proposed in
                  the existing TEI scheme, although these place limits on what can be described.
                  Specifically, the <gi>zone</gi> element as currently defined can represent only a
                  rectangular area; it also lacks any way of stating the baseline applicable to any
                  writing contained within it </p>
               <p>The size of the writing surface is defined by a set of cartesian coordinates
                  measured from the top left corner. The co-ordinates of all zones identified within
                  the writing surface are given in terms of the same co-ordinates, as further
                  discussed in the TEI proposals for <gi>facsimile</gi>. It will often be the case
                  that explicit dimensions for a manuscript page (expressed in mm for example) are
                  also supplied in a <gi>msDesc</gi> element in the TEI Header, but this is not a
                  requirement; in particular there is no assumption that the co-ordinate system
                  defined by a <gi>surface</gi> maps to any particular external dimensions, nor that
                  the co-ordinate systems of different documents necessarily correspond. </p>
               <p>A <gi>surface</gi> element may contain any number of <gi>zone</gi>,
                     <gi>graphic</gi>, <gi>ge:line</gi> or <gi>table</gi>elements. The
                     <gi>graphic</gi> element is used to point to any graphic (non textual)
                  component forming part of the page, in the usual TEI manner. The <gi>zone</gi>
                  element is used to delimit any contiguous section of writing which the encoder
                  wishes to identify for some purpose. </p>
               <p>Zones can be nested and grouped, and can also overlap. Their positioning with
                  respect to the <gi>surface</gi> element is defined by coordinate values taken from
                  the same co-ordinate system as the surface itself, measured from the top left
                  corner. The element carries a <att>rotate</att> attribute which describes (in
                  degrees) the orientation of the surface with respect to the content (writing,
                  images) in that <gi>zone</gi>, with respect to its normal orientation. Note that
                  the mechanism aims to describes the process by which the content of a specific
                     <gi>zone</gi> has been supplied (i.e. the author has physically rotated the
                  writing surface) rather than the orientation of the writing.</p>
               <!-- fotis wants to generalise rotation to things other than zones 
actually he wants to kill it... -->
               <p>Zones are arbitrarily defined by the encoder according to the layout of the
                  writing surface and can make use of a standardised vocabulary (e.g. the top
                  margin). <!-- means what? --></p>
               <p>To overcome the inherent limitations of the existing <gi>zone</gi> and
                     <gi>surface</gi> elements, we need to extend their capability to include the
                  definition of arbitrary polygons, using an attribute
		  such as <att>svg:points</att>, from the Standard
		  Vector Graphics (SVG) XML namespace. This  would
		  also provide a way of defining a baseline for the writing. This work is not
                  yet fully elaborated. </p>
               <p>The attribute <att>stage</att> is used to indicate the <term>stage</term> in a
                  writing campaign to which this zone has been assigned by the encoder, as further
                  discussed in <ptr target="#stages"/> below. </p>
               <p>Within a zone, individual lines of writing are usually, but not necessarily,
                  distinguished using the <gi>ge:line</gi>. Zones can
		  also include <gi>table</gi>
                  elements, as lines and tables represent the principal ways of organising
                  texts on a surface.<!--note>Can we have <gi>cell</gi> restricted to contain only what
                     is allowed within <gi>ge:line</gi>? Namely: <specList>
                        <specDesc key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                        <specDesc key="model.pPart.editorial"/>
                        <specDesc key="model.hiLike"/>
                        <specDesc key="model.gLike"/>
                        <specDesc key="model.global"/>
                     </specList>
                  </note--> In the case of an interlineated text, interlinear writing can be treated as a
                  line on its own (perhaps characterised by a <att>type</att> attribute) or as
                  textual addition, encoded with an <gi>add</gi> (see below <ptr
                     target="#alterations"/>).<!-- more discussion
	       needed --></p>
               <p>In the following imaginary example, there are two main areas of writing, the diary
                  entry (black ink) and another (supposedly later) annotation in blue ink. <figure>
                     <graphic url="examples/D1.png" width="400px"/>
                  </figure> Note that the diary entry forms a zone which itself contains two zones:
                  one containing the date, and the other containing three lines about birds. The
                  five lines of annotation in blue ink form another zone, to record which the diary
                  page has been rotated 90° clockwise by the author. Using the elements discussed so
                  far, the page might be transcribed as follows:</p>
               <!-- D1_1.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <ge:document>
                     <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
                        <zone ulx="10" uly="43" lrx="185" lry="84" rotate="0">
                           <zone>
                              <ge:line rend="right"> 1 April 2009 </ge:line>
                           </zone>
                           <ge:line>Fed Birds in the park today.</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>Might write an article about </ge:line>
                           <ge:line>the Thick-billed Warbler. </ge:line>
                        </zone>
                        <zone ulx="9" uly="20" lrx="70" lry="60" rotate="90">
                           <ge:line>Samaria is a Greek </ge:line>
                           <ge:line>brand of water that</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>comes from the natural</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>springs of Stilos, in </ge:line>
                           <ge:line>Crete </ge:line>
                        </zone>
                     </surface>
                  </ge:document>
               </egXML>
               <p>On the other hand, if the encoder considers it inconvenient to mark the text
                  within <gi>ge:line</gi> elements, one could encode the same text as follows:
                     <!-- D1_2.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ge:document>
                        <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
                           <zone ulx="10" uly="43" lrx="185" lry="84" rotate="0">
                              <zone>1 April 2009 </zone>
                              <lb/>Fed Birds in the park today.<lb/> Might write an article about
                              <lb/> the Thick-billed Warbler. </zone>
                           <zone ulx="9" uly="20" lrx="70" lry="60" rotate="90">
                              <lb/>Samaria is a Greek <lb/> brand of water that <lb/> comes from the
                              natural <lb/> springs of Stilos, in <lb/> Crete </zone>
                        </surface>
                     </ge:document>
                  </egXML>
               </p>
               <p>For comparison, here is a typical TEI transcription of the same page, focussing on
                  its textual structure <!-- D1_3.xml --><egXML
                     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <div type="diary-entry">
                        <dateline>
                           <date value="2009-04-01"> 1 April 2009 </date>
                        </dateline>
                        <p><lb/>Fed Birds in the park today.<lb/> Might write an article about <lb/>
                           the Thick-billed Warbler. </p>
                     </div>
                     <div type="note" rend="rotated">
                        <p><lb/>Samaria is a Greek <lb/> brand of water that <lb/> comes from the
                           natural <lb/> springs of Stilos, in <lb/> Crete</p>
                     </div>
                  </egXML>
               </p>
               <!--<p>[We need here an example discussing problem of interlinear markup
]</p>-->
               <p>Is it possible to combine both perspectives (documentary and textual views) within
                  a single encoding? In general a document-based transcription, which is done
                  page-by-page and possibly line-by-line, is almost certain to overlap with some
                  part of a the text-based structure. The cleanest solution may be to encode both
                  structures separately, providing both a <gi>ge:document</gi> and a distinct
                     <gi>text</gi> solution, perhaps using some form of external pointing to link
                  the two, and minimizing redundancy of encoding by using XInclude. This option is
                  further discussed below and also in the TEI Guidelines. </p>
               <p>A further, and possibly simpler, approach is to apply to the textual elements such
                  as <gi>p</gi> exactly the same kind of <soCalled>flattening</soCalled> approach as
                  has been applied to the <gi>ge:line</gi> elements in the preceding example.
                  Instead of marking the textual paragraphs as full elements, we mark only their
                  frontiers, using the standard TEI <gi>milestone</gi> element, with the addition of
                  a spanning attribute, as follows: <!-- D1_4.xml --><egXML
                     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
                        <zone stage="#stage1" seq="0" ulx="10" uly="43" lrx="185" lry="84">
                           <zone>
                              <milestone unit="date" spanTo="#endDate"/>1 April 2009 <anchor
                                 xml:id="endDate"/>
                           </zone>
                           <milestone unit="p" spanTo="#p2"/>
                           <ge:line>Fed Birds in the park today.</ge:line>
                           <ge:line> Might write an article about </ge:line>
                           <ge:line>the Thick-billed Warbler.</ge:line>
                        </zone>
                        <zone stage="#stage2" ulx="9" uly="20" lrx="70" lry="60" rotate="90">
                           <milestone unit="p" xml:id="p2" spanTo="#end"/>
                           <ge:line>Samaria is a Greek</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>brand of water that</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>comes from the natural</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>springs of Stilos, in</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>Crete</ge:line>
                           <anchor xml:id="end"/>
                        </zone>
                     </surface>
                  </egXML>
               </p>
               <p>Elements <gi>zone</gi>,  <gi>ge:line</gi>, and
	       <gi>cell</gi> may all contain a selection of the phrase
                  level elements which have been considered essential to a document based
                  transcription. These elements are all drawn from the
		  following existing TEI classes: <specList>
                     <specDesc key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                     <specDesc key="model.pPart.editorial"/>
                     <specDesc key="model.hiLike"/>
                     <specDesc key="model.gLike"/>
                     <specDesc key="model.global"/>
                  </specList> A subset of the elements provided by
		  these classes needs to be defined. In addition, a
		  mechanism is needed to constrain the content of the
		  selected elements such that they contain only
		  elements which are allowed within <gi>ge:line</gi>.
<!-- TODO: refer to model.zonePart/linePart as an extension point for the content model -->
<!--                  <note place="foot">Can we limit the content of seg within this specific context?
                     Or do we need another element with such a content? This is point is left open
                     for the Council to evaluate.</note--> The generic
<gi>seg</gi> element can  also be used to
                  encode any semantic aspect of the transcribed document (e.g. dates or names), though
                  it is recommended that such an approach is kept to a minimum. In case extensive
                  semantic markup is to be applied, the textual perspective should be preferred or
                  included alongside, as suggested above. </p>
               <p>The written surfaces of which a document is composed are not always homogenous. In
                  the following example, taken from the Walt Whitman archive, two pieces of
                  newsprint have been glued to a piece of blue paper on which a poem is being
                  drafted: <figure>
                     <graphic url="examples/whitman01.jpg" width="400px"/>
                     <head rend="it">Image from
                        http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/duk.00258.001.jpg</head>
                  </figure> The two pieces of newsprint might perhaps be regarded as special kinds
                  of zone, but they are effectively new surfaces, since they might contain
                  additional written zones themselves (such as the numbers in this case). We
                  therefore propose a distinct element, <gi>ge:patch</gi>, which can appear within a
                     <gi>surface</gi>, and behaves effectively like one, except that it contains
                  specialized attributes to provide additional information. <specList>
                     <specDesc key="patch" atts="binder type height width"/>
                  </specList> Using this element, the Whitman draft above might be encoded as
                  follows: <!-- whitman01.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <surface>
                        <zone>
                           <ge:line>Poem</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>As in Visions of — at</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>night —</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>All sorts of fancies running through</ge:line>
                           <ge:line>the head</ge:line>
                        </zone>
                        <ge:patch type="newsprint" binder="glue" height="40" width="90"> Spring has
                           just set in here, and the weather.... a steamer <zone>
                              <ge:metaMark function="sequence">2</ge:metaMark>
                           </zone>
                        </ge:patch>
                        <ge:patch type="newsprint" binder="glue" height="35" width="90"> "The shores
                           on either side of the Sound are... The In- <zone>
                              <ge:metaMark function="sequence">3</ge:metaMark>
                           </zone>
                        </ge:patch>
                     </surface>
                  </egXML> The <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> element used in this example is further
                  discussed below (<ptr target="#mm"/>)</p>
               <p>Surfaces can also be damaged, perforated, and cut. In such cases a combination of
                     <gi>damageSpan</gi> and <gi>gap</gi> elements may be used. <specList>
                     <specDesc key="damageSpan" atts="group"/>
                     <specDesc key="gap"/>
                  </specList> Suppose that a piece of paper has been cut from the page
                  encoded by a <gi>surface</gi> element, and that we can infer the dimensions of the
                  missing piece. This could be encoded as follows: <!-- damageSpan_1.xml --><egXML
                     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
                        <zone>...</zone>
                        <damageSpan hand="#author" spanTo="#zoneEnd" agent="knife_or_scissors"
                           group="1" extent="3x5" unit="cm"/>
                        <zone ulx="9" uly="20" lrx="70" lry="60"/>
                        <anchor xml:id="zoneEnd"/>
                     </surface>
                  </egXML> In the example an empty <gi>zone</gi> element has been provided in order
                  to give the coordinates of the missing piece of <gi>surface</gi>, assuming that
                  those are reconstructible. If a full page is missing, <gi>damageSpan</gi> can be
                  used within <gi>ge:document</gi>, perhaps in conjunction with a <gi>gap</gi>
                  element. <!-- damageSpan_2.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ge:document>
                        <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
                           <zone>...</zone>
                        </surface>
                        <damageSpan spanTo="#p3"/>
                        <gap extent="1" unit="folio">
                           <desc>Stub of a missing folio</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300" xml:id="p3">
                           <zone>...</zone>
                        </surface>
                     </ge:document>
                  </egXML> Now suppose that the missing folio is by chance found somewhere; in this
                  case it is likely that the editor might want to encode the two statuses of the
                  document, before and after the damage, tracing the genesis of the document as well
                  as the genesis of the text. In this case, the same mechanism used to
                  describe the genetic history of the text can be used to describe the genesis of
                  the document (see below <ptr target="#stages"/>):  a
                     <att>stage</att> attribute linked to a
		     <gi>ge:stageNote</gi> element can identify the different
		     states in the history of the document.
                     <!-- damageSpan_3.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ge:document>
                        <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300">
                           <zone>...</zone>
                        </surface>
                        <damageSpan spanTo="#P3" stage="#stage2"/>
                        <gap extent="1" unit="folio" stage="#stage2">
                           <desc>Stub of a missing folio</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <surface corresp="folio.xml#p1" stage="#stage1"/>
                        <surface corresp="folio.xml#p2" stage="#stage1"/>
                        <surface ulx="0" uly="0" lrx="200" lry="300" xml:id="P3">
                           <zone>...</zone>
                        </surface>
                     </ge:document>
                  </egXML> In this example, we assume that the two
		  recovered pages (i.e. both sides of the missing
		  folio) have been encoded in some separate XML
		  document which can be obtained from the URL
		  <code>folio.xml</code>. This could be referenced via
		  the <att>corresp</att> attribute, transcluded by means
		  of a <gi>ptr</gi> or included by XInclude. The
		  content could also simply be encoded
                  within the same document as  content for the
		  otherwise empty <gi>surface</gi>s). Note that the
                     <gi>damageSpan</gi> and <gi>gap</gi> belong to a second stage in the life of
                  the document; the descriptions of <val>#stage1</val> and <val>#stage2</val> can be
                  found in the header, within the <gi>ge:stageNote</gi> section.</p>
<!--               <note><hi rend="bold">EP:</hi> I cannot include Lebrave example because, even if I
                  asked a couple of times, he did not answer to my requests of using his material,
                  so I don't know if the images are protected by copyright or not.</note>-->
               <!-- need to add Lebrave's scarey example of virtual reconstructed document -->
            </div>
            <div xml:id="alterations">
               <head>Textual Alterations</head>
               <p>Traces of authorial alteration (correction, addition, deletion, etc.) are
                  frequently found within a single document, and may also be inferred when different
                  documents are compared. It is however an open question as to whether
                  inter-document discrepancies at the dossier level should be regarded in the same
                  way as intra-document alterations. If two witnesses are collated, we may observe
                  that a word present in one is missing from the other: does it necessarily follow
                  that this is an addition or a deletion, which we would not hesitate to mark with
                  an <gi>add</gi> or <gi>del</gi> tag if we are transcribing a single manuscript? We
                  return to this question <ref target="#collation">below</ref>.
                  <!-- Or do we need a completely new
set of elements to do it? In a genetic process, at any point the
author can decide to stop revising the text within a given document
and decide to move to a new document (i.e. copy it anew), so the two
phenomena (alterations at document level and alterations at dossier
level) are indeed closely related. On the other hand we need to
differentiate them because the one within a single document is
explicitly marked by the author, while the one detected by comparison
is only implicit. It may also happen that implicit alterations were
perhaps marked in a lost intermediate version. This remains an open
problem (see .</p> <p>The following discussion-->
               </p>
               <p>In this section we discuss elements introduced for the markup of alterations at
                  the document level, within a single document, complementary to the elements
                  already provided for this purpose by the TEI scheme. We discuss specifically: <list>
                     <item><soCalled>meta-marks</soCalled>, that is a kind of authorial markup
                        present in the source and indicating how it should be read; </item>
                     <item>additions, where a passage has been rewritten to fix or clarify it; </item>
                     <item>deletions, where a passage had been struck through to indicate that it
                        has been removed, or where a deletion has itself been cancelled</item>
                     <item>transpositions, where passages have been reorganized or resequenced.
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The TEI already provides the following basic elements for transcription, which
                  constitute the <ident>model.pPart.transcriptional</ident> class: <specList>
                     <specDesc key="add"/>
                     <specDesc key="app"/>
                     <specDesc key="corr"/>
                     <specDesc key="damage"/>
                     <specDesc key="del"/>
                     <specDesc key="orig"/>
                     <specDesc key="reg"/>
                     <specDesc key="restore"/>
                     <specDesc key="sic"/>
                     <specDesc key="subst"/>
                     <specDesc key="supplied"/>
                     <specDesc key="unclear"/>
                  </specList> The present proposals extend this list by adding the following
                  elements to the same class: <specList>
                     <specDesc key="mod" atts="rend type"/>
                     <specDesc key="modSpan" atts="spanTo"/>
                     <specDesc key="metaMark" atts="function  targets"/>
                     <specDesc key="used" atts="spanTo"/>
                     <specDesc key="undo" atts="spanTo"/>
                     <specDesc key="redo" atts="spanTo"/>
                     <specDesc key="rewrite" atts="cause"/>
                     <specDesc key="transposeGrp"/>
                     <specDesc key="transpose"/>

                  </specList> .</p>
               <p>Most of these elements imply a certain level of semantic
                  interpretation; for instance the usage of the <gi>add</gi> element to encode, say,
                  interlinear insertions involves a decision that the
		  interlinear text has been deliberately inserted rather
		  than simply misplaced. As discussed
above (see <ptr target="#act_vs_state"/>), the use of these elements
                  when transcribing from a documentary perspective is
		  a pragmatic shortcut. In cases where it is felt
                   desirable to keep the recording of
		  <soCalled>what is on the page</soCalled> entirely separate from
                  <soCalled>what is the editor’s
		  interpretation</soCalled> (see <ptr
		  target="#deutung"/>), we provide  two generic elements, <gi>ge:mod</gi> and
                     <gi>ge:modSpan</gi>, which can  be used to
		     record any kind of modification identified in
		     the document. These elements can be
		     categorised by means of their <att>type</att>
		     attribute, and visual aspects of their appearance
		     can be described by means of  the <att>rend</att>
		     attribute, but they provide no further
		     interpretation of the function or intention of
		     the passage so marked up.</p>
<p> Whether such a modification, for instance a struck-out passage, is
                  to be interpreted as a deletion or as some other
		  phenomenon (e.g. as being already used) should be
be expressed using the other, more semantically motivated, elements,
which function at a  different level of description.</p>
               <div>
                  <head>Additions, fixations and clarifications</head>
                  <p>A writer may sometimes rewrite material a second time without significant
                     change and in the same place. We consider this a distinct activity from
                     addition as usually defined because no new textual material results but the
                     status of existing material changes. We distinguish two variants of this:
                        <term>fixation</term> where the first version was a tentative draft which is
                     subsequently fixed, for example by inking it over; and
                        <term>clarification</term>, where the first version was badly written and
                     has been rewritten for clarity. The element <gi>ge:rewrite</gi> is provided to
                     cover both cases. </p>
                  <p>In this simple example, taken from the papers of Henrik Ibsen, the writer wrote
                     the word <mentioned>skuldren</mentioned> hastily, and then returned to it to
                     make the letter <mentioned>l</mentioned> larger and clearer: <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/skuldren.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head rend="it">Image from a ms of Peer Gynt, Collin 2869, 4°, I.1.1, the
                           Royal Library of Copenhagen</head>
                     </figure> We might transcribe this word as follows: <!-- skuldren.xml --><egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line>... Sku<ge:rewrite cause="unclear">l</ge:rewrite>dren </ge:line>
                     </egXML>
                  </p>
                  <p>The following example, taken from a manuscript of Jane Austen's
                        <title>Sanditon</title>, shows a rewriting where a pencilled passage has
                     been fixed with ink, with some modification: <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/AusSand70.png" width="400px"/>
                        <head rend="it">Image from page 70 of the Sanditon manuscript</head>
                     </figure> In this example, Austen sees in the fixation an opportunity to
                     manipulate the text previously written, and thus changes the pencilled
                        <mentioned> could but get a young</mentioned> to the inked <mentioned>could
                        get a young</mentioned>, writing the inky <mentioned>get</mentioned> on top
                     of pencilled <mentioned>but</mentioned> and striking over with black ink the
                     pencilled <mentioned>but</mentioned>. A simple way of encoding this might be as
                     follows: <!-- AusSand70.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:rewrite cause="fix" hand="#ja2" stage="#s1">Now, if we could <subst
                              stage="#s1">
                              <add>get</add>
                              <del>but</del>
                           </subst>
                           <del stage="#s1" rend="overstrike">get</del> a young Heiress</ge:rewrite>
                     </egXML> where the <att>stage</att> attribute groups the operations that belong
                     to the rewriting stage, assuming an implied previous stage (the first layer of
                     writing). If the first layer need to be addressed independently, another
                     pointer can be added to the <att>stage</att> attribute:
                        <!-- AusSand70.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line stage="#s0"> <ge:rewrite cause="fix" hand="#ja2" stage="#s1">Now...</ge:rewrite></ge:line>
                     </egXML> 
where <val>#s0</val> and <val>#s1</val> both point to the declaration
                     of such stages in the header, the first one conventionally representing the
                     first layer of writing and the second the rewriting stage. </p>
                  <!-- note that the  hand specified for the rewrite is the second one -->
                  <p>A single rewrite may not be sufficient, and it may be that the document becomes
                     almost unreadable as a result of repeated clarification. In the following
                     example, we can distinguish at least two attempts to write the letters
                        <mentioned>er</mentioned> in the word <mentioned>bægerklang</mentioned>: <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/munch01.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head rend="it">Image from http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms.html </head>
                     </figure> We might encode this by nesting the <gi>rewrite</gi> element as
                     follows: <!-- munch01.jpg --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line>ved Bæg<ge:rewrite cause="unclear" stage="#stage2">
                              <ge:rewrite cause="unclear" stage="#stage1">er</ge:rewrite>
                           </ge:rewrite> ...</ge:line>
                     </egXML> The <att>stage</att> attribute used here is discussed further below
                        (<ptr target="#stages"/>). </p>
                  <p>Metamarks and other markup-like strokes can also
		  be inked over with the same purpose as the fixation
		  or clarification of text passages. For
                     instance, in a draft version of Goethe’s Faust, a passage was struck through
                     once in pencil during one revision and then again
		     with ink during a later revision, supposedly to fixate the deletion.</p>
                  <figure>
                     <graphic url="examples/faust_redo.jpg"/>
                     <head rend="it">Fixation of a deletion in Goethe’s Faust</head>
                  </figure>
                  <p>We propose an element <gi>redo</gi> (the opposite
		  of  <gi>undo</gi>, see
                        <ptr target="#undo"/>), which can be used to encode this process as follows:</p>
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ge:line><ge:redo xml:id="redo_3" hand="#g_t" target="#mod_1" cause="fix"
                           /><ge:modSpan xml:id="mod_1" rend="strikethrough" spanTo="#anchor_1"
                           hand="#g_bl"/>Ihr hagren, triſten, krummgezog<ge:mod rend="strikethrough"
                           >nen</ge:mod>ener Nacken</ge:line>
                     <ge:line>Wenn ihr nur piepſet iſt die Welt ſchon matt.<anchor xml:id="anchor_1"
                        /></ge:line>
                  </egXML>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Deletions and marked as used</head>
                  <p>In general, deletion in a source is marked using the <gi>del</gi> or
                        <gi>delSpan</gi> element. However, it is useful to distinguish cases where a
                     passage has been <q>indicated as superfluous or spurious in the copy text by an
                        author, scribe, annotator, or corrector</q> (TEI P5, s.v. <gi>del</gi>) from
                     cases where a passage has been struck through or otherwise marked as having
                     been used or copied to another location. In this latter case, the author does
                     not intend to suppress the content, but only to mark that it has been
                     transferred or reused. The element <gi>ge:used</gi> is provided to mark this
                     kind of <soCalled>deletion</soCalled>.</p>
                  <p>The following page from the Walt Whitman archive has been crossed through to
                     indicate used material: <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/whitman02.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head>Page from
                           http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/20051105_0650.jpg</head>
                     </figure> This page contains many internal deletions, but these should be
                     distinguished from the <soCalled>deletion</soCalled> signalled by the large
                     cross, which actually shows that the page has been transferred or re-used, not
                     deleted. </p>
                  <p>Material marked as re-used in this way often spans more than one zone or line.
                     For that reason, the <gi>ge:used</gi> element is a spanning element, indicating
                     the end of the used area by means of a <att>spanTo</att> attribute. We might
                     encode the above page as follows: <!-- whitman02.xml --><egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <surface>
                           <ge:used rend="cross" spanTo="#X2"/>
                           <zone>
                              <ge:line rend="underline">The Poet</ge:line>
                              <ge:line><del rend="strikethrough">I think</del> His sight is
                                 the</ge:line>
                              <ge:line> sight of the ? and</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>has sent the instinct of the</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>? dog</ge:line>
                           </zone>
                           <zone>
                              <ge:line>I think <ge:rewrite>ten</ge:rewrite> million</ge:line>
                              <!-- ... -->
                              <ge:line>well; those <subst>
                                    <del rend="strikethrough">supple-fingered gods</del>
                                    <add>journeymen divine.</add>
                                 </subst></ge:line>
                              <anchor xml:id="X2"/>
                           </zone>
                        </surface>
                     </egXML>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="mm">
                  <head>Metamarks</head>
                  <p>By <term>metamark</term> we mean marks such as numbers, arrows, crosses, or
                     other symbols introduced by the writer into a document expressly for the
                     purpose of indicating how the text is to be read. Such marks thus constitute a
                     kind of markup of the document, rather than forming part of the text. </p>
                  <p>Unlike marginal notes or other additions to the text, meta-marks indicate a
                     deliberate alteration of the writing (e.g. <q>move this passage over
                     there</q>). We also consider as metamarks dates introduced to mark the
                     beginning of a manuscript or a revision, but not forming part of it.</p>
                  <p>The <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> element carries a <att>function</att> attribute which
                     specifies the function of the meta-mark and a <att>target</att> attribute which
                     points to the element or elements concerned. </p>
                  <p>The following example is taken from <title>Kundige bok 2</title>, a 15th
                     century legal book from the city of Göttingen, containing regulations of
                     everyday life issued by the city council <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/ka04_1v-dtl.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head>Malte's example</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the second paragraph, the sentence beginning <q>Ock en schullen de
                        bruwere...</q> was first written along with the word <mentioned
                        xml:lang="lat">lege</mentioned> ("read") in the left hand margin,
                     functioning as a metamark to indicate that this sentence forms part of the
                     regulations. A further sentence was then added, while at some later stage or
                     stages the text and also the metamark were deleted. We might encode this as
                     follows: <!-- ka04_1v-dtl.xml --><egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <del>
                           <ge:metaMark function="flag" target="#s1">lege</ge:metaMark>
                           <s xml:id="s1">Ock en schullen de bruwere des hilgen dages nicht over
                              <lb/>setten noch uppe den stillen fridach bruwen.</s>
                           <add>
                              <s>Noch nymande <lb/>over setten, se en sehin denne erst, dat uppe den
                                 bonen <lb/>neyn stro noch, huw noch flaß ligghe, by pine eyner
                                 halven <lb/>roden, deme bruwere so wol alse dem bruwheren to
                                 murende.</s>
                           </add>
                        </del>
                     </egXML>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here are some further examples showing the use of this element, taken from the
                     manuscript drafts of Thomas Moore's <title>Lalla Rookh</title>
                     (1817)<!--, provided by Justin Tonra, NUIG-->. The first shows a simple use of
                     a metamark used to take stock of the progress of composition: <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/moore02.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head>Lalla Rookh</head>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
                  <p>At regular points throughout the various drafts of the work, a number occurs,
                     usually in the right margin (in this instance, "100"). These numbers result
                     from the author counting the number of verse lines he has composed to the given
                     point, and are not part of the text, but represent a stage at which Moore is
                     taking stock of the progress of his composition. </p>
                  <p>
                     <!-- moore02.xml -->
                     <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <surface>
                           <zone>
                              <!-- main zone -->
                              <ge:line>Be this she cried &amp; wing’d her flight</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>My offering at the Gates of Bliss</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>
                                 <del>Fully to know the odours <gap extent="1" unit="word"
                                       reason="illegible"/></del>
                              </ge:line>
                              <ge:line>
                                 <del>Tho foul to heaven the vapour went</del>
                              </ge:line>
                              <ge:line>
                                 <del>From vulgar</del>
                                 <add>common</add>
                                 <del>victors</del>, blood like this</ge:line>
                              <ge:line> Shed out for freedom, flows so bright. <ge:metaMark
                                    function="count">100</ge:metaMark></ge:line>
                              <ge:line> It would not stain the purest <subst>
                                    <del>fount</del>
                                    <add>rill</add>
                                 </subst> .</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>“That sparkles thro the fields of light. <del>
                                    <ge:metaMark function="count">100</ge:metaMark>
                                 </del></ge:line>
                              <ge:line> Behold her in the skies again —</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>
                                 <subst>
                                    <del>But</del>
                                    <add>And</add>
                                 </subst>, tho so fleet her pinions bore</ge:line>
                              <ge:line> The spirit of the Warriors slain,</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>Now reach’d &amp; pass’d the gates before her</ge:line>
                           </zone>
                           <zone>
                              <!-- left zone -->
                              <ge:line> Tho foul too oft the</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>tears that still</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>Tho foul the droppings <add>weepings</add></ge:line>
                              <ge:line>that distil</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>Tho foul the tears that</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>oft distil</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>From glory’s faulchion’</ge:line>
                           </zone>
                        </surface>
                     </egXML>
                  </p>
                  <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/moore03.png" width="400px"/>
                        <head>Lalla Rookh 2</head>
                     </figure> This example demonstrates the use of a common proof-correction mark:
                     in the left margin of the page, adjacent to a group of three cancelled lines of
                     verse, the word "stet" is written. "Stet", a Latin word meaning "let it stand"
                     is commonly used by authors, editors, and proofreaders where a previous action
                     should be disregarded. In this instance, Moore is indicating that the three
                     deleted verse lines should be let stand, as evidenced by their appearance in
                     the first printed edition of <title>Lalla Rookh</title>. The word, "stet" does
                     not form part of the text, but rather declares that a certain function be
                     performed upon the text. <!-- moore03.xml --><egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <surface>
                           <zone>
                              <ge:line><gap extent="1" unit="word" reason="illegible"/>
                                 <del>in his light</del>
                                 <add>within</add> eyelids, within the spray</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>From Eden’s fountain, when it lies</ge:line>
                              <ge:line><hi rend="underline">On that blue</hi>
                                 <del>before that</del> flower, which, Brahmins say</ge:line>
                              <ge:line> Can only <add>blooms nowhere but</add> bloom in
                                 Paradise,</ge:line>
                              <ge:line>
                                 <del xml:id="del1">“Nymph of a bright, fair but erring line!</del>
                              </ge:line>
                              <ge:line>
                                 <ge:metaMark function="undo" target="#del1 #del2 #del3"
                                    >stet</ge:metaMark>
                                 <del xml:id="del2">(He gently <add>gently</add> he said) one hope
                                    is thine</del>
                              </ge:line>
                              <ge:line>
                                 <del xml:id="del3">One hope (he gently said) is thine</del>
                              </ge:line>
                           </zone>
                        </surface>
                     </egXML>
                  </p>
                  <p>Other examples of <gi>ge:metaMark</gi> can be seen in marked-up proofs such as
                     the following, taken from the Walt Whitman archive: <!-- wrong example -->
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/moore04.png" width="400px"/>
                        <head>http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/loc.00295.jpg</head>
                     </figure></p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Alternative Readings</head>
                  <p><figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/moore04.png" width="400px"/>
                        <head>Lalla Rookh 3</head>
                     </figure> In this example two alternative readings are provided, without either
                     one being prioritised or subordinated. While the author apparently first
                     composed the line "Alone before his native river -", at some later point, he
                     entertained the possibility of using the word "beside" instead of "before." In
                     the context of this manuscript, there is no indication of which word the Moore
                     favours, so the status of these words as possible alternative readings needs to
                     be encoded. The evidence of the first edition of <title>Lalla Rookh</title>
                     shows that the word "beside" was chosen, but for the purposes of encoding this
                     manuscript, the facility to encode two equally-possible alternative readings
                     needs to be available. </p>
                  <!-- moore04.xml -->
                  <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <zone>
                        <ge:line>Alone <seg type="alternative" xml:id="alt1">before</seg>
                           <add place="above" type="alternative" xml:id="alt2">beside</add> his
                           native river ­—</ge:line>
                        <alt targets="#alt1 #alt2" mode="excl" weights="0 1"/>
                     </zone>
                  </egXML>
                  <!--<p>As a further example, consider the manuscript of a poem by Emily Dickinson discussed by   Vetter and McDonald
                     2003 <note place="foot">
                     <bibl>
                     <author>Lara Vetter and Jarom McDonald</author>
                     <title level="a">Witnessing Dickinson's Witnesses</title>
                     <title level="j">Literary Linguistic Computing</title>
                     <biblScope type="vol">18</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="issue">2</biblScope>
                     <biblScope type="pp">151-165</biblScope>
                     <date>2003</date>
                     <ptr
                     target="http://llc.oxfordjournals.org/cgi/reprint/18/2/151?maxtoshow=&amp;HITS=10&amp;hits=10&amp;RESULTFORMAT=&amp;fulltext=vetter&amp;searchid=1&amp;FIRSTINDEX=0&amp;resourcetype=HWCIT"
                     />
                     </bibl>
                     </note>. In this case, a plus sign is used to indicate that there are two
                     possible alternatives for the word following it, concerning which the
                     writer remains undecided. We can mark this up as follows: <egXML
                     xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                     <ge:line>        <ge:metaMark function="alternative" targets="#alt01">+<alt
                     targets="#alt01 #alt02 #alt03" mode="excl" weights="1 0 0"
                     /></ge:metaMark>
                     <hi rend="underlined" xml:id="alt01">estranged</hi> -
                     <ge:metaMark function="alternative" targets="#alt2"
                     >+</ge:metaMark>
                     <add type="alternative" xml:id="alt02" place="inline"
                     >alarmed</add>
                     </ge:line>
                     <ge:line>
                     <ge:metaMark function="alternative" targets="#alt03">+</ge:metaMark>
                     <add type="alternative" xml:id="alt03">submerged</add> - </ge:line>
                     </egXML> 
                     Note here the use of the existing TEI element <gi>alt</gi> to indicate
                     that the three elements indicated are mutually exclusive alternates:  the word
                     <mentioned>estranged</mentioned> can be alternated with
                     <mentioned>alarmed</mentioned> (written in-line, aster
                     <mentioned>estranged</mentioned>) and <mentioned>submerged</mentioned>
                     written at the bottom of the page. Since <mentioned>estranged</mentioned> is
                     underlined, the editors argue  (loc cit pp. 155-162)
                     that  this possibility is to be preferred to the others and hence give it a
                     weight of 1.</p>
                  -->
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Transpositions</head>
                  <p>Metamarks are commonly used in the context of <term>transposition</term>, that
                     is, the moving of words or blocks by the author to a different position using
                     arrows, asterisks or numbers, or other metamarks. One possible approach (used,
                     for instance in HNML) would be to regard such transpositions as a special kind
                     of substitution, and actually to represent the result of the transposition
                     indicated by the metamarks in the encoding, for example by considering the
                     segment previous to the transposition as deleted, and substituted by the one
                     after the transposition. </p>
                  <p>Our recommendation is to record the actual state of the witness, but in such a
                     way as to facilitate its reorganization as a distinct processing step. We
                     propose to represent the re-alignment of transposed blocks or segments by means
                     of a stand-off mechanism. The elements <gi>ge:transposeGrp</gi> and
                        <gi>ge:transpose</gi> are provided for this purpose. For example, in the
                     following extract from an Ibsen manuscript <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/ibsen01.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head>Extracted from
                           <ref>http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms.html</ref></head>
                     </figure>, the underlined numbers 1 and 2 indicate that, although the word
                        <mentioned>bör</mentioned> precedes the word <mentioned>hör</mentioned> in
                     the text, the order of the two words should be reversed. We may encode this as
                     follows: <!-- ibsen01.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line><seg xml:id="ib01">bör</seg><ge:metaMark rend="underline"
                              function="transposition" target="#ib1" place="above">2.</ge:metaMark>
                           og <seg xml:id="ib02">hör</seg><ge:metaMark rend="underline"
                              function="transposition" target="#ib02" place="above"
                           >1.</ge:metaMark></ge:line>
                        <ge:transposeGrp>
                           <ge:transpose>
                              <ptr target="#ib02"/>
                              <ptr target="#ib01"/>
                           </ge:transpose>
                        </ge:transposeGrp>
                     </egXML>
                  </p>
                  <p>Note the use of the generic <gi>seg</gi> element to identify the sections of
                     text being transposed. When (as in the following example) the whole of line is
                     to be transposed, there is no need to delimit the sections concerned: <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/ibsen04.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head>Extracted from
                           <ref>http://www.emunch.no/tei-mm-2008/ms3.html</ref></head>
                     </figure>
                     <!-- ibsen04.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line xml:id="ib3"><ge:metaMark function="transposition"
                              place="margin-left">2.)</ge:metaMark> thi da er du med Himmelen i
                           Pagt; — </ge:line>
                        <ge:line xml:id="ib4">
                           <ge:metaMark function="transposition" place="margin-left"
                              >1.)</ge:metaMark> da kan du Folkets Jøkelhjerter tine;</ge:line>
                        <ge:transposeGrp>
                           <ge:transpose>
                              <ptr target="#ib4"/>
                              <ptr target="#ib3"/>
                           </ge:transpose>
                        </ge:transposeGrp>
                     </egXML> When transposition is made, the whole element indicated is understood
                     to be moved, not just its contents. In the above example, the metamarks are
                     thus understood to be moved along with the lines to which they apply. </p>
                  <p>In case the area to be transposed is overlapping with some other kind of
                     markup, the generic <gi>milestone</gi> can be used instead of <gi>seg</gi> or
                     any other existing elements.</p>
                  <p>One or more <gi>transposeGrp</gi> elements may be supplied either embedded
                     within the text or in the <gi>profileDesc</gi> of the header, depending on
                     local preference. Each <gi>transposeGrp</gi> can contain one or more
                        <gi>transpose</gi> elements, each of which defines a single
                     transposition.</p>
               </div>
               <div>
                  <head>Substitution</head>
                  <p>In the current model for the TEI <gi>subst</gi> element, one or more additions
                     and deletions may be combined if they are considered as representing a single
                     editorial act, a substitution. Without extension, this model could not
                     therefore include cases such as the following example taken from Thomas Moore's
                        <title>Lalla Rooke</title>
                     <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/moore01.png" width="400px"/>
                     </figure> Here the word <mentioned>pondering</mentioned> is deleted, and the
                     phrase <mentioned>she mus'd</mentioned> are added, while the word
                        <mentioned>thus</mentioned> remains unchanged. It seems appropriate to treat
                     all of this as a single substitution. This would require a modification to the
                     content model of <gi>subst</gi> so as to permit text along with other members
                     of <ident type="class">model.pPart.transcriptional</ident>, so that this
                     example could be encoded as follows: <!-- moore01.xml --><egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line>While <subst><del>pondering</del> thus <add>she
                           mus'd</add></subst>, her pinions fann'd</ge:line>
                     </egXML></p>
               </div>
               <div xml:id="undo">
                  <head>Undoing alterations</head>
                  <p>In some cases an author indicates that an alteration is itself to be altered:
                     for example, a struck through passage may be restored via a dotted underlining,
                     or the underlining of a passage may be deleted by a wavy line. </p>
                  <!-- need a simpler example first, need to discuss relation with restore -->
                  <p>The TEI provides an element <gi>restore</gi> for one specific kind of
                     alteration to an alteration, namely the undoing of a deletion. We propose a
                     more general element, <gi>ge:undo</gi>. The element <gi>ge:undo</gi> usually
                     encloses the element (e.g. the <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi> etc.) to be undone.
                     If it appears within such an element, the implication is that only this part of
                     the parent element has been cancelled. For example, in this passage taken from
                     Giacomo Leopardi's <title>Zibaldone</title> (p. 3595), the phrase <mentioned>si
                        rechi á</mentioned> was underlined word by word, and then the underlining of
                     the word <mentioned>si</mentioned> was cancelled. <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/leop01.png" width="400px"/>
                     </figure>This could be encoded as follows: <!-- leop01.xml --><egXML
                        xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line> che e’ <hi rend="underline"><ge:undo spanTo="#x2"/>si <anchor
                                 xml:id="x2"/> rechi a’</hi>
                           <del rend="overstrike">dotti</del>
                           <hi rend="underline">denti</hi> l’un d’essi cibi</ge:line>
                     </egXML></p>
                  <!-- not sure I remember what we said but it seems to me we decided to 
                  point from the undo to the element to be undone-->
                  <p>To make explicit the relation between the undoing act and the initial act, we
                     propose an alternative way of encoding these scribal acts, namely an empty
                        <gi>ge:undo</gi> element, which points to the
			element the effect of which is being  cancelled. If
                     more than one (not coherent) part of the deletion
		     is undone, more than one <gi>undo</gi> element
		     will be needed, and each part undone must be
		     given an identifier.</p>
                  <p>In the following example, three text stages can be identified: <list>
                        <item>s1 (initial): This is just some sample text, we need a real example. <figure>
                              <graphic url="examples/undoing1.jpg" width="400px"/>
                           </figure></item>
                        <item>s2: This is not a real example.</item>
                        <item>s3: This is just some text, not a real example.</item>
                     </list></p>
                  <p>This can be encoded using empty <gi>ge:undo</gi> elements as follows:
                        <!-- undoing1.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line>This is <del stage="#s2" xml:id="del_1" rend="overstrike"><ge:undo
                                 target="#del_1" spanTo="#X02" rend="dotted" stage="#s3"/>just some
                                 <anchor xml:id="X02"/>sample <ge:undo target="#del_1" spanTo="#x4"
                                 rend="dotted" stage="#s3"/>text,<anchor xml:id="x4"/> we need
                              </del><add stage="#s2">not </add>a real example.</ge:line>
                     </egXML> The <att>target</att> attributes on <gi>undo</gi> point to
                     the elements representing the initial acts  (the
		     deletions) which are undone. The <att>rend</att>
		     attribute indicates the way this reversion is
		     indicated. The <att>spanTo</att> attributes
		     points to the <gi>anchor</gi> which marks the
		     point in the text where this reversion
		     finishes.  Since two non-contiguous parts
                     of the deletion are undone, there are two
		     <gi>ge:undo</gi> elements, each with the
		     appropriate attribute values.  If
		     <att>spanTo</att> is not supplied, the
		  <gi>ge:undo</gi> is understood to refer to the
		  whole of the text contained by the element indicated
		  by its <att>target</att> attribute. </p>
               </div>
               <!-- my version in talk is different -->
               <div>
                  <head>Instant corrections</head>
                  <p>The use of tags such as <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> necessarily implies that
                     the modification concerned was made at some time after the original writing. An
                     exception to this is where a false start or <soCalled>instant</soCalled>
                     correction has been identified: the author starts to write, and then
                     immediately corrects what has been written. A special mechanism is provided for
                     this case: an <att>instant</att> attribute has been introduced to
                        <ident>att.editLike</ident>, whose datatype is
                        <ident>data.xTruthValue</ident> and <code>false</code> is the default value.
                     When the value of <att>instant</att> is <code>true</code> this indicates that
                     the addition or deletion is considered to belong to the same writing stage as
                     the rest of the unmodified document, while <code>false</code> means some stage
                     later than the current stage.</p>
                  <p> An example of false start can be seen in the following line: <figure>
                        <graphic url="examples/whitman03a.jpg" width="400px"/>
                        <head>http://www.whitmanarchive.org/resources/sleepers/uva.00256.001.jpg</head>
                     </figure> in which we can detect the following sequence of events: <list
                        type="ordered">
                        <item>The letter T is written and then immediately deleted</item>
                        <item>The word The is written, deleted, and replaced by the word His</item>
                        <item>The added word His is then deleted</item>
                        <item>The initial letter i of the words iron necklace is overwritten with a
                           capital I</item>
                     </list> To indicate that the first of these acts must have taken place before
                     the others, we might encode this revision campaign as follows:
                        <!-- whitman03a.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <ge:line><del instant="true">T</del>
                           <subst>
                              <del>The</del>
                              <add place="above">
                                 <del rend="overstrike">His</del>
                              </add>
                           </subst>
                           <subst>
                              <del rend="overwritten">i</del>
                              <add place="superimposed">I</add>
                           </subst>ron necklace</ge:line>
                     </egXML>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>The dossier level</head>
            <p>The term <term>dossier</term> is used to refer to the set of documents which a
               genetic editor considers as having contributed to the evolution of a particular text.
               These may include drafts, revisions, or documents related in other ways.</p>
            <div>
               <head>Assembling a dossier</head>
               <p>Since a dossier needs to be assembled from many documents, which will most
                  probably be encoded in distinct TEI documents, one way to assemble a dossier’s
                  contents for further processing would be to use the existing
                     <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element in combination with <ref
                     target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xinclude/">XML
		     Inclusions (XInclude)</ref>. The
		     <gi>teiCorpus</gi> construct  provides for a
		     common place to record metadata
                  regarding the organization of the dossier itself, independently of
                  the metadata regarding each particular document contained within it, which would
                  be held in a discrete TEI Header attached to that particular encoded document. The
                  XInclude mechanism provides a convenient means of managing the
                  many separate resources which are likely to be needed to constitute a complete
                  dossier. For example, supposing we have a dossier comprising three documents, each
                  of which has been encoded in its own document:</p>
               <!-- dossier_1.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <teiCorpus xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
                     xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                     xmlns:ge="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions">
                     <![CDATA[<teiHeader>
                        <!-- information about the dossier -->  
                     </teiHeader>
                     <xi:include href="document1.xml"/>
                     <xi:include href="document2.xml"/>
                     <xi:include href="document3.xml"/>
                     ]]>
                  </teiCorpus>
               </egXML>
               <p>(Note that each of the documents referenced (<ident>document1.xml</ident> etc)
                  should contain a complete <gi>TEI</gi> element.)</p>
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Genetic Graphs</head>
               <p>Looking at the documents which constitute a given dossier, there are many types of
                  relationships which can be identified, both amongst complete documents, and
                  amongst parts of those documents, including alterations, revisions, stages and
                  other compositional phenomena. A further complexity arises if for example an
                  author chooses to correct two different versions at the same time,<note
                     place="foot">Manzoni, for instance, used to modify an old draft to see how a
                     new variant fitted with the context before copying it into a new draft.</note>.
                  We may thus need to express that two or more documents are related in different
                  ways; for instance, one document may be the sequel of another, one may have been
                  drafted at the same time as another, one may contain material or treat topics
                  related to those of another, for example a newspaper article may inspire or be
                  quoted by a given work.</p>
               <p>We propose to model the <soCalled>genetic relations</soCalled> one can deduce from
                  such penomena by means of a <term>graph</term>. <note place="foot">Graph-like data
                     structures have many applications. An early proposal to use such a formalism
                     for handling textual variation is <bibl><author>Sperberg-McQueen, C.M.</author>
                        (1989). <title>A directed-graph data structure for text
                        manipulation</title>. In: <title>ICCH/ALLC Conference. The Dynamic Text at
                           the University of Toronto.</title>
                        <ref type="URL"
                           >http://www.w3.org/People/cmsmcq/1989/rhine-delta-abstract.html</ref></bibl>.
                     For a recent one, see <bibl><author>Desmond Schmidt</author>
                        <author>Robert Colomb</author> (2009): <title>A data structure for
                           representing multi-version texts online</title> (in <title level="s"
                           >International Journal of Human-Computer Studies</title>,
                           <biblScope>Volume 67 , Issue 6 (June 2009)</biblScope>
                        <biblScope type="pp">497-514 </biblScope>
                     </bibl>
                  </note> A graph is a mathematical representation composed of <term>node</term>s
                  and <term>arcs</term>. Nodes represent objects, which are related: Typical objects
                  in our case are documents, document components, text stages (as defined in <ptr
                     target="#stages"/> below) or even single phenomena (acts of writing or a
                  textual alterations). Each arc between two nodes then represents a relation, 
                  in our case a genetic relation, between the two
		  objects it links. Arcs may be typed and directed to further specify the kind of
                  relationship they represent. For our purposes one can assume that a typical
                  genetic graph is directed and acyclic, because we generally expect the
                     <term>paths</term> through a genetic graph (formally defined as an ordered set
                  of nodes traversed by following its arcs) to represent genetic processes with an
                  implied chronological order. In this respect a genetic graph resembles a family tree,
                  in that there is a single terminal node,
		  representing the final or published version
                  of a text with many preceding nodes linking to it, either directly or via other
                  nodes, each of which represents draft versions of various parts. Alternatively,
                  there may be more than one final state, e. g. in the case of multiple published
                  texts or unpublished fragments.</p>
               <p>A visual representation of an exemplary genetic graph might look as follows:<figure>
                     <graphic url="examples/geneticRel.png" width="400px"/>
                  </figure></p>
               <p>What can be seen here is on a very abstract level: The nodes (drawn as rectangular
                  shapes with letters) represent parts of the dossier, the directed arcs (drawn as
                  lines with arrows) represent relationships between the parts (probably of an
                  evolutionary type). Thus the graph can be read as A and B being precursors of C, C
                  in turn leading to F, F to G, G to H, and H leading to the final state Z, which
                  additionally draws influences from E and D.</p>
               <p>All this abstract information can be encoded using the following elements (see
                  also the Guidelines chapter 19. Graphs, Networks, and Trees): <specList>
                     <specDesc key="graph" atts="type"/>
                     <specDesc key="node" atts="value"/>
                     <specDesc key="arc" atts="from to value"/>
                  </specList>
               </p>
               <!--geneticRel.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <graph type="directed">
                     <node xml:id="A" value="http://edition.net/witness/A">
                        <label>A</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="B" value="http://edition.net/witness/B">
                        <label>B</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="C" value="http://edition.net/witness/C">
                        <label>C</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="D" value="http://edition.net/witness/X#part1">
                        <label>D</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="E" value="http://edition.net/witness/X#part2">
                        <label>E</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="F" value="http://edition.net/witness/F">
                        <label>F</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="G" value="http://edition.net/witness/G">
                        <label>G</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="H" value="http://edition.net/witness/H">
                        <label>H</label>
                     </node>
                     <node xml:id="Z" value="http://edition.net/text/">
                        <label>Z</label>
                     </node>
                     <arc xml:id="AC" from="#A" to="#C"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#ac"/>
                     <arc xml:id="BC" from="#B" to="#C"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#bc"/>
                     <arc xml:id="CF" from="#C" to="#F"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#cf"/>
                     <arc xml:id="FG" from="#F" to="#G"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#fg"/>
                     <arc xml:id="GH" from="#G" to="#H"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#gh"/>
                     <arc xml:id="DZ" from="#D" to="#Z"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#dz"/>
                     <arc xml:id="EZ" from="#E" to="#Z"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#ez"/>
                     <arc xml:id="HZ" from="#H" to="#Z"
                        value="http://edition.net/genetic/analysis#hz"/>
                  </graph>
               </egXML>
               <p>Such an abstract graph structure can be easily imported into or exported from a
                  graph database, transformed into other XML-based representations of graph-based
                  data models like <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-rdf-syntax/">RDF/XML</ref>,
                  or it can be serialized to <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/SVG11/">SVG</ref> for
                  interactive visualization.</p>
               <!-- <p>The number of possible paths that might be drawn for a given dossier is not of
                  course limited in any way: the encoder may derive as many as they wish. They may
                  also wish to represent other forms of syntagmatic structure, for narratalogical or
                  other purposes, using essentially the same mechanism. </p> -->
               <!-- TODO: show transformation of a path to a timeline -->
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Genetic analysis</head>
               <p>With the graph’s abstract structure defined, one can now go on and specify what
                  the nodes and arcs actually represent. This is done by assigning properties to
                  them via the <att>value</att> attribute. In the example the nodes A-H point to
                  individual witnesses, D and E being an exception as they point to different parts
                  of the same witness. The node Z (the final state in our example) supposedly points
                  to the edited text and each arc’s value points to a resource, whose contents
                  comprise the <term>genetic analysis</term>, which underlies the assumed genetic
                  relations expressed in the graph.</p>
               <p>[...]</p>
               <!-- TODO: example for the contents of a genetic analysis with commentary, discussion of certainty etc. -->
            </div>
            <div>
               <head>Constructing genetic graphs</head>
               <p>It is highly unlikely, that editors will construct and encoded genetic graphs by
                  hand, unless the dossier is as simply structured as the given example. Rather a
                  typical workflow might be:</p>
               <list type="ordered">
                  <item>The editor transcribes each witness in a separate TEI document.</item>
                  <item>During the transcription process phenomena of genetic relevance are
                     annotated with identifiers, that classify these phenoma as belonging to a
                     certain genetic process or that simply relates these phenomena in a
                     well-defined way.</item>
                  <item>By automatically collecting and evaluating all those annotations from all
                     transcribed documents, a preliminary graph is constructed, that can be
                     visualized and navigated.</item>
                  <item>Steps 1-3 are repeated up to the point, where the graph cannot be further
                     refined via this procedure.</item>
                  <item>Optionally, the automatically constructed graph can be annotated
                     manually.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For example in the genetic edition of Goethe’s Faust, the final text is known and
                  can therefore serve as a canonical reference system for constructing genetic
                  relations. Each verse has a unique number:</p>
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <speaker>Faust.</speaker>
                  <lg>
                     <l n="354">Habe nun, ach! Philosophie,</l>
                     <l n="355">Juristerei und Medicin,</l>
                     <l n="356">Und leider auch Theologie!</l>
                     <l n="357">Durchaus studirt, mit heißem Bemühn.</l>
                     <l n="358">Da steh' ich nun, ich armer Thor!</l>
                     <l n="359">Und bin so klug als wie zuvor;</l>
                  </lg>
               </egXML>
               <p>This makes it possible to express genetic relations
	       by using these same verse numbers to index
	       corresponding verses or ranges of verse-numbers throughout their various
	       witnesses, stages or variants. Although a genetic graph generated from
                  the coindexed verses will not be of a very fine
		  granularity, it can be a useful preliminary  base
		  for subsequent refinement. By incorporating metadata for the witnesses (especially
                  dating information) and results of collation eith other relevant information, the
                  graph can be  enriched in an iterative manner and periodically checked for
                  consistency. Finally, together with the transcriptions, collation results, and a
                  critical apparatus it can be archived as an integral part of the genetic
                  edition.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div xml:id="collation">
            <head>*Collation and Critical Apparatus</head>
            <p>As noted <ref target="#alteration">above</ref>, not all kinds of variation within and
               between documents are equivalent. For example, most people would regard authorial
               modifications within a single draft or between subsequent drafts as having a
               different significance from modifications assigned to scribal variation within a long
               textual tradition, despite their formal similarities.</p>
            <p>When a passage has been visibly deleted in one version of a text we will generally
               mark it explicitly; if however a passage present in one version (A) is omitted in
               another (B), it may be a matter of uncertainty as to whether it has been deleted from
               B, or added to A. Even if this is certain (perhaps because the order of the two
               versions is known), the omission from B of material in A is not entirely the same
               phenomenon as an explicit deletion.</p>
            <p>The addition (or deletion) of a segment from a version is normally a deliberate act
               of the author and we would like to be able to record that in positive way; whether we
               need another set of editorial elements or we should use the same set that are used
               for transcription remains an open question. </p>
            <p>Identifying additions or deletions on the basis of a comparison of different versions
               of a text is possible, using existing TEI elements for critical editing such as
                  <gi>app</gi> and its child <gi>rdg</gi> elements. This method uses the argument
                  <foreign xml:lang="lat">e silentio</foreign>: for example, to identify that
               something is missing from a witness, all available readings must be compared, and
               there is no way of explicitly marking an absent (or additional) reading. For
               instance, the 1856 edition of <title>Leaves of Grass</title>of the 1856 omits the
               words <soCalled>all, all</soCalled> which are included in the 1881-82 version. We may
               record this as an apparatus: <!-- app.xml --><egXML
                  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l n="22">And the enraged and treacherous dispositions <app>
                        <rdg wit="#Leaves81-82">, all, all</rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#Leaves56"/>
                     </app> sleep</l>
               </egXML> but this does not indicate whether the words were deleted consciously from
               the 1856 dedition, or added in the 1881 version. Furthermore, if we decided to use
               the existing <gi>add</gi> or <gi>del</gi> elements within the <gi>rdg</gi>, for
               example: <!-- app.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <l n="22">And the enraged and treacherous dispositions <app>
                        <rdg wit="#Leaves81-82">
                           <add>, all, all</add>
                        </rdg>
                        <rdg wit="#Leaves56"/>
                     </app>...</l>
               </egXML> the result would be ambiguous: it might indicate that there is an explicit
               addition (for example, by interlinear or marginal interpolation) within the 1881
               text, or it might indicate that this addition appears as a result of collating the
               1881 and 1856 texts. </p>
            <!--

attach difference information to arcs; examples needed

need to invent a null-reading element for app

qualifications 

standoff for readings

transposition can also be included in apparatus

-->
            <!-- 
<list >
   <item>Only one document has been entirely transcribed (perhaps the first or
             the last version), while the others are only reconstructable via
             collation, which can be stored within the same document or in a separate
             one.</item>
   <item>All documents composing a dossier have been transcribed and the
             collation is stored in a separate document</item>
</list></p>
    <div>
<head>One document is transcribed</head>
<p>If, beside the base-text which is fully transcribed, all extant witnesses
          have to be reconstructed via collation, it is essential to be able to
          distinguish alterations that happen within them and between witnesses. For
          instance, using the existing tag set we could possibly encode as follows:
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
 <l n="22">And the enraged and treacherous dispositions<app>
     <lem wit="#Leaves81-82">
 <add>, all, all</add>
     </lem>
     <rdg wit="#Leaves56"/>
  </app> sleep</l>
   </egXML></p>
<p>Nevertheless, this might force the intended usage of <gi>add</gi> as it
          might imply that there is an addition (interlinear, marginal or wherever) on
          the edition 1881-82 (a problem which will certainly be magnified with
          manuscripts) which is not the case. -->
            <p>One solution might be to use a different element (say <gi>ge:interAdd</gi>) for
               addition implied by collation, reserving <gi>add</gi> for deletions that happen at
               the document level. Another, if all the documents have been fully transcribed, might
               be to use stand off techniques to represent the collation. This is a more promising
               possibility which the workgroup has not yet fully explored. If all the alterations
               occurring at document level are already encoded within each transcription, the
               dossier-level collation will only need to point to passages within the separate files
               and classify the types of readings resulting from the collation:
                  <!-- app.xml --><egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <app xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                     <rdg wit="#Leaves81-82">
                        <span from="#v22-5" to="#v22-8" type="add"/>
                     </rdg>
                     <rdg wit="#Leaves56">
                        <span from="#v22-5" type="del"/>
                     </rdg>
                  </app>
               </egXML>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div>
            <head>Manuscript and Dossier Levels</head>
            <div xml:id="stages">
               <head>Stages/ Revision campaigns</head>
               <p>A major purpose of genetic editing is the identification of <soCalled>revision
                     campaigns</soCalled> or, more generally, <term>stages</term>. A genetic editor
                  needs to be able to assign a set of alterations (deletions, additions,
                  substitutions, transpositions, etc.) and/or an act of writing to a particular
                  stage, to indicate both that one or more of such phenomena preceded or followed
                  another and also to indicate that they are related in some way, for example that
                  one is a consequence of the other. To document this we need: <list>
                     <item>a system to assign phenomena to a particular stage</item>
                     <item>a way to characterize a stage, in itself and in relation to other
                        stages.</item>
                  </list></p>
               <p>The existing element <gi>creation</gi> (within the TEI Header profile description)
                  is defined as the appropriate location for all information relating to the genesis
                  or production of a text. We modify it slightly to permit a new
                     <gi>stageNotes</gi> element which contains a number of <gi>stageNote</gi>
                  elements, one for each identified stage:
<listSpec>
<specDesc key="stageNotes" atts="ordered"/>
<specDesc key="stageNote"/>
</listSpec>
	       </p>
               <p>In the following example taken from the genetic edition of Goethe’s
                  Faust, the editor has identified four distinct stages:</p>
               <!-- faust_1.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <profileDesc>
                     <creation>
                        <ge:stageNotes ordered="true">
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="ST-1">First stage, written in ink by a
                              writer</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="ST-2">Second stage, written in Goethe's hand using
                              pencil</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="ST-3">Fixation of the revised passages and
                              further revisions by Goethe using ink</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="ST-4">Addition of
			   another stanza in a different hand, probably
                              at a later stage</ge:stageNote>
                        </ge:stageNotes>
                     </creation>
                  </profileDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p>The  <gi>stageNotes</gi> elements
                  carries an attribute <att>ordered</att>, which can take the values
                     <code>true</code>  or <code>false</code> (the default). The attribute specifies
                  whether the order of child elements signifies a temporal order for the 
                  revision campaigns which they document. In the Faust example above, the
		   editor has asserted that the four stages distinguished are ordered chronologically
                  according to the order of the <gi>stageNote</gi> elements. Note that asserting a
                  specific order early on, though probably one of the hardest tasks in a genetic
                  analysis, can considerably reduce the encoding effort in assigning textual alterations to
                  stages during the transcription, as we will see below. For instance
                  deletions can only be assigned to a stage that follows the one in which the
                  passage being deleted was written down. Hence, having a certain order of stages put in
                  place before transcription begins, will allow the encoder to reduce verbose
                  tagging, where default assumptions based on the natural order of actions can be
                  made.</p>
               <p>If necessary, <gi>stageNotes</gi> elements can be nested hierarchically. This may
                  be helpful in two cases. Firstly one can build up hypotheses about related
                  revisions step-by-step, starting with stages of smaller coverage, whose members
                  are certainly related, and then in a subsequent pass grouping these stages in
                  turn, thereby extending their reach.</p>
               <!-- stages.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <profileDesc>
                     <creation>
                        <ge:stageNotes>
			  <ge:stageNote xml:id="o">An unrelated stage note</ge:stageNote>
			  <ge:stageNotes xml:id="m" cert="low"> 
			    <ge:stageNote xml:id="m1">Alterations on one manuscript page, certainly
                                 related</ge:stageNote>
                             <ge:stageNote xml:id="m2">Alterations on another manuscript page,
                                 certainly related</ge:stageNote>
			  <ge:stageNote xml:id="p">Another unrelated stage note</ge:stageNote>
                        </ge:stageNotes>
			</ge:stageNotes>			
                     </creation>
                  </profileDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p>Another use case for nested <gi>stageNote</gi> elements would be the need to
                  express a <emph>partial</emph> ordering of revision campaigns.</p>
               <!-- stages.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <ge:stageNotes ordered="true">
                     <ge:stageNote xml:id="ST1">The first stage</ge:stageNote>
                     <ge:stageNotes xml:id="STlast"> 
<!-- We have no indication, which  of the following revision
campaigns took place first, but we know they followed ST1 -->.
                        <ge:stageNote xml:id="ST-rev1">A revision of the first stage</ge:stageNote>
                        <ge:stageNote xml:id="ST-rev2">Another revision of the first
                           stage</ge:stageNote>
		     </ge:stageNotes>
		  </ge:stageNotes>
               </egXML>
               <p>In addition to the possibility of ordering text stages in relation to each other,
                     <gi>stageNote</gi> elements may carry a number of attributes from the
                     <ident>att.datable</ident> class (<att>period</att>, <att>when</att>,
                     <att>notBefore</att>, <att>notAfter</att>, <att>from</att>, and <att>to</att>)
                  which allow each stage to be dated as exactly or inexactly as necessary, in the
                  same way as is currently possible for the TEI <gi>date</gi> element.</p>
               <!-- Maybe note that absolute dates and relative order can conflict -->
               <!-- stages.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <profileDesc>
                     <creation>
                        <date notAfter="1816-07-18"/>
                        <ge:stageNotes ordered="true">
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="mod1" when="1816-07-16">The first draft of
                                 <title>Persuasion</title> is completed by the <date>July 16
                                 1816</date> written after the word <q>Finis</q> at <ref
                                 target="#pers-30">page 30</ref>.</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="mod2" notBefore="1816-07-16">After the <date>16th
                                 of July</date> Austen starts revision of the two final chapters, by
                              rewriting the end and adding a new block (<ref target="#transp-1"
                                 >pages 32-35</ref>) to be inserted at <ref target="#insertion-p1"
                                 >page 19</ref>. This stage is documented by the deletion of the
                              date (<date>July 16 1816</date>) at <ref target="#pers-30">page
                                 30</ref>, and the addition of more text and of a new date
                                 (<date>July 18. 1816</date>) at <ref target="#pers-31">page
                                 31</ref></ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote notBefore="1816-07-18">Before publication, after <date>July
                                 18th, 1816</date> chapters 10-11 were broken into three chapters,
                              10, 11, 12, as witnessed by the print.</ge:stageNote>
                        </ge:stageNotes>
                     </creation>
                  </profileDesc>
               </egXML>
               <p>Each <gi>stageNote</gi> element, apart from
	       declaring a text stage, may also contain references to other
                  annotations contained within the <gi>teiHeader</gi> or in the document (as shown
                  in the previous example). Such references, along with the textual content are
                   purely documentary and do not affect the textual
		   stage associated with any element thus referred
		   to. The association of a textual component with a
		   writing stage is always made  explicitly, either by
		   pointing from the <gi>stageNote</gi>  attribute
                     <att>target</att> to one or more elements, or
		     (for preference) by pointing from the element
		     concerned to the
                     <gi>stageNote</gi> element by means of its <att>stage</att> attribute:</p>
               <!-- stages.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <ge:line stage="#firstStage">This is a <subst stage="#secondStage">
                        <del>house</del>
                        <add>mouse</add>
                     </subst>.</ge:line>
               </egXML>
               <p>This simple example shows the latter of the two options: The relevant stages are
                  declared in the header; then textual alterations and acts of writing are assigned
                  to them. So the whole sentence was realized in the first stage, while the
                  substitution of “house” with “mouse” happened at the second stage. <!--Here the
                  assumed ordering of the stages and default assumptions about the natural ordering
                  of the textual alterations allows to reduce the tagging considerably, as only the
                  addition has to be annotated, whereas the substitution and consequently the
                  deletion are assumed to happen at the same stage.--></p>
               <p>A more complex and complete example:</p>
               <!-- faust_1.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <profileDesc>
                     <creation>
                        <ge:stageNotes type="ordered">
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="firstStage">First stage, written in ink by a
                              writer</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="secondStage">Revised by Goethe using
                              pencil</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="thirdStage">Fixation of the revised passages and
                              further revisions by Goethe using ink</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote xml:id="fourthStage">Addition of another stanza, probably
                              at a later stage</ge:stageNote>
                        </ge:stageNotes>
                     </creation>
                  </profileDesc> [...] <div stage="#firstStage">
                     <l n="11656">
                        <subst>
                           <del>Ihr</del>
                           <add>
                              <ge:rewrite stage="#thirdStage">
                                 <seg stage="#secondStage">Nun</seg>
                              </ge:rewrite>
                           </add>
                        </subst> wanſtige Schuften mit den Feuerbacken</l>
                     <l n="11657">Ihr glüht ſo recht vom Höllen Schwefel <subst
                           stage="#secondStage
                           #thirdStage">
                           <del>ſatt</del>
                           <add>feiſt</add>
                        </subst>.</l>
                     <l n="11658">
                        <delSpan spanTo="#anchor_delSpan_1" stage="#thirdStage"/>Ihr hagren,
                        triſten, krummgezog<subst>
                           <del>nen</del>
                           <add>ener</add>
                        </subst> Nacken</l>
                     <l>Wenn ihr nur piepſet iſt die Welt ſchon matt.<anchor
                           xml:id="anchor_delSpan_1"/></l>
                  </div>
               </egXML>
               <p>Note first, that a stage, once assigned to an element, is inherited by all
                  descendents of that element, unless overridden by a subsequent assignment. So in
                  the example above the three verses are assigned to the first stage initially. The
                  writing of <mentioned>Nun</mentioned> (as part of the substitution in the first verse) takes place in
                  the second stage and is repeated or fixated in the third. Also the
                  substitution in the second verse is done repeatedly: initially it takes place in
                  the second stage, but is fixated as a whole in the third.</p>
               <p>As one can see, the interpretation of what the stage assignments mean for a
                  particular text passage and the actions upon it can be based on a number of
                  implicit assumptions and constraints which have the
		  effect of  minimizing the amount of tagging necessary. If
                  it is desired to make these presuppositions more explicit, one can differentiate between
                  acts of writing and textual alterations and accordingly between their assignment
                  to stages as follows:</p>
               <!-- faust_2.xml -->
               <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                  <profileDesc>
                     <creation>
                        <ge:stageNotes type="ordered">
                           <ge:stageNote target="#zone_1 #subst_3">First stage, written in ink by a
                              writer</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote
                              target="#zone_2 #mod_1 #line_1 #line_2 #subst_1 #subst_2
                              #subst_4 #delSpan_1"
                              >Revised by Goethe using pencil</ge:stageNote>
                           <ge:stageNote
                              target="#redo_1 #redo_2 #redo_3 #subst_1 #subst_2
                              #delSpan_1 #add_1"
                              >Fixation of the revised passages and further revisions by Goethe
                              using ink</ge:stageNote>
                        </ge:stageNotes>
                     </creation>
                  </profileDesc> [...] <ge:document>
                     <surface>
                        <zone xml:id="zone_1">
                           <ge:line xml:id="line_1">
                              <handShift new="#g_bl"/>
                              <ge:rewrite hand="#g_t" xml:id="redo_1">Nun</ge:rewrite>
                           </ge:line>
                           <ge:line><handShift new="#jo_t"/>Ihr wanſtige Schuften mit den
                              Feuerbacken</ge:line>
                           <ge:line xml:id="line_2">
                              <handShift new="#g_bl"/>
                              <ge:rewrite hand="#g_t" xml:id="redo_2">feiſt</ge:rewrite>
                           </ge:line>
                           <ge:line>Ihr glüht ſo recht vom Höllen Schwefel ſatt.</ge:line> [...]
                        </zone>
                     </surface>
                  </ge:document>
                  <text>
                     <body>
                        <l n="11656">
                           <subst xml:id="subst_1">
                              <del>Ihr</del>
                              <add>Nun</add>
                           </subst> wanſtige Schuften mit den Feuerbacken</l>
                        <l n="11657">Ihr glüht ſo recht vom Höllen Schwefel <subst xml:id="subst_2">
                              <del>ſatt</del>
                              <add>feiſt</add>
                           </subst>.</l>
                     </body>
                  </text>
               </egXML>
               <p>Here two transcriptions of the same passage are given, one from a documentary
                  perspective stressing the writing process, and one from the textual perspective
                  emphasizing textual alterations. The assignment to stages is also done
                  differently here, pointing from the stage notes to the text passages and
                  alterations in question. From  the documentary perspective, the stage
                  assignments describe the writing process, in that they specify, which segment has
                  been written when and how often. From the textual
		  perspective, the markup
                  concentrates on the order of textual alterations and
		  makes no assumptions about
                  the order of writing.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div>
            <head>ODD</head>
            <p>TEI Extension for Genetic Editions -- preliminary version</p>
            <schemaSpec ident="geneticTEI" docLang="en" xml:lang="en" targetLang="en">
               <!-- =============== Modules =============== -->
               <moduleRef key="core"/>
               <moduleRef key="tei"/>
               <moduleRef key="header"/>
               <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
               <moduleRef key="certainty"/>
               <moduleRef key="analysis"/>
               <moduleRef key="drama"/>
               <moduleRef key="linking"/>
               <moduleRef key="msdescription"/>
               <moduleRef key="nets"/>
               <moduleRef key="figures"/>
               <moduleRef key="textcrit"/>
               <moduleRef key="transcr"/>
               <moduleRef key="gaiji"/>
               <moduleRef key="namesdates"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="analytic" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="biblItem" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="biblStruct" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="binaryObject" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="broadcast" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="analysis" ident="cl" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="analysis" ident="c" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div1"/>
               <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div2"/>
               <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div3"/>
               <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div4"/>
               <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div5"/>
               <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div6"/>
               <elementSpec module="textstructure" mode="delete" ident="div7"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="equipment" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="equiv" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="fsdDecl" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="headItem" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="headLabel" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="meeting" mode="delete"/>
               <!-- <elementSpec module="figures" ident="table" mode="delete"/>-->
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="metDecl" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="metSym" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="monogr" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="postBox" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="postCode" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="recording" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="recordingStmt" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="state" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="stdVals" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="street" mode="delete"/>
               <!--elementSpec module="header" ident="tagsDecl" mode="delete"/-->
               <elementSpec module="analysis" ident="w" mode="delete"/>
               <!--elementSpec module="header" ident="tagUsage" mode="delete"/-->
               <elementSpec module="core" ident="imprint" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="header" ident="rendition" mode="delete"/>
               <!--elementSpec module="header" ident="namespace" mode="delete"/-->
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="addName" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="age" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="birth" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="bloc" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="death" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="district" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="education" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="event" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="faith" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="floruit" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="forename" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="genName" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="geo" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="geogFeat" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="geogName" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="langKnowledge" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="langKnown" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="lisEvent" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="lystNym" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="listOrg" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="listPerson" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="listPlace" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="location" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="nameLink" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="nationality" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="nym" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="occupation" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="offset" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="org" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="orgName" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="person" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="personGrp" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="place" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="population" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="region" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="residence" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="roleName" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="sex" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="socecStatus" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="surname" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="terrain" mode="delete"/>
               <elementSpec module="namesdates" ident="trait" mode="delete"/>
               <!-- =============== Content models for the documentary view =============== -->
               <classSpec ident="model.zonePart" type="model" mode="add">
                  <desc>elements which can form part of a zone</desc>
               </classSpec>
               <classSpec ident="model.linePart" type="model" mode="add">
                  <desc>elements which can form part of a line</desc>
               </classSpec>
               <!-- =============== Topographical document structure =============== -->
               <elementSpec ident="document" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>contains a document-centric transcription of a primary source, providing
                     topographical information as well as transcription</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.resourceLike"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:oneOrMore>
                        <rng:ref name="surface"/>
                        <rng:zeroOrMore>
                           <rng:ref name="model.global.edit"/>
                        </rng:zeroOrMore>
                     </rng:oneOrMore>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="surface" module="physdesc" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="att.typed" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:zeroOrMore>
                        <rng:choice>
                           <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
                           <rng:ref name="model.glossLike"/>
                           <rng:ref name="model.graphicLike"/>
                           <rng:ref name="zone"/>
                           <rng:ref name="patch"/>
                        </rng:choice>
                     </rng:zeroOrMore>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="patch" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>contains a part of a written surface which was originally physically
                     distinct but became attached to it at the time that one or more written zones
                     were created.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="att.coordinated"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:zeroOrMore>
                        <rng:choice>
                           <rng:text/>
                           <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
                           <rng:ref name="zone"/>
                        </rng:choice>
                     </rng:zeroOrMore>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="binder" mode="add">
                        <desc>Describe the method by which a patch is or was connected to the main
                           surface</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.enumerated"/>
                        </datatype>
                        <valList type="open">
                           <valItem ident="glued">
                              <desc>patch is glued in place</desc>
                           </valItem>
                           <valItem ident="pinned">
                              <desc>patch is pinned or stapled in place</desc>
                           </valItem>
                           <valItem ident="sewn">
                              <desc>patch is sewn in place</desc>
                           </valItem>
                        </valList>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="flipping" mode="add">
                        <desc>indicates whether the patch is attached and folded in such a way as to
                           provide two writing surfaces</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.truthValue"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="height">
                        <desc>height of the patch</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.outputMeasurement"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="width">
                        <desc>width of the patch</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.outputMeasurement"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="zone" module="physdesc" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="att.coordinated" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:zeroOrMore>
                        <rng:choice>
                           <rng:text/>
                           <rng:ref name="model.zonePart"/>
                           <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
                        </rng:choice>
                     </rng:zeroOrMore>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="rotate" mode="add">
                        <desc>indicates the amount by which this zone has been rotated clockwise,
                           with respect to the normal orientation of the parent <gi>surface</gi>
                           element as implied by the dimensions given in the <gi>msDesc</gi> section
                           or by the coordinates of the <gi>surface</gi> itself. The orientation is
                           expressed in arc degrees.</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
                           <rng:ref name="data.count"/>
                        </datatype>
                        <defaultVal>0</defaultVal>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="line" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>contains the transcription of a topographic line in the source
                     document</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:zeroOrMore>
                        <rng:choice>
                           <rng:text/>
                           <rng:ref name="model.global"/>
                           <rng:ref name="model.linePart"/>
                        </rng:choice>
                     </rng:zeroOrMore>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- =============== Text stages =============== -->
               <classSpec ident="att.staged" type="atts" mode="add" module="tei">
                  <desc>groups elements which can be assigned to a specific text stage by means of
                     the attributes it provides.</desc>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="stage" mode="add">
                        <desc>points to one or more <gi>stageNote</gi> elements which contain a
                           description of a text-stage to which the editors think the alteration/
                           text passage marked by the element bearing this attribute (and its
                           children) belongs.</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                           <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </classSpec>
               <classSpec type="atts" ident="att.global" mode="change" module="tei">
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="att.global.linking"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global.analytic"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global.facs"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.staged" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </classSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="creation" mode="change">
                  <content>
                     <rng:ref name="macro.phraseSeq.limited"/>
                     <rng:optional>
                        <rng:ref name="stageNotes"/>
                     </rng:optional>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="stageNotes" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions"
                  mode="add">
                  <desc>contains one or more descriptions of the stages which have been identified
                     in the genesis of a text.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:oneOrMore>
		       <rng:choice>
			 <rng:ref name="stageNotes"/>
                        <rng:ref name="stageNote"/>
		       </rng:choice>
                     </rng:oneOrMore>
                  </content>
<attList>
<attDef ident="ordered" mode="add">
                        <desc>indicates whether or not the order in which
			the children of this element are presented is significant</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <ref xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" name="data.truthValue"/>
                        </datatype>
			<defaultVal>true</defaultVal>
                     </attDef>
</attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="stageNote" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions"
                  mode="add">
                  <desc>documents a particular stage in the genesis of a text.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="att.datable"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:zeroOrMore>
                        <rng:choice>
                           <rng:ref name="macro.specialPara"/>
                           <rng:ref name="stageNote"/>
                        </rng:choice>
                     </rng:zeroOrMore>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
                        <desc>points to one or more elements that belong to this stage.</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                           <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- =============== Textual alterations =============== -->
               <elementSpec ident="mod" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>represents any kind of modification identified within a text at a documentary level.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="modSpan" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>represents any kind of modification identified
		  within a text at a documentary level, where this
		  extends over other XML markup constructs in the document.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.global.edit"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:empty/>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="subst" module="transcr" mode="change">
                  <!-- should be in different namespace -->
                  <content>
                     <rng:group>
                        <rng:group>
                           <rng:ref name="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                        </rng:group>
                        <rng:oneOrMore>
                           <rng:choice>
                              <rng:text/>
                              <rng:ref name="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                           </rng:choice>
                        </rng:oneOrMore>
                     </rng:group>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="type" mode="add">
                        <desc>The type of substitution.</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
                           <rng:ref name="data.name"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="transposeGrp" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions"
                  mode="add">
                  <desc>supplies a list of transpositions indicated at some point in the text,
                     typically by means of metamarks.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.profileDescPart"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.global.meta"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:oneOrMore>
                        <rng:ref name="transpose"/>
                     </rng:oneOrMore>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="transpose" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions"
                  mode="add">
                  <desc> describes a single textual transposition as an ordered list of at least two
                     pointers specifying the order in which the elements indicated should be
                     re-combined. </desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:group>
                        <rng:ref name="ptr"/>
                        <rng:oneOrMore>
                           <rng:ref name="ptr"/>
                        </rng:oneOrMore>
                     </rng:group>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- =============== Undo/Redo/Rewrite =============== -->
               <elementSpec ident="undo" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>points to any marked-up intervention in a
		  text which has subsequently been
		  marked as to be cancelled or undone.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:empty/>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
                        <desc>points to the element representing the intervention to be undone.</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
                           <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>


               <classSpec type="atts" ident="att.repeatable">
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="cause">
                        <desc>documents the presumed cause of the repeated act of writing.</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:ref name="data.enumerated"/>
                        </datatype>
                        <valList type="closed">
                           <valItem ident="fix">
                              <desc>repeated for the purpose of fixation</desc>
                           </valItem>
                           <valItem ident="unclear">
                              <desc>repeated to clarify a previously illegible or badly written text
                                 or mark</desc>
                           </valItem>
                        </valList>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </classSpec>

               <elementSpec ident="redo" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
<desc>points to a marked-up intervention in a
		  text which  has subsequently been
		  marked for a second time in a different way. </desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.repeatable"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:empty/>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="target" mode="add">
                        <desc>points to the element representing
			the intervention which is to be repeated.</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="1">
                           <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>

               <elementSpec ident="rewrite" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>contains a sequence of text which has been rewritten by the author, for
                     example by over-inking, to clarify or fix it.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.repeatable"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.transcriptional"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:ref name="macro.paraContent"/>
                  </content>
                  <remarks>
                     <p>Multiple rewritings are indicated by nesting one <gi>rewrite</gi> within
                        another. In principle, a rewriting differs from a substitution in that
                        second and subsequent rewrites do not materially alter the content of an
                        element. Where there are minor changes made during the rewriting however
                        these may be marked up using <gi>del</gi>, <gi>add</gi>, etc. with an
                        appropriate value for the <att>stage</att> attribute.</p>
                  </remarks>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- =============== Authorial changes =============== -->
               <elementSpec ident="metaMark" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>contains any textual or graphical mark in 
		  a written text intended to signal how the text
		  should be read and not forming part of the text itself.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.placement"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
<!--, for example some which 
                     functional but not part of the text. Could transform the text, like a
                     strikethrough, or provide meta-information, like a date-->
                  <content>
                     <rng:ref name="macro.specialPara"/>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="function" mode="add">
                        <desc>describes the function (e.g. add, delete, alternate) of the
                           mark.</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1">
                           <rng:ref name="data.word"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="target">
                        <desc>indicates the element(s) to which the function of the meta-mark
                           refers. Pointers are separated by a white space</desc>
                        <datatype minOccurs="1" maxOccurs="unbounded">
                           <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="used" ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions" mode="add">
                  <desc>a  passage  of text which has been marked as used, usually
                     meaning that it  has been transcribed to a fair copy.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.pPart.transcriptional"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.global"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:empty/>
                  </content>
<remarks><p>The mark is often a
                     strikethrough, but can be any author-specific mark.</p></remarks>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- =============== Genetic Groups =============== -->
               <elementSpec ident="geneticGrp" mode="add"
                  ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions">
                  <desc>Group texts and document which are somehow related in a genetic
                     process</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.profileDescPart"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:oneOrMore>
                        <rng:ref name="geneticNote"/>
                     </rng:oneOrMore>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="geneticNote" mode="add"
                  ns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions">
                  <desc>describes a particular set of documents or document fragments which are
                     considered to be mutually associated in some way.</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.editLike"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:oneOrMore>
                        <rng:ref name="linkGrp"/>
                     </rng:oneOrMore>
                     <rng:oneOrMore>
                        <rng:ref name="model.pLike"/>
                     </rng:oneOrMore>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- =============== Adjust existing classes to new schema =============== -->
               <elementSpec ident="arc" module="nets" mode="change">
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="value" usage="opt" mode="add">
                        <equiv/>
                        <desc>provides the value of an arc, which is a feature structure or other
                           analytic element.</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
                        </datatype>
                        <valDesc>A valid identifier.</valDesc>
                        <remarks>
                           <p>Copied from the node element to support full-featured property graphs,
                              where also arcs may be annotated.</p>
                        </remarks>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <classSpec type="atts" ident="att.editLike" mode="change">
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="instant" mode="add">
                        <desc>Is this an instant revision?</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:ref name="data.xTruthValue"/>
                        </datatype>
                        <defaultVal>false</defaultVal>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </classSpec>
               <!-- TODO: We are note sure, whether it is wise to add so much to the documentary markup -->
               <classSpec type="model" ident="model.gLike" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.linePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </classSpec>
               <classSpec type="model" ident="model.segLike" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.linePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </classSpec>
               <classSpec type="model" ident="model.hiLike" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.linePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </classSpec>
               <classSpec type="model" ident="model.pPart.editorial" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.linePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </classSpec>
               <classSpec type="model" ident="model.pPart.transcriptional" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.linePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </classSpec>
               <classSpec type="model" ident="model.pPart.msdesc" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.linePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </classSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="unclear" module="core" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="att.editLike" mode="add"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="table" mode="change">
                  <classes mode="change">
                     <memberOf key="model.zonePart" mode="add"/>
                  </classes>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- add milestone to att.spanning (this should be done for all
                  model.milestoneLike elements actually -->
               <elementSpec ident="milestone" module="core" mode="change">
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="att.spanning"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.milestoneLike"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                     <memberOf key="att.sourced"/>
                  </classes>
               </elementSpec>
               <!-- =============== XInclude support =============== -->
               <elementSpec ident="include" ns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" mode="add">
                  <desc>The W3C XInclude element</desc>
                  <classes>
                     <memberOf key="model.common"/>
                     <memberOf key="model.headerPart"/>
                  </classes>
                  <content>
                     <rng:optional>
                        <rng:ref name="fallback"/>
                     </rng:optional>
                  </content>
                  <attList>
                     <attDef ident="href">
                        <desc>pointer to the resource being included</desc>
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:ref name="data.pointer"/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="parse" usage="opt">
                        <defaultVal>xml</defaultVal>
                        <valList type="closed">
                           <valItem ident="xml"/>
                           <valItem ident="text"/>
                        </valList>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="xpointer" usage="opt">
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:text/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="encoding" usage="opt">
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:text/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="accept" usage="opt">
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:text/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="accept-charset" usage="opt">
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:text/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                     <attDef ident="accept-language" usage="opt">
                        <datatype>
                           <rng:text/>
                        </datatype>
                     </attDef>
                  </attList>
               </elementSpec>
               <elementSpec ident="fallback" ns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" mode="add">
                  <desc>Wrapper for fallback elements if an XInclude fails</desc>
                  <content>
                     <rng:ref name="AnyThing"/>
                  </content>
               </elementSpec>
               <macroSpec type="pe" ident="AnyThing" mode="add">
                  <desc>Matches any element</desc>
                  <content>
                     <zeroOrMore xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
                        <choice>
                           <element>
                              <anyName/>
                              <zeroOrMore>
                                 <attribute>
                                    <anyName>
                                       <except>
                                          <name>xml:id</name>
                                          <name>xml:lang</name>
                                       </except>
                                    </anyName>
                                 </attribute>
                              </zeroOrMore>
                              <ref name="AnyThing"/>
                           </element>
                           <text/>
                        </choice>
                     </zeroOrMore>
                  </content>
               </macroSpec>
            </schemaSpec>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
