<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xmlns:ge="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Genetic Editions meeting 2010-02-25</title>
		<author>notes taken by Sebastian Rahtz</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p></p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
	<p>This meeting too place at Oxford University Computing Services
	on 25/26 February 2010. Present were
	Malte Rehbein, Elena Pierazza, Lou Burnard, Fotis Jannidis,
	Gregor Middell, James Cummings and Sebastian Rahtz.</p>

	<div>
	  <head>Targets for genetic editions meeting</head>
	  <p>The interaction with this SIG and the TEI Technical
	  Council was discussed. The Council meets in April, and it
	  was agreed that at least part of the proposals which
	  affected the schema of the TEI (ie new and changed elements)
	  should be presented there for agreement. This could be done
	  in a modular way, but with dependencies (ie start with
	  low-level changes and move up to larger components such as
	  <gi>document</gi>?). It is clear that some proposed
	  changes/additions would be to existing chapters, other parts
	  might need a new chapter. The Genetic document as  it stands
	  can be/may be maintained as ongoing tutorial/exemplar
	  (comparable to Lite and Tite), or completely subsumed into
	  the Guidelines. It was agreed that the meeting would attempt
	  to present at least some concrete changes to the Council for
	  April.
	  </p>
	</div>
	<div>
	  <head>Principles</head>
	  <p>Straight into document models, and concepts of stages,
	  layers, physical depth of material etc.</p>
	  <p>Pages torn from
	  diaries and later found, how recorded? How to model
	  <gi>surface</gi>s which are lost, damaged, refound
	  etc. Should be possible to use a combination of
	  <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi> etc. Needs a discussion of the
	  problem in first part of section 3.1.</p>
	  <p>Not clear whether <gi>damage</gi> is a specialization of
	  <gi>zone</gi>, or whether the two concepts are
	  orthogonal. This affects the content model of <gi>zone</gi>
	  - in fact, of <gi>line</gi>, because it is regarded as
	  mandatory that text is always described as one or more lines.
	  </p>

	  <p>The very important point of principle as to whether one
	  should be allowed to encode any analytical elements within
	  <gi>line</gi> caused a long discussion. Do we have just a
	  <gi>seg</gi> wrapper (and allow all the children of
	  <gi>seg</gi>), or nothing, or a new element
	  <gi>segment</gi>, or by-default-empty
	  model.linePart class to let future generations hang
	  themselves. Do we need <gi>hi</gi> to indicate colour, size
	  etc? Probably. <seg type="ACTION">Finally agreed the the content model of
	  <gi>line</gi> should be cut back to hiLike, transcriptional,
	  editorial, gLike and global and <hi>something very like, or
	  itself, <gi>seg</gi></hi> (but without all the baggage
	  inside it).</seg>
	  </p>

	  <p>Did the argument end there? No.</p>

	  <p>What about constructs like tables, formulae and lists?
	  are they part of the document or the interpretation? Tables
	  seem to be special, as they model a system of organizing
	  writing on paper which is different from
	  <gi>line</gi>s. <seg type="ACTION">Agreed to allow <gi>table</gi> as sibling of
	  <gi>line</gi>.</seg> Unfortunately, this has the same problem as
	  <gi>seg</gi>, that <gi>cell</gi> can contain almost anything!.

	  </p>

	</div>

	<div>
	  <head>Manuscript and dossier levels</head>
	  <p><gi>revisionCampaign</gi> and stages. How to encode the 
	  identifed timeline(s) for the document. We need to have some
	  explicit structure, which cannot simply be derived from the
	  document. The TEI <gi>timeline</gi> element is only a
	  skeleton to which parts of the text point, and cannot have
	  its own content. A possible <gi>evolution</gi> element might
	  reverse things and point from itself into the text, but also
	  have its own content. Relationshiop to <gi>graph</gi>? An
	  "evolution" documents a particular path through a
	  graph. Problems over sub-sequences of stages. Stop trying to
	  be so detailed for the moment. In the simplest case of
	  grouping, we used to say use <gi>mod</gi>, otherwise if that falls over
	  point from individual changelets to overall stage model. But
	  why bother, because it fails with overlapping sequences
	  anyway, so <seg type="ACTION">let's drop <gi>mod</gi> and let each event point
	  explicitly to a <gi>change</gi></seg> (remembering that <gi>change</gi>
	  can be nested, so you can be as granular as you like in the
	  linking.)  Forget about <att>seq</att>. What about <eg>stage="0"</eg>?
	  Lord knows. Proposal is to instead <seg type="ACTION">add a new attribute <att>instant</att>,
	  with boolean value which provides some sort of . <q>yes</q> means <q>so close to the current
	  stage that its not worth recording the difference</q>, while
	  <q>no</q> means <q>some stage later than the current stage
	  stage</q>.</seg></p>

	  <p>Dateable objects: is <att>stage</att> the same as <att>period</att> in
	  att.dateable? apparently yes. Both pointers to an location
	  defining a period of time; <att>stage</att> is slightly more
	  general. 
	  <seg type="ACTION">So the relationship of
	  att.staged and att.dateable needs to be resolved. The SIG
	  believes that transcriptional objects should be
	  <q>stageable</q> but not <q>dateable.</q></seg></p>


	  <p>Discussing <gi>rewrite</gi></p>

	  <p>Now discussing spanning modification, like a
	  strikethrough across a whole page. Proposed to resurrect
	  <gi>mod</gi> for this, to mark some spanning-type
	  modification to an arbitrary part of a surface; so
	  <seg type="ACTION"><gi>mod</gi> has to be allowed at any level within a
	  surface. Remove the rider <q>which are
	  considered as belonging to the same revision campaign</q>
	  because we want to get rid of that idea.</seg>
	  </p>

	  <p>Discussion of headings from Gregor (see next section). I
	  don't think I quite got a sense of the discussion :-}</p>

	  <p><hi>Action plan.</hi> Revise the current draft of the document
	  over the next 4 weeks, complete by 2nd April. From that,
	  prepare an executive list of requests to Council by 19th
	  April for submission. Everyone to edit the document on
	  Sourceforge now - ask Lou or Sebastian for commit rights if
	  needed.</p>

	  <p>Jobs for people to concentrate on
	  <list>
	    <item>Gregor: genetic</item>
	    <item>Fotis: <gi>change</gi></item>
	    <item>Elena: document level. She also has to talk about
	    <q>virtual</q> documents</item>
	  </list>
	  </p>

	  <p>Where does all this stuff go in the Guideines? Each of
	  these bits can be done as a separate TEI enhancement
	  <list> 
	    <item>Section 3: improves the current transcriptional
	    chapter. <att>stage</att> belongs in names/people/places/dates
	    chapter, probably</item>
	    <item>Section 1/4: dossiers and documents is a new concept, goes in new
	    section</item>
	    <item>Section 5: improves the critical apparatus/editions
	  chapter</item></list>
	  </p>
	</div>

	<div>
	  <head>Discussion points from Gregor</head>
	  <p>(for the record)</p>
	  <div><head> Theoretical framework (1) </head>
	  
	  <p><hi>Status vs. Process</hi>: The theoretical framework does not address the  
	  question, what is supposed to be encoded on the documentary level: the  
	  text as it is given on the manuscript or the process of its writing?  
	  That decision has practial consequences, e.g. whether a fixation of a  
	  textual passage is transcribed once (because the text is identical) or  
	  twice (because it has been written twice)?</p>
	  </div>
	  
	  <div><head> Aspects of Genetic Editions (2) </head>
	  
	  <p><hi>The topological description</hi>: Besides the transcription/ layout of  
	  the text, to what degree should we offer means of encoding for non- 
	  textual artifacts? It seems, that in trying to classify the different  
	  objects on a manuscript, we observe 4 classes: 1.) purely textual  
	  inscriptions, 2.) purely graphical artifacts (e.g. drawings), 3.)  
	  graphical elements with a stable type/token relationship and 4.)  
	  graphical elements, where this is not the case. We should discuss,  
	  whether this classification is sound and what encoding guidelines we  
	  can give for each class.</p>
	  
	  <p><hi>(Textual) Alterations</hi>: Alterations (additions, deletions,  
	  substitutions etc.) could be distinguished between those, that act on  
	  the text itself (characters added/ removed), and those, that act on  
	  markup (underlining undone/removed, paragraph boundary removed etc.).  
	  We should therefore handle *textual* alterations on the text level,  
	  not on the documentary level, and rethink the concept of alteration/ 
	  variance on the document level.</p>
	  </div>
	  
	  <div><head> Transcription of a document (3.1) </head>
	  
	  <p><hi>Lines</hi>: Lines should be optionally typed (att.typed), e. g. for  
	  normal vs. interlinear lines or counted vs. uncounted lines etc.</p>
	  
	  <p><hi>Topological annotations</hi>: Zones should not be the only target for  
	  the annotation of topological information (coordinates, rotation  
	  etc.). Such information could also make sense on a line, word or even  
	  on a character level. Thus it would be necessary to make arbitrary  
	  segments of character data addressable and to bundle topological  
	  information into a separate class/model (e.g. att.topological), so it  
	  can be attached to elements, that partition the transcription on the  
	  preferred granularity level.</p></div>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Textual alterations (3.2) </head>
	
	<p><hi>Befund vs. Deutung</hi>: A deletion encoded uniquely on the text level  
	(<gi>del/</gi>) can be expressed in different ways on the document level. For  
	example the passage can be striked through (probably the default case)  
	or it can be made invisible by placing a patch over it or ... 1.) We  
	should differentiate between both levels in our draft. 2.) Do we need  
	different tags for each level, or could we make the semantics of  
	existing tags depend on their usage context (<gi>del/</gi> in <gi>ge:line/</gi> vs.  
	<gi>del/</gi> in <gi>p/</gi>)?</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Additions and rewritings (3.2.1) </head>
	
	<p><hi><gi>ge:rewrite/</gi></hi>: As noted above, this element flags a passage as  
	being rewritten, thereby freeing the transcriber from typing the same  
	text twice. As soon as it comes to the genetic analysis of the passage  
	though, one might want to address the two acts of writing separately.</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Deletions and mark as used (3.2.2) </head>
	
	<p><hi>Befund vs. Deutung</hi>: What might be indicated via the same  
	expression on the document level (e. g. a passage being striked  
	through), might to be interpreted differently on the textual level  
	(e.g. text deleted vs. text marked as used). The <gi>ge:used/</gi> element  
	therefore would be bound to the textual level of markup. On the  
	documentary level then, a redefined <gi>del/</gi> or <gi>delSpan/</gi> would suffice.</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Metamarks (3.2.3) </head>
	
	<p>Should <gi>att</gi>function<gi>/att</gi> be specified more thoroughly? What’s clear is, that  
	metamarks are not part of the text (the “meta” aspect). On the  
	contrary, what kind of „markup“ they represent (in the end: their  
	semantics and their interpretation) is only explained by example in  
	our draft and might need clarification.</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Transpositions (3.2.4) </head>
	
	<p>Arbitrary segments of text could be transposed. Could we promote a  
	"model.global" element like <gi>milestone/</gi> to be a spanning element, so  
	that such segments can be addressed?</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Substitution (3.2.5) </head>
	
	<p>Is the distinction between a substitution and a grouping of changes  
	(aka. "revision campaign") clear? Could a substitution be reformulated  
	as a grouping of an addition and a deletion or do we loose specific  
	semantics of "substitution" in this case?</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Undoing alterations (3.2.6) </head>
	<p>Can any kind of markup be undone? <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> for example have  
	clearly defined semantics on the textual level. So their reverse  
	effect is properly defined as well. Extending the notion of undoing to  
	a potentially open set of markup, trades flexibility in expression for  
	clarity of what’s expressed.</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Revision campaigns (3.3) </head>
	
	<p><hi><gi>change/</gi></hi>: In the Faust-Edition we would like to group revision  
	campaigns, so that we can start with smaller campaigns on a single  
	page, for example motivated by adherence to a rhyme scheme, and then  
	walk our way up to larger groupings by assembling smaller campaigns,  
	maybe because they have been executed with the same writing material.  
	Could we encode this properly by nesting <gi>change/</gi> elements?</p>
	</div>
	
	<div><head> Collation and Critical Apparatus (5) </head>
	
	<p>How do we express variance in/ alteration of markup? For example how  
	does one express the removal of a paragraph boundary? In the Faust- 
	Edition we currently use the inline-apparatus construct with each  
	reading representing one markup alternative. This has the obvious  
	drawback of necessarily doubling the affected segment and the markup  
	that might go unaltered.</p>
	</div>
      </body>
    </text>
  </TEI>