<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"  xmlns:ge="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/geneticEditions">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Genetic Editions meeting 2010-02-25</title>
		<author>notes taken by Sebastian Rahtz</author>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <p></p>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p/>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    
    <text>
      <body>
	<p>This meeting too place at Oxford University Computing Services
	on 25/26 February 2010. Present were
	Malte Rehbein, Elena Pierazza, Lou Burnard, Fotis Jannidis,
	Gregor Middell, James Cummings and Sebastian Rahtz.</p>

	<div>
	  <head>Targets for genetic editions meeting</head>
	  <p>The interaction with this SIG and the TEI Technical
	  Council was discussed. The Council meets in April, and it
	  was agreed that at least part of the proposals which
	  affected the schema of the TEI (ie new and changed elements)
	  should be presented there for agreement. This could be done
	  in a modular way, but with dependencies (ie start with
	  low-level changes and move up to larger components such as
	  <gi>document</gi>?). It is clear that some proposed
	  changes/additions would be to existing chapters, other parts
	  might need a new chapter. The Genetic document as  it stands
	  can be/may be maintained as ongoing tutorial/exemplar
	  (comparable to Lite and Tite), or completely subsumed into
	  the Guidelines. It was agreed that the meeting would attempt
	  to present at least some concrete changes to the Council.
	  </p>
	</div>
	<div>
	  <head>Principles</head>
	  <p>Straight into document models, and concepts of stages,
	  layers, physical depth of material etc.</p>
	  <p>Pages torn from
	  diaries and later found, how recorded? How to model
	  <gi>surface</gi>s which are lost, damaged, refound
	  etc. Should be possible to use a combination of
	  <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi> etc. Needs a discussion of the
	  problem in first part of section 3.1.</p>
	  <p>Not clear whether <gi>damage</gi> is a specialization of
	  <gi>zone</gi>, or whether the two concepts are
	  orthogonal. This affects the content model of <gi>zone</gi>
	  - in fact, of <gi>line</gi>, because it is regarded as
	  mandatory that text is always described as one or more lines.
	  </p>

	  <p>The very important point of principle as to whether one
	  should be allowed to encode any analytical elements within
	  <gi>line</gi> caused a long discussion. Do we have just a
	  <gi>seg</gi> wrapper (and allow all the children of
	  <gi>seg</gi>), or nothing, or a new element
	  <gi>segment</gi>, or by-default-empty
	  model.linePart class to let future generations hang
	  themselves. Do we need <gi>hi</gi> to indicate colour, size
	  etc? Probably. Finally agreed the the content model of
	  <gi>line</gi> should be cut back to hiLike, transcriptional,
	  editorial, gLike and global and <hi>something very like, or
	  itself, <gi>seg</gi></hi> (but without all the baggage
	  inside it).
	  </p>

	  <p>Did the argument end there? No.</p>

	  <p>What about constructs like tables, formulae and lists?
	  are they part of the document or the interpretation? Tables
	  seem to be special, as they model a system of organizing
	  writing on paper which is different from
	  <gi>line</gi>s. Agreed to allow <gi>table</gi> as sibling of
	  <gi>line</gi>. Unfortunately, this has the same problem as
	  <gi>seg</gi>, that <gi>cell</gi> can contain almost anything!.

	  </p>

	</div>

      </body>
    </text>
</TEI> 