<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TCW18: Summary of Genetic Working Group proposals</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <p>Unpublished working document for the TEI Council
        </p>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Unpublished </p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
    <head>Notes for Council on the Genetic Workgroup Proposal</head>
<p>These notes summarize very briefly some proposals for change to the
TEI Guidelines arising out of the work of the Genetic
Working Group (GWG). Further discussion and rationale for these proposals is
provided by the full report of the GWG, available in source form at
<ptr
    target="http://tei.svn.sourceforge.net/viewvc/tei/trunk/genetic/"/>. An
HTML version of this full report has also  been prepared for Council's
use and is available at <ptr
target="http://www.tei-c.org/Activities/Council/Working/tcw19.html"/>.
</p>

<p>The report proposes the following schema changes:
<list type="ordered">
<item>A new element <gi>document</gi> which holds <q>a genetic
transcription of a document</q>, parallel to the existing
<gi>facsimile</gi> and <gi>text</gi> elements.</item>
<item>A new attribute <att>rotate</att> for the existing <gi>zone</gi>
element which <q>indicates the amount by which this zone has been
rotated clockwise, with respect to the normal orientation of the
parent <gi>surface</gi> element</q></item>
<item>A need is recognized to define non-rectangular zones and the SVG
<att>points</att> attribute proposed for this purpose.</item>
<item>The content model of <gi>zone</gi> is changed, so that it may
contain members of the new
class <ident>model.zonePart</ident> as well as model.global. This
class contains a further new element <gi>line</gi>; the existing
<gi>table</gi> and <gi>zone</gi> elements; and available members of the classes
model.gLike, model.segLike, model.hiLike, model.pPart.*. </item>
<item>A new surface-like element <gi>patch</gi> is proposed which
<q>contains a part of a written surface which was originally
physically distinct but became attached to it at the time that one or
more written zones were created</q></item>
<item>Several new elements are added to the
model.pPart.transcriptional class: a <gi>mod</gi> generic element for
any kind of textual alteration; a <gi>metaMark</gi> element for marks
indicating how text is to be read; various elements indicating the status of
parts of a document: <gi>used</gi>,
<gi>undo</gi>, <gi>redo</gi>, and <gi>rewrite</gi>;  and elements to
indicate how text has been re-ordered or transposed: <gi>transpose</gi>, <gi>transposeGrp</gi>. </item>
<item>Change the content model of <gi>subst</gi> to permit text</item>
<item>Add an attribute <att>instant</att> to indicate instant
correction.</item>
<item>Use a slightly modified version of the existing<gi>graph</gi>
element to mark up genetic relations</item>
<item>Add a new header element called <gi>stageNotes</gi> (within <gi>creation</gi>) to document
the genetic stages identified in a documentary analysis, each
described as a <gi>stageNote</gi>, and pointed to by means of a
pervasive <att>stage</att> attribute.</item>
</list></p>
</body>
  </text>
</TEI>
