<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- intended to be valid against the current TEI Lite (P5) schema -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 1.1 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date when="2008-07-07">7 July 2008</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>No source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~lou" when="2007-07-28">created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>This is a maintenance release, implementing several changes
            agreed following the review of outstanding feature requests
	    undertaken at the Council meeting in Galway in April (see <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Council/Working/tcw12.xml">Working
	    Paper TCW12</ref> for a complete list)</p>

<p>In addition to these specific responses to feature requests, a
number of minor corrections and clarifications in the text of the
Guidelines have been made. Examples of these include:
<list>
<item>make <gi>foliation</gi> element repeatable, as stated in the
text of the Guidelines</item>
<item>clarify the distinction between <term>conformable</term> and
<term>conforming</term> schemas</item>
<item>remove lurking references to a non-existent
<soCalled>divn</soCalled> class</item>
<item>add discussion of use of milestone tagging to mark  speaker
changes etc.</item>
<item>tidy up usage of the <gi>att</gi> element in the text of the
Guidelines</item>
<item>harmonise and clarify usage of <att>age</att> attribute on
<gi>person</gi> and <gi>personGrp</gi></item>
<item>permit text as content for <gi>interp</gi> element</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>Several changes were made in the tool chain used to produce the
Guidelines, most of these with a view to producing an enhanced PDF
version for publication on paper. Changes have also been made in the
stylesheets controlling the visualisation of the Guidelines on the
web, in response to criticisms of earlier releases. These changes do
not, of course, affect the text of the guidelines proper.</p>

<p>The I18N project continues; at this release, substantial amounts of new
material have been added in  Chinese, Japanese, and
Spanish. </p>

<p>A systematic review of element specifications was undertaken; each
specification now includes an example of its usage.</p>

</body></text>

</TEI>
