<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 1.4 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date when="2009-06-20">20 June 2009</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~lou"
	      when="2009-06-20"/>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>This release contains the following substantive changes
<list>
<item>The chapter on
      Certainty and Responsibility has been revised extensively,
      introducing a new element (<gi>precision</gi>) for markup of
      numerical precision, and an entirely new mechanism for
      defining the scope of uncertainty, based on XSLT match
      expressions. </item>
<item>A new element <gi>pc</gi> (punctuation character) has been added to the Analysis and
Interpretation module, permitting the explicit markup of
punctuation. The discussion of punctuation markup in the Core elements
chapter was substantially revised. </item>
<item>New elements <gi>constraintSpec</gi> and <gi>constraint</gi>
were introduced to the Tag Documentation module  as a means of
documenting formally  constraints on an element's content additional to
those of its content model. </item>
<item>A new generic <gi>dim</gi> element and associated class were
added to the support all kinds of measurements. </item>
</list></p>

<p>In addition, the following pervasive editorial changes were made: 
<list>
<item>All exemples have been given an explicit language code,
wherever possible, and some missing bibliographic references were added. </item>
<item>Some further changes made to extend support for Korean and Japanese.
</item>
<item>The G5 group added a very large number of  French translations
to the reference documentation. </item>
</list> </p>


<p>Other changes made are listed briefly below in date order. Where 
further discussion of the change is available in the SF bug tracker,
the ticket number is indicated in parentheses
below:

<list>
<item>2009-06-09: Add origPlace to att.naming for consistency (2510548)</item>
<item>2009-06-04: Add a missing example to the Verse chapter (2800854)
</item>
<item>2009-06-02: Create a free standing feature structure exemplar</item>
<item>2009-06-01: Change data.numeric to permit fractions as a legal value ()</item>
<item>2009-05-23: Added clarificatory text and revised discussion at
various points, per SF comments (2763441, 2740718, 2788297, 2777567
2712046)</item>
<item>2009-05-12: Change content model for <gi>am</gi> to permit
pPart.edit elements (2209933)</item>
<item>2009-05-12: Define new class for quotation-like elements
appearing in <gi>msDescription</gi> (1962972)</item> 
<item>2009-05-04: A number of minor changes to tei tite ODD</item>
</list></p>


</body></text>

</TEI>
