<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
-->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 3.4.0 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2018-07-23">Monday, 23 July 2018</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from ChangeLog and GitHub trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      
      <p>Release 3.4.0 (code name: <ref target="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dog_days">Dog Days</ref>) of the TEI Guidelines introduces new features and resolves a
        number of issues raised by the TEI community. As always, the majority of these changes and
        corrections are a consequence of feature requests or bugs reported by the TEI community
        using the GitHub tracking system. A full list of the issues resolved in
        the course of this release cycle may be found under the <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues?q=is%3Aissue+milestone%3A%22Guidelines+3.4.0%22+is%3Aclosed">3.4.0 milestone</ref>.</p>
      
      <p>Highlights of this release include: <list>
        
        <item>A new element <gi>path</gi> has been introduced. It can be used for the encoding of individual non-closed lines within a <gi>surface</gi> or <gi>zone</gi>
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1453">#1453</ref>).</item>
       
        <item>The section on the <gi>content</gi> element in the Guidelines has been rewritten and improved
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1459">#1459</ref> and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1718">#1718</ref>).
        </item>
        
        <item>A new element, <gi>unit</gi>, has been added for encoding units of measurement in any kind of formal or informal system
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1461">#1461</ref>).</item>
        
        <item>The values of the <att>unit</att> attribute have been harmonized for more consistency
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1630">#1630</ref>).</item>
        
        <item>The description of <gi>classDecl</gi> has been revised and an example added in the Guidelines
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1640">#1640</ref>).</item>
        
        <item>The model.physDescPart has been moved from the TEI module to the msDescription module
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1650">#1650</ref>).</item>
        
        <item>To allow for the encoding of information about whom a speech act or physical action is directed to, a new attribute class, <name type="class">att.ascribed.directed</name>, has been added. 
          It provides several elements with the new <att>toWhom</att> attribute (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1679">#1679</ref>).</item>
        
        
        <item>The <att>streams</att> attribute has been added to <gi>layout</gi> for indicating the number of text streams per page 
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1687">#1687</ref>).</item>
        
        
        <item>After adjustments to the content model and membership, the elements <gi>pc</gi> and <gi>lbl</gi> can now occur directly as a child of the elements <gi>entry</gi> and <gi>hom</gi> 
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1702">#1702</ref>).</item>
        
        
        <item>The unused datatype teidata.percentage has been removed, including all references and mentions 
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1706">#1706</ref>).</item>
        
        
        <item>The <att>type</att> attribute is now deprecated on the <gi>macroSpec</gi> element
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1737">#1737</ref>).</item>
        
        <item>The <gi>figure</gi> element has been made a member of <name type="class">att.written</name> to indicate different authors of drawings and the like in a manuscript  
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1765">#1765</ref>).</item>
        
        <item>The documentation of the attribute class <name type="class">att.linguistic</name> has been extended, especially by providing documentation inside the "Simple Analytic Mechanism" chapter 
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1753">#1753</ref> and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1754">#1754</ref>).</item>
        
        <item>Vestigal references to macro.schemaPattern in the schemas, exemplars, and English prose have been removed (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1768">#1768</ref>).</item>
        
        
        <item>The elements <gi>publisher</gi>, <gi>distributor</gi> and <gi>authority</gi> are members of <name type="class">att.canonical</name> now 
          (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1775">#1775</ref>).</item>
        
         
        
        </list>
        
        
      </p>

      <p>Dozens of wording improvements and corrections of typographic errors have been
        made to the <title>Guidelines</title>.</p>
      
      <p>Furthermore, a number of translations have been added or updated</p>

      <p>In addition, many improvements have been made to the XSLT
      stylesheets (which provide processing of TEI ODD files for <ref target="https://roma.tei-c.org/">Roma</ref> and <ref target="http://oxgarage.tei-c.org/">OxGarage</ref> as
      well as other TEI conversions). The Stylesheets are maintained
      separately from the Guidelines and are at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
