<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>P5 version 2.0 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2011-12">December 2011</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>This is a major new release of the P5 Guidelines, which
      introduces some significant new material as well as implementing
      an unusually large set of other changes and error
      corrections. Since the last release in March 2011, members of
      the TEI community have proposed over 60 feature requests and
      reported about the same number of errors; dealing with these has
      kept the TEI Council busy, and most of these tickets have now
      been closed. Discussion of each modification and each action
      taken is available on the relevant sourceforge ticket, which is
      also referenced in the change log, as usual. </p>

<p>We mention here just a few of the more notable changes carried out
for this release:
      <list type="ordered">
	<item>Several new elements have been introduced to facilitate
	a more "document-focussed" (as opposed to "text-focussed") way
	of working. A new <gi>document</gi> element can now be used to
	organize digital images of a source document in much the same
	way as the existing <gi>facsimile</gi>, but with the added
	ability to embed detailed source transcriptions of the source
	within the same structure. A number of other elements have
	been added or modified to support the detailed encoding of
	transcriptions of individual documents, and a mechanism has
	been defined for the encoder to represent the evolution of a
	text through various writing stages. The existing chapter on
	<title>Physical Transcription</title> has been exhaustively
	revised to cater for these revisions which will, it is hoped,
	go some way to improve the support offered by the TEI scheme
	for documentary and genetic editing. </item>

<item>the licensing conditions applicable to TEI products were made
more explicit and evident; the source code tree was tidied up, with
all unused items being moved out; some old annoyances --  notably the
meaningless distinction between "mwa" and "opt" -- were removed </item> 

<item>a new <gi>notatedMusic</gi> element was added to support
representation of musical notation within texts in a way compatible
with the existing Music XML standard. </item>

<item>a number of minor changes were made to make it possible to
represent dates, and normalised dates, using non-Julian calendar
systems; a new attribute class was defined to facilitate provision of
sort keys. </item>

<item>several modifications were made to enhance the representation of
more carefully structured or richer bibliographic entries, notably the
ability to nest one <gi>bibl</gi> within another, and the ability to
specify a work's language. </item>

<item>all examples were revised to drastically reduce the amount of
unnecessarily divergent and encoding practices (such as the values used for
the @rend attribute, or for language identifier  codes ) </item>

<item>the content models of some  elements were relaxed in light of
the experience of converting ECCO to TEI P5, to permit for example stage
directions within verse, or verse within headings.  </item>

</list></p>

<p>As far as possible, and in line with stated
policy,  none of the changes  made at this release should 
invalidate existing documents. Rather than simply removing features or practices
which are now considered erroneous, care has been taken to indicate
that such features are <soCalled>deprecated</soCalled> and may be
removed at a subsequent release. Work is ongoing on how exactly to
formalise this policy.  </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
