<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
-->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 3.1.0 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2016-12-15">Thursday, 15 December 2016</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from ChangeLog and GitHub trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>This release (Codename: Tea Day) marks the completion of two major new features
        introduced in the previous release. First, Pure ODD is now completely pure: all content
        models in TEI ODDs may now be represented entirely in TEI, with no requirement for RELAX NG
        (which may still be used if desired). In the previous release, RELAX NG was still needed in
        macros that permitted any XML content, which are used in content models such as <gi>egXML</gi>. Second, this release contains the first Exemplar which implements
        the Processing Model specification introduced in 3.0.0 and produced as part of the work of
        the <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI-Simple"><title>TEI Simple</title></ref>
        project, which was funded by the <ref target="https://mellon.org/">Andrew W. Mellon
          Foundation</ref>. TEI simplePrint is an entry-level customization, focused primarily on
        the needs of those encoding Western European early modern printed material such as that
        produced by the Text Creation Partnership. We hope that, beyond its value as a customization
        for working with this type of material, it will serve as a template for producing other new
        customizations that leverage the Processing Model.</p>
      <p>Release 3.1.0 of the TEI Guidelines also introduces other new features and resolves a
        number of issues raised by the TEI community. As always, the majority of these changes and
        corrections are a consequence of feature requests or bugs reported by the TEI community
        using the GitHub tracking system. If you find something you think needs to change in the TEI
        Guidelines, schemas, tools, or website, please submit a feature request or bug issue at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues</ref> for
        consideration. A full list of the issues resolved in the course of this release cycle may be
        found under the <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/milestone/2?closed=1">3.1.0
          milestone</ref>.</p>
      <p>
        <list>
          <item>The <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-att.global.source.html"><att>source</att></ref> attribute is now global.</item>
		<item>There is a new <gi>schemaRef</gi> element for pointing to one's TEI ODD customization.</item>
          <item><gi>note</gi> and <gi>witDetail</gi> are now permitted in <gi>rdgGrp</gi>.</item>
          <item>A new datatype <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-teidata.prefix.html"><name type="datatype">teidata.prefix</name></ref> has been introduced to allow
            restricting an attribute value to one that could be use as a URI scheme name.</item>
          <item>The <att>ident</att> attribute of <gi>prefixDef</gi> is now restricted to the new <name type="datatype">teidata.prefix</name> datatype. This will avoid errors which would occur if a
            character that is not legal as a URI scheme were used as part of this attribute’s
            value.</item>
          <item>Further formal constraints on the <att>output</att> and <att>predicate</att>
            attributes of <gi>model</gi> have been added to try to help users avoid ambiguous sets of
              <gi>model</gi>s elements.</item>
          <item>ISO Schematron is now the only flavor of Schematron used or supported by the
              <title>Guidelines</title>.</item>
          <item>The following constructs are now deprecated: <list>
              <item>the value <val>isoschematron</val> of <att>scheme</att> of <gi>constraintSpec</gi> (use <val>schematron</val> instead, as they mean
                the same thing now).</item>
              <item>the default value (<val>false</val>) of <att>defective</att> of <name type="class">att.msExcerpt</name></item>
              <item>the default value (<val>unknown</val>) of <att>status</att> of <gi>availability</gi></item>
              <item>the default value (<val>unknown</val>) of <att>status</att> of <gi>correction</gi></item>
              <item>the default value (<val>unknown</val>) of <att>aloud</att> of <gi>said</gi></item>
              <item>the default value (<val>unknown</val>) of <att>discrete</att> of <gi>sound</gi></item>
            </list>
          </item>
          <item>The rules regarding <gi>f</gi>, its content, and its <att>fVal</att> attribute, have been cleaned up
            to fix a contradiction.</item>
          <item>The <gi>title</gi> element is now a member of <name type="class">att.datable</name>.</item>
          <item>The <gi>listBibl</gi> element is now a member of <name type="class">model.frontPart</name>.</item>
          <item>A new element called <gi>anyElement</gi> has been introduced, which permits any XML content in a
            content model. This removes the last remaining requirement for RELAX NG in content
            models, allowing us to define TEI entirely in TEI.</item>
          <item>A new element called <gi>dataFacet</gi> for restricting references to W3C datatypes in ODD has
            been introduced.</item>
          <item><gi>supplied</gi> is now part of <name type="class">model.choicePart</name>,
	        so it can be used within
		<gi>choice</gi>.</item>
          <item>A new attribute <att>require</att> has been added to <name type="class">att.textCritical</name>. It can be used to indicate
            interdependance between variant readings.</item>
          <item>The <att>extent</att> attribute on the <gi>orth</gi> and <gi>pron</gi> elements no longer has a default value.
          </item>
          <item>A new Exemplar called <name>simplePrint</name> has been added. Developed as part
            of the <title>TEI Simple</title> project, it makes extensive use of the processing model
            techniques introduced in the previous release and is fully documented by the ODD
            included in this release.</item>
          <item>The TEI conference and members meeting 2016 in Vienna saw the first <q>TEI2German
              Translatathon</q> to translate several descriptions, glosses, and remarks of the TEI
            specification into German. The results of this community effort have been added to this
            release – many thanks again to all participants and the local organizers for all the
            commitment and enthusiasm!</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p>In addition, dozens of wording improvements and corrections of typographic errors have been
        made to the <title>Guidelines</title>.</p>
      <p>Many improvements, including support for the new <gi>anyElement</gi> and for the
          <att>minOccurs</att> and <att>maxOccurs</att> attributes used by Pure ODD have been made
        to the XSL stylesheets (which provide processing of TEI ODD files for Roma and OxGarage as
        well as other TEI conversions). The Stylesheets are maintained separately from the
        Guidelines and are at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>. </p>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
