<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
       <titleStmt>
         <title>P5 version 0.3.1 release notes</title>
       </titleStmt>
       <editionStmt>
	 <edition>
	   <date>30 January 2006</date>
	 </edition>
       </editionStmt>
       <publicationStmt>
            <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
	 <p>TEI Web</p>      
       </publicationStmt>
       <sourceDesc>
	 <p>No source</p>
       </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
     <profileDesc>
     </profileDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
<body>
<p>Notable changes since the last packaged  release (0.2.1) are listed
briefly below (please refer to the ChangeLog on Sourceforge for the
full list). 

<list>
<item>A major revision of the TEI class system has been initiated to
complement the work on datatypes in the previous release. Details of
the specific changes  made so far are listed in 
<ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Drafts/edw92.xml"/>
</item><item>
The chapter formerly known as <title>Structure of the TEI DTD</title> has been
renamed <title>TEI Infrastructure</title> and almost entirely rewritten. 
</item><item>
A number of further  minor corrections have been made to the MS
chapter. A new <gi>listPerson</gi> element has been introduced to facilitate
encoding of data about real or imaginary people: this still forms part of the
Corpora module, but will probably move elsewhere.
</item><item>
New draft material on xinclude and on standoff markup has been added
  to the chapter on Segmentation and Analysis.
</item><item>
The test suite continues to be expanded.
</item><item>
Several stylesheet bugs were fixed and a new CSS style is now used to
present the HTML version of the Guidelines.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Amongst minor changes made at this release:
<list>
<item>the <gi>change</gi> element now has a much simpler content model
and two new attributes</item>
<item>the more antiquated parts of the discussion on graphics systems
in chapter FT have been removed or updated</item>
<item>in the Verse module, a new phrase level element <gi>rhyme</gi>
has been added  and numbered linegroups removed</item>
<item>in the Manuscript Description module, several elements now have
simpler content models using macro.specialPara rather than a sequence
of paragraphs </item>
<item>the new <gi>person</gi> element can now record <gi>death</gi> as
well as <gi>birth</gi> and <gi>nationality</gi> as well as <gi>occupation</gi></item>
<item>the P5 source itself has been improved. Class names and other identifiers
are now tagged more consistently; consistent wording has been
introduced to describe how modules are combined.</item>
<item>the <gi>measure</gi> element is  redefined and given extra
normalizing attributes</item>
<item>the naming of modules, classes, macros, datatypes is now more consistent
</item>
<item>the <gi>TEI</gi> and <gi>teiCorpus</gi> elements are now
provided by the default Structure module rather than by the
Infrastructure module</item>
<item>the macro schemapattern was changed so that valid DTD content models
can be generated</item>
<item>the Names and Dates module now has a new <gi>district</gi>
element, and the discussion of place names in ND has been improved a
little</item>
<item>all resp and who attributes are now consistently pointers rather than
only occasionally so</item>
</list>
</p>
</body>
</text>
</TEI>
