<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
-->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 4.7.0 and Stylesheets version 7.56.0 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2023-11-16">Thursday, 16 November 2023</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>Created retrospectively from ChangeLog and GitHub trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>Release 4.7.0 is codenamed <q>in nova fert animus</q>.</p>
      <p>This release introduces new features and resolves a number of issues raised by the TEI
        community. As always, the majority of these changes and corrections are a consequence of
        feature requests or bugs reported by the TEI community using the GitHub tracking system. A
        full list of the issues resolved in the course of this release cycle may be found under the
          <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/milestone/17?closed=1">4.7.0 milestone</ref>.</p>
      <p>The following changes are particularly worth highlighting in this release:
      
      <list>
          <head>New encoding features</head>
          <item>New with this release is the <gi>eventName</gi> element, which may be used to encode
            names of events in general transcribed text, or in the <gi>event</gi> element. The new
              <gi>eventName</gi> element also has membership in several attribute classes associated
            with named entities, including <name type="class">att.datable</name> to supply a date
            range for the use of an event’s name, and <name type="class">att.typed</name>, allowing
            it <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> attributes. It is also a member of <name
              type="class">att.editLike</name>, giving it the <att>evidence</att> attribute (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2382">#2382</ref>).</item>
          <item>The content model of <gi>event</gi> has been modified to contain <gi>eventName</gi>
            elements, but still allows older ways of labeling events. See <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/pull/2483">PR #2483</ref>. </item>
          <item>The <gi>taxonomy</gi> and <gi>category</gi> elements are now added to <name
              type="class">att.datcat</name> (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2419"
              >#2419</ref>).</item>
        </list>

        <list>
          <head>Changes to content models</head>
          <item>The content model of <gi>content</gi> has been changed to permit only one child
            element from <name type="class">model.contentPart</name> (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2381">#2381</ref>).</item>
          <item>At the request of the Manuscript SIG, the content model of <gi>additional</gi> is
            now more flexible, permitting any alternation of <name type="class">model.pLike</name>
              (<gi>p</gi> or <gi>ab</gi>) instead of zero or one each of <gi>adminInfo</gi>,
              <gi>surrogates</gi>, or <gi>listBibl</gi> (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2195">#2195</ref>).</item>
          <item>The content model of <gi>revisionDesc</gi> now permits multiple <gi>listChange</gi>
            elements (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2420">#2420</ref>).</item>
          <item>A Schematron constraint has been added to the specification for <gi>dataSpec</gi> in
            order to prevent the possibility of elements being included in the specification for an
            attribute’s datatype (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/pull/2443">PR #2443</ref>
            and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2426">#2426</ref>).</item>
          <item>A <att>scheme</att> attribute is now optional on a <gi>constraintSpec</gi>
	  with a <att>mode</att> of either <val>change</val> or
	  <val>delete</val> (it is still required when <att>mode</att>
	  is <val>add</val>, <val>replace</val>, or unspecified — see <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/pull/2453">PR
              #2453</ref> and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2261">#2261</ref>). </item>
          <item>The datatype of the <att>class</att> attribute on <gi>attRef</gi> has been changed
            from teidata.word to teidata.name (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2276"
              >#2276</ref>).</item>
        </list>
        <!--  <list>
          <head>Changes to classes</head>
          <item/>
      
        </list>-->
      </p>
      <p>With these release notes we are beginning a practice of documenting changes that could
        invalidate ODD customizations in TEI projects if they are working with the
        current release of these TEI Guidelines. Those maintaining ODD customizations of the TEI may
        want to be aware of the following changes and adapt your ODD files accordingly. <list>
          <head>ODD-breaking changes and deprecation</head>
          <item>The <att>calendar</att> attribute has been removed from <name type="class"
              >att.datable</name> because it is supposed to designate information about a date
            represented in an element’s contents, and thus should not be applied to elements that do not contain
            dates. To clarify its intended usage, <att>calendar</att> has been moved to a new class,
              <name type="class">att.calendarSystem</name>, and its use is now deprecated on many
            elements. The <att>calendar</att> attribute is now properly available only on
              <gi>date</gi>, <gi>time</gi>, <gi>origDate</gi>, and <gi>docDate</gi>. See <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2045">#2045</ref>.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p>
        <list>
          <head>Improvements of prose and examples</head>
          <item>The title of the Guidelines section 2.2.8 has been changed to more accurately
            reflect its content (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2415"
            >#2415</ref>).</item>
          <item>Several revisions were applied to the explanation of TEI XPointer Schemas in the
            Guidelines section 16.2.4 (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2083"
              >#2083</ref>).</item>
          <item>A new example was added for <gi>langKnown</gi> (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2139">#2139</ref>). </item>
          <item>The examples for use of the <att>key</att> attribute are updated and a source
            attribution corrected (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2144"
            >#2144</ref>).</item>
          <item>Several Japanese translations have been added to element, attribute, and class
            specifications (PRs <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/pull/2448">#2448</ref>,
              <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/pull/2449">#2449</ref>, and <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/pull/2461">#2461</ref>).</item>
          <item>Inconsistencies have been corrected in initial capitalization and initial spacing of
            the French descriptions in element specifications (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2486">#2486</ref>) </item>
          <item>Descriptions of the <att>ident</att> and <att>usage</att> attributes on the
              <gi>language</gi> element have been improved (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2447">#2447</ref>).</item>

        </list>
        <!-- 
          <list>
          <head>Documentation</head>
          <item/>
        </list> 
        -->
        <list>
          <head>Housekeeping</head>
          <item>Bugs have been corrected in the processing of Guidelines release notes to HTML
             (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2070" >#2070</ref>). </item>
          <item>The version <q>P5</q> is now properly represented in footers and headings of the
            published TEI Guidelines on the web (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2413">#2413</ref>).</item>
          <item>Bookmark links on examples in the Guidelines now feature mouseover text (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2137">#2137</ref>).</item>
        </list>
      </p>

      <p>In addition, many improvements have been made to the XSLT stylesheets (which provide
        processing of TEI ODD files for <ref target="https://romabeta.tei-c.org/">Roma</ref> and
          <ref target="https://teigarage.tei-c.org/">TEIGarage</ref> as well as other TEI
        conversions). The Stylesheets are maintained separately from the Guidelines at <ref
          target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>. A
        full list of the issues resolved in the course of this release cycle may be found under the
          <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/milestone/16?closed=1">7.56.0
          milestone</ref>.</p>

      <p>Highlights of this release include:<list>

          <item>Attributes shown on element and class specification pages are now formatted as
            a vertical nested list to improve legibility
	  (<ref
	  target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/pull/619">PR
	  #619</ref> and 
	  <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2489">#2489</ref>).</item>
          <item>A bug in Stylesheets ODD processing that had produced output files with multiple
            superfluous filename extensions has now been corrected (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/543">Stylehsheets 543</ref>).</item>
          <item>A serious problem in the processing of <att>ns</att> attributes in ODD
            customizations has been fixed (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/424">Stylesheets #424</ref>). </item>
          <item>The Guidelines now output the sch: prefix consistently when representing elements in
            the Schematron namespace (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/529"
              >Stylesheets #529</ref>)</item>
          <item>A bug has been fixed in the ODD processing of more than one <gi>anyElement</gi> in a
            content model so that it no longer generates an invalid Relax NG output (<ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/631">Stylesheets
            #631</ref>).</item>
          <item>The <att>xml:id</att> on <gi>list</gi> elements is now properly being translated to
            an HTML <att>id</att> attribute in HTML list container elements (Stylesheets <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/616">#616</ref> and <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/pull/617">PR #617</ref>).</item>
          <item>The teitohtml stylesheet now properly highlights <gi>val</gi> and <gi>tag</gi>
            elements in HTML output (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/567"
              >#567</ref>).</item>
          <item>Improvements and bug corrections have been applied to the docx to tei conversion
            (Stylesheets <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/pull/524">#524</ref>, <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/610">#610</ref>, and PR <ref
              target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/pull/634">#634</ref>).</item>
        </list>
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
