<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
-->
<?xml-model href="../Exemplars/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../Exemplars/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 3.0.0 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2016-03-29">29 March 2016</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from ChangeLog and GitHub trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>This version of the TEI Guidelines is a major step forward,
      and thus merits incrementing the <soCalled>major</soCalled>
      portion of the version number from <q>2</q> to <q>3</q>. The
      significant changes that warrant this change are twofold, as
      follows.
      <list>
	<item>The first is the implementation of Pure ODD, which
	replaces RELAX NG content models with TEI elements in the
	definitions of new elements and attributes. This means that
	apart from Schematron constraints, TEI is now defined entirely
	in TEI. The new specification elements and their use are
	described in <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html">Chapter
	22</ref>. The TEI Stylesheets have been extensively modified
	to handle Pure ODD content models.</item>
	<item>The second is the introduction of the new Processing
	Model specification in <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/3.0.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html#TDPM">section
	22.5.5</ref>. TEI Processing Models permit the writer of an
	ODD to specify how TEI elements might be processed for
	different output formats.</item>
      </list></p>
      <p>Release 3.0.0 of the TEI Guidelines also introduces other new
      features and resolves a number of issues raised by the TEI
      community. As always, the majority of these changes and
      corrections are a consequence of feature requests or bugs
      reported by the TEI community using the GitHub tracking system.
      If you find something you think needs to change in the TEI
      Guidelines, schemas, tools, or website, please submit a feature
      request or bug issue at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues</ref>
      for consideration. A full list of the issues resolved in the
      course of this release cycle may be found under the <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues?q=milestone%3AGuidelines-3.0.0+is%3Aclosed">3.0.0 milestone</ref>.</p>
      <p>Some of the notable changes other than the Processing Model and Pure ODD in
      <ref target="en/html/index.html">this release</ref> include:
      <list>
          <item>The new <gi>msFrag</gi>
          element was added to permit Manuscript Descriptions to
          contain virtual reconstructions of fragmented documents as
          well as to analyse their components.</item>
          <item>The new <gi>annotationBlock</gi>
          element was added to group together linguistic annotations.
         </item>
          <item>The new <gi>transcriptionDesc</gi>
          element was added to describe the set of transcription
          conventions used, particularly for spoken material.</item>
	  <item>The <gi>oVar</gi> and <gi>pVar</gi> elements are no
	  longer recommended; rather, use of <gi>oRef</gi> and
	  <gi>pRef</gi> is recommended instead. The attributes of
	  <gi>oRef</gi> and <gi>pRef</gi> have been adjusted to
	  accommodate this usage.</item>
	  <item>The <att>type</att> attribute of <gi>stage</gi> now
	  allows multiple values.</item>
	  <item>The <gi>TEI</gi> and <gi>table</gi> elements now claim
	  membership in <name type="class">att.typed</name> (and
	  thus gets the <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att>
	  attributes).</item>
	  <item>The <att>hand</att> attribute was removed from <name type="class">att.damaged</name>, <name type="class">att.textCritical</name>, and <name type="class">att.transcriptional</name>, and added to a new
	  <name type="class">att.written</name> class, to which
	  <name type="class">att.damaged</name>, <name type="class">att.textCritical</name>, <name type="class">att.transcriptional</name>, <gi>ab</gi>,
	  <gi>closer</gi>, <gi>div</gi>, <gi>fw</gi>, <gi>head</gi>,
	  <gi>hi</gi>, <gi>label</gi>, <gi>line</gi>, <gi>note</gi>,
	  <gi>opener</gi>, <gi>p</gi>, <gi>salute</gi>, <gi>seg</gi>,
	  <gi>text</gi>, and <gi>zone</gi> belong.</item>
	  <item>The <gi>seg</gi> element was added to the content of <gi>notatedMusic</gi>.</item>
	  <item>The explanations and discussions of several features have been improved, including:
	  <list>
	    <item>the <name type="class">att.scoping</name> attributes
	    <att>target</att> and <att>match</att></item>
	    <item>the attributes of <name type="class">att.datable.w3c</name></item>
	    <item>the <gi>attRef</gi> element</item>
	    <item>the <gi>revisionDesc</gi> element</item>
	  </list>
	  </item>
	  <item>The display of element documentation has been
	  re-ordered so that notes and examples now precede the
	  content models (given in both Pure ODD and RELAX NG).</item>
          <item>And, of course, many typos were corrected.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p>In addition, improvements have been made to the XSL stylesheets (which provide processing
        of TEI ODD files for Roma and OxGarage as well as other TEI conversions). The Stylesheets
        are maintained separately from the Guidelines and are at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>.</p>
      <p>This release is dedicated to the memory of our colleague
      Sebastian Rahtz (13 February 1955 – 15 March 2016). We are
      greatly diminished without his generosity, wisdom, and humor.
      Release 3.0.0, however, has a lot of him in it. He was the
      architect of the new Processing Model, and had implemented most
      of the support for Pure ODD in the Stylesheets. Unlike poets,
      the creators of software and living standards generally don't
      get to make a <foreign xml:lang="la">monumentum aere
      perennius</foreign>. At best, we can hope that our work will be
      carried on, rewritten, extended, and refactored. That process
      has already begun for Sebastian's TEI Stylesheets, and they will
      continue to evolve to meet the community's needs going forward;
      but they, and we, are immeasurably better off for his
      contributions.
      </p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
