<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 1.4 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date when="2009-06-20">20 June 2009</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="http://users.ox.ac.uk/~lou" when="2009-06-20"/>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>This release contains the following substantive changes
<list>
<item>The chapter on
      Certainty and Responsibility has been revised extensively,
      introducing a new element (<gi>precision</gi>) for markup of
      numerical precision, and an entirely new mechanism for
      defining the scope of uncertainty, based on XSLT match
      expressions. </item>
<item>A new element <gi>pc</gi> (punctuation character) has been added to the Analysis and
Interpretation module, permitting the explicit markup of
punctuation. The discussion of punctuation markup in the Core elements
chapter was substantially revised (2372570). </item>
<item>New elements <gi>constraintSpec</gi> and <gi>constraint</gi>
were introduced to the Tag Documentation module as a means of formally
documenting  constraints on an element's content or usage additional to
those of its content model (1933198). </item>
<item>A new generic <gi>dim</gi> element and associated class were
added to support all kinds of measurements; content model of
<gi>dimensions</gi> was relaxed to allow any mixture of dimensional
specifications, but constrained to forbid repetitions (2594174). </item>
</list></p>

<p>Over this period, a number of  pervasive editorial changes were made: 
<list>
<item>All examples have been given an explicit language code,
wherever possible, and some missing bibliographic references were added. </item>
<item>Some further changes were made to extend support for Korean and Japanese.
</item>
<item>The G8 (AFNOR) group updated a very large number of  French translations
to the reference documentation. </item>
</list> </p>


<p>Other significant changes made are listed briefly below in date order. Where 
further discussion of the change is available in the SF bug tracker,
the ticket number is indicated in parentheses.

<list>
<item>2009-06-17: Allow <gi>place</gi> and <gi>listPlace</gi> as
children of <gi>settingDesc</gi>, for consistency with
<gi>particDesc</gi> (2779741)</item>
<item>2009-06-09: Add <gi>origPlace</gi> to att.naming for consistency (2510548)</item>
<item>2009-06-05: Corrected error which caused <code>rwa</code> (the code for
"recommended when applicable")  to be 
mistakenly rendered as "required when applicable" in formatting of the
Guidelines (2740718)</item>
<item>2009-06-04: Replace the requirement that at least
<gi>location</gi> appear within a <gi>msIdentifier</gi> by a more
forgiving set of schematron constraints (2672530)
</item>
<item>2009-06-04: Add a missing example to the Verse chapter (2800854)
</item>
<item>2009-06-02: Create a free standing feature structure exemplar </item>
<item>2009-06-01: Change data.numeric to permit fractions as a legal value (2673045)</item>
<item>2009-05-29: Add new @scope attribute to <gi>rendition</gi> to
support use of CSS pseudo-elements (2525586)</item>

<item>2009-05-23: Add clarificatory text and revised discussion at
various points, per SF comments (2763441, 2740718, 2788297, 2777567
2712046, 2517629, 2744482)</item>
<item>2009-05-12: Change content model for <gi>am</gi> to permit
pPart.edit elements (2209933)</item>
<item>2009-05-12: Define new class for quotation-like elements
appearing in <gi>msDescription</gi> (1962972)</item> 
<item>2009-05-04: Review and make some  minor changes required by
Council in the "TEI Tite" ODD exemplar. </item>
<item>2009-04-05: Permit  elements from the model.hiLike class within <gi>origDate</gi> (2542813)</item>
</list></p>

<p>Finally, as requested (2728369),  the  HTML
version of the Guidelines has been enhanced so that each element is
linked to a list of all the usage examples given for it throughout the Guidelines.</p>

</body></text>

</TEI>
