<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- intended to be valid against the current TEI Lite (P5) schema -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 0.6 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date value="2007-03-12">12 March 2007</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>No source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
    <revisionDesc>
      <change who="#sbauman.emt" date="2007-03-12">Added a few items;
      inserted some phrase-level encoding</change>
      <change who="#lburnard.ond" date="2007-03-12">created</change>
    </revisionDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>Changes since the last packaged release (0.5, October 2006)
      are listed briefly below (please refer to the file <name
      type="file">ChangeLog</name> in directory <name
      type="dir">ReleaseNotes</name> at the Sourceforge archive for a
      full list).</p>

      <p>This (somewhat delayed) release contains a large number of
      minor changes, many of them consequent on a purge of outstanding
      Sourceforge feature requests.</p>
     

<list>

<item>I18N work has continued: Japanese and Chinese translations for many
element descriptions were merged in, and the file organization was
modified.</item>

<item>A number of utilities were introduced to streamline the
editorial process, including a tool for producing a linked catalogue of all TEI objects
(elements, classes, etc.) </item>

<item>A major headache in  the way that the content models for high
level objects (all kinds of <gi>div</gi>, <gi>body</gi> etc.) are
defined was  addressed. This made it possible for a schema to
select either numbered or vanilla div elements without causing
ambiguity. </item>

<item>The low-level component elements of <gi>date</gi> and
<gi>time</gi> (<gi>day</gi>, <gi>hour</gi> etc.) were
removed. </item>

<item>The <gi>dateRange</gi> and <gi>timeRange</gi> elements were
removed; the <gi>date</gi> and <gi>time</gi> elements were added to
<name type="class">att.datable</name> in order to accomodate encoding
of temporal ranges.</item>

<item>The P5 source was reorganized and restructured very slightly,
and also revised to use vanilla <gi>div</gi>s (as opposed to numbered
<gi>div</gi>s).</item>

<item>Many long-standing feature requests were dealt with.Examples
include: 
<list>
  <item><gi>roleDesc</gi> within <gi>castGroup</gi></item>
  <item>adding new <gi>email</gi> and <gi>stamp</gi> elements </item>
  <item>making <gi>note</gi> globally available</item>
  <item>making the <att>label</att> attributes of elements for encoding trees and graphs
    (<gi>tree</gi>, <gi>eTree</gi>, etc.) into child elements</item>
  <item>making <gi>quote</gi> available rather than <gi>q</gi> within <gi>msItem</gi></item>
  <item>creating a new class <name type="class">att.msExcerpt</name> for the <att>defective</att>
    attribute.</item>
    <item>changing <att>ink</att> of <gi>hand</gi> and <gi>handShift</gi> and <att>medium</att>
    of <gi>handNote</gi> to data.enumerated.</item>
</list></item>

<item>The tools and stylesheets used to produce HTML version of the
Guidelines were enhanced.</item>

<item>The content modelm for <gi>front</gi> was modified to  permit
titlepages and divisions in any order</item>

<item>A number of datatype changes were implemented, consequent on a
decision to change  the way that multiple attribute values are
specified in ODD</item>

<item>The class <name type="class">model.divPart.spoken</name> was
redefined as a child of <name type="class">model.inter</name> in order
to fix a long-standing bug</item>

<item>Some minor typographic errors have been corrected.</item>
      </list>
      
<p>In addition, a project plan to enable a first release of P5 1.0 at the Members
Meeting 2007 was developed, and a tracking system for use of the Council and
Editors was set up.</p>


    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
