<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 2.4.0 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2013-07-05">5 July 2013</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog and SourceForge
        trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>This version of the TEI introduces new features and resolves
      a number of issues raised by the TEI community. As always, the
      majority of these changes and corrections are a consequence of
      feature requests or bugs reported by the TEI community using the
      SourceForge tracking system. If you find something you think
      needs to change in the TEI Guidelines, schemas, tools, or
      website, please submit a feature request or bug ticket at <ref
      target="http://tei.sf.net/">http://tei.sf.net/</ref> for
      consideration. Lists of <ref
      target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/search/?q=status%3Aclosed-wont-fix+or+status%3Aclosed-rejected+or+status%3Aclosed-out-of-date+or+status%3Aclosed-accepted+or+status%3Aclosed-works-for-me+or+status%3Aclosed+or+status%3Aclosed-duplicate+or+status%3Aclosed-invalid+or+status%3Aclosed-fixed"
      >closed bugs</ref> and <ref
      target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/search/?q=status%3Aclosed-wont-fix+or+status%3Aclosed-later+or+status%3Aclosed-rejected+or+status%3Aclosed-out-of-date+or+status%3Aclosed-accepted+or+status%3Aclosed-remind+or+status%3Aclosed+or+status%3Aclosed-duplicate+or+status%3Aclosed-invalid+or+status%3Aclosed-fixed"
      >closed feature requests</ref> are available on the site. The
      software provided by SourceForge has changed and some old URLs
      for tickets may eventually break (they currently forward). This
      new system gives much more readable URLs (e.g.
      http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/445/) and so Council has
      stopped using the purl URLs (e.g.
      http://purl.org/tei/bugs/3572502) created as shortcuts to
      SourceForge's previously long URLs. As part of this software
      change users who check out a copy of the TEI-C Subversion
      repository must update its location to that provided at <ref
      target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/code/"
      >http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/code/</ref>.</p>

      <p>Some of the highlights of the TEI P5 2.4.0 release include:
      <list>
        <item>A new simplified index/table-of-contents page for the
        web version of the Guidelines was created</item>
        <item>A very large number of typos fixed, prose clarification,
        and formatting issues have been solved. Of particular note are
        the contributions by Martin Holmes and Jens Østergaard
        Petersen in finding typos</item>
        <item>The addition, revision, and correction of numerous
        examples throughout the prose and reference pages for
        consistency or clarity</item>
        <item>The <title level="a">Representation of Non-standard
        Characters and Glyphs</title> chapter was renamed <title
        level="a">Non-standard Characters and Glyphs</title></item>
        <item>Element <gi>sex</gi> and attributes <att>value</att> and
        <att>sex</att> were changed to allow more inclusive values
        (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/425/">FR
        425</ref>)</item>
        <item>Usage of <gi>app</gi> with no <gi>lem</gi> or just
        <gi>note</gi> explained and illustrated (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/366/">BUG
        366</ref>)</item>
        <item>Suggested values for <att>unit</att> on
        <gi>biblScope</gi>, <gi>citedRange</gi>, and
        <gi>relatedUnit</gi> modified for consistency (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/429/">FR
        429</ref>)</item>
        <item>The <gi>am</gi> element now claims membership to
        <ident type="class">att.typed</ident> (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/449/">FR
        449</ref>
        </item>
        <item>The <gi>pc</gi> element is now allowed inside
        <gi>pc</gi> (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/566/">Bugs
        566</ref>)</item>
        <item>A clarification of the conformance requirement for order
        of children in <gi>publicationStmt</gi> (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/468/">Bugs
        468</ref>) </item>
        <item>The <gi>stage</gi> element is now a member of
        <ident type="class">att.ascribed</ident> (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/441/">FR
        441</ref>) </item>
        <item>The content model of the <gi>eg</gi> element was
        significantly loosened to allow use for the display and
        formatting of modern code examples (per <ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/430/">FR
        430</ref>)</item>
        <item>The discussion of <gi>substJoin</gi> was clarified (per
        <ref
            target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/448/">FR
        448</ref>)</item>
        <item>A number of changes to loosen content models, mostly
        driven by experience of TCP EEBO project:
        <list>
          <item>allow a <gi>teiCorpus</gi> to have <gi>facsimile</gi>
          and <gi>sourceDoc</gi> children, like <gi>TEI</gi> (per <ref
          target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/456/"
          >FR 456</ref>)</item>
          <item>loosen content model of <gi>cell</gi> to make it the
          same as <gi>p</gi> (per <ref
          target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/455/">FR
          455</ref>)</item>
          <item>expand content model of <gi>figure</gi> to allow more
          components (per <ref
          target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/454/">FR
          454</ref>)</item>
          <item>allow <gi>foreign</gi> to contain <gi>q</gi> (per <ref
          target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/442/">FR
          442</ref>)</item>
          <item>allow <gi>epigraph</gi> at end of <gi>front</gi> (per
          <ref
              target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/434/">FR
          434</ref>)</item>
        </list>
        </item>
        <item>Implementation of a new notation in the specifications
        for previously deprecated elements and attributes, which now
        have a <q>valid until</q> date recorded:
        <list>
          <item><att>targets</att> on <gi>alt</gi>, <gi>join</gi>, and
          <gi>link</gi></item>
          <item><att>type</att> on <gi>biblScope</gi></item>
          <item><att>form</att> on <gi>quotation</gi></item>
          <item><att>status</att> on members of <ident
          type="class">att.identified</ident></item>
          <item><gi>relationGrp</gi></item>
        </list>
        </item>
        <item>A number of Schematron constraints, as well as
        modifications to the TEI Guidelines building and testing
        process, were added, revised, or removed</item>
        <item>As part of continuing improvements to the build process,
        all of the source files for the TEI Guidelines now use an
        <name>xml-model</name> processing instruction to point to the
        last successful build of an NVDL schema</item>
        <item>A change to Guidelines practice in the use of
        <att>type</att> vs <att>rend</att> as part an ongoing
        discussion of consistency of terminology (<ref
        target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/460/">Bugs
        460</ref>)</item>
        <item>Addition of remarks in the specifications (displayed as
        a <quote>Note</quote>) for practices that have been deemed no
        longer recommended:
        <list>
          <item><att>key</att> on members of <ident
          type="class">att.canonical</ident></item>
          <item>use of <gi>entry</gi> without at least one
          <gi>sense</gi></item>
        </list>
        </item>
      </list>
      </p>
      <p>Since the last P5 release, several releases have also been
      made to the family of XSL stylesheets maintained for the TEI,
      largely fixing bugs in conversion to ePub, and to or from Word
      docx format.</p>
      <p>A new translation of the TEI Lite tutorial into French has
      been completed, and is now included in the Exemplars directory.
      The French translations for a number of element descriptions
      were corrected at the same time. Unlike earlier versions, this
      version of the TEI Lite tutorial now uses only French language
      examples.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
