<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 2.9.1 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2015-10-15">15 October 2015</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from ChangeLog and Github trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      <p>Release 2.9.0 surfaced some issues with the TEI's release processes and required a 
        followup 2.9.1 release to correct some minor issues. The text of the 2.9.0 release notes
        are reproduced below.</p>
      <p>This version of the TEI Guidelines introduces new features and resolves a number of issues
        raised by the TEI community. As always, the majority of these changes and corrections are a
        consequence of feature requests or bugs reported by the TEI community using the Github
        tracking system. If you find something you think needs to change in the TEI Guidelines,
        schemas, tools, or website, please submit a feature request or bug issue at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues">https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues</ref> for consideration. Lists of <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aclosed+label%3Abug">closed bugs</ref> and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues?q=is%3Aissue+is%3Aclosed+label%3AFeatureRequest">closed feature requests</ref> are available on the site. </p>
      <p>Some of the more noticeable changes in <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.9.1/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html">this release</ref>
        include: <list>
          <!-- Add items below here in the form of: <item><gi>stage</gi>
           now claims membership of att.placement (and thus gets the
           <att>place</att> attribute) as per <ptr
           target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/476/"
           />.</item>
      -->
          <item>Probably the most significant change in this release involves no real change 
            to the Guidelines themselves, but a big shift in the way their development and
            publication proceeds. The TEI Guidlines are now hosted on 
            <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI">Github</ref>. This has
            entailed significant changes to our testing and release processes and will,
            we hope, make it both easier for us to develop the Guidelines and easier for the 
            TEI community to engage with their development. This change, and the associated 
            work has unfortunately meant a delay in the release of two major new features: 
            the Pure ODD content model revision and TEI Simple, which depends on Pure ODD. 
            We plan to release these features before the end of 2015.</item>
          <item>A new element has been added, <gi>xenoData</gi>, which provides encoders with 
            a place to put non-TEI data they wish to embed in TEI documents. See 
            <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/453"/>.</item>
          <item>The critical apparatus elements <gi>lem</gi> and <gi>rdg</gi> may now contain 
            structural elements, such as <gi>l</gi>, <gi>p</gi>, and <gi>div</gi>, allowing
            the creators of critical editions to describe textual variation at the structural
            level. See <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/522"/> and 
            <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1322"/>.</item>
          <item>A new element to mark text secluded by an editor, <gi>secl</gi>
            was added, per <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/531"/>.</item>
          <item>The <gi>event</gi> element is now allowed in <gi>org</gi>, per 
            <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/616"/>.</item>
          <item>The element <gi>hi</gi> is now permitted inside <gi>m</gi>, per 
            <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/556"/>.</item>
          <item>The deprecated <att>status</att> attribute was removed from 
            <name type="class">att.identified</name>.</item>
          <item>Added a new <att>selector</att> attribute on <gi>rendition</gi>, per <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/520"/>.</item>
          <item>The deprecated <att>degree</att> attribute on <gi>precision</gi> has been 
            removed. See <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/468"/> and <ptr target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1324"/>.</item>
          <item>And, of course, many typos were corrected.</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p>In addition, improvements have been made to the XSL stylesheets (which provide processing
        of TEI ODD files for Roma and OxGarage as well as other TEI conversions). The Stylesheets
        are maintained separately from the Guidelines and are at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>.</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
