<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
-->
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
        <title>TEI P5 version 4.2.1 and Stylesheets version 7.51.1 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
        <edition>
          <date when="2021-03-01">Monday, 1st March</date>
        </edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
        <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
        <p>created retrospectively from ChangeLog and GitHub trackers</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
      
      <p>Release 4.2.0 surfaced an issue with the conversion of the
      constraints on attirubtes to XHTML. This problem did not effect
      the schemas, but made the “Schema Declaration” portion of the
      references pages of several elements unreadable. Thus a followup
      version 4.2.1 of the Guidelines and version 7.51.1 of the
      Stylesheets has been released to handle the issue. The following
      change was made in the Stylesheets:
        <list>
          <item>The <gi>constraintSpec</gi> element is now ignored
          when processing an <gi>attDef</gi> in order to generate the
          “Schema Declaration” portion of the documentation for the
          attribute being defined (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/488">#488</ref>).</item>
        </list>
      </p>
        
      <p>For completeness, the full release notes of the TEI P5
      version 4.2.0 and Stylesheets version 7.51.0 are copied
      below.</p>
      
      <p>Release 4.2.0 is codenamed <q>Ruby</q>.</p>
      <p>This release introduces new features and resolves a number of issues raised by the TEI
        community. As always, the majority of these changes and corrections are a consequence of
        feature requests or bugs reported by the TEI community using the GitHub tracking system. A
        full list of the issues resolved in the course of this release cycle may be found under the
          <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues?q=is%3Aissue+milestone%3A%22Guidelines+4.2.0%22+is%3Aclosed">4.2.0 milestone</ref>.</p>


      <p>The following changes are particularly worth highlighting in this release: <list>
          <head>New encoding features</head>

          <item>New elements have been introduced for the encoding of ruby annotations, a particular
            method of glossing runs of text which is common in East Asian scripts (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2054">#2054</ref>, with thanks to Kiyonori
            Nagasaki, Satoru Nakamura, Kazuhiro Okada, Duncan Paterson, and Martin Holmes): <list>
              <item>The <gi>ruby</gi> element contains a passage of base text along with its
                associated ruby gloss(es).</item>
              <item>The <gi>rb</gi> element contains the base text annotated by a ruby gloss.</item>
              <item>The <gi>rt</gi> element contains a ruby text, an annotation closely associated
                with a passage of the main text.</item>
              <item>A subsection on <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/CO.html#COHTGRB">Ruby Annotations</ref> has been added, which is also referenced from several
                suitable places in the Guidelines.</item>
            </list> With this first take we hope to initiate further discussion and the
            implementation of additional use cases.</item>

          <item>The new element <gi>persPronouns</gi> has been introduced to indicate the personal
            pronouns used, or assumed to be used, by the individual being described (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2010">#2010</ref>).</item>

          <item>Two new elements and an attribute class have been introduced to allow documents to
            declare their citation structure and to specify how structural information may be
            extracted from them (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1957">#1957</ref>): <list>
              <item>The attribute class <name type="class">att.citeStructurePart</name> provides
                attributes for selecting particular elements within a document.</item>
              <item>The <gi>citeData</gi> element specifies how information may be extracted from
                citation structures.</item>
              <item>The <gi>citeStructure</gi> element declares a structure and method for citing
                the current document.</item>
            </list>
          </item>

          <item>A new element, <gi>noteGrp</gi>, for grouping notes has been introduced (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1833">#1833</ref>).</item>

        </list>
        <list>
          <head>Changes to content models</head>

          <item>The attribute class <name type="class">att.translatable</name> has been moved from
            the <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ST.html">TEI Infrastructure</ref> module to the <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/TD.html">Documentation Elements</ref> module (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2036">#2036</ref> and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2097">#2097</ref>).</item>

          <item>The <gi>interp</gi>, <gi>interpGrp</gi>, <gi>span</gi>, and <gi>spanGrp</gi>
            elements now have a <att>type</att> attribute (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2012">#2012</ref>).</item>

          <item>The <gi>material</gi> element is now a member of the attribute class <name type="class">att.typed</name>. Furthermore, a free-standing <att>function</att>
            attribute has been added to the <gi>material</gi> element, including a sample values
            list (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1911">#1911</ref>).</item>

          <item>The <gi>altIdentifier</gi> element is now a member of the attribute class <name type="class">att.datable</name> (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1986">#1986</ref>).</item>

          <item>The elements <gi>author</gi>, <gi>editor</gi>, <gi>funder</gi>, <gi>meeting</gi>,
              <gi>principal</gi>, and <gi>sponsor</gi> are now members of the attribute class <name type="class">att.datable</name> (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1992">#1992</ref>).</item>

          <item>Elements from the RELAX NG annotations namespace are now allowed alongside elements
            from the RELAX NG schema language namespace inside <gi>content</gi> elements (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1937">#1937</ref>).</item>

          <item>The <gi>certainty</gi> element is now a member of the attribute class <name type="class">att.typed</name>, and has a sample values list for the <att>type</att>
            attribute (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1934">#1934</ref>).</item>

          <item>The free-standing <att>predicate</att> attribute on <gi>model</gi> has been replaced
            with a reference to the newly introduced attribute class <name type="class">att.predicate</name>. The <gi>equiv</gi> element is now also a member of the new
            class (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1925">#1925</ref>).</item>

          <item>In several previous releases the schema permitted <gi>altIdent</gi> as a child of
              <gi>category</gi>, <gi>joinGrp</gi>, and <gi>taxonomy</gi>. This was a corrigible
            error that has been fixed in this release
            <!--
            It was accomplished by replacing the reference to the
            <ident type="class">model.glossLike</ident> class with
            element references to <gi>equiv</gi> and <gi>gloss</gi> in
            the content models of <gi>category</gi>, <gi>joinGrp</gi>,
            and <gi>taxonomy</gi>.-->
              (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1919">#1919</ref>).</item>

          <item>The <gi>object</gi> element is now allowed in the <gi>witness</gi> element (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1868">#1868</ref>).</item>

          <item>The <gi>name</gi> element is now directly allowed in the <gi>place</gi> element
              (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1484">#1484</ref>).</item>
        </list>
        <list>
          <head>Improvements of prose and examples</head>

          <item>The remarks of the <att>match</att> attribute in the attribute class <name type="class">att.scoping</name> and the description of the class itself have been
            improved (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2078">#2078</ref>).</item>

          <item>The subsection on <title>Dates and Times</title> has been promoted to the new
            section <ref target="https://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/4.2.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ND.html#NDDATE">Dates</ref> (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2066">#2066</ref> and
              <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2033">#2033</ref>).</item>

          <item>The description for the <gi>specDesc</gi> element has been improved and the
              <att>key</att> attribute is now required (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2061">#2061</ref> and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2062">#2062</ref>).</item>

          <item>The prose discussion of the location of a place has been expanded (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2042">#2042</ref>).</item>

          <item>Several comments in ODD customization exemplars were changed to expository prose.
            This change was motivated by the realization that the placement of each comment made it
            ambiguous as to which bit of ODD it was referring to, especially after processing with
            Roma (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1987">#1987</ref>).</item>

          <item>Chapter 5 on <title>Characters, Glyphs, and Writing Modes</title> now refers
            potential proposers of new characters to the Unicode Standards to the UC Berkeley Script
            Encoding Initiative for assistance (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1963">#1963</ref>).</item>

          <item>The examples demonstrating the usage of the <att>type</att> attribute on
              <gi>listPerson</gi> elements has been improved (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1953">#1953</ref>).</item>

          <item>Several indefinite articles in front of element and attribute names have been
            corrected (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1951">#1951</ref> and <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2015">#2015</ref>).</item>

          <item>A number of translations have been added, updated or improved (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1989">#1989</ref>, <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2082">#2082</ref>, <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2101">#2101</ref>, <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2074">#2074</ref>).</item>

          <item>Several examples have been corrected and improved (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1932">#1932</ref>, <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2087">#2087</ref>).</item>

          <item>A new <gi>xenoData</gi> example using GeoJSON has been added demonstrating the usage
            of non-XML data (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1884">#1884</ref>).</item>

          <item>The descriptions of several modules have been improved (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1786">#1786</ref>).</item>

        </list>
        <list>
          <head>Housekeeping</head>

          <item>Some warning messages in tei_customization have been improved (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2052">#2052</ref>).</item>

          <item>The outdated <name type="dir">genetic</name> directory has been removed (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2043">#2043</ref>).</item>

          <item>For each specification element in the <title>Guidelines</title> that has glosses in
            any language, an English gloss has been added (if not already present), even if it had
            been previously considered unnecessary. Furthermore, a Schematron rule has been added to
            enforce continued use of English glosses. This change was made to facilitate maintaining
            glosses in multiple languages, and has the added benefit of treating all languages more
            equally (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2037">#2037</ref>).</item>

          <item>Licensing information has been added explicitly to the repository (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1962">#1962</ref>).</item>

          <item>Unused test files have been removed from the <name type="dir">Test</name> directory
              (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/1942">#1942</ref>).</item>

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2006 -->

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2044 -->

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2047 -->

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2050 -->

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2056 -->

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2058 -->

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2077 -->

          <!-- https://github.com/TEIC/TEI/issues/2080 -->

        </list>
      </p>

      <p>In addition, many improvements have been made to the XSLT stylesheets (which provide
        processing of TEI ODD files for <ref target="https://romabeta.tei-c.org/">Roma</ref> and
          <ref target="http://oxgarage.tei-c.org/">OxGarage</ref> as well as other TEI conversions).
        The Stylesheets are maintained separately from the Guidelines at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>. A
        full list of the issues resolved in the course of this release cycle may be found under the
          <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues?q=is%3Aissue+milestone%3A%22Release+7.51.0%22+is%3Aclosed">7.51.0 milestone</ref>.</p>

      <p>Highlights of this release include: <list>
          <item>Test2 has been updated to use its own copy of source/p5subset.xml (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/456">#456</ref>).</item>
          <item>A permalink has been added to all examples (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/471">#471</ref>).</item>
          <item>An erroneous <att>resp</att> attribute on the <gi>note</gi> element has been
            replaced with the <att>type</att> attribute in the OpenEdition output (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/474">#474</ref>).</item>
          <item>The hard-coded word <mentioned>bibliography</mentioned> used to link to the
            bibliography at the bottom right of many examples has been replaced with an i18n key
              (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/478">#478</ref>).</item>
          <item>An obsolete email address has been removed from the Guidelines pages (<ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets/issues/484">#484</ref>).</item>

        </list>
      </p>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
