<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>TEI P5 version 2.6.0 release notes</title>
            </titleStmt>
            <editionStmt>
                <edition> <date when="2014-01-20">20 January 2014</date> </edition>
            </editionStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog and SourceForge trackers</p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>

            <p>This version of the TEI Guidelines introduces new features and resolves a number of issues
                raised by the TEI community. As always, the majority of these changes and
                corrections are a consequence of feature requests or bugs reported by the TEI
                community using the SourceForge tracking system. If you find something you think
                needs to change in the TEI Guidelines, schemas, tools, or website, please submit a
                feature request or bug ticket at <ref target="http://tei.sf.net/">http://tei.sf.net/</ref> for consideration. Lists of <ref target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/search/?q=status%3Aclosed-wont-fix+or+status%3Aclosed-rejected+or+status%3Aclosed-out-of-date+or+status%3Aclosed-accepted+or+status%3Aclosed-works-for-me+or+status%3Aclosed+or+status%3Aclosed-duplicate+or+status%3Aclosed-invalid+or+status%3Aclosed-fixed">closed bugs</ref> and <ref target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/search/?q=status%3Aclosed-wont-fix+or+status%3Aclosed-later+or+status%3Aclosed-rejected+or+status%3Aclosed-out-of-date+or+status%3Aclosed-accepted+or+status%3Aclosed-remind+or+status%3Aclosed+or+status%3Aclosed-duplicate+or+status%3Aclosed-invalid+or+status%3Aclosed-fixed">closed feature requests</ref> are available on the site. </p>


            <p>Some of the more noticeable changes in <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/P5/2.6.0/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/index.html">this release</ref> include: <list>
                <item>Footnotes in the Guidelines now appear in a popup box when you click on them,
                    rather than causing a jump to the bottom of the page. (This function depends on
                    JavaScript; if you have JS turned off, the old behaviour will still
                    work.)</item>
                <item>The prose restriction that the <gi>pubPlace</gi>, <gi>address</gi>,
                    <gi>idno</gi>, <gi>availability</gi>, and <gi>date</gi> children of
                    <gi>publicationStmt</gi> occur in that order has been removed.</item>
                <item>The content model of <gi>publicationStmt</gi> has been updated to reflect the
                    restrictions detailed in the prose of section <ref target="en/html/HD.html#HD24">2.2.4
                    Publication, Distribution, Licensing, etc.</ref>. For more information on this please see 
		<ref target="http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/PublicationStmt-Changes">http://wiki.tei-c.org/index.php/PublicationStmt-Changes</ref>.</item>
                <item><gi>stage</gi> now claims membership of <name type="class">att.placement</name> (and thus gets the
                    <att>place</att> attribute) as per <ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/476/"/>.</item>
                <item><gi>docDate</gi> is now available as a child of <gi>dateLine</gi> (<ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/472/">https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/472/</ref>), and the content
                    models of <gi>signed</gi> and <gi>salute</gi> have
		    been loosened (<ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/433/"/>; <ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/478/"/>) to allow more
                    flexibility in the <q>top</q> <q>tail</q> of sections (prompted by experience in
                    EEBO TCP)</item>
                <item><gi>l</gi> is now allowed in the <gi>trailer</gi></item>
                <item>Usage of <att>corresp</att> has been clarified (<ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/506/">https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/506/</ref>).</item>
                <item>The value of the <att>matchPattern</att> attribute is now defined as W3C XPath
                    syntax rather than W3C XML Schema Language (<ref target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/432/">https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/432/</ref>). This allows for
                    more powerful regular expressions.</item>
                <item><att>perf</att> on <gi>tech</gi> now has the datatype 1+ data.pointer, instead
                    of data.enumerated (<ref target="http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/524/">http://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/524/</ref>).</item>
                <item>Support for <soCalled>pure ODD</soCalled>: it is now possible to define
                    content models using TEI XML constructs only, as an alternative to the use of
                    RELAX NG. This change is discussed further in a paper by Burnard and Rahtz
                    presented at <ref target="http://www.doceng2013.org/programme">2013's ACM
                    Document Engineering conference</ref>. Support for the new syntax in ODD
                    processing scripts is incomplete, however, and not yet fully tested.</item>
                <item>Use of the element <gi>valDesc</gi> throughout the TEI specifications code was
                    rationalised: mostly this involved removal of redundant commentary, but in some
                    cases element or attribute descriptions have been extended or modified.</item>
                <item>A new <gi>abstract</gi> element has been added to support descriptive metadata
                    about a <soCalled>born-digital</soCalled> item (such as a journal article in a review) to be stored
                    in the TEI Header per <ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/471"/></item>
                <item><att>name</att> has been made optional (previously required) on
                    <gi>relation</gi> as per <ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/467/"/> since a Schematron
                    test is in place to check whether one of <att>name</att>, <att>ref</att>, or <att>key</att> is
                    available.</item>
                <item><gi>forest</gi> and <gi>forestGrp</gi>, <gi>colloc</gi> and others are
                    examples of elements which used to have locally-declared <att>type</att>
                    attributes which benefit from the ability to now modify class-provided
                    attributes locally to the element. They now claim membership of <name type="class">att.typed</name> (and
                    thus get <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> attributes). Similarly
                    <gi>desc</gi> is now also a member of <name type="class">att.typed</name> as per <ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/feature-requests/473/"/>. </item>

                <item>The <gi>s</gi> element has been modified to not allow it to self-nest as per
                    <ptr target="https://sourceforge.net/p/tei/bugs/578"/></item>


                </list> </p>

            <p>There are also some changes to the way the Council is managing the Guidelines: <list>
                <item>Pre-release versions of the TEI P5 development tree are now tagged as <soCalled>alpha</soCalled>
                    and <soCalled>beta</soCalled> in their version information.</item>
                <item>In preparation for a program to get translations of reference documentation up
                    to date, all <gi>desc</gi> and <gi>gloss</gi> elements have been dated. This
                    allows us to easily generate lists of translated blocks which need
                    revising.</item>
                <item>More examples were added or corrected in this release and improvements to the
                    overall way examples are maintained is under consideration by the TEI Technical
                    Council.</item>
                </list> </p>

            <p>In addition, the XSL stylesheets which provide processing of TEI ODD files for Roma and OxGarage
                have been updated, notably providing better support for multi-namespace ODD. The
                Stylesheets are being maintained separately from the Guidelines and are at <ref target="https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets">https://github.com/TEIC/Stylesheets</ref>.</p>
        </body>
    </text>
</TEI>
