<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 1.7 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date when="2010-07">7 July 2010</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>created retrospectively from svn ChangeLog</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<p>This release introduces significant additional features to the way
in which the ODD system for TEI customization may be expressed. The
new features introduced allow a customization to be expressed by
inclusion (specifying only the elements it requires) rather than by
exclusion (specifying the elements which it does not require). They
also permit specification of a particular version of the Guidelines as
source for a schema. </p>
<p>Support for this entailed a number of changes, including definition
of new attributes for <gi>moduleRef</gi>, and new elements
<gi>elementRef</gi>, <gi>macroref</gi> and <gi>classRef</gi> as well
as revision to the prose of the relevant Guidelines
chapters. Some clarification of the way the odd-to-odd transformation
process works, for example when generating pattern prefixes for
RelaxNG, was also necessary. The new features greatly simplify the
process of generating user specific customisations, while retaining
all the existing behaviours. In addition, the test suite has been
revised and extended to check that the new facilities worked as
intended. Expanded tutorial material for the revised system will be
the subject of a Workshop to be taught at the 2010 General Meeting.
</p>

<p>As usual, several minor clarifications and corrections were made to
the wording of the Guidelines in response to Sourceforge tickets (e.g.
3026326 3025031 3025032 3025017 3010481 2991129 2989088 2982439
2942469 2965680 2981703 2982056) and discussion on Council and TEI-L
mailing lists. </p>

<p>The work of the AFNOR group providing and correcting French
translations and examples also continued; in particular, during May and June
substantial work on a new suite of French language examples was undertaken.</p>

<p>Other specific changes are listed below in reverse date order:

<list>

<item> 2010-07-02 : add constraint to prevent <gi>relatedItem</gi> supplying both a @target and some content (2728061)</item>

<item>2010-06-30 : stylesheet tei-to-epub, accidentally omitted from previous release, restored to release ( 3023242)</item>

<item>2010-06-21 : table referencing bug and other errors in tei-to-latex stylesheet fixed (3019186, 3007060)</item>
 
<item>2010-05-08 : add new source attribute and revise datatype of
existing version attributes for consistency  </item>

<item>2010-05-06 : add new att.docStatus attribute class (2812634)</item>

<item>2010-05-06 : add <gi>material</gi> to att.canonical class
(2811234)</item>

<item>2010-05-01 : rationalise and make consistent datatype of the
@target attribute (2531384)</item>

<item>2010-05-01 : revised class memberships for consistency amongst
elements which can appear within choice (2834505)</item>

<item>2010-04-30 : new attribute @points  added to att.coordinated to enable definition of non-rectangular zones in facsimile (2971316) </item>

<item>2010-04-30 : added idno to model.nameLike, thus permitting use of standard identifiers of various kinds in person, place etc. (2949985) </item>

<item> 2010-04-30 : add <gi>ref</gi> wherever <gi>title</gi> is permitted in highlevel components of <gi>biblStruct</gi> (2976608)</item>
<item> 2010-04-06 : make @url mandatory and scaling attributes optional for all graphic elements (2965521)</item>

</list>
</p>    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
