<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 1.0.1 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date value="2008-02-03">3 February 2008</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>No source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>
<p>
After the P5 1.0 release on November 1st 2007, the TEI Technical  
Council has continued to refine the Guidelines and respond to error  
reports, with over 300 sets of changes committed to Sourceforge.
</p><p>
The vast majority of changes are to the text, at the grammatical,  
technical, and explanatory level.
</p><p>
We would like to acknowledge here the pre-eminent part played by  
Brett Zamir,
who has read every chapter carefully, and made a huge number of  
important corrections and clarifications.
</p><p>
A very few changes have been made which affect generated schemas:
<list type="bulleted">
<item> model.gLike was added to the content model of <gi>measureGrp</gi></item>
<item> <gi>ptr</gi>  was adjusted so that either @cRef or @target is mandatory</item>
<item>an error generating schema from attribute classes was fixed</item>
<item> some Schematron rules have been adjusted</item>
<item> the datatype of the @ref attribute in the att.naming class has been  
changed to allow multiple URIs, which is taken to indicate the single  
name refers to more than one referents</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>
This release also includes a complete set of reference documentation  
generated for Chinese, French, German, Italian, Japanese and Spanish.  
The translation work is not finished yet, but is starting to be  
useable for these languages.
</p>
<p>
For the first time, the Guidelines are available in PDF as well as  
HTML. The design of this printable format was a collaborative effort  
by many members of the TEI Board of Directors and Technical Council,  
coordinated and implemented by Sebastian Rahtz.
</p>
<p>
New releases of Roma and the TEI XSL stylesheet family accompany this  
release, correcting reported bugs and providing more  
internationalisation.
</p>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
