<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!-- intended to be valid against the current TEI Lite (P5) schema -->
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>P5 version 0.6 release notes</title>
      </titleStmt>
      <editionStmt>
	<edition>
	  <date>12 March 2007</date>
	</edition>
      </editionStmt>
      <publicationStmt>
	<authority>The Text Encoding Initiative</authority>
      </publicationStmt>
      <sourceDesc>
	<p>No source</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <body>

      <p>Changes since the last packaged release (0.5, October 2006)
      are listed briefly below (please refer to the ChangeLog in
      directory ReleaseNotes at the Sourceforge archive for a full
      list).</p>

      <p>This (somewhat delayed) release contains a large number of
      minor changes, many of them consequent on a purge of outstanding
       Sourceforge feature requests.</p>
      

<list>

<item>I18N work has continued: Japanese and Chinese translations for many
element descriptions were merged in, and the file organization was
modified.</item>

<item>A number of utilities were introduced to streamline the
editorial process, including a tool for producing a linked catalogue of all TEI objects
(elements, classes, etc.) </item>

<item>A major headache in  the way that the content models for high
level objects (all kinds of <gi>div</gi>, <gi>body</gi> etc.) are
defined was  addressed. This made it possible for a schema to
select either numbered or vanilla div elements without causing
ambiguity. </item>

<item>The low-level component elements of <gi>date</gi> and
<gi>time</gi> ( <gi>day</gi>, <gi>hour</gi> etc.) were
removed. </item>


<item>The P5 source was reorganized and restructured very slightly,
and also revised to use vanilla <gi>div</gi>s.</item>

<item>A project plan to enable a first release of P5 1.0 at the Members
Meeting 2007 was developed, and a tracking system for use of Council and
Editors was set up.</item>

<item>Many long-standing feature requests were dealt with (examples
include roleDesc within castGroup, adding new <gi>email</gi> and
<gi>stamp</gi> elements, making <gi>note</gi> globally available, make
the @label attributes of <gi>etree</gi> and a few others  into child elements;
making <gi>quote</gi> available rather than <gi>q</gi> within
<gi>msItem</gi>)</item>

<item>The tools and stylesheets used to produce HTML version of the
Guidelines were enhanced.</item>

<item>The content modelm for <gi>front</gi> was modified to  permit
titlepages and divisions in any order</item>

<item>A number of datatype changes were implemented, consequent on a
decision to change  the way that multiple attribute values are
specified in ODD</item>

<item>The class model.dibPart.spoken was redefined as a child of
model.inter in order to fix a long-standing bug</item>

<item>Some minor typographic errors have been corrected.</item>
      </list>
      
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
