<div type="div1" xml:id="CF" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">

  <!-- OVERALL NOTES:
  - standardise use of scheme vs schema
  - the phrase 'Valid TEI ODD file' is used but we don't really define
  what  this means in the section about it, nor where in the header
  to point to the ODD.
  - 
  -->
<head>Conformance</head>

<p>The notion of <term>TEI Conformance</term> is intended to assist
    in the description of the format and contents of a particular XML
    document instance or set of documents. It may be found useful in
    such situations as: <list>
    <item> interchange or integration of documents amongst different
    researchers or users; </item>
<item>software specifications for TEI-aware processing tools; </item>
    <item> agreements for the deposit of texts in, and distribution
        of texts from, archives; </item>
    <item> specifying the form of documents to be produced by or for a given
        project. </item>
<!--    <item>characterising the extent to which a document may be
        re-used by some other project than that which originated it,
        or integrated with other documents. </item>-->
  </list> It is not intended to provide any other evaluation, for
    example of scholarly merit, intellectual integrity, or value
    for money. A document may be of major intellectual importance and
    yet not be TEI Conformant; a TEI Conformant document may be of no
    scholarly value whatsoever.</p>

<p>In this section we explore several aspects of conformance, and in
particular attempt to define how the term <term>TEI Conformant</term>
should be used. The terminology defined here should be considered
normative: users and implementors of the TEI Guidelines should use the
phrases <soCalled>TEI Conformant</soCalled>,
<soCalled>TEI Conformable</soCalled>, and
<soCalled>TEI Extension</soCalled> only in the senses given and with
the usages described. </p>

<p> A document is <term>TEI Conformant</term> if it: <list>
<item> is a well-formed XML document (<ptr target="#CFWF"/>)</item>
<item>can be validated against a <term>TEI Schema</term>, that is, a
schema derived from the TEI Guidelines (<ptr target="#CFVL"/>)</item>
<item> conforms to the TEI Abstract Model (<ptr target="#CFAM"/>)</item>
<item> uses the <term>TEI Namespace</term> correctly (<ptr target="#CFNS"/>)</item>
<!--    <item> contains a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element that includes
        elements for at least a title statement and publication
        statement</item>-->
<item> documents the subset of the TEI scheme used to validate it,
either implicitly or explicitly by means of a TEI Conformant <term>ODD
file</term> (<ptr target="#CFOD"/>)</item>
 </list> Each of these criteria is discussed in more detail below. </p>

<p>A document is said to be <term>TEI Conformable</term> if it is a
well-formed XML document which can be transformed algorithmically and
automatically into a TEI Conformant document without loss of
information and by means described below.</p>

<p>A document is said to use a <term>TEI Extension</term> if it is a
well-formed XML document which cannot be so transformed without loss
of information, because it contains additional distinctions,
representing concepts not present in the TEI abstract model, and
therefore not documented in these Guidelines. </p>

<p>A TEI Conformant (or Conformable) document is said to follow
<term>TEI Recommended Practice</term> if, wherever the Guidelines
prefer one encoding practice to another, the preferred practice is
used.</p>

<div type="div3" xml:id="CFWF">

 <head>Well-formedness criterion</head>

<p>These Guidelines currently mandate the use of well-formed XML as
representation format. Documents must conform to the World Wide Web
Consortium recommendation of the <title>Extensible Markup Language
(XML) 1.0 (Fourth Edition)</title> or successor editions found at <ref
target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/"
>http://www.w3.org/TR/xml/</ref>. Other ways of representing the
concepts of the TEI abstract model are possible, and other
representations may be considered appropriate for use in particular
situations (for example, for data capture, or project-internal
processing). But such alternative representations are at best
<soCalled>TEI conformable</soCalled>, and cannot be considered in any
way TEI Conformant.</p>

<p>Previous versions of these Guidelines used SGML as a representation
format. With release P5, the only representation format supported
by these Guidelines becomes valid XML; legacy documents in SGML format
should therefore be converted using appropriate software.</p>

<p>The use of XML greatly reduces the need to consider hardware or
software differences between processing environments when exchanging
data. No special packing or interchange format is required for an XML
document, beyond that defined by the W3C recommendations, and no
special <soCalled>interchange</soCalled> format is therefore proposed
by these Guidelines. For discussion of encoding issues that may arise
in the processing of special character sets or non-standard writing
systems, see further chapter <ptr target="#CH"/>.</p>

<p>In addition to the well-formedness criterion, the W3C defines the
notion of a <term>valid</term> document, as being a well-formed
document which matches a specific set of rules or syntactic
constraints, defined by a <term>schema</term>. As noted above, TEI
conformance implies that the schema used to determine validity of a
given document should be derived from the present Guidelines,
preferably by means of an ODD which references and documents the
schema fragments which the Guidelines define.
</p></div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="CFVL">
  <head>Validation Constraint</head>

<p>All <term>TEI Conformant</term> documents must validate against
one or more  schema files that have been derived from the published TEI
schema modules, combined and documented in the manner described in
section <ptr target="#MD"/>. We call the formal output of this process a
<term>TEI Schema</term>. </p>
   
 <p>A TEI Schema may be expressed in any or all of the XML DTD
 language, W3C XML Schema, and RELAX NG (both compact and XML
 formats); the TEI does not mandate use of any particular schema
 language<note place="foot">Here and elsewhere we use the word
 <mentioned>schema</mentioned> to refer to any formal document grammar
 language, irrespective of the formalism used to represent it.</note>
 only that this schema should have been generated from a <term>TEI ODD
 file</term> that references the TEI Guidelines. Some of what is
 syntactically possible using the ODD formalism cannot be represented
 by all schema languages; and there are some features of some schema
 languages which have no counterpart in ODD. As far as possible,
 however, these Guidelines avoid reliance on features which cannot be
 represented in all schema languages; exceptions to this general rule
 are documented in chapters <ptr target="#TD"/> and <ref>chapter on
 ODD processes to be supplied</ref>.</p>

<p>As noted in section <ptr target="#MD"/>, many varieties of TEI
schema are possible and not all of them are necessarily
<term>TEI Conformant</term>; derivation from an ODD is a necessary but
not a sufficient condition for this.</p>
</div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="CFAM">
<head>Conformance to the TEI Abstract Model</head>

<p>The <term>TEI Abstract Model</term> is the conceptual schema
instantiated by the TEI Guidelines. These Guidelines define, both
formally and informally, a set of abstract concepts such as
<q>paragraph</q> or <q>heading</q>, and their structural
relationships, for example stating that
<soCalled>paragraph</soCalled>s do not contain
<soCalled>heading</soCalled>s. These Guidelines also define classes of
elements, which have both semantic and structural properties in
common. Those semantic and structural properties are also a part of
the TEI abstract model; the class membership of an existing TEI
element cannot therefore be changed without changing the
model. Elements can however be removed from a class by deletion, and
new non-TEI elements can be added to existing TEI classes.</p>


<div><head>Semantic constraints</head>

<p>It is an important condition of TEI conformance that elements
defined in the TEI Guidelines as having one specific meaning should
not be used with another.  For example, the element <gi>l</gi> is
defined in the TEI Guidelines as containing a line of verse. A schema
in which it is redefined to mean a typographic line, or an ordered
queue of objects of some kind, cannot therefore be TEI Conformant,
whatever its other properties.</p>

<p>The semantics of elements defined in the TEI Guidelines are
conveyed in a number of ways, ranging from formally verifiable
datatypes to informal descriptive prose. In addition, a mapping
between TEI elements and concepts in other conceptual models may be
provided by the <gi>equiv</gi> element where this is available. </p>

<p>A schema which shares equivalent concepts to those of the TEI
conceptual model may be mappable to the TEI Schema by means of such a
mechanism. For example, the concept of paragraph, expressed in the TEI
scheme by the <gi>p</gi> element is probably the same concept as that
expressed in the Docbook scheme by the <gi>para</gi> element. In this
respect (though not in others) a Docbook-conformant document might
therefore be considered to be TEI Conformable. Such areas of overlap
facilitate interoperability, because elements from one namespace may
be readily integrated with those from another, but do not affect the
definition of conformance.</p>

<p>A document is said to follow the <term>TEI Abstract Model</term> if
it encodes those features specified in the TEI Guidelines, and the
structural interrelations of this encoding agrees with that specified
in a valid schema for <term>TEI Conformant</term> documents. That is,
the abstract definition and markup structurally corresponds to that in
the TEI Guidelines even if the names of elements and attributes might
not. Although it may be possible to transform a document following the
<term>TEI Abstract Model</term> into a <term>TEI Conformant</term>
document, it is not itself conformant.</p>

<p>A particularly important special case of this kind of mapping is
provided by ongoing efforts within the library community to define
metadata interoperability standards. The relationship of the TEI
Header to such efforts is discussed in <ptr target="#SH" /> below.</p>
</div>

<div type="div3">
<head>Mandatory components of a TEI Document</head>

<p>It is a long-standing requirement for any
    <term>TEI Conformant</term> document that it should contain a
      <gi>teiHeader</gi> element. To be more specific a
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> document must contain either: <list>
      <item> a single <gi>teiHeader</gi> element followed by a single
      <gi>text</gi> element, in that order; or</item>
      <item> in the case of a corpus or collection, a single overall
          <gi>teiHeader</gi> element followed by a series of
        <gi>TEI</gi> elements each with its own
      <gi>teiHeader</gi></item>
    </list> All <gi>teiHeader</gi> elements in a
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> document must include elements
      for: <list type="gloss">
      <label>Title Statement</label>
      <item>This should include the title of the TEI document
          expressed using a <gi>titleStmt</gi> element.</item>
      <label>Publication Statement</label>
      <item>This should include the place and date of publication or
          distribution of the TEI document, expressed using the
          <gi>publicationStmt</gi> element.</item>
      <label>Source Statement</label>
      <item>For a document derived from some previously existing
          document, this must include a bibliographic description of
          that source. For a document not so derived, this must
          include a brief statement that the document has no
          pre-existing source. In either case, this will be expressed
          using the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element. </item>
    </list></p>
</div>

</div>


<div type="div3" xml:id="CFNS">
  <head>Use of the <term>TEI Namespace</term></head>

<p>The Namespace Recommendation of the W3C, found at <ref
target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-names/">http://www.w3.org/TR/xml-names/</ref>
provides a way for an XML document to combine markup from different
vocabularies without risking name collision and consequent processing
difficulties.  While the scope of the TEI is large, there are many
areas in which it makes no particular recommendation, or where it
recommends that other defined markup schemes should be adopted, such
as graphics or mathematics. It is also considered desirable that users
of other markup schemes should be able to integrate  documents using
TEI markup with their own system. To meet these objectives, a TEI
conformant document is required to make appropriate use of the TEI
namespace.</p>

<p>All elements and attributes in a TEI Schema which represents
concepts from the TEI abstract model belong to the TEI namespace,
<ident type="ns">http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0</ident>, maintained by
the TEI along with additional namespaces for language variants. A
TEI Conformant document is required to declare the namespace for all
the elements it contains whether  these come from the TEI namespace or
from other schemes. </p>

<p>A TEI Schema may be created which assigns TEI elements to some
other namespace, or to no namespace at all. A document using such a
schema must be regarded as a TEI extension and cannot be considered
TEI Conformant, though it may be TEI Conformable. A schema which
introduces non-TEI elements or attributes within the TEI namespace is
also non-TEI Conformant; such practices are strongly deprecated as
they may lead to serious difficulties for processing or
interchange. 
</p>

</div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="CFOD">
  <head>Documentation Constraint</head>

<p>As noted in <ptr target="#CFVA"/> above, a TEI Schema can only be
generated from a TEI ODD, which also serves to document the semantics
of the elements defined by it. A TEI Conformant document should
therefore always be accompanied by (or refer to) a valid <term>TEI ODD
file</term> specifying which modules, elements, classes, etc. are in
use together with any modifications or renamings applied, and from
which a TEI Schema can be generated to validate the document. The TEI
supplies a number of predefined <term>TEI Customization exemplar ODD
files</term> and the schemas already generated from them (see <ptr
target="#MDlite"/>), but most projects will typically need to
customize the TEI beyond what these examples provide. It is assumed,
for example, that most projects will customize the TEI scheme by
removing those elements that are not needed for the texts they are
encoding, and by providing further constraints on the attribute values
and element content models the TEI provides. All such customizations
must be specified by means of a valid <term>TEI ODD</term> file. </p>

<p>As different sorts of customization have different implications for
the interchange and interoperability of TEI documents, it cannot be
assumed that every customization will necessarily result in a schema
that validates only TEI Conformant documents. The ODD language permits
modifications which conflict with the TEI abstract model, even though
observing this model  is a requirement for TEI conformance. The ODD
language can in fact be used to describe many kinds of markup scheme,
including schemes  which have nothing to do with the TEI at all. </p>

<p>Equally, it is possible to construct a TEI Schema which is
identical to that derived from a given TEI ODD file without using the
ODD scheme to document it. A schema can constructed simply by
combining the predefined schema language fragments corresponding with
the required set of TEI modules and other statements in the relevant
schema language. The status of such a schema with respect to the
<ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema cannot however be
determined, in general; it may therefore be impossible to determine
whether such a schema represents a clean modification or an
extension. This is one reason for making the presence of a TEI ODD
file a requirement for conformance. </p>

</div>




<div type="div3" xml:id="CFCATSCH">
<head>Varieties of TEI Conformance</head>

<p>The conformance status of a given document may be assessed by
answering the following questions, in the order indicated:
<list type="ordered">
<item>Is it a valid XML document, for which a TEI Schema exists? If
not, then the document cannot be considered TEI Conformant in any
sense.</item>
<item>Is the document accompanied by a TEI Conformant ODD
specification describing its markup scheme and intended semantics? If
not, then the document can only be considered TEI Conformant if it
validates against a predefined TEI Schema and conforms to the TEI
abstract model.</item>
<item>Does the markup in the document correctly represent the TEI
abstract model? Though difficult to assess, this is essential to TEI
conformance.</item>
<item>Does the document claim that all of its elements come from
some namespace other than the TEI (or no namespace)? If so, the
document cannot be TEI Conformant, though it may be TEI conformable.</item>
<item>If the document claims to use the TEI namespace, in part or
wholly, do the elements associated with that namespace in fact belong
to it? If not, the document cannot be TEI Conformant; if so, and if
all non-TEI elements and attributes are correctly associated with
other namespaces, then the document may be TEI Conformant.</item>
<item>Is the document valid according to a schema made by combining
all TEI modules as well as valid according to the schema derived from
its associated ODD specification? If so, the document is TEI
Conformant and the schema associated with it is a
<soCalled>clean</soCalled> modification. </item>
<item>Is the document valid according to the schema derived from its
associated ODD specification, but not according to <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident>? If so, the
document uses a TEI extension. </item>
<item>Is it possible automatically to transform the document into a
document which is valid according to <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident>, using
only information supplied in the accompanying ODD and without loss of
information? If so, the document is TEI Conformable.</item>
</list>
</p>

<p>In the following table, we examine more closely some specific,
though imaginary, cases:

<table>
<row>
<cell/>
<cell>A</cell>
<cell>B </cell>
<cell>C</cell>
<cell>D</cell>
<cell>E </cell>
<cell>F</cell>
<cell>G</cell>
<cell>H</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Conforms to TEI abstract model</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>?</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>?</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Valid ODD present</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Uses only non-TEI namespace(s) or none</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Uses TEI and other namespaces correctly</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Document is valid as a subset of <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident></cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
</row>
<row>
<cell>Document can be converted automatically to a form which is
valid as a subset of <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident></cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>Y</cell>
<cell>N</cell>
<cell>?</cell>
</row>
</table>
</p>
<p>We assume firstly that each sample document assessed here is a
well-formed XML document, and that it is valid against some schema.  
</p>
<p>The document in column A is TEI Conformant. Its tagging follows the
TEI Abstract Model, both as regards syntactic constraints (its
<gi>l</gi> elements appear within <gi>div</gi> elements and not the
reverse) and semantic constraints (its <gi>l</gi> elements appear to
contain verse lines rather than typographic ones). It is acccompanied
by a valid ODD which documents exactly how it uses the TEI. All the
TEI-defined elements and attributes in the document are placed in the
TEI namespace. The schema against which it is valid is a
<soCalled>clean</soCalled> subset of the tei_all schema. </p>

<p>The document in column B is not a TEI document. Although it is
accompanied by a valid TEI ODD, the resulting schema includes some
<soCalled>unclean</soCalled> modifications, and represents some
concepts from the TEI Abstract Model using non-TEI elements; for
example, it re-defines the content model of <gi>p</gi> to permit
<gi>div</gi> within it, and it includes an element
<gi>pageTrimming</gi> which appears to have the same meaning as the
existing TEI <gi>fw</gi> element. It uses the TEI namespace correctly
to identify the TEI elements it contains, but the ODD does not contain
enough information automatically to convert its non-TEI elements into
TEI equivalents.</p>

<p>The document in column C is TEI Conformable. It is almost the same
as the document in column A, except that the names of the elements
used are not those specified by the TEI namespace. Because the ODD
accompanying it contains an exact mapping for each element name (using
the <gi>altIdent</gi> element) and there are no name conflicts, it is
possible to make an automatic conversion of this document.</p>

<p>The document in column D is a TEI Extension. It combines elements
from its own namespace with unmodified TEI elements in the TEI
namespace. Its usage of TEI elements conforms to the TEI Abstract
Model. Its ODD defines a new <gi>blort</gi> element which has no exact
TEI equivalent, but which is assigned to an existing TEI class;
consequently its schema is not a clean subset of
<ident>tei_all</ident>. If the associated ODD provided a way of
mapping this element to an existing TEI element, then this would be
TEI Conformable.</p>

<p>The document in column E is superficially similar to document D,
but because it does not use any namespace declarations (or,
equivalently, it assigns unmodified TEI elements to its own
namespace), it may contain name collisions; there is no way of knowing
whether a <gi>p</gi> within it is the same as the TEI's <gi>p</gi> or
has some other meaning. The accompanying ODD file may be used to
provide the human reader with information about equivalently named
elements in the TEI namespace, and hence to determine whether the
document is valid with respect to the TEI Abstract Model but this is
not an automatable process. In particular, cases of apparent conflict
(for example use of an element <gi>p</gi> to represent a concept not
in the TEI Abstract Model but in the Abstract Model of some other
system, whose namespace has been removed as well) cannot be reliably
resolved. By our current definition therefore, this is not a TEI
document.</p>

<p>The document in column F is TEI Conformable. The difference
between it and that in column D is that the new element <gi>blort</gi>
which is used in this document is a specialisation of an existing TEI
element, and the ODD in which it is defined specifies the mapping (a
<gi>my:blort</gi> may be automatically converted to  a <gi>tei:seg
type="blort"</gi>, for example). For this to work, however, the
<gi>blort</gi> must observe to the same syntactic constraints as the
<gi>seg</gi>; if it does not, this would also be a case of TEI
Extension.</p>

<p>The document in column G is not a TEI document. Its structure is
fully documented by a valid TEI ODD, but it does not claim to
represent the TEI Abstract Model, does not use the TEI namespace, and
is not intended to validate against any TEI schema. </p>

<p>The document in column H is very like that in column A, but it
lacks an accompanying ODD. Instead, the schema used to validate it is
produced simply by combining TEI schema fragments in the same way as
an ODD processor would, given the ODD. If the resulting schema is a
clean subset of tei_all, such a document is indistinguishable from a
TEI conformant one, but there is no way of determining (without
inspection) whether this is the case if any modification or extension
has been applied. Its status is therefore, like that of Text E,
impossible to determine.</p>

</div>


</div>


<!--



<p>The definition of TEI conformance permits several different
      kinds of schema of varying interchangeability. We define names
      for some of the chief varieties here: <list type="gloss">
      <label>
        <term>TEI Pure Subset Schema</term>
      </label>
      <item>A <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> is one which is
          identical to or further constrains the <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema. This
          may include: the removal of unused elements, attributes, and
          classes; the provision of attribute value lists; or the
          further constraint of existing datatypes or content models. 
          A <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> only documents elements in
          the TEI namespace.  A document instance that validates against a
          <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> must always also
          validate against the <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema; in the terminology
          introduced in <ptr target="#MDMD"/>, it is the result of
          <term>clean modification</term>. </item>
      <label>
        <term>TEI Renaming Subset Schema</term>
      </label>
      <item>A <term>TEI Renaming Subset schema</term> is one which
          is identical to or further constrains a <term>TEI Pure
            Subset schema</term>, but which can also rename existing
          elements or attributes if and only if an <gi>equiv</gi> element in
          their valid <term>TEI ODD file</term> documents an existing
          <term>TEI Pure Subset schema</term> equivalent for them.
          None of these changes should conflict with the names of
          existing TEI elements, attributes or classes and to ensure
          this they should be in a user-defined namespace. A document instance that
          validates against a <term>TEI Renaming Subset schema</term>
          must always also validate against the <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema if the
          renamings are reversed or replaced with their documented
          equivalents from the TEI namespace. </item>
      <label>
        <term>TEI Modification Schema</term>
      </label>
      <item> A <term>TEI Modification schema</term> is one which
          modifies a <term>TEI Pure Subset</term> or <term>TEI
            Renaming Subset</term> by: changing existing elements,
          attributes, or classes; adding existing elements or
          attributes to members of existing classes; or changing
          existing datatypes or content models. These changes should
          not add new elements, attributes or classes, and all changes
          should be documented in a <term>TEI ODD file</term>. Any
          elements or attributes to which unclean modifications (see
          <ptr target="#MDMD"/>) have been been made should be
          placed in a user-defined namespace. A document instance that
          validates against a <term>TEI Modification schema</term> is
          not expected to validate against the <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema or
          subsets of this schema. </item>
      <label>
        <term>TEI Extension Schema</term>
      </label>
      <item> A <term>TEI Extension schema</term> is one that extends
          a <term>TEI Pure Subset</term>, <term>TEI Renaming
          Subset</term>, or <term>TEI Modification schema</term> by
          adding new elements, attributes, classes, datatypes or
          content models. All new elements and attributes, which are
          not renamings of current elements and attributes, must be
          added in a separate namespace. The relationship of any
          extensions to the TEI should be documented in a <term>TEI
            ODD file</term>. Additionally any renamings of existing
          TEI elements and attributes should be documented with an
          <gi>equiv</gi> element to an existing <term>TEI Pure
            Subset schema</term> equivalent for them and appear in a
          user-defined namespace. A document
          instance that validates against a <term>TEI Extension
          schema</term> is not expected to validate against the
          <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema. </item>
      <label>
        <term>TEI Supported Extension schema</term>
      </label>
      <item>A <term>TEI Supported Extension schema</term> is a
          special case of the <term>TEI Extension schema</term>, where
          the extension has been created and is (to some degree)
          supported by the TEI. This includes the <term>TEI
            Customization Exemplars</term> detailed above (see <ptr
            target="#MDlite"/>. A document instance that validates
          against a <term>TEI Supported Extension schema</term> is not
          expected to validate against the <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema. </item>
    </list>
  </p>
</div>



<div type="div3">
  <head>Non-Conformant Customizations</head>
  <p> In some cases those using the TEI may wish to customize the
      TEI in a non-conformant manner. While producing
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> customizations is always to be
      preferred, it is recognised there are situations where this may
      not be possible or practical. Most of these situations are
      entirely reasonable, and conformance, while desirable, should
      not be confused with quality. </p>
  <p>It is also recognised that data destined to be in a
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> document may originate in a
      variety of forms. Data might be captured by keyboarding or other
      processing pipelines into a locally defined data creation
      format. This may itself be a non-conformant format; as may the
      local storage or format used internally for a project because of
      local processing needs. Whenever possible, however, local
      storage in a <term>TEI Conformant</term> format is recommended
      as this is likely to record more information than the input
      format for a single application or processing need. It is
      possible that there may be entirely different formats at
      different stages in the processes of data creation, local
      storage and processed dissemination. However, even if any of the
      data creation, local storage or processing formats are not
      <term>TEI Conformant</term>, they may still follow TEI
      recommendations in the selection of textual features to be
      marked up, element names and content models, or additionally the
      <term>TEI Abstract Model</term>.</p>
    
  <p>As noted above, the TEI ODD system may be used to document any
      markup scheme, whether or not it is TEI Conformant. We therefore
      use the term <term>TEI-Based Customization</term> to define an
      application of a valid <term>TEI ODD file</term> that defines any
      non-TEI Conformant markup scheme<note place="foot">Such a
        specification, being a TEI ODD, is ipso facto TEI Conformant
        of course</note>.        
      A document instance that validates against a
      <term>TEI-Based customization </term> is not expected to
      validate against the <ident type="schema">tei_all</ident> schema or be interoperable with
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> documents. Where such a document
      makes use of elements defined in the TEI abstract model it may
      signal this fact by making use of the TEI namespace for them.      
  </p>
</div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="CFNS">
  <head>Namespaces and <term>TEI Conformance</term></head>
  <p>It is a requirement of <term>TEI Conformance</term> that, in a
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> document, all existing TEI
      elements and attributes be in the <term>TEI Namespace</term>:
      "http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0/". Moreover,
    <term>TEI Conformant</term> documents must not extend the
      <term>TEI Namespace</term> with additional elements and
      attributes. All new elements or attributes
       must appear in a separate namespace, either a user-defined one or if the
      elements are taken from an existing schema, the namespace
      appropriate to that schema. In a <term>TEI Extension
      schema</term> a TEI element may have an attribute not from the
      <term>TEI Namespace</term>, provided that the expanded-name of
      the attribute has a non-null namespace URI. It is an error for
      an element from the <term>TEI Namespace</term> to have
      attributes with expanded-names which have null namespace URIs
      (i.e. attributes with unprefixed names) other than attributes
      defined for the element in the TEI Guidelines. A
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> document might have only one
      namespace, that is the <term>TEI Namespace</term>, or it might
      have any number of namespaces whose relationship and point of
      attachment has been documented in a valid <term>TEI ODD file</term>.
      In choosing user-defined namespaces care should be taken to
      avoid conflicts with existing namespaces, while simultaneously
      indicating the nature of the extension being added. </p>
  <p>It is recognised that some processing software may find coping
      with multiple (or any) namespaces difficult, and that as a
      result the local storage or processing format may conflate or
      remove namespaces. While this is regrettable, and will make
      those document instances non-conformant, it highlights one
      reason that any new elements, even in a separate namespace,
      should not have identical names to existing elements.  There are
      many reasons for the TEI's use of namespaces.  These include the avoidance of
      element name collision and the clear signalling of elements the
      TEI has created.  Wherever possible the removal or conflation of namespaces should be avoided.</p>
</div>


<div type="div2">
  <head><term>TEI Conformance</term> and <term>TEI ODD Files</term></head>
  <p>As it is a requirement for conformance that any new
      customizations of the TEI Schemas should be documented in a
      valid <term>TEI ODD file</term>, it is recommended practice that
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> document instances should indicate
      the URI of a <term>TEI ODD file</term> from which their
      applicable schemas have been generated. When interchanging TEI
      documents with others, providing this ODD file (or making it
      freely accessible on the internet) is recommended practice. In
      many cases users may simply wish to use the schemas derived from
      the <term>TEI Customization Exemplars</term> such as those
      detailed above. In this case they should indicate either in
      prose or via a URI the ODD and/or schema it validates against.
      Where different versions of this schema have been produced, it
      should be assumed that the document instance validates against
      the most recent version of the schema at the date of publication
      recorded in its header. Although the TEI attempts to support XML
      DTDs, W3C XML Schema, and RELAX NG (both compact and XML
      formats), it does not mandate the schema language you should
      use, only that this schema should have been generated through
      the use of a <term>TEI ODD file</term> that references the TEI
      Guidelines. </p>
</div>


<div type="div2">
  <head><term>TEI Conformance</term> and Document Interchange</head>
  <p>Although a wide variety of documents are able to be
      <term>TEI Conformant</term>, it should be stressed that this
      does not in any way imply that interchange or interoperability
      of these documents will be straightforward. While it should be
      mostly unproblematic with documents that validate against a TEI
      Pure Subset or TEI Renaming schema, any form of TEI Modification
      or <term>TEI Extension</term> schema will necessarily be less
      suitable for interchange or interoperable use. For this reason,
      whenever it is possible it is recommended that where a local
      storage format is validated against a <term>TEI
      Modification</term> or <term>TEI Extension</term> schema, the
      possibilities for transforming these to forms which validate
      against a <term>TEI Pure Subset</term> schema should be investigated. Every care should
      be taken to preserve all the intellectual content that resides
      in the incompatible markup, and wherever possible the
      differences between the two should be documented not only in the
      existing valid <term>TEI ODD file</term>, but also in accompanying
      project documentation. One strategy is to move incompatible
      markup into separate files and use stand-off markup to retain
      the information. </p>
</div>


<div type="div2">
  <head><term>TEI Conformance</term> and Funding Bodies</head>
  <p>The TEI is aware that some academic funding bodies view
      <term>TEI Conformant</term> documents as superior to
      non-conformant TEI documents. It should be stressed to these
      bodies that although TEI Conformance does imply additional
      documentation (through the <term>TEI ODD file</term>), and some
      very basic format requirements, it should not be confused with a
      marker of quality. It is possible that a non-conformant TEI
      document may be of superior quality, provide more significantly
      detailed documentation, and have been subjected to greater
      academic scrutiny than one which is technically
      <term>TEI Conformant</term>. While the TEI recommends the
      production of documents which are <term>TEI Conformant</term>,
      it recognises that the goals such as textual fidelity,
      documentation, and academic rigour are more important. Although
      the TEI encourages these funding bodies to suggest <term>TEI
        Conformance</term>, and in addition <term>TEI Recommended
        Practice</term>, their prime concern should be the overall
      quality of the documents for the funded purpose and their
      potential for re-use.</p>
</div>

-->
