<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
-->
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="div1"
    xml:id="CMC">
    <head>Computer-mediated Communication</head>
    <div type="div2" xml:id="CMC1">
        <head>General Considerations and Overview</head>
        <p>This chapter describes the TEI encoding mechanisms available for genres of
            computer-mediated communication (CMC) and thus social media. It is intended to provide
            the basic framework needed to encode CMC corpora.</p>
        <p>While the term “computer-mediated communication” might be used to describe all sorts of
            communications between humans in the modern age (for example, internet video meetings or
            cellular telephony), herein we use the term to apply to the more traditional forms of
            computer-mediated asynchronous communication like text messages, instant messaging,
            email, chat rooms, online forums, social network services.</p>
        <p>The salient feature of these CMC mediums is that a communicative act is generated,
            typically at the author’s leisure, in the private space of the author, and then
            transmitted en bloc to the recipient(s). Even though in some CMC genres (e.g.,
            WhatsApp), the other parties are informed by an automated alert about the fact that
            another party is currently composing a new post, they cannot track the process of
            verbalization, i.e. how the written utterance emerges in the entry form on the user
            interface of its author. It is not until the author performs a ‘posting’ action (for
            example, by hitting the ‘enter’ key or by activating a ‘send’ button with the mouse)
            that the result of the composition process — the post — is made available for the other
            parties. From the perspective of its addressees or readers, a post is a stretch of text
            that has been composed in advance. Different from spoken utterances but similar to
            edited text, (1) the reader of a post does not have access to the verbalization process
            and (2) the mental processing of a post is not possible until the process of
            verbalization (the composition) has been finished and the posting action has been
            performed by the author. Posts occur in a broad range of written CMC genres, including
            (but not limited to): as user ‘messages’ in chats and WhatsApp dialogues, as SMS
            messages, as tweets in Twitter timelines, as individual comments following a status
            update on Facebook pages, as posts in forum threads, as contributions on Wikipedia talk
            pages, and in the comments section of a weblog.</p>

    </div>
    <div>
        <head>Documenting CMC (and providing general meta data)</head>
        <!-- 
        Still an open issue. How to document the source (e.g. database dump, web scraping, query parameters) of the current CMC encodings
        * Source: made tag abuse for documenting the source: <biblStruct> or <recordingStmt>
        * Timeline: in textDesc/interaction/
        * Participant description (in profile description)
        -->
    </div>
    
    
    <div>
        <head>Encoding Unique to CMC</head>
        <!--
            * Some introductory sentence
            * specList (will automatically insert post including its attributes)
            * Cf. https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-specList.html 
        -->
        <div xml:id="CMCPOST">
            <head>CMC Posts</head>
            <p>The element <gi>post</gi> characterizes computer-mediated communication (CMC). A post
                is defined as a written (sometimes spoken) contribution to an ongoing CMC
                interaction which (1) has been composed by its author in its entirety as part of a
                private activity, and (2) has been sent to the server en bloc. It may co-occur with
                    <gi>u</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>, <gi>incident</gi>, or other existing TEI elements
                within a <gi>div</gi>, or directly within the <gi>body</gi>, and may contain
                headings, paragraphs, openers, closers, or salutations. </p>
            <p>As a member of the TEI attribute classes <ident type="class">att.ascribed</ident>,
                    <ident type="class">att.canonical</ident>, <ident type="class"
                    >att.datable</ident>, <ident type="class">att.global</ident>, <ident
                    type="class">att.timed</ident>, and <ident type="class">att.typed</ident>, posts
                may take a variety of attributes. Common attributes used in conjunction with
                    <gi>post</gi> include <att>who</att>, <att>synch</att>, <att>type</att>,
                    <att>subtype</att>, <att>rend</att>, and <att>xml:id</att>. </p>
        </div>
        
        <div>
            <head>Attributes specific to CMC <gi>post</gi></head>
            <p>Three attributes pertain specifically to <gi>post</gi>:
            <specList>
                <specDesc key="post" atts="modality replyTo indentLevel"/>
            </specList>
                The <att>modality</att> attribute is required on the <gi>post</gi> element in order to describe the creation mechanism used in the CMC environment. The type of the content (i.e., whether the content of the post is written, an image, a video clip, etc.) is indicated by the child elements of the <gi>post</gi>. For example a written post from WhatsApp might include an audio-visual clip copied into the post, and in such case may not actually have any writing. Such a post is still considered in the “written” modality.
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06" xml:id="m12">
                            <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
                                <desc>Screenshot von der Google-Suche nach dem Friseur "Haarraum" mit der Durchschnitts-Google-Bewertung (4,5 von 5 Sternen), der Adresse, der Telefonnummer und den Öffnungszeiten</desc>
                            </figure>
                        </post>
                    </egXML>
            </p>
            <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute is used to capture information drawn from the original metadata associated with a post that asserts to which previous post the current post is a response, or to which previous post it refers. This metadata is included by many, but not all, CMC environments, when the user executes a formal reply action (e.g., by clicking or tapping a reply button). This attribute should not be used to encode interpreted or inferred reply relations based on linguistic cues or discourse markers.
            </p>
            <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute indicates the replied-to or referred-to posts by providing one or more pointers to them. For example:
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="p28" who="#u7" replyTo="#p1" when-iso="2015-07-29T21:44">
                        <p>Es hat den Anschein, als wäre bei BER durchaus große Kompetenz am Bau, allerdings nicht in Form von Handwerkern….</p>
                        <p>http://www.zeit.de/2015/29/imtech-flughafen-berlin-ber-verzoegerung/komplettansicht</p>
                    </post>
                    <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="p29" who="#u8" replyTo="#p28" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:11">
                        <p>Nein Nein, an den Handwerkern kann es rein strukturel nicht gelegen haben.
                            Niemand lässt seine Handwerker auf der Baustelle derart allein. Zudem gibt es
                            höchstoffizielle “Abnahmen” von Bauabschnitten/phasen. Welcher Mangel auch
                            bestanden hatte, er hätte Zeitnah auffallen müssen.</p>
                        <p>Uuups, für Imtek hab ich mal in einer Nachunternehmerfirma gearbeitet. Imtek is offenbar ein universeler Bauträger, der alles baut.</p>
                    </post>
                    <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="p30" who="#u8" replyTo="#p29" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:26">
                        <p>Stahlkunstruktionen dacht ich mal, was die bauen – oder bauen lassen.</p>
                        <p>Das ist schon ein übles Ding. Die Ausschreibungenund Angebote sind unauffällig, aber wenn Unregelmässigkeiten auftreten (im Bauverlauf) dann gibt es die saftigen Rechnungen. Da steht dann der Bauherr da und fragt sich, wie er denn so schnell einen fähigen Ersatz herbekommt. Und diese Frage erübrigt sich meist,
                            weil der Markt der Baufirmen das nicht hergibt – weil tendenziel 100 % Auslastung. (und noch schlimmer: Absprachen) Was auch Folge des Marktdrucks gewesen war.</p>
                    </post>
                </egXML>
                Example: Three blog comments where, by the reply references in the source, the first is a reply to the initial blog post (not part of the example), the second is a reply to the first, and the third is a reply to the second. 
                <!-- 
                    BIBL: should refer to the TEI encoding of a section of the blog page 
                    https://scilogs.spektrum.de/wild-dueck-blog/scheinzwerge-oder-viele-probleme-werden-groesser-wenn-man-sie-anpackt-griechenland/
                -->
            </p>
            <p>In the CMC genre of Wiki talk, users insert their contribution to a discussion by modifying the wiki page of the discussion — the talk page. Since there is no technical reply action available in wiki software, users apply textual indentation in the wiki code to indicate a reply to a previous message, and a threaded structure is formed by a series of such indentations. The attribute <att>indentLevel</att> records the level of indentation, that is the nesting depth of the current post in such a thread-like structure (as defined by its author and in relation to the standard level of non-indentation which is to be encoded as <code>indentLevel="0"</code>). It is used in wiki talk corpora but may also be used for other threaded genres e.g. when HTML was used as a source. 
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <div type="thread" xml:id="i.10031_19">
                        <head>[[WP:AUTO]]</head>
                        <post indentLevel="0" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-07T03:09+00" who="#WU00010808" xml:id="i.10031_19_1">
                            <p> I would kindly request from Mr. Meyer to allow others to edit the [...]</p>
                        </post>
                        <post indentLevel="1" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T03:49+00" who="#WU00010804" xml:id="i.10031_19_2">
                            <p>I dont agree, this article is not about Dr. Meyer, [...]</p>
                        </post>
                        <post indentLevel="2" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T04:16+00" who="#WU00005520" xml:id="i.10031_19_3">
                            <p>Why don't you read the policy. [...]</p>
                        </post>
                        <post indentLevel="3" modality="written" when-iso="2006-11-01T22:58+00" who="#WU00010815" xml:id="i.10031_19_4">
                            <p>Because the policy makes no sense, [...]</p>
                        </post>
                    </div>
                </egXML>
                Example: File 10031.tei.xml from the EFG Wikipedia corpus 2019. Exchange between four different users. (Page Talk:Eiffel (programming language) from the English Wikipedia)
            </p>
        </div>
        
        <div>
            <head>Attributes for general CMC encoding</head>
            <!-- discussion of @generatedBy -->
        </div>
    </div>
    
    
    <div>
        <head>Recommendations for encoding CMC</head>
        <!-- 
            Discussion of phenomena — short discussions, maybe with some code snippets, and references to the other chapters where the TEI encoding is introduced;
        -->
        <div>
            <head>Emojis and Emoticons</head>
            <!-- add source for example in TEI <example> with ref to bibl element -->
            <p>Emojis and emoticons are interaction signs represented by pictograms or icons such as
                smileys used abundantly in CMC.</p>

            <p>Emoticons predate emojis and are typed on a keyboard using a combination of ASCII
                punctuation and other characters such as “;-)”, and occurred in newsgroup and chat
                communication as early as the mid-1980s.</p>

            <p><emph>Emojis</emph> are more recent interaction signs that are encoded as Unicode
                characters and offered in CMC environments as small icon graphics such as . An emoji
                is typically a single Unicode character which is intended to be mapped directly to a
                pictorial symbol. An emoticon is typically several Unicode characters (from the
                subset known as ASCII) in a row, each of which has an intended use other than as
                part of an emoticon.</p>

            <p>Either emoticons or emojis may be simply transcribed as a sequence of characters. As
                with any other characters, they may be entered as numeric character entities if this
                is more convenient. (E.g., “&#x01F637;” might be transcribed as “&amp;#x01F637;” in
                any XML document, including a TEI document; see <!--<ptr target="#D4-44"/>-->.)</p>

            <p> When the text of a post is being tokenized, e.g. for linguistic analysis, it may be
                useful to encode the emoticon or emoji as a separate token. In such cases elements
                like <gi>w</gi> and <gi>pc</gi> may be used for tokenization, and the <att>pos</att>
                attribute may be used to indicate that the encoded string is an emoji or an
                emoticon. (See <ptr target="#AILC"/>.)</p>

            <p>For example, the source post “da bin ich nicht so empfindlich ;)” ends with an
                emoticon, and might be encoded as follows:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post>
                    <w pos="ADV">da</w>
                    <w pos="VAFIN">bin</w>
                    <w pos="PPER">ich</w>
                    <w pos="PTKNEG">nicht</w>
                    <w pos="ADV">so</w>
                    <w pos="ADJD">empfindlich</w>
                    <w pos="EMOASC">;)</w>
                </post>
            </egXML>
            <p>Similarly, the source post “Klar☺” might be encoded as follows:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03" xml:id="lscLB.m6">
                    <w pos="ADV">Klar</w>
                    <w pos="EMOIMG">☺</w>
                </post>
            </egXML>
            <p>The values of <att>pos</att> in the above examples are from the STTS_IBK Tagset for German (see <ptr type="cit" target="#STTS_IBK"/>), which includes tags for interaction signs in CMC such as ‘EMOASC’ for an ASCII-based emoticon and ‘EMOIMG’ for an icon-based emoji.</p>
            <p>Alternatively, e.g. when <gi>w</gi> is not regularly used to encode tokens in the TEI document, <gi>c</gi> can be used to mark an emoji. For example, the source post “Da kostet ein Haarschnitt 50 € &#x01F631;” might be encoded as follows:</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post xml:lang="de">
                    Da kostet ein Haarschnitt
                    50 € <c type="emoji" ana="#fsif" generatedBy="template">&#x01F631;</c>
                </post>
            </egXML>
            <p>Sometimes, e.g. when the source of the TEI document was a web page in HTML, the emojis may occur only as an icon graphic in the source. In that case, they can be encoded in TEI using <gi>figure</gi>. The corresponding unicode character can then be recorded in the <gi>desc</gi> element by the encoder if desired. </p>
            <p>Source text: ... ich überlege noch &#x1F648;</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03" xml:id="lscLB.m6"> 
                    ... ich überlege noch 
                    <figure type="emoji" generatedBy="template">
                        <graphic url="fig1.png"/>
                        <desc type="gloss">see no evil monkey</desc>
                        <desc type="unicode">U+1F648</desc>
                    </figure> 
                </post>
            </egXML>
        </div>
        
        <div>
            <head>Post with graphics</head>
            <p>A post in a CMC interaction may contain a graphic in addition to some text or even
                contain only a graphic (without any text). As explained in [REF section on
                @modality], the modality of such a post should be considered as “written”. To encode
                the graphic information, the TEI element <gi>figure</gi> should be used in the
                appropriate place.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#UND">
                <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06" xml:id="m12">
                    <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
                        <desc>Screenshot von der Google-Suche nach dem Friseur "Haarraum" mit der
                            Durchschnitts-Google-Bewertung (4,5 von 5 Sternen), der Adresse, der
                            Telefonnummer und den Öffnungszeiten</desc>
                    </figure>
                </post>
            </egXML>
            <p>Example: A private chat post that contained only a screenshot of a google search
                result for a hairdresser. A link to the graphic file itself is not included because
                it has not been retained for the corpus. </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post type="tweet" key="1043823300479258624" mode="written" generatedBy="human"
                    synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t006" xml:id="p8" who="#u1" xml:lang="deu">
                    <time generatedBy="system"> 16:24 </time> Bro Tri-Engel...so hab ich mir das
                    vorgestellt!!! @AndreLo79 #bcrn18 #wikidach @Heiko komm' mal Twitter! #Engel
                        <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
                        <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DnxnwN9XsAEHXw2.jpg:large"/>
                    </figure>
                </post>
            </egXML>
            <p>Example: Encoding of a tweet that contains some text (including hashtags and
                mentions) and a graphic. The <gi>graphic</gi> element retains the url of the graphic
                on the web just as in the source. </p>
        </div>
    </div>
    
    
    <div>
        <head>“Putting it all together” – genre specific examples</head>
        <!--
            * Twitter
            * WhatsApp
            * Wikipedia talk
            * NB: not necessarily add complete examples (whole TEI file) but rather snippets
        -->
    </div>
    
    
    <div>
        <head>The TEI CMC Module</head>
        <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:
            <moduleSpec ident="cmc">
                <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2021-09-07">Elements, Attributes, and Models for
                    Computer-mediated communication (CMC). This module collects all cmc-specific
                    extensions. Hence these will only be added to a TEI schema when this module is
                    selected in a customisation.</desc>
                <altIdent>TEI-CMC</altIdent>
                <altIdent xml:lang="en">Computer-Mediated Communication</altIdent>
            </moduleSpec> The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described
            in <ptr target="#STIN"/>.</p>
        <specGrp xml:id="CMCincludes">
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.cmc.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                href="../../Specs/macro.specialPara.cmc.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.cmc.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../Specs/post.xml"/>
        </specGrp>
    </div>
</div>
