<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
-->
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="div1"
  xml:id="CMC">
  <head>Computer-mediated Communication</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the TEI encoding mechanisms available for textual data which represents
    discourse from genres of computer-mediated communication (CMC). It is intended to provide the
    basic framework needed to encode CMC corpora.</p>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="CMCoverview">
    <head>General Considerations and Overview</head>
    <p>While the term <q>computer-mediated communication</q>, in a broader sense, might be used to
      describe all sorts of communications between humans which are mediated by digital technologies
      (for example, text on web pages, dialogic written interaction in chats and forums, the spoken
      language in internet video meetings), herein we use the term to apply to forms of
      communication which share the following features: <list rend="bulleted">
        <item>they are <emph rend="italic">dialogic</emph>;</item>
        <item>they are organized in the form of interactional sequences so that each communicative
          move determines the context for subsequent moves (taken by another interlocutor) and
          reacts to the context created by a prior move;</item>
        <item>the communicative moves which may be put into practice as posts (cf. <ptr
            target="#CMCcmcpost"/>), utterances, onscreen activities, or bodily activities exerted
          by a virtual avatar are created and displayed using <emph rend="italic">computer
            technology</emph> (keyboard, mouse, speech-to-text conversion software, monitor or
          screen) and mediated over a <emph rend="italic">computer network</emph> (typically the
          internet).</item>
      </list>
    </p>
    <p>Computer-mediated communication is conducted using <list rend="simple">
        <item>communication technologies such as chats, messengers, or online forums;</item>
        <item>social media platforms and applications such as Twitter, Facebook, Instagram, or
          WhatsApp;</item>
        <item>the communication functions of collaborative platforms and projects (e.g. an online
          learning environment, or a Wikipedia <soCalled>talk</soCalled> page);</item>
        <item>3D environments (e.g. Second Life, gaming environments);</item>
        <item>or similar technologies and services on the internet.</item>
      </list></p>
    <p>CMC is, by default, multimodal. Whereas early CMC systems (e.g. the prototypes of today’s
      chat and messaging applications or Usenet developed in the 70s and 80s) were completely
      ASCII-based, the lion’s share of contemporary CMC technologies and applications allow for the
      combination of different semiotic resources (e.g. written or spoken language with graphic
      icons and images) and even for the combined use of different CMC technologies in one and the
      same platform (e.g. combined use of an audio connection, a chat system, and a 3D interface in
      which users control a virtual avatar as in many MMORPGs or in virtual worlds such as Second
      Life).</p>
  </div>

  <div type="div2" xml:id="CMCUnits">
    <head>Basic Units of CMC</head>
    <p>This section describes the encoding mechanisms for the basic units of CMC and for their
      combined use to encode CMC data.</p>
    <p>We refer to units which are produced by an interlocutor to contribute to an ongoing CMC
      interaction or joint CMC activity as <emph rend="italic">basic CMC units</emph>. Contributions
      to an ongoing interaction are produced to perform a move as part of the further development of
      the interactional sequence, for instance in chats or forum discussions. In some cases
      contributions to joint CMC activities may not all be directly interactional; some may be part
      of a collaborative project of the involved individuals, for instance editing activities in a
      shared text editor or whiteboard in parallel with an ongoing CMC interaction (chat, audio
      conversation, or audiovideo conference) in the same CMC environment in which these editing
      activities are discussed by the collaborators.</p>
    <p>Basic units of CMC can be described according to three criteria: (i) the temporal properties
      of how these contributions are produced by their creators, transmitted via CMC systems, and
      made accessible for the recipients; (ii) whether the unit as a whole is realised in a verbal
      or nonverbal mode; (iii) for verbal units: whether the unit is realised in the written or
      spoken mode. A taxonomy of basic CMC units resulting from these criteria is given in Fig. <ptr
        target="#cmcunits-taxonomy"/>
    </p>
    <figure xml:id="cmcunits-taxonomy">
      <graphic url="Images/cmcunits-taxonomy.png"/>
      <head>Taxonomy of basic CMC units.<ptr type="cit" target="#BIB_CMC_Core"/></head>
    </figure>
    <p>The most important distinction in <ref target="#cmcunits-taxonomy">the taxonomy</ref>
      concerns the temporal nature of units exchanged via CMC technologies. The left part of the
      taxonomy describes units that are performed (by a producer) and perceived (by a recipient) as
      a continuous stream of behaviour. Units of this type can be performed as</p>
    <list rend="bulleted">
      <!--Should this be a list of <lable>-<item> pairs? —Syd, 2022-08-11-->
      <item><emph rend="bold">spoken utterances,</emph> i.e. stretches of speech which are produced
        to perform a speaker turn in a conversation,</item>
      <item><emph rend="bold">bodily activity,</emph> i.e. nonverbal behavior (gesture, gaze)
        produced to perform a speaker turn, either performed by the real body of an interlocutor
        (e.g. in a video conference) or through the virtual avatar of an interlocutor in a 3D
        environment,</item>
      <item><emph rend="bold">onscreen activities,</emph> i.e. non-bodily forms of behaviour that
        are transmitted to the group of interacting or coworking participants, for instance the
        editing of content in a shared text editor which can be perceived by the other parties
        simultaneously (as may be the case in learning or collaboration environments).</item>
    </list>
    <p>The right part of <ref target="#cmcunits-taxonomy">the taxonomy</ref> describes units in
      which the production, transmission, and perception of contributions to CMC interactions are
      organised in a strictly consecutive order: The content — verbal, nonverbal, or multimodal — of
      the contribution has to be produced before it can be transmitted via the internet and made
      available on the computer monitor or mobile screen of any other party as a preserved and
      persistent unit. We term this type of unit a <emph rend="italic">post</emph>. Posts occur in
      two different variants: <list rend="bulleted">
        <item>as <emph rend="bold">written / multimodal posts,</emph> which are produced with an
          editor form that is designed for the composition of stretches of written text. Most
          contemporary post-based CMC technologies provide features for the inclusion of graphic and
          audiovisual content (emoji graphics, images, videos) into posts and even to produce posts
          without verbal content (which then may consist only of emojis, an image, or a video file).
          Written / multimodal posts are the standard format for user contributions in primarily
          text-based CMC genres and applications such as chat, SMS, WhatsApp, Instagram, Facebook,
          Twitter, online forums, or Wikipedia talk pages.</item>
        <item>as <emph rend="bold">audio posts</emph>, which are produced using a recording
          function. In contrast to CMC units of the type <emph rend="italic">utterance</emph> which
          are produced and transmitted simultaneously, audio posts first have to be recorded as a
          whole and are then transmitted — as audio files — via the internet; the availability of
          the recording is indicated in the screen protocol by a template-generated, visual post;
          the recipients can play the recording (repeatedly) by activating the play button displayed
          in the post on the screen. Examples of CMC applications that implement audio posts are
          WhatsApp or RocketChat.</item>
      </list></p>
    <p>Three of the four basic CMC units described above can be represented with models that are
      described elsewhere in the TEI Guidelines:</p>
    <table>
      <row rend="underline">
        <cell>CMC unit</cell>
        <cell>Type of corpus data</cell>
        <cell> </cell>
        <cell>TEI P5 element</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell>utterance</cell>
        <cell>transcription of speech</cell>
        <cell>&#x21D2;</cell>
        <cell><gi>u</gi></cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell>bodily activity</cell>
        <cell>texual description</cell>
        <cell>&#x21D2;</cell>
        <cell><gi>kinesic</gi></cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell>onscreen activity</cell>
        <cell>textual description</cell>
        <cell>&#x21D2;</cell>
        <cell><gi>incident</gi></cell>
      </row>
    </table>
    <p><gi>u</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>, and <gi>incident</gi> are encoding elements which are not
      specific to CMC but which are used to encode textual transcriptions of spoken turns, bodily
      activity, and onscreen activity that occur in CMC data. The unit post, which is specific to
      CMC, is introduced in <ptr target="#CMCcmcpost"/>.</p>
  </div>

  <div xml:id="CMCmacrometa">
    <head>Macrostructure and documentation of CMC (and providing general metadata)</head>

    <p>In many CMC genres, posts come in a CMC document in which they are grouped and according to
      which they are displayed e.g. in a sequence or in threads. For example, in chat communication
      such WhatsApp, posts are part of "a chat" of one user with another user or among a group of
      users. When a whole chat is downloaded and saved, a <emph>logfile</emph> of the chat is
      obtained. Similarly, Wikipedia discussions come in a <emph rend="italic">talk page</emph>,
      which ultimately is a web page containing the user posts, sub-structured in threads. Likewise,
      youtube comments come in a webpage containing the YouTube video with its comment posts and
      replying posts to these comments displayed below the video. The video serves as a <hi
        rend="italic">prompt</hi> for the whole discussion. In forum discussions, the prompt may be
      a news item, and in Wikipedia, an article may be viewed as the prompt for the discussion on
      the talk page associated with the article. </p>

    <!-- p>ToDo: Post as document</p-->

    <div xml:id="CMCmacro">
      <head>Macrostructure of CMC collections and documents</head>

      <p>When CMC documents are compiled in a collection, dataset, or corpus, we distinguish the
        following levels in the macrostructure of CMC in TEI:</p>

      <p><emph rend="bold">The corpus level</emph>: The level of a corpus or collection of CMC texts
        of a particular genre, generally obtained from a particular CMC platform, sometimes even
        from several platforms. This level may be represented by either a <gi>TEI</gi> element or a
          <gi>teiCorpus</gi> element.
        <!-- For simplicity in diffentiating information about the
           corpus level from the document level, this chapter
           discusses and exemplifies corpora as if they were encoded
           with <gi>teiCorpus</gi>. -->
        The <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus (i.e., the <gi>teiHeader</gi> that is a child of the
        outermost <gi>TEI</gi> or <gi>teiCorpus</gi>) will contain metadata in its
          <gi>sourceDesc</gi> about the CMC platform(s).
        Metadata about the project responsible for collecting the data and building the corpus, if
        applicable, should be recorded as well.</p>

      <p><emph rend="bold">The document level</emph>: A set of posts collected (or sampled) by a
        researcher for analysis. The posts of the document will often map directly to the set of
        posts grouped on an existing web page, thread, or document within a CMC environment. Within
        the CMC environment the document as such is often created by a particular user, thereby
        initiating the communication which other users may read, and to which some other users might
        contribute. This level will naturally be represented by the <gi>TEI</gi> element. The
          <gi>teiCorpus</gi> (or <gi>TEI</gi>) element that represents the corpus will contain one
        or more <gi>TEI</gi> elements as usual.</p>

      <p>In the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of a document level <gi>TEI</gi>, the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> will
        contain metadata about the CMC document such as its title, its author or owner, its URL, the
        date of its creation, the date of the last change made to it, and other metadata that are
        available and to be recorded such as one or more categories associated with the
        document.</p>

      <p>The document sometimes contains, or is associated with, a prompt such as a video or a news
        item, either provided by the initiating user herself or located elsewhere and referenced at
        the beginning of the document. In such cases, the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the document should
        also contain metadata about this prompt.</p>

      <p><emph rend="bold">The post level</emph>: The level of the individual post is naturally
        represented by the element <gi>post</gi> and its encoding it further described in section
          <ptr target="#CMCcmcpost"/>. A <gi>TEI</gi> element will contain a number of <gi>post</gi>
        elements, which can be grouped or ordered in <gi>div</gi> elements representing sequences or
        threads (section <ptr target="#CMCthreads"/>) if appropriate. </p>

      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="macrostructure" valid="feasible">
        <teiCorpus>
          <!-- a corpus, collection or dataset of CMC documents -->
          <teiHeader>
            <!-- metadata pertaining to the corpus or CMC dataset-->
          </teiHeader>
          <TEI>
            <!-- a CMC document such as a chat log or a discussion page -->
            <teiHeader>
              <!-- metadata pertaining to the CMC document -->
            </teiHeader>
            <text>
              <body>
                <div>
                  <!-- subdivisions of the CMC document e.g. in sections or threads if applicable-->
                  <post>
                    <!-- one post -->
                  </post>
                  <!-- more posts -->
                </div>
              </body>
            </text>
          </TEI>
          <!-- more documents -->
        </teiCorpus>
      </egXML>

    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMCthreads">
      <head>Threads, sections, sequences</head>
      <?tei winita?>
      <!-- Threads, Sections, or simply sequences -->
    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMCmetadata">
      <head>Documenting CMC (and providing general meta data)</head>

      <div xml:id="CMCCorpusSource">
        <!-- source Description of a teicorpus header -->
        <head>Documenting the source of a corpus of CMC data</head>

        <p>The <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus should contain metadata about the CMC platform(s),
          e.g. its name, information about its owner (often a company) including their address or
          location, the URL of the server where the CMC data were collected from, or the filename of
          a database dump that was used as a source. Metadata about the project responsible for
          collecting the data and building the corpus, if applicable, should be recorded as
          well.</p>

        <p>The following example shows the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of a Twitter corpus.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Twitter Sample Corpus</title>
              </titleStmt>
              <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Twitter International Company</distributor>
                <address>
                  <addrLine>1 Cumberland Place</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Fenian Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Dublin 2</addrLine>
                  <postCode>D02 AX07</postCode>
                  <country>Ireland</country>
                </address>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
        </p>
        <p>The following example shows how a Wikipedia database dump may be encoded as the
          source.
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
            <sourceDesc>
              <biblFull>
                <titleStmt>
                  <title>German Wikipedia Data Dump of 2019-08-01</title>
                </titleStmt>
                <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Dump file in XML (compressed)</edition>
                </editionStmt>
                <extent>
                  <measure unit="GiB" quantity="7.9"/>
                </extent>
                <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Wikimedia Foundation, Inc.</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>
                    <ptr target="https://dumps.wikimedia.org/"/>
                  </pubPlace>
                  <date when="2019-08-01">01 Aug 19</date>
                  <idno type="dump-filename">dewiki-2019-08-01-pages-meta-current</idno>
                </publicationStmt>
              </biblFull>
            </sourceDesc>
          </egXML>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div xml:id="CMCDocumentSource">
        <head>Documenting the source of a CMC document</head>

        <p>A CMC document may be chat log, a discussion page or thematical thread of posts and is
          encode within a <gi>TEI</gi> element. Among the metadata to be recorded in the
            <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of its <gi>teiHeader</gi> are, if available, its title, author or
          owner, its URL, the date of its creation and/or the date of its last change (i.e. the time
          when the last post was added to it). </p>

        <p>The following example is the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of a YouTube page that contained a video
          and user comments to the video (which are encoded in the <gi>body</gi> of the text as
          posts). The metadata contain a URL reference to the video and the YouTube channel that
          posted the video in <gi>relatedItem</gi> elements. The date when the page was created is
          not known. The video itself is not contained in the corpus.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
              <title type="main">Iron Man 3 in 3D (Official Trailer German) Parodie</title>
              <respStmt>
                <name type="user">DieAussenseiter</name>
                <resp>posted video, created page</resp>
              </respStmt>
              <distributor>YouTube</distributor>
              <ptr type="url" target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T-WU_3-0UpU"/>
              <series>
                <title>DieAussenseiter’s Channel</title>
                <ptr target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UCKn1vL4Ou4DKu0BlcK3NlDQ"/>
              </series>
            </bibl>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
        </p>

        <p>The following example is the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of a Wikipedia talk page. Note that the
          reference to the Wikipedia article that the discussion is about is given in the
            <gi>relatedItem</gi> element.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
              <title type="main">Diskussion:FKM-Richtlinie</title>
              <author><name type="user">OnkelSchuppig</name>, et al.</author>
              <publisher>Wikimedia Foundation, Inc.</publisher>
              <ptr target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diskussion:FKM-Richtlinie" type="page_url" targetLang="de"/>
              <date type="last-change" when="2013-09-14T17:04:48Z"/>
              <idno type="wikipedia-id">7632113</idno>
              <relatedItem type="articleLink">
                <ref n="5138958" target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/FKM-Richtlinie" targetLang="de">FKM-Richtlinie</ref>
              </relatedItem>
            </bibl>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
        </p>
      </div>

      <div xml:id="CMCSampling">
        <!-- sampling declaration -->
        <head>Documenting the sampling of CMC data</head>

        <p>The documentation of how the data were collected i.e. how it was downloaded, scraped or
          sampled from the web, should be recorded in the <gi>samplingDecl</gi>. It maybe part of
          the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus level, and/or of the document level. It has five
          potential components:</p>

        <list>
          <item>interface: The API that was used for the download</item>
          <item>client: The client or tool that was used for the download</item>
          <item>query: The query or command used for the download</item>
          <item>date: The date of the download</item>
          <item>respStmt: The person(s) or project responsible for the download</item>
        </list>

        <p>The information may be provided as prose in the <gi>samplingDecl</gi>. In the case of a
          twitter corpus it may look like the following:</p>

        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <samplingDecl>
            <p>Sampled using the Twitter "Filtered stream" v2-API (see
              https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/tweets/filtered-stream/api-reference/get-tweets-search-stream)
              Filtered for countries (DE, AT, BE, CH, DK, LU) and lang=de</p>
          </samplingDecl>
        </egXML>

        <p>The <gi>samplingDecl</gi> of a Usenet Newsgroup corpus:</p>

        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <samplingDecl>
            <p> Download from server news.individual.de 2016-01-15 using nntp client in Python</p>
          </samplingDecl>
        </egXML>


      </div>

      <div xml:id="CMCTimeline">
        <head>Timeline</head>
        <!-- Timeline -->
      </div>

      <div xml:id="CMCParticipants">
        <head>Participants</head>
        <!-- Participants -->
      </div>

      <?tei winita 
        Still an open issue. How to document the source (e.g. database dump, web scraping, query parameters) of the current CMC encodings
        * Source: made tag abuse for documenting the source: <biblStruct> or <recordingStmt>
        * Timeline: in textDesc/interaction/
        * Participant description (in profile description)
        ?>


    </div>
  </div>

  <div xml:id="CMCcmc">
    <head>Encoding Unique to CMC</head>
    <?tei winita
            * Some introductory sentence
            * specList (will automatically insert post including its attributes)
            * Cf. https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-specList.html 
        ?>
    <p>This chapter describes elements, attributes, and models which are unique to CMC and the TEI
      CMC module.</p>

    <div xml:id="CMCcmcpost">
      <head>CMC Posts</head>
      <p>The element <gi>post</gi> is unique to computer-mediated communication (CMC). <specList>
          <specDesc key="post"/>
        </specList> A post is defined as a written (or spoken) contribution to an ongoing CMC
        interaction which has been composed (or recorded) by its author in its entirety as part of a
        private activity, transmitted through the internet, and made available on the monitor or
        screen of the other parties en bloc. Posts occur in a broad range of written CMC genres,
        including (but not limited to) <q>messages</q> in chats and WhatsApp dialogues, tweets in
        Twitter timelines, comments on Facebook pages, posts in forum threads, and comments or
        contributions to discussions on Wikipedia talk pages or in the comments section of
        weblogs.</p>
      <p>Posts can be either written or spoken: <list>
          <item><emph rend="bold">written / multimodal posts</emph>: In the majority of CMC
            technologies posts are composed as stretches of text using an entry form on the screen
            and the keyboard or speech-to-text conversion software. In many cases the technology
            allows authors to include or embed graphics (emijos or images), video files, and
            hyperlinks into their posts.</item>
          <item><emph rend="bold">audio posts</emph>: A growing number of CMC technologies, e.g.
            messenger software such as WhatsApp or RocketChat, allow for an alternative, spoken
            production of posts providing a recording function which allows users to record a
            stretch of spoken language and transmit the resulting audio file to the other
            parties.</item>
        </list></p>
      <p>The element <gi>post</gi> may co-occur with <gi>u</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>,
        <gi>incident</gi>, or other existing TEI elements within a <gi>div</gi>, or directly within
        the <gi>body</gi>, and may contain headings, paragraphs, openers, closers, or
        salutations.</p>
      <p>As a member of the TEI attribute classes <ident type="class">att.ascribed</ident>, <ident
          type="class">att.canonical</ident>, <ident type="class">att.datable</ident>, <ident
          type="class">att.global</ident>, <ident type="class">att.timed</ident>, and <ident
          type="class">att.typed</ident>, posts may take a variety of attributes. Common attributes
        used in conjunction with <gi>post</gi> include <att>who</att>, <att>synch</att>,
          <att>type</att>, <att>subtype</att>, <att>rend</att>, and <att>xml:id</att>.</p>
    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMCcmcpostatts">
      <head>Attributes specific to CMC <gi>post</gi></head>
      <p>Three attributes pertain specifically to <gi>post</gi>: <specList>
          <specDesc key="post" atts="modality replyTo indentLevel"/>
        </specList> The <att>modality</att> attribute is recommended on the <gi>post</gi> element in
        order to describe the creation mechanism used in the CMC environment. The type of the
        content (i.e., whether the content of the post is written, an image, a video clip, etc.) is
        indicated by the child elements of the <gi>post</gi>. For example a written post from
        WhatsApp might include an audio-visual clip copied into the post, and in such case may not
        actually have any writing. Such a post is still considered to be in the <q>written</q>
        modality. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06" xml:id="cmcEG01m12">
            <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
              <desc>Screenshot von der Google-Suche nach dem Friseur <q>Haarraum</q> mit der
                Durchschnitts-Google-Bewertung (4,5 von 5 Sternen), der Adresse, der Telefonnummer
                und den Öffnungszeiten</desc>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute is used to capture information drawn from the original
        metadata associated with a post that asserts to which previous post the current post is a
        response, or to which previous post it refers. This metadata is included by many, but not
        all, CMC environments, when the user executes a formal reply action (e.g., by clicking or
        tapping a reply button). This attribute should not be used to encode interpreted or inferred
        reply relations based on linguistic cues or discourse markers.</p>
      <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute indicates the replied-to or referred-to posts by providing
        one or more pointers to them. In the following example, reply references in the source
        indicate that the first <gi>post</gi> is a reply to an initial post that is not part of the
        example, the second is a reply to the first, and the third is a reply to the second. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="cmc_ex_p28" who="#u7"
            replyTo="#cmc_ex_p1" when-iso="2015-07-29T21:44">
            <p>Es hat den Anschein, als wäre bei BER durchaus große Kompetenz am Bau, allerdings
              nicht in Form von Handwerkern….</p>
            <p>http://www.zeit.de/2015/29/imtech-flughafen-berlin-ber-verzoegerung/komplettansicht</p>
          </post>
          <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="cmc_ex_p29" who="#u8"
            replyTo="#cmc_ex_p28" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:11">
            <p>Nein Nein, an den Handwerkern kann es rein strukturel nicht gelegen haben. Niemand
              lässt seine Handwerker auf der Baustelle derart allein. Zudem gibt es höchstoffizielle
              “Abnahmen” von Bauabschnitten/phasen. Welcher Mangel auch bestanden hatte, er hätte
              Zeitnah auffallen müssen.</p>
            <p>Uuups, für Imtek hab ich mal in einer Nachunternehmerfirma gearbeitet. Imtek is
              offenbar ein universeler Bauträger, der alles baut.</p>
          </post>
          <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="cmc_ex_p30" who="#u8"
            replyTo="#cmc_ex_p29" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:26">
            <p>Stahlkunstruktionen dacht ich mal, was die bauen — oder bauen lassen.</p>
            <p>Das ist schon ein übles Ding. Die Ausschreibungenund Angebote sind unauffällig, aber
              wenn Unregelmässigkeiten auftreten (im Bauverlauf) dann gibt es die saftigen
              Rechnungen. Da steht dann der Bauherr da und fragt sich, wie er denn so schnell einen
              fähigen Ersatz herbekommt. Und diese Frage erübrigt sich meist, weil der Markt der
              Baufirmen das nicht hergibt — weil tendenziel 100 % Auslastung. (und noch schlimmer:
              Absprachen) Was auch Folge des Marktdrucks gewesen war.</p>
          </post>
        </egXML>
        <?tei winitia
          BIBL: should refer to the TEI encoding of a section of the blog page
          https://scilogs.spektrum.de/wild-dueck-blog/scheinzwerge-oder-viele-probleme-werden-groesser-wenn-man-sie-anpackt-griechenland/
        ?>
      </p>
      <p>In the CMC genre of Wiki talk, users insert their contribution to a discussion by modifying
        the wiki page of the discussion — the talk page. Since there is no technical reply action
        available in wiki software, users apply textual indentation in the wiki code to indicate a
        reply to a previous message, and a threaded structure is formed by a series of such
        indentations. The attribute <att>indentLevel</att> records the level of indentation, that is
        the nesting depth of the current post in such a thread-like structure (as defined by its
        author and in relation to the standard level of non-indentation which should be encoded with
        an <att>indentLevel</att> of <val>0</val>). It is used in wiki talk corpora but may also be
        used for other threaded genres e.g. when HTML was used as a source. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <div type="thread" xml:id="i.10031_19">
            <head>[[WP:AUTO]]</head>
            <post indentLevel="0" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-07T03:09+00"
              who="#WU00010808" xml:id="i.10031_19_1">
              <p> I would kindly request from Mr. Meyer to allow others to edit the [...]</p>
            </post>
            <post indentLevel="1" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T03:49+00"
              who="#WU00010804" xml:id="i.10031_19_2">
              <p>I dont agree, this article is not about Dr. Meyer, [...]</p>
            </post>
            <post indentLevel="2" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T04:16+00"
              who="#WU00005520" xml:id="i.10031_19_3">
              <p>Why don't you read the policy. [...]</p>
            </post>
            <post indentLevel="3" modality="written" when-iso="2006-11-01T22:58+00"
              who="#WU00010815" xml:id="i.10031_19_4">
              <p>Because the policy makes no sense, [...]</p>
            </post>
          </div>
        </egXML> Example: File 10031.tei.xml from the EFG Wikipedia corpus 2019. Exchange between
        <?tei winita What are to do with this? —Syd, 2022-08-11 ?> four different users. (Page
        Talk:Eiffel (programming language) from the English Wikipedia) </p>
    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMCcmcatts">
      <head>Attributes for General CMC Encoding</head>
      <p>The attribute <att>generatedBy</att> is also unique to CMC encoding. But unlike
          <att>modality</att>, <att>replyTo</att>, and <att>indentLevel</att>, it is available not
        only on the <gi>post</gi> element, but also on all its possible children as well. <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.cmc" atts="generatedBy"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p><att>generatedBy</att> may indicate, for <gi>post</gi> or any of its children, how its
        content was generated in a CMC environment; i.e. whether it was created by a human user,
        generated by the respective CMC system (e.g. a status message, a timestamp), or the user
        activated a template that subsequently generated the textual content, such as in a
        signature. The attribute is optional, and it might not be appropriate to use it when all
        text content has been created in the same mode and no distinction needs to be made.
        <!-- Is the above sentence necessary? Does it mean that @generatedBy is inherited? —Syd, 2022-08-11 -->
        A list of suggested values for <att>generatedBy</att> follows: <list type="gloss">
          <label>human</label>
          <item>when then content of the respective element was <q>naturally</q> typed or spoken by
            a human user (cf. the chat posts in Example <ptr target="#ex.haarschnitt"/>)</item>
          <label>template</label>
          <item>when the content of the respective element was generated after a human user
            activated a template for its insertion (cf. <gi>signed</gi> e.g., the signatures in wiki
            talk in Listing 2)</item>
          <!-- What is “Listing 2”? —Syd, 2022-08-11 -->
          <label>system</label>
          <item>when the content of the respective element was generated by the system, i.e. the CMC
            environment (cf. the system message in an IRC chat in Listing 6)</item>
          <!-- ditto -->
          <label>bot</label>
          <item>when the content of the respective element was generated by a bot i.e. a non-human
            agent, mostly external to the CMC environment</item>
          <label>unspecified</label>
          <item>when it is unspecified or unknown how the content of the respective element was
            generated (cf. the <gi>post</gi> of the retweet cmc_ex_p2 in Listing 5)</item>
          <!-- ditto -->
        </list>
      </p>

      <p>An example of an emoji in a chat post marked as generated by template:</p>

      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.haarschnitt">
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t003" who="#A02" xml:id="m8"> Da kostet
          ein Haarschnitt 50 € <figure type="emoji" generatedBy="template">
            <desc type="label">face screaming in fear</desc>
            <desc type="unicode">U+1F631</desc>
          </figure>
        </post>
      </egXML>

      <p>In the following example, the user signature of a wiki talk post was inserted by activating
        a template and marked accordingly:</p>

      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.naturally">
        <post modality="written" xml:id="cmc_ex_p2" indentLevel="0" who="#u005" synch="#t005">
          <p>I'm not sure that this is a proper criterium, or even what this means. What if we set
            an explosion that breaks a comet into two pieces? What if we build a moon? Cheers,
            </p><signed generatedBy="template" rend="inline"><ref target="/wiki/User:Greenodd"
              >Greenodd</ref> (<ref target="/wiki/User_talk:Greenodd">talk</ref>) <time>01:00, 21
              July 2011 (UTC)</time></signed>
        </post>
      </egXML>

      <p> A tweet is specified for having been written by a human, however inside the tweet, the
        timestamp is marked as generated by the system:</p>

      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.grunzen" xml:lang="de">
        <post modality="written" key="1043764753502486528" type="tweet" generatedBy="human"
          synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t001" xml:id="cmc_ex_p1" who="#u1" xml:lang="deu">
          <time generatedBy="system"> 12:31 </time> Heute mit super Unterstützung, wir grunzen, wenn
          die Zeit vorbei ist. <ref type="hashtag"
            target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash">#bcrn18</ref>
          <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wikidach?src=hash">#wikidach</ref>
          PS: Die beiden brauchen noch Namen. Hinweise dazu am Empfang abgeben! <ref
            type="twitter-account" target="https://twitter.com/AndreLo79">@AndreLo79</ref>
          <figure type="image">
            <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DnwygdSW4AAoTUn.jpg:large"/>
          </figure>
        </post>
      </egXML>

      <p>Finally, in the following example of an IRC post, the status message that user "Interseb
        has entered the room" was generated by the system, i.e. the chat environment. SYSTEM is also
        listed among: </p>

      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.listPerson" xml:lang="de">
        <post type="event" generatedBy="system" who="#SYSTEM" rend="color:navy">
          <p>
            <name type="nickname" corresp="#A07">Interseb</name> betritt den Raum.</p>
        </post>
      </egXML>

    </div>
  </div>

  <div xml:id="CMCrecs">
    <head>Recommendations for encoding CMC</head>
    <?tei winita
      Discussion of phenomena — short discussions, maybe with some code snippets, and references
      to the other chapters where the TEI encoding is introduced; ?>
    <div xml:id="CMCemos">
      <head>Emojis and Emoticons</head>
      <?tei winita add source for example in TEI <example> with ref to bibl element ?>
      <p>Emojis are iconic or symbolic, invariant graphic units which the users of social media
        applications such as WhatsApp, Instagram, and Twitter can select from a menu or ‘emoji
        keyboard’ and embed into their written posts. Examples are &#x1F601;, &#x1F637;, &#x01F308;,
        &#x1F631;, and &#x1F648;. An emoji is encoded by one or more Unicode characters which are
        intended to be mapped directly to a pictorial symbol.</p>
      <p>Emoticons predate emojis and are created as combinations of ASCII punctuation and other
        characters using the keyboard. Examples are <code>:-)</code>, <code>;-)</code>,
          <code>:-(</code>, <code>:-x</code>, <code>\O/</code>, and <code>Oo</code>. They first
        occured on a Usenet newsgroup (cf. <ref target="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/~sef/Orig-Smiley.htm "
          >original newsgroup post by Scott Fahlman of 19-Sep-82</ref>) and then became frequent in
        chat communications during the mid-1980s. An emoticon typically consists of several Unicode
        characters (from the ASCII subset) in a row, each of which has an intended use other than as
        part of an emoticon.</p>
      <p>Both emoticons and emojis may be simply transcribed as a sequence of characters. As with
        any other characters, they may be entered as numeric character entities if this is more
        convenient. (E.g., <mentioned>&#x2764;;</mentioned> might be transcribed as
          <code>&amp;#x2764;</code> in any XML document, including a TEI document; see <ptr
          target="#D4-44"/>.)</p>
      <p>When the text of a post is being tokenized, e.g. for linguistic analysis, it may be useful
        to encode the emoticon or emoji as a separate token. In such cases elements such as
          <gi>w</gi> or <gi>c</gi> may be used for tokenization, and the <att>pos</att> attribute
        may be used to indicate that the encoded string is an emoji or an emoticon. (See <ptr
          target="#AILC"/>.)</p>
      <p>For example, the source post <q>da bin ich nicht so empfindlich ;)</q> (engl. 'I am not so
        touchy with that ;) ') ends with an emoticon, and might be encoded as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <post>
            <w pos="ADV">da</w>
            <w pos="VAFIN">bin</w>
            <w pos="PPER">ich</w>
            <w pos="PTKNEG">nicht</w>
            <w pos="ADV">so</w>
            <w pos="ADJD">empfindlich</w>
            <w pos="EMOASC">;)</w>
          </post>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>Similarly, the source post <q>Klar &#x01F601;</q> (engl. 'Sure &#x01F601;') might be
        encoded as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03"
            xml:id="lscLB.m6a">
            <w pos="ADV">Klar</w>
            <w pos="EMOIMG">&#x01F601;</w>
          </post>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>The values of <att>pos</att> in the above examples are from the STTS_IBK Tagset for German
        (see <ptr type="cit" target="#STTS_IBK"/>), which includes tags for CMC-specific elements
        such as <val>EMOASC</val> for an ASCII-based emoticon and <val>EMOIMG</val> for an
        icon-based emoji.</p>
      <p>Alternatively, e.g. when <gi>w</gi> is not regularly used to encode tokens in the TEI
        document, <gi>c</gi> may be used to mark an emoji. For example, the source post <q>Da kostet
          ein Haarschnitt 50 € &#x01F631;</q> (engl. 'A haircut there costs 50 € &#x01F631;' ) might
        be encoded as follows:</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <post xml:lang="de"> Da kostet ein Haarschnitt 50 € <c type="emoji" ana="#fsif"
            generatedBy="template">&#x01F631;</c>
        </post>
      </egXML>
      <p>Sometimes, e.g. when the source of the TEI document was a web page in HTML, the emojis may
        occur only as an icon graphic in the source. In such a case, they may be encoded using
          <gi>figure</gi>. The corresponding unicode character can then be recorded in the
          <gi>desc</gi> element by the encoder if desired.</p>
      <p>For example, the source text: <q>... ich überlege noch &#x1F648;</q> (engl. '... I'm still
        thinking &#x1F648;' ) might be encoded as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03"
            xml:id="lscLB.m6b"> ... ich überlege noch <figure type="emoji" generatedBy="template">
              <graphic url="fig1.png"/>
              <desc type="gloss">see no evil monkey</desc>
              <desc type="unicode">U+1F648</desc>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML></p>
    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMCgraphic">
      <head>Posts with Graphics</head>
      <p>A post in a CMC interaction may contain a graphic in addition to some text or even contain
        only a graphic (without any text). As explained in <ptr target="#CMCcmcpostatts"/>, the
        modality of such a post should be considered as <val>written</val>. To encode the graphic
        information, the TEI element <gi>figure</gi> may be used in the appropriate place.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#UND">
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06" xml:id="cmcEG08m12">
          <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
            <desc>Screenshot von der Google-Suche nach dem Friseur "Haarraum" mit der
              Durchschnitts-Google-Bewertung (4,5 von 5 Sternen), der Adresse, der Telefonnummer und
              den Öffnungszeiten</desc>
          </figure>
        </post>
      </egXML>
      <p>The preceding example represents an encoding of a private chat post that contained only a
        screenshot of a google search result for a hairdresser. A link to the graphic file itself is
        not included because it has not been retained for the
        <!-- This sentence needs a bit of re-wording, but I do not
           actually know when the graphic was not retained, so need to
           ask, first. —Syd, 2022-08-12 -->
        corpus.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <post type="tweet" key="1043823300479258624" modality="written" generatedBy="human"
          synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t006" xml:id="cmc_ex_p8" who="#u1" xml:lang="de">
          <time generatedBy="system"> 16:24 </time> Bro Tri-Engel...so hab ich mir das
          vorgestellt!!! @AndreLo79 #bcrn18 #wikidach @Heiko komm' mal Twitter! #Engel <figure
            type="image" generatedBy="human">
            <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DnxnwN9XsAEHXw2.jpg:large"/>
          </figure>
        </post>
      </egXML>
      <p>The preceding example represents an encoding of a tweet that contains some text (including
        hashtags and mentions) and a graphic. The <gi>graphic</gi> element retains the URL of the
        graphic on the web just as in the source.</p>
    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMCcirculation">
      <head>Circulation</head>
      <!-- ToDo: Check twi21 corpus -->
      <?tei winita Need an intro paragraph here to explain what
        “Circulation” means —Syd, 2022-08-12 ?>
      <p>The following recommendations on how to encode features of the circulation of posts, such
        as IDs, re-posts (retweets), hashtags, and mentions use twitter posts (tweets) as an
        example; this phenomenon is not in any way unique to Twitter, however.</p>
      <p>First, we encode the type of post (in this case, a tweet) in the <att>type</att> attribute,
        and if it is a specific subtype of tweet, such as a retweet, that will be encoded in the
          <att>subtype</att> attribute on the <gi>post</gi> element accordingly.</p>
      <p>Second, we distinguish between the ID that the post gets as part of the text collection
        (e.g. a corpus or a dataset), and the original Tweet-ID as supplied by Twitter. The
        collection-related post ID should go on the global attribute <att>xml:id</att>, while the
        original tweet ID should go on the canonical attribute <att>key</att>.</p>
      <p>Third, a retweet and its corresponding retweeted tweet are encoded as two separate posts
        each with its own set of attributes. The post representing the retweet itself is specified
        with <code>subtype="retweet"</code> and does not contain or duplicate the content of the
        retweeted tweet. Instead it refers to the ID of the retweeted tweet via the pointing
        attribute <att>ref</att>. All original content of the retweet goes in the content of the
          <gi>post</gi> element. In the example
        <!-- ptr target="#ex.tweets"/  This pointer to the example below does not look good in the HTML, Harald 2022-09-01 -->,
        the retweeted tweet happens to be a retweet itself.</p>
      <p>Fourth, hashtags occur on the in the body of tweets and are links like any other hyperlink
        and should be encoded using the element <gi>ref</gi>. The <att>type</att> attribute of the
        ref should contain the value <val>hashtag</val>, the <att>target</att> attribute should
        contain the URL of the hashtag, and the content of <gi>ref</gi>should be the string of the
        hashtag itself.</p>

      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.tweets">
        <post modality="written" key="1043796550101716993" generatedBy="human" type="tweet"
          subtype="retweet" who="#u1" xml:id="cmc_ex_p4" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t004" ref="#cmc_ex_p5"
          xml:lang="de"> Ich mich auch? <ref type="hashtag"
            target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dynamicduo?src=hash">#dynamicduo</ref>
          <ref type="hashtag"
            target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wirk%C3%BCmmernunsauchumIhrenEmpfang?src=hash"
            >#wirkümmernunsauchumIhrenEmpfang</ref>
          <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash">#bcrn18</ref>
          <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wikidach?src=hash">#wikidach</ref>
        </post>
        <post modality="written" key="1043796093786566656" generatedBy="human" type="tweet"
          subtype="retweet" who="#u2" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t003" xml:lang="de" xml:id="cmc_ex_p5">
          <time generatedBy="system"> 14:35 </time> Immer wieder gerne. Kann ich mich schon für
          nächstes Jahr als Empfangs- <ref type="hashtag"
            target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Engel?src=hash">#Engel</ref> für das nächste BarCamp
          bewerben <w pos="EMO">&#x1F92A;</w>
          <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash">#bcrn18</ref>
          <trailer>
            <!-- CoMeRe Style encoding of the counts of favouriting and likes: -->
            <fs>
              <f name="favoritecount">
                <numeric value="4"/>
              </f>
            </fs>
          </trailer>
        </post>
      </egXML>
      <!-- Is the “CoMeRe Style encoding of the counts of favouriting
           and likes:” intended to be part of the example (i.e., to
           show up in the output)?
           Either way, we should probably also exemplify other methods
           of encoding such information, no? E.g.:
           <measure unit="count" commodity="favorites" quantity="4"/>
      -->
    </div>
  </div>

  <div xml:id="CMChow">
    <head>Putting it all Together — Genre Specific Examples</head>
    <?tei winita
        * Twitter
        * WhatsApp
        * Wikipedia talk
        * NB: not necessarily add complete examples (whole TEI file) but rather snippets
      ?>
  </div>

  <div xml:id="CMCmodule">
    <head>The TEI CMC Module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components: <moduleSpec
        ident="cmc">
        <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2021-09-07">Computer-mediated communication</desc>
        <idno type="FPI">TEI-CMC</idno>
      </moduleSpec> The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
        <ptr target="#STIN"/>.</p>
    <specGrp xml:id="CMCincludes">
      <!-- att.cmc.xml and model.cmc.xml are included from ST -->
      <xi:include href="../../Specs/macro.specialPara.cmc.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="../../Specs/post.xml"/>
    </specGrp>
  </div>
</div>
