<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
-->
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="div1"
    xml:id="CMC" n="9">
    <head>Computer-mediated Communication</head>
    <div type="div2" xml:id="CMC1">
        <head>General Considerations and Overview</head>
        <p>This chapter describes the TEI encoding mechanisms available for genres of
            computer-mediated communication (CMC) and thus social media. It is intended to provide
            the basic framework needed to encode CMC corpora.</p>
        <p>While the term “computer-mediated communication” might be used to describe all sorts of
            communications between humans in the modern age (for example, internet video meetings or
            cellular telephony), herein we use the term to apply to the more traditional forms of
            computer-mediated asynchronous communication like text messages, instant messaging,
            email, chat rooms, online forums, social network services.</p>
        <p>The salient feature of these CMC mediums is that a communicative act is generated,
            typically at the author’s leisure, in the private space of the author, and then
            transmitted en bloc to the recipient(s). Even though in some CMC genres (e.g.,
            WhatsApp), the other parties are informed by an automated alert about the fact that
            another party is currently composing a new post, they cannot track the process of
            verbalization, i.e. how the written utterance emerges in the entry form on the user
            interface of its author. It is not until the author performs a ‘posting’ action (for
            example, by hitting the ‘enter’ key or by activating a ‘send’ button with the mouse)
            that the result of the composition process — the post — is made available for the other
            parties. From the perspective of its addressees or readers, a post is a stretch of text
            that has been composed in advance. Different from spoken utterances but similar to
            edited text, (1) the reader of a post does not have access to the verbalization process
            and (2) the mental processing of a post is not possible until the process of
            verbalization (the composition) has been finished and the posting action has been
            performed by the author. Posts occur in a broad range of written CMC genres, including
            (but not limited to): as user ‘messages’ in chats and WhatsApp dialogues, as SMS
            messages, as tweets in Twitter timelines, as individual comments following a status
            update on Facebook pages, as posts in forum threads, as contributions on Wikipedia talk
            pages, and in the comments section of a weblog.</p>

    </div>
    <div>
        <head>The TEI CMC Module</head>
        <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:
                <moduleSpec ident="cmc">
                <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2021-09-07">Elements, Attributes, and Models for
                    Computer-mediated communication (CMC). This module collects all cmc-specific
                    extensions. Hence these will only be added to a TEI schema when this module is
                    selected in a customisation.</desc>
                <altIdent>TEI-CMC</altIdent>
                <altIdent xml:lang="en">Computer-Mediated Communication</altIdent>
            </moduleSpec>
            The selection and combination of
            modules to form a TEI schema is described in <ptr target="#STIN"/>.</p>
    </div>
    <div>
        <specGrp xml:id="CMCincludes">
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.cmc.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../Specs/macro.specialPara.cmc.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.cmc.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" href="../../Specs/post.xml"/>
        </specGrp>
    </div>
</div>
