<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
-->
<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="div1" xml:id="CMC" xml:lang="en">
  <head>Computer-mediated Communication</head>
  <p>This chapter describes the TEI encoding mechanisms available for textual data that represents
    discourse from genres of computer-mediated communication (CMC). It is intended to provide the
    basic framework needed to encode CMC corpora.</p>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="CMCintro">
    <head>General Considerations</head>
    <p>While the term <term>computer-mediated communication</term> might be used broadly to
      describe all kinds of communications that are mediated by digital technologies
      (such as text on web pages, written exchanges in chats and forums, interactions with artificial intelligence systems, the spoken
      conversations in internet video meetings), for the purposes of these Guidelines we use the term to apply to forms of
      communication that share the following features: <list rend="bulleted">
        <item>they are dialogic;</item>
        <item>they are organized as interactional sequences so that each communicative
          move may determine the context for subsequent moves (typically taken by another
          interlocutor) and may react to the context created by a prior move;</item>
        <item>they are created and displayed using computer
            technology or human-machine interfaces such as keyboard, mouse, speech-to-text conversion software, monitor or
          screen and transmitted over a computer network (typically the
          internet).</item>
      </list>
      Such communications may be expressed as posts (cf. <ptr
        target="#CMCcmcpost"/>), utterances, onscreen activities, or bodily activities exerted
      by a virtual avatar. 
    </p>
    <p>The following kinds of platforms support CMC: <list rend="simple">
        <item>chats, messengers, or online forums;</item>
        <item>social media platforms and applications;</item>
        <item>the communication functions of collaborative platforms and projects (e.g. an online
          learning environment, or a <soCalled>talk</soCalled> page);</item>
        <item>3D virtual world environments;</item>
        <item>other interactive services supported by the internet.</item>
      </list></p>
    <p>CMC supports multimodal expression combining text, images, sound. Whereas early CMC systems
      (e.g. Internet Relay Chat, <soCalled>IRC</soCalled> for short, the Usenet
      <soCalled>newsgroups</soCalled>, or even the Unix <name>talk</name> system)
      were completely ASCII-based, most CMC applications now permit combining media formats (e.g. written or spoken
      language with graphic icons and images) and mixing communication technologies on one platform (e.g. combined use of an audio connection, a chat system, and a
      3D interface in which users control a virtual avatar as in many multiplayer online computer
      games or in virtual worlds).</p>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="CMCUnits">
    <head>Basic Units of CMC</head>
    <p>This section describes the encoding mechanisms for the basic units of CMC and for their
      combined use to encode CMC data.</p>
    <p>We use the term <term>basic CMC unit</term> to refer to a communication produced by an interlocutor to initiate or contribute to an ongoing
      CMC interaction or joint CMC activity. Contributions
      to an ongoing interaction are produced to perform a move to develop
      the interactional sequence, for instance to respond in chats or forum discussions. Contributions to joint
      CMC activities may not all be directly interactional; some may be part of a collaborative
      project of the involved individuals. Such collaboration could involve editing activities in a shared text editor
      or whiteboard in parallel with an ongoing CMC interaction (chat, audio conversation, or
      audio-video conference) in the same CMC environment in which these editing activities are
      discussed by the participants.</p>
    <p>Basic units of CMC can be described according to three criteria: 
      <list rend="numbered">
        <item>the temporal properties
          of when these contributions are produced by their creators, transmitted via CMC systems, and
          made accessible for the recipients;</item>
        <item>the modality of the unit as a whole, whether verbal or nonverbal;</item>
        <item>for verbal units: whether the unit is expressed in the written or
          spoken mode.</item>
      </list>
    A taxonomy of basic CMC units resulting from these criteria is given in the following figure.
    </p>
    <figure xml:id="cmcunits-taxonomy">
      <graphic url="Images/cmcunits-taxonomy.png"/>
      <head>Taxonomy of basic CMC units according to <ptr type="cit" target="#BIB_CMC_Core"/></head>
    </figure>
    <p>The most important distinction in the <ref
    target="#cmcunits-taxonomy">CMC taxonomy</ref>
      concerns the temporal nature of units exchanged via CMC technologies. The left part of the
      taxonomy describes units that are performed (by a producer) and perceived (by a recipient) as
      a continuous stream of behaviour. Units of this type can be performed as</p>
    <list type="gloss">
      <label rend="bold">spoken utterances,</label>
      <item>i.e. stretches of speech which are produced to perform a speaker turn in a
        conversation,</item>
      <label rend="bold">bodily activity,</label>
      <item>i.e. nonverbal behaviour (gesture, gaze) produced to perform a speaker turn, either
        performed by the real body of an interlocutor (e.g. in a video conference) or through the
        virtual avatar of an interlocutor in a 3D environment,</item>
      <label rend="bold">onscreen activities,</label>
      <item>i.e. non-bodily expressions that are transmitted to the group of interacting or
        coworking participants, for instance the editing of content in a shared text editor which
        can be perceived by the other parties simultaneously (as may be the case in learning or
        collaboration environments).</item>
    </list>
    <p>The right part of <ref target="#cmcunits-taxonomy">the CMC taxonomy</ref> describes units in
      which the production, transmission, and perception of contributions to CMC interactions are
      organized in a strictly consecutive order: The content—verbal, nonverbal, or multimodal—of
      the contribution has to be produced before it can be transmitted through a network and made
      available on the computer monitor or mobile screen of any other party as a preserved and
      persistent unit. We term this type of unit a <term>post</term>. Posts occur in
      two different variants: <list rend="bulleted">
        <item>as <emph rend="bold">written or multimodal posts,</emph> which are produced with an
          editor form that is designed for the composition of stretches of written text. Most
          contemporary post-based CMC technologies provide features for the inclusion of graphic and
          audio-visual content (emoji graphics, images, videos) into posts and even to produce posts
          without verbal content (which then may consist only of emojis, an image, or a video file).
          Written and multimodal posts are the standard formats for user contributions in primarily
          text-based CMC genres and applications such as chat, SMS, WhatsApp, Instagram, Facebook, X
          (Twitter), online forums, or Wikipedia talk pages.</item>
        <item>as <emph rend="bold">audio posts</emph>, which are produced using a recording
          function. In contrast to CMC units of the type <term>utterance</term> which
          are produced and transmitted simultaneously, audio posts first have to be recorded as a
          whole and are then transmitted, as audio files, via the internet; the availability of
          the recording is indicated in the screen protocol by a template-generated, visual post;
          the recipients can play the recording (repeatedly) by activating the play button displayed
          in the post on the screen. Examples of CMC applications that implement audio posts are
          WhatsApp or RocketChat.</item>
      </list></p>
    <p>Three of the four basic CMC units described above can be represented with models that are
      described elsewhere in the TEI Guidelines:</p>
    <table>
      <row rend="underline">
        <cell>CMC unit</cell>
        <cell>Type of corpus data</cell>
        <cell>TEI P5 element</cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell>spoken utterance</cell>
        <cell>transcription of speech</cell>
        <cell>
          <gi>u</gi>
        </cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell>bodily activity</cell>
        <cell>textual description</cell>
        <cell>
          <gi>kinesic</gi>
        </cell>
      </row>
      <row>
        <cell>onscreen activity</cell>
        <cell>textual description</cell>
        <cell>
          <gi>incident</gi>
        </cell>
      </row>
    </table>
    <p>The <gi>u</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>, and <gi>incident</gi> elements are not limited to CMC, but
      apply to encode textual transcriptions of spoken turns and CMC data about bodily activity and
      onscreen activity. The CMC unit <term>post</term>, which is specific to
      CMC, is introduced in <ptr target="#CMCcmcpost"/>.</p>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="CMCcmc">
    <head>Encoding Unique to CMC</head>
    <p>This section describes elements, attributes, and models which are unique to CMC and the TEI
      CMC module.</p>
    <div xml:id="CMCcmcpost">
      <head>CMC Posts</head>
      <p>While the concept of a <term>post</term> is not unique to
      computer-mediated communication (ask anyone who has posted a
      <q>lost cat</q> sign in the local market), this chapter concerns
      itself only with postings within a framework of a CMC system.
      Thus the element <gi>post</gi> is unique to the encoding of
      computer-mediated communication (CMC).
      <specList>
        <specDesc key="post"/>
      </specList> Posts occur in a broad range of written CMC genres,
        including (but not limited to) messages in chats and WhatsApp dialogues, tweets in X
        (Twitter) timelines, comments on Facebook pages, posts in forum threads, and comments or
        contributions to discussions on Wikipedia talk pages or in the comment sections of
        weblogs.</p>
      <p>Posts can be either written or spoken: <list>
          <item><emph rend="bold">written</emph> or <emph rend="bold">multimodal posts</emph>: In
            the majority of CMC technologies posts are composed as stretches of text using a
            keyboard or speech-to-text conversion software in an entry form on the screen. In
            many cases the technology allows authors to include or embed graphics (emojis or
            images), video files, and hyperlinks into their posts.</item>
          <item><emph rend="bold">spoken (audio posts)</emph>: A growing number of CMC technologies, e.g.
            messenger software such as WhatsApp or RocketChat, allow for an alternative, spoken
            production of posts by providing a recording function which allows users to record a
            stretch of spoken language and transmit the resulting audio file to the other
            parties.</item>
        </list></p>
      <p>The element <gi>post</gi> may co-occur with <gi>u</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>,
        <gi>incident</gi>, or other existing TEI elements within a <gi>div</gi>, or directly within
        the <gi>body</gi>, and may contain headings, paragraphs, openers, closers, or
        salutations.</p>
      <p>The <gi>post</gi> element is a member of several TEI attribute classes, including <ident type="class"
          >att.ascribed</ident>, <ident type="class">att.canonical</ident>, <ident type="class"
          >att.datable</ident>, <ident type="class">att.global</ident>, <ident type="class"
          >att.timed</ident>, and <ident type="class">att.typed</ident>, and as such may take a
        variety of attributes. <!-- 2024-07-01 jt and ebb find this sentence a bit too prescriptive and unnecessary: 
          Common attributes used in conjunction with <gi>post</gi> include
          <att>who</att>, <att>synch</att>, <att>type</att>, <att>subtype</att>, <att>rend</att>,
        and <att>xml:id</att>.--></p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCcmcpostatts">
      <head>Attributes Specific to CMC <gi>post</gi></head>
      <p>Three attributes pertain specifically to <gi>post</gi>:
        <specList>
          <specDesc key="post" atts="modality replyTo"/>
          <specDesc key="att.indentation" atts="indentLevel"/>
        </specList>
        The type of the content of a post (i.e., whether the content is text, an
        image, a video clip, etc.) is indicated by the child elements of the <gi>post</gi>. (E.g., a
        <gi>post</gi> might have a child <gi>p</gi>, or a child <gi>figure</gi> with a
        <gi>graphic</gi>, or a child <gi>figure</gi> with a <gi>media</gi>, or some combination
        thereof.) How that content was created—whether it was recorded speech or not—may be described with the <att>modality</att> attribute. Because spoken language differs
        significantly from written language, the suggested values only separate the <val>spoken</val> modality from the <val>written</val>
        modality, which covers all cases other than spoken natural language. The use of <att>modality</att> is recommended but not required.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06" xml:id="cmc_post09">
            <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
              <desc xml:lang="en">screenshot of the google search for hairdresser "Pasha's Haare'm"
                with the average google rating (4,5 of 5 stars), the address, the phone number, and
                the opening hours.</desc>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute is used to capture information drawn from the original
        metadata associated with a post that asserts to which previous post the current post is a
        response, or to which previous post it refers. This metadata is included by many, but not
        all, CMC environments, when the user executes a formal reply action (e.g., by clicking or
        tapping a reply button). This attribute should not be used to encode interpreted or inferred
        reply relations based on linguistic cues or discourse markers.</p>
      <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute indicates the replied-to or referred-to posts by providing
        one or more pointers to them. In the following example, reply references in the source
        indicate that the first <gi>post</gi> is a reply to an initial post that is not part of the
        example, the second is a reply to the first, and the third is a reply to the second.
        <egXML xml:id="e9" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de" source="#BIB_scilog1">
          <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="cmc_post10" who="#u7"
            replyTo="#cmc_post09" when-iso="2015-07-29T21:44">
            <p>Es hat den Anschein, als wäre bei BER durchaus große Kompetenz am Bau, allerdings
              nicht in Form von Handwerkern….</p>
            <p>http://www.zeit.de/2015/29/imtech-flughafen-berlin-ber-verzoegerung/komplettansicht</p>
          </post>
          <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="cmc_post11" who="#u8"
            replyTo="#cmc_post10" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:11">
            <p>Nein Nein, an den Handwerkern kann es rein strukturel nicht gelegen haben. Niemand
              lässt seine Handwerker auf der Baustelle derart allein. Zudem gibt es höchstoffizielle
              “Abnahmen” von Bauabschnitten/phasen. Welcher Mangel auch bestanden hatte, er hätte
              Zeitnah auffallen müssen.</p>
            <p>Uuups, für Imtek hab ich mal in einer Nachunternehmerfirma gearbeitet. Imtek is
              offenbar ein universeler Bauträger, der alles baut.</p>
          </post>
          <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="cmc_post12" who="#u8"
            replyTo="#cmc_post11" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:26">
            <p>Stahlkunstruktionen dacht ich mal, was die bauen—oder bauen lassen.</p>
            <p>Das ist schon ein übles Ding. Die Ausschreibungenund Angebote sind unauffällig, aber
              wenn Unregelmässigkeiten auftreten (im Bauverlauf) dann gibt es die saftigen
              Rechnungen. Da steht dann der Bauherr da und fragt sich, wie er denn so schnell einen
              fähigen Ersatz herbekommt. Und diese Frage erübrigt sich meist, weil der Markt der
              Baufirmen das nicht hergibt — weil tendenziel 100 % Auslastung. (und noch schlimmer:
              Absprachen) Was auch Folge des Marktdrucks gewesen war.</p>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>In the CMC genre of wiki talk, users insert their contribution to a discussion by modifying
        the wiki page of the discussion—the talk page. Since there is no technical reply action
        available in wiki software, users apply textual indentation in the wiki code to indicate a
        reply to a previous message, and a threaded structure is formed by a series of such
        indentations. The attribute <att>indentLevel</att> records the level of indentation, that is
        the nesting depth of the current post in such a thread-like structure (as defined by its
        author and in relation to the standard level of non-indentation which should be encoded with
        an <att>indentLevel</att> of <val>0</val>). It is used in wiki talk corpora but may also be
        used for other threaded genres, for example when HTML is used as a source.</p>
      <p>The following is a sample encoding of a portion of a discussion among four different users
        on a Wikipedia talk page.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#BIB_WPTalkEiffel" xml:lang="en">
          <div type="thread" xml:id="i.10031_19">
            <head>[[WP:AUTO]]</head>
            <post indentLevel="0" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-07T03:09+00"
              who="#WU00010808" xml:id="cmc_post13">
              <p> I would kindly request from Mr. Meyer to allow others to edit the [...]</p>
            </post>
            <post indentLevel="1" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T03:49+00"
              who="#WU00010804" xml:id="cmc_post14">
              <p>I dont agree, this article is not about Dr. Meyer, [...]</p>
            </post>
            <post indentLevel="2" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T04:16+00"
              who="#WU00005520" xml:id="cmc_post15">
              <p>Why don't you read the policy. [...]</p>
            </post>
            <post indentLevel="3" modality="written" when-iso="2006-11-01T22:58+00"
              who="#WU00010815" xml:id="cmc_post16">
              <p>Because the policy makes no sense, [...]</p>
            </post>
          </div>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCcmcatts">
      <head>Attributes for General CMC Encoding</head>
      <p>The attribute <att>generatedBy</att> is also unique to CMC encoding. But unlike
          <att>modality</att>, <att>replyTo</att>, and <att>indentLevel</att>, <att>generatedBy</att> is available not
        only on the <gi>post</gi> element, but on any of its descendants as well. <specList>
          <specDesc key="att.cmc" atts="generatedBy"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The <att>generatedBy</att> attribute may indicate, for <gi>post</gi> or any of its
        descendants, how the content transcribed in an element was generated in a CMC environment.
        That is, whether the source text being transcribed was created by a human user, created by
        the CMC system at the request of a human user (e.g., when the user activates a template that
        generates the content, such as in a signature), generated by the CMC system (e.g. a
        status message or a timestamp), or generated by an automated process external to the CMC
        system itself. This attribute is optional; when it is not specified on a <gi>post</gi>
        element its value is presumed to be <val>unspecified</val>; when it is unspecified on any
        descendant of <gi>post</gi> its value is inherited from the immediately enclosing element.
        In turn, if <att>generatedBy</att> is not specified on that element it inherits the
        value from its immediately enclosing element, and so on up the document hierarchy until a
          <gi>post</gi> is reached; the <gi>post</gi> either has a <att>generatedBy</att> attribute
        specified or its presumed value is <val>unspecified</val>.</p>
      <!-- BEGIN duplicative section %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% … -->
      <!--
          If you make a change here, make it in the att.cmc.xml file,
          as well!
      -->
      <p>A list of suggested values for <att>generatedBy</att> follows:
      <list type="gloss">
          <label>human</label>
          <item>when the content of the respective element was <q>naturally</q> typed or spoken by
            a human user (cf. the chat posts in example <ref target="#ex.haarschnitt"
            >haircut</ref>)</item>
          <label>template</label>
          <item>when the content of the respective element was generated after a human user
            activated a template for its insertion
            (often applicable to <gi>signed</gi> and <gi>time</gi>; e.g. see the
            signature in wiki talk in <ref target="#ex.naturally">this example below</ref>)</item>
          <label>system</label>
          <item>when the content of the respective element was generated by the system, i.e. the CMC
            environment (see, e.g., the system message in an IRC chat in the <ref target="#ex.listPerson">this other example below</ref>)</item>
          <label>bot</label>
          <item>when the content of the respective element was generated by a bot, i.e. a non-human
            agent, typically one that is not part of the CMC environment itself</item>
          <label>unspecified</label>
          <item>when it is unspecified or unknown how the content of the respective element was
            generated (see, e.g. the retweet that forms the second <gi>post</gi> in <ref target="#ex.grunzen">this example below</ref>).</item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <!-- … END duplicative section %%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%%% -->
      <p>The following is a sample encoding of a chat post that contains an emoji.
        Although the post was written by a human, the emoji itself was marked in
        the source as having been generated by a template:
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.haarschnitt" source="#BIB_MoCoDa2" xml:lang="en">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t003" who="#A02" xml:id="cmc_post18" xml:lang="de">
            Da kostet ein Haarschnitt 50 €
            <figure type="emoji" generatedBy="template">
              <desc type="label" xml:lang="en">face screaming in fear</desc>
              <desc type="unicode">U+1F631</desc>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>In the following example, the user signature of a wiki talk post was inserted by activating
        a template, and is thus marked accordingly: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
          xml:id="ex.naturally" source="#BIB_WPTalkAstronomicalObject" xml:lang="en">
          <post modality="written" xml:id="cmc_post19" indentLevel="0" who="#u005" synch="#t005">
            <p>I'm not sure that this is a proper criterium, or even what this means. What if we set
              an explosion that breaks a comet into two pieces? What if we build a moon? Cheers,
              </p><signed generatedBy="template" rend="inline"><ref target="/wiki/User:Greenodd"
                >Greenodd</ref> (<ref target="/wiki/User_talk:Greenodd">talk</ref>) <time>01:00, 21
                July 2011 (UTC)</time></signed>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>In the following example, a tweet is specified as having been written by a human; however
        inside the tweet, the timestamp is marked as generated by the CMC system: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.grunzen" xml:lang="de">
          <post modality="written" type="tweet" generatedBy="human" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t001"
            xml:id="cmc_post_1043764753502486528" who="#u1" xml:lang="de">
            <time generatedBy="system"> 12:31 </time> Heute mit super Unterstützung, wir grunzen,
            wenn die Zeit vorbei ist. <ref type="hashtag"
              target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash">#bcrn18</ref>
            <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wikidach?src=hash"
              >#wikidach</ref> PS: Die beiden brauchen noch Namen. Hinweise dazu am Empfang abgeben!
              <ref type="twitter-account" target="https://twitter.com/AndreLo79">@AndreLo79</ref>
            <figure type="image">
              <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DnwygdSW4AAoTUn.jpg:large"/>
            </figure>
          </post>
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="unspecified" type="tweet" who="#u1"
            synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t002" xml:id="cmc_post_1043769240136880128">
            <ptr type="retweet" target="#cmc_post_1043767827927388160"/>
          </post>
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" type="tweet" who="#u3" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t002"
            xml:lang="de" xml:id="cmc_post_1043767827927388160">
            <time generatedBy="system"> 12:43 </time>
            <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
              <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/Dnw1TRNXgAAKqlK.jpg:large"/>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Finally, in the following example of an IRC post, the status message that user <q>Interseb
          has entered the room</q> was generated by the system, i.e. the chat environment. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.listPerson" xml:lang="de"
          source="#BIB_DCK">
          <post type="event" generatedBy="system" who="#SYSTEM" rend="color:navy">
            <p><name type="nickname" ref="#A07">Interseb</name> betritt den Raum.</p>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="CMCmacrometa">
    <head>CMC Macrostructure</head>
    <p>In many CMC genres, posts may occur in a variety of ways: e.g. in a sequence or in threads, or grouped in some other way.
      For example, in chat communication such as WhatsApp, posts are part of <q>a chat</q> of one user with another user or among a
      <!-- shouldn’t “a chat” above be <soCalled> like “logfile” ?? —Syd, 2024-01-31 -->
      <!-- or maybe each should just be <term>? —Syd, 2024-05-17 -->
      group of users. When an entire chat is saved, typically a <soCalled>logfile</soCalled> of the
      chat is obtained from the CMC system and downloaded. Similarly, Wikipedia discussions occur on
      a <term>talk page</term>, which ultimately is a web page containing the user posts,
      sub-structured in threads. Likewise, YouTube comments occur on a webpage containing the YouTube
      video along with comment posts and posts replying to those comments displayed below the video.
      The video serves as a <term>prompt</term> for the whole discussion. In forum discussions, the
      prompt may be a news item, and in Wikipedia, an article may be viewed as the prompt for the
      discussion on the talk page associated with that article.</p>
    <div xml:id="CMCmacro">
      <head>Macrostructure of CMC Collections and Documents</head>
      <p>When CMC documents are compiled into a collection, dataset, or corpus, we distinguish the
        following levels in the macrostructure of CMC in TEI: <list type="gloss">
          <label rend="bold">The corpus level</label>
          <item><p>The level of a corpus or collection of CMC texts of a particular genre, generally
              obtained from a particular CMC platform, sometimes even from several platforms. This
              level may be represented by either a <gi>TEI</gi> element or a <gi>teiCorpus</gi>
              element. The <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus (i.e., the <gi>teiHeader</gi> that is a
              child of the outermost <gi>TEI</gi> or <gi>teiCorpus</gi>) will contain metadata in
              its <gi>sourceDesc</gi> about the CMC platform(s). Metadata about the project
              responsible for collecting the data and building the corpus, if applicable, should be
              recorded as well.</p>
          </item>
          <label rend="bold">The document level</label>
          <item><p>A set of posts collected (or sampled) by a researcher for analysis. The posts of
              the document will often map directly to the set of posts grouped on an existing web
              page, thread, or document within a CMC environment. Within the CMC environment the
              document as such is often created by a particular user, thereby initiating the
              communication which other users may read, and to which some other users might
              contribute. This level will naturally be represented by the <gi>TEI</gi> element. The
                <gi>teiCorpus</gi> (or <gi>TEI</gi>) element that represents the corpus will contain
              one or more <gi>TEI</gi> elements as usual.</p>
            <p>In the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of a document level <gi>TEI</gi>, the <gi>sourceDesc</gi>
              will contain metadata about the CMC document such as a title, its author or owner,
              its URL, the date of its creation, the date of the last change made to it, and other
              metadata that are available and to be recorded such as one or more categories
              associated with the document.</p>
            <p>The document sometimes contains, or is associated with, a prompt such as a video or a
              news item, either provided by the initiating user herself or located elsewhere and
              referenced at the beginning of the document. In such cases, the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of
              the document should also contain metadata about this prompt.</p>
          </item>
          <label rend="bold">The post level</label>
          <item><p>The level of the individual post is naturally represented by the <gi>post</gi>
              element; its encoding is further described in section <ptr target="#CMCcmcpost"/>. A
                <gi>TEI</gi> element will contain a number of <gi>post</gi> elements, which can be
              grouped or ordered in <gi>div</gi> elements representing sequences or threads (section
                <ptr target="#CMCthreads"/>) if appropriate.</p></item>
        </list>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="macrostructure" valid="feasible">
          <teiCorpus>
            <!-- a corpus, collection or dataset of CMC documents -->
            <teiHeader>
              <!-- metadata pertaining to the corpus or CMC dataset-->
            </teiHeader>
            <TEI>
              <!-- a CMC document such as a chat log or a discussion page -->
              <teiHeader>
                <!-- metadata pertaining to the CMC document -->
              </teiHeader>
              <text>
                <body>
                  <div>
                    <!-- subdivisions of the CMC document e.g. in sections or threads if applicable-->
                    <post>
                      <!-- one post -->
                    </post>
                    <!-- more posts -->
                  </div>
                </body>
              </text>
            </TEI>
            <!-- more documents -->
          </teiCorpus>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCthreads">
      <head>Sequences, Sections, Threads</head>
      <p>As shown in Example <ptr target="#CMCcmcpostatts"/> above, nested threads of posts may be
        encoded sequentially, while the <att>indentLevel</att> attribute of <gi>post</gi> is used to
        keep track of the original nesting depth. This is especially meant for CMC text obtained
        from a wiki code or HTML source, where it is not always entirely clear whether the
        indentation information actually reflects a reply action from a user.</p>
      <p>In genres where technical reply information is available for each post, reply links can be
        encoded using the <att>replyTo</att> attribute on <gi>post</gi> elements, as shown in the
        second example of <ptr target="#CMCcmcpostatts"/>. The network of all reply links will then
        also form a threaded structure, and visual indentations can be reconstructed from it and
        need not be explicitly encoded.</p>
      <p>Threads may also be explicitly encoded as nested <gi>div</gi> elements as in the following
        skeleton: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <div type="thread" n="0">
            <post>...</post>
            <div type="thread" n="1">
              <post> ... </post>
              <post> ... </post>
              <div type="thread" n="2">
                <!-- posts -->
              </div>
            </div>
          </div>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Using this encoding strategy, <ref target="#e9">this example</ref> from <ptr
          target="#CMCcmcpostatts"/> could be encoded as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de" source="#BIB_scilog1">
          <div type="thread" n="0">
            <post type="comment" xml:id="cmc_post01" who="#u7" when-iso="2015-07-29T21:44">
              <p>Es hat den Anschein, ...</p>
            </post>
            <div type="thread" n="1">
              <post type="comment" xml:id="cmc_post02" who="#u8" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:11">
                <p>Nein Nein, an den Handwerkern kann es ...</p>
              </post>
              <div type="thread" n="2">
                <post type="comment" xml:id="cmc_post03" who="#u8" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:26">
                  <p>Stahlkunstruktionen dacht ich mal, ....</p>
                </post>
              </div>
            </div>
          </div>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCmultimodal">
      <head>Multimodal CMC</head>
      <p>As explained in section <ptr target="#CMCUnits"/>, the elements <gi>post</gi>, <gi>u</gi>,
          <gi>kinesic</gi>, and <gi>incident</gi> are available to encode textual transcriptions
        of written posts, spoken turns, bodily activities of avatars, and onscreen activity by users
        that occur in CMC data; and, as discussed in section <ptr target="#CMCcmcpostatts"/>,
        graphics or other media data within posts are encoded in a <gi>post</gi> with
          <att>modality</att> set to <val>written</val>. When two or more of these features occur in
        a CMC interaction, we can speak of <term>multimodal</term> CMC.</p>
      <p>Some basic multimodality is available in many private chat systems such as WhatsApp, where spoken and
        written posts and media posts containing images or video clips can alternate in the sequence
        of posts. The following shows the suggested encoding of an extended part of the <hi
          rend="italic">haircut</hi> chat example from above, including a spoken post, several
        written posts, and a post containing a graphic image (adapted from the MoCoDa2 corpus <ptr
          target="#BIB_MoCoDa2"/>) </p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#BIB_MoCoDa2" xml:lang="de">
        <post modality="spoken" generatedBy="human" synch="#cmc-haircut_t004" who="#cmc-haircut_A05"
          xml:id="cmc-haircut_m9"> In Düsseldorf gibt's da so Abstufungen. Da gibt's einmal Oliver
          Schmidt, Oliver Schmidt's Hair Design, also dann, ist eher also, keine Ahnung, zum
          Beispiel ich war da bei dem etwas Günstigeren dann. Ich weiß nicht, ob's das in Essen auch
          gibt diese Abstufungen </post>
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#cmc-haircut_t004"
          who="#cmc-haircut_A02" xml:id="cmc-haircut_m10"> Ich schau mal :) </post>
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#cmc-haircut_t005"
          who="#cmc-haircut_A06" xml:id="cmc-haircut_m11"> Ich gehe immer nach Katernberg zu Pasha’s
          haarem Hahaha also die sind echt entspannt und gut und nicht teuer </post>
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#tcmc-haircut_005"
          who="#cmc-haircut_A06" xml:id="cmc-haircut_m12">
          <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
            <desc xml:lang="en">screenshot of the google search for hairdresser "Pasha's Haare'm"
              with the average google rating (4,5 of 5 stars), the address, the phone number, and
              the opening hours. </desc>
          </figure>
        </post>
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#cmc-haircut_t006"
          who="#cmc-haircut_A03" xml:id="cmc-haircut_m13"> Olivers hair und Oliver Schmidt gehören
          zusammen </post>
      </egXML>
      <p>In the graphical user interface (GUI) of a more complex multimodal CMC environment such as
        Second Life, a gaming and learning platform, interactions may consist of interleaved
        occurrences of posts (<gi>p</gi>), utterances (<gi>u</gi>) and nonverbal acts such as
        bodily activities (<gi>kinesic</gi>) or other on-screen activities (<gi>incident</gi>). In
        the following example a spoken utterance, an avatar's bodily activity, and a written post
        occur on the same level within the <gi>body</gi> element, representing parts of a multimodal
        chat in Second Life (adapted from the <ref type="cit" target="#BIB_ChanierWigham2015"
          >Archi21 corpus</ref>). <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
          source="#BIB_ChanierWigham2015" xml:lang="en">
          <text>
            <body>
              <u xml:id="cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-a191" who="#tingrabu"
                start="#cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-ts373" end="#cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-ts430">ok
                hm for me this presentation was hm <pause dur="PT1S"/> become too fast because it's
                always the same in our architecture school euh we have not time and hm <pause
                  dur="PT1S"/> too quickly sorry [...]</u>
              <kinesic xml:id="cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-a192" who="#romeorez"
                start="#cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-ts376" end="#cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-ts377"
                type="body" subtype="kinesics">
                <desc>
                  <code>eat(popcorn)</code>
                </desc>
              </kinesic>
              <!-- more bodily activities of avatars -->
              <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-a195"
                who="#tfrez2" start="#cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-ts380"
                end="#cmr-archi21-slrefl-es-j3-1-ts381" type="chat-message">
                <p>it went too quickly?</p>
              </post>
            </body>
          </text>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Note that the spoken utterance <gi>u</gi> represents a speaker turn that was transmitted
        via an audio channel of the application that is continuously open during a session, whereas
        a spoken <gi>post</gi> represents a spoken message that has been recorded in private and
        been posted to the CMC server as a whole. See section <ptr target="#CMCUnits"/>.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="CMCmetadata">
    <head>Documenting CMC (and providing general metadata)</head>
    <div xml:id="CMCCorpusSource">
      <head>Documenting the Source of a Corpus of CMC data</head>
      <p>The <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus should contain metadata about the CMC platform(s),
        e.g. its name, information about its owner (often a company) including their address or
        location, the URL of the server where the CMC data were collected from, or the filename of a
        database dump that was used as a source. Metadata about the project responsible for
        collecting the data and building the corpus, if applicable, should be recorded as well.</p>
      <p>The following example shows the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of a X (Twitter) corpus.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>Twitter Sample</title>
              </titleStmt>
              <publicationStmt>
                <distributor>Twitter International Company</distributor>
                <address>
                  <addrLine>1 Cumberland Place</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Fenian Street</addrLine>
                  <addrLine>Dublin 2</addrLine>
                  <postCode>D02 AX07</postCode>
                  <country>Ireland</country>
                </address>
                <ptr target="https://twitter.com/"/>
                <date when="2024-04-27"/>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>The following example shows how a Wikipedia database dump may be encoded as the source.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
              <titleStmt>
                <title>German Wikipedia Data Dump of 2019-08-01</title>
              </titleStmt>
              <editionStmt>
                <edition>Dump file in XML (compressed)</edition>
              </editionStmt>
              <extent>
                <measure unit="GiB" quantity="7.9"/>
              </extent>
              <publicationStmt>
                <publisher>Wikimedia Foundation, Inc.</publisher>
                <pubPlace>
                  <ptr target="https://dumps.wikimedia.org/"/>
                </pubPlace>
                <date when="2019-08-01">01 Aug 19</date>
                <idno type="dump-filename">dewiki-2019-08-01-pages-meta-current</idno>
              </publicationStmt>
            </biblFull>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCDocumentSource">
      <head>Describing the Source of a CMC Document</head>
      <p>A CMC document may be a chat logfile, a discussion page, or a thematical thread of posts
        as encoded within a <gi>TEI</gi> element. Among the metadata to be recorded in the
          <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of its <gi>teiHeader</gi> are, if available, its title, author or
        owner, its URL, the date of its creation and/or the date of its last change (i.e. the time
        when the last post was added to it). </p>
      <p>The following example is the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of a TEI encoding of a YouTube page that
        contained a video and user comments on the video (which are encoded in the <gi>body</gi> of
        the text as posts). The metadata contain a URL reference to the video and the YouTube
        channel that posted the video in <gi>relatedItem</gi> elements. The date when the page was
        created is not known. The example is adapted from the NottDeuYTSch corpus (<ptr
          target="#BIB_Cotgrove"/>), where the video itself is not contained in the corpus. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#BIB_Cotgrove" xml:lang="en">
          <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
              <title type="main">Iron Man 3 in 3D (Official Trailer German) Parodie</title>
              <respStmt>
                <name type="user">DieAussenseiter</name>
                <resp>posted video, created page</resp>
              </respStmt>
              <distributor>YouTube</distributor>
              <ptr type="url" target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=T-WU_3-0UpU"/>
              <series>
                <title>DieAussenseiter’s Channel</title>
                <ptr target="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=UCKn1vL4Ou4DKu0BlcK3NlDQ"/>
              </series>
            </bibl>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>The following example is the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> of a Wikipedia talk page. Note that a
          <gi>relatedItem</gi> element is used to record a reference to the Wikipedia article that
        the transcribed discussion is about. <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
              <title type="main">Diskussion:FKM-Richtlinie</title>
              <author><name type="user">OnkelSchuppig</name>, et al.</author>
              <publisher>Wikimedia Foundation, Inc.</publisher>
              <ptr target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/Diskussion:FKM-Richtlinie" type="page_url"
                targetLang="de"/>
              <date type="last-change" when="2013-09-14T17:04:48Z"/>
              <idno type="wikipedia-id">7632113</idno>
              <relatedItem type="articleLink">
                <ref n="5138958" target="https://de.wikipedia.org/wiki/FKM-Richtlinie"
                  targetLang="de">FKM-Richtlinie</ref>
              </relatedItem>
            </bibl>
          </sourceDesc>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCSampling">
      <head>Documenting the Sampling of CMC data</head>
      <p>The documentation of how the data were collected, e.g. how it was scraped or sampled from
        the web, or downloaded from a server, should be recorded in the <gi>samplingDecl</gi>. Like
        other metadata, information about sampling should be recorded at the highest level
        applicable. That is, if the information applies to an entire corpus, the
          <gi>samplingDecl</gi> should appear in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of the corpus level; if the
        information is different for each document, it should appear in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> of
        the document level texts.</p>
      <p>The sampling information typically considered of interest consists of at least the
        following four components: <list>
          <item>interface: The API that was used for the download, possibly encoded as a <tag>name
              type="API"</tag>;</item>
          <item>client: The client or other tool that was used for the download, possibly encoded as
            a <tag>name type="client"</tag>;</item>
          <item>query: The query or command used for the download, possibly encoded with a <tag>ptr
              type="query"</tag> when it is a URI, or a <gi>code</gi> when it is a command;</item>
          <item>date: The date of the download.</item>
        </list> For example, in the case of an X (Twitter) corpus a sampling declaration might look
        like the following: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <samplingDecl>
            <p>Sampled using the <name type="API">Twitter Filtered stream v2-API</name> (see <ptr
                type="APIdoc"
                target="https://developer.twitter.com/en/docs/twitter-api/tweets/filtered-stream/api-reference/get-tweets-search-stream"
              />) Filtered for the German language and the following countries: Germany, Austria,
              Belgium, Switzerland, Denmark, and Luxembourg. Downloaded on <date when="2022-12-12"
                >Mon 12 Dec 22</date> using the command
                <code>requests.get("https://api.twitter.com/2/tweets/search/stream",
                headers=headers, params=params, stream=True,)</code> in the python script <name
                type="script">collectFilteredTwitterStream.py</name>. </p>
          </samplingDecl>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>The <gi>samplingDecl</gi> of a Usenet Newsgroup corpus: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <samplingDecl>
            <p>Downloaded from the news.individual.de server on 2016-01-15 using nntp client in
              Python</p>
          </samplingDecl>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCParticipants">
      <head>Participants</head>
      <p>A <gi>listPerson</gi> may be used to maintain an inventory of users and bots taking part in
        a CMC interaction, along with information about them. As with other such contextual
        information, it may be kept in the <gi>teiHeader</gi> (where it would occur in a
          <gi>particDesc</gi> within a <gi>profileDesc</gi>) or in a separate document completely.
        In either case, an encoded <gi>post</gi> may then be linked to its author by use of the
          <att>who</att> attribute.</p>
      <p>In the following example, a list of participants is maintained in a <gi>teiHeader</gi>.
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="en" source="#BIB_WPTalkAstronomicalObject">
          <!-- In the <teiHeader>: -->
          <profileDesc>
            <particDesc>
              <listPerson>
                <person role="user" sex="male" xml:id="cmc_user_01">
                  <persName type="userName">M</persName>
                  <note type="link">/wiki/User:M</note>
                  <affiliation>
                    <email>mike@mydomain.com</email>
                    <country>CH</country>
                  </affiliation>
                </person>
                <!-- … more persons … -->
                <person role="user" sex="female" xml:id="cmc_user_06">
                  <persName type="userName">P</persName>
                  <note type="link">/wiki/User:P</note>
                  <affiliation>
                    <email>pat@super.net</email>
                    <country>ES</country>
                  </affiliation>
                </person>
                <person role="user" xml:id="cmc_user_07">
                  <persName type="userName">PKP</persName>
                  <note type="link">/wiki/User:Pi</note>
                </person>
              </listPerson>
            </particDesc>
          </profileDesc>
          <!-- In the <body>: -->
          <div type="wiki_discussion_page" n="073">
            <!-- 4 other <post>s -->
            <post modality="written" xml:id="cmc_post04" indentLevel="1" replyTo="#cmc_post_073.004"
              who="#cmc_user_06">
              <p>Those haven't happened. If they do, we can revisit the concern.</p>
              <signed generatedBy="template" rend="noLineBreak">
                <ref target="/wiki/User:P">P</ref>
                <date>01:35, 8 April 2014 (UTC)</date>
              </signed>
            </post>
          </div>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>In the following version of the <gi>body</gi> portion of the same example, the list of
        interactants is stored in a separate file (in this case the file <name type="file"
          >userList.xml</name> in the same directory). <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#BIB_WPTalkAstronomicalObject"
          xml:lang="en">
          <!-- In the <body>: -->
          <div type="wiki_discussion_page" n="073">
            <!-- 4 other <post>s -->
            <post modality="written" xml:id="cmc_post05" indentLevel="1" replyTo="#cmc_post_073.004"
              who="./userList.xml#cmc_user_06">
              <p>Those haven't happened. If they do, we can revisit the concern.</p>
              <signed generatedBy="template" rend="noLineBreak">
                <ref target="/wiki/User:P">P</ref>
                <date>01:35, 8 April 2014 (UTC)</date>
              </signed>
            </post>
          </div>
        </egXML> Alternatively, a <gi>prefixDef</gi> may be used to declare a prefix which can be
        used in the value of <att>who</att> to generate a complete URI, thus making the values of
          <att>who</att> shorter, less error-prone, and easier to maintain. For example, the prefix
          <code>uL:</code> could be used to map the value <val>uL:06</val> to
          <code>file:/userList.xml#cmc_user_06</code>. See <ptr target="#SAPU"/> for more
        information on establishing prefix definitions.</p>
      <p>This indirection—using a <gi>listPerson</gi>, particularly one in a separate file, to
        store information about the users involved in a CMC interaction—is particularly useful
        when there is both a need to keep such information locally, and to remove it (e.g., to
          <soCalled>anonymize</soCalled> the data) when the data are published or shared with other
        researchers.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCTimeline">
      <head>Timeline</head>
      <p>From most CMC environments, user posts come provided with a timestamp marking the time
        (often down to the second) when the post arrived and was registered at the CMC server.
        In the display of chat interactions, for instance, the time is automatically added by the
        system and usually precedes or follows the actual content of the post. In Wikipedia talk, a
        timestamp is automatically added when the user inserts his or her signature. A timestamp in
        the text body may be transcribed using a <gi>date</gi> or <gi>time</gi> element, in which
        case the <att>when</att> attribute may be used to record a normalized version of the date,
        time, or date and time if this information is available or reconstructible.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="'BIB_DCK" xml:lang="de">
          <post modality="written" rend="color:black" who="#f2213001.A06" xml:id="cmc_post06">
            <time generatedBy="system">21:52</time>
            das ist auf jedenfall krankheit
          </post>
        </egXML>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#BIB_WPTalkAstronomicalObject" xml:lang="en">
          <post modality="written" xml:id="cmc_post07" indentLevel="1" who="#u006" synch="#t006">
            <p>Those haven't happened. If they do, we can revisit the concern.</p>
            <signed generatedBy="template">
              <ref target="/wiki/User:P">P</ref>
              <date when="2014-04-08T01:35:00Z">01:35, 8 April 2014 (UTC)</date>
            </signed>
          </post>
        </egXML>
        Alternatively the timestamp may be recorded using the
        <att>when</att> attribute of <gi>post</gi>. In this case, if
        the details of how the timestamp appeared in the original are
        considered unimportant, the actual transcription may be omitted.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#BIB_WPTalkAstronomicalObject" xml:lang="en">
          <post modality="written" when="2014-04-08T01:35:00Z" who="#u006">
            <p>Those haven't happened. If they do, we can revisit the concern.</p>
            <signed generatedBy="template">
              <ref target="/wiki/User:P">P</ref>
            </signed>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Instead of transcribing timestamps or recording the timestamp
      directly on an attribute of <gi>post</gi>, all timestamps of a
      set of posts can be collected in <gi>when</gi> elements in a
      <gi>timeline</gi> element in the <gi>teiHeader</gi>, most
      suitably in the <gi>interaction</gi> element (itself in the
      <gi>textDesc</gi> in the <gi>profileDesc</gi>). In which case,
      similar to the encoding of transcripts of spoken utterances (for
      which see <ptr target="#TS"/>), each individual post can be
      linked to its timestamp via the <att>synch</att> attribute as in
      the following alternative encoding of the Wikipedia talk example
      above.
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
        <profileDesc>
          <particDesc>
            <listPerson>
              <person role="user" xml:id="u001">
                <persName type="userName">M</persName>
                <note type="link">/wiki/User:M</note>
              </person>
              <!-- more persons -->
              <person role="user" xml:id="u006">
                <persName type="userName">P</persName>
                <note type="link">/wiki/User:P</note>
              </person>
              <person role="user" xml:id="u007">
                <persName type="userName">PKP</persName>
                <note type="link">/wiki/User:Pi</note>
              </person>
            </listPerson>
          </particDesc>
          <textDesc>
            <channel/>
            <constitution/>
            <derivation/>
            <domain/>
            <factuality/>           
            <interaction>
              <timeline>
                <when xml:id="t001" absolute="2011-03-23T19:56:00"/>
                <when xml:id="t002" absolute="2011-06-14T21:22:00"/>
                <when xml:id="t003" absolute="2011-06-14T23:28:00"/>
                <when xml:id="t004" absolute="2011-07-02T07:20:00"/>
                <when xml:id="t005" absolute="2011-07-21T01:00:00"/>
                <when xml:id="t006" absolute="2014-04-08T01:35:00"/>
              </timeline>
            </interaction>
            <preparedness/>
            <purpose/>
          </textDesc>
        </profileDesc>
      </egXML>
      Note that the <att>synch</att> attribute is provided by the module described in
      chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.</p>
      <p>Removing timestamps from the text body can help meet
        requirements of text anonymization. For instance, if the <gi>particDesc</gi> and the
        <gi>timeline</gi> are stored in a separate file, the rest of the corpus can be distributed
        without this separate file. Thus the recipient of the corpus may know in what order posts
        were made (if the values of the <att>synch</att> are sequential), and will be able to
        group posts made by the same user, but will not have exact timestamps or actual user names,
        thus providing a significant degree of anonymization.
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="e10" xml:lang="en" source="#BIB_WPTalkAstronomicalObject">
        <post modality="written" xml:id="cmc_post08" indentLevel="1" who="#u006" synch="#t006">
          <p>Those haven't happened. If they do, we can revisit the concern. </p>
          <signed generatedBy="template">
            [_DELETED-SIGNATURE_]
            <date synch="#t007">[_DELETED-TIMESTAMP_]</date>
          </signed>
        </post>
      </egXML>
      As demonstrated above, the <att>synch</att> attribute can be
      used on <gi>date</gi> or <gi>time</gi> (or indeed any other
      element) rather than on the <gi>post</gi> itself.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="CMCrecs">
    <head>Recommendations for Encoding CMC Microstructure</head>
    <div xml:id="CMCemos">
      <head>Emojis and Emoticons</head>
      <p>Emojis are iconic or symbolic, invariant graphic units which the users of social media
        applications such as WhatsApp, Instagram, and X (Twitter) can select from a menu or
          <soCalled>emoji keyboard</soCalled> and embed into their written posts. Examples are
        &#x1F601;, &#x1F637;, &#x01F308;, &#x1F631;, and &#x1F648;. An emoji is encoded by one or
        more Unicode characters which are intended to be mapped directly to a pictorial symbol.</p>
      <p>Emoticons predate emojis and are created as combinations of ASCII punctuation and other
        characters using the keyboard. Examples are <code>:-)</code>, <code>;-)</code>,
          <code>:-(</code>, <code>:-x</code>, <code>\O/</code>, and <code>Oo</code>. They first
        occurred on a computer bulletin board system at Carnegie
        Mellon University (<ref target="#BIB_smiley">Fahlman, 2021</ref>) and then
        became frequent in chat communications during the mid-1980s. An emoticon typically consists
        of several Unicode characters (from the ASCII subset) in a row, each of which has an
        intended use other than as part of an emoticon.</p>
      <p>Both emoticons and emojis may be simply transcribed as a sequence of characters. As with
        any other characters, they may be entered as numeric character entities if this is more
        convenient. (E.g., <mentioned>&#x2764;</mentioned> might be transcribed as
          <code>&amp;#x2764;</code> in any XML document, including a TEI document; see <ptr
          target="#D4-44"/>.)</p>
      <p>When the text of a post is being tokenized, e.g. for linguistic analysis, it may be useful
        to encode the emoticon or emoji as a separate token. In such cases elements such as
          <gi>w</gi> or <gi>c</gi> may be used for tokenization, and the <att>pos</att> attribute
        may be used to indicate that the encoded string is an emoji or an emoticon. (See <ptr
          target="#AILC"/>.)</p>
      <p>For example, the source post <q>da bin ich nicht so empfindlich ;)</q> (English:. <q>I am not
          so touchy with that ;)</q>) ends with an emoticon, and might be encoded as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post>
            <w pos="ADV">da</w>
            <w pos="VAFIN">bin</w>
            <w pos="PPER">ich</w>
            <w pos="PTKNEG">nicht</w>
            <w pos="ADV">so</w>
            <w pos="ADJD">empfindlich</w>
            <w pos="EMOASC">;)</w>
          </post>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>Similarly, the source post <q>Klar &#x01F601;</q> (<q>Sure &#x01F601;</q> in English) might
        be encoded as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03"
            xml:id="cmc_post21">
            <w pos="ADV">Klar</w>
            <w pos="EMOIMG">&#x01F601;</w>
          </post>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>The values of <att>pos</att> in the above examples are from the STTS_IBK Tagset for German
        (see <ptr type="cit" target="#STTS_IBK"/>), which includes tags for CMC-specific elements
        such as <val>EMOASC</val> for an ASCII-based emoticon and <val>EMOIMG</val> for an
        icon-based emoji.</p>
      <p>Alternatively, e.g. when <gi>w</gi> is not regularly used to encode tokens in the TEI
        document, <gi>c</gi> may be used to mark an emoji. For example, the source post <q>Da kostet
          ein Haarschnitt 50 € &#x01F631;</q> (from the corpus <ptr target="#CMC_Mocoda2"/>, in
        English <q>A haircut there costs 50 € &#x01F631;</q>) might be encoded as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <post xml:lang="de">Da kostet ein Haarschnitt 50 € <c type="emoji" ana="#fsif"
              generatedBy="template">&#x01F631;</c></post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Sometimes, e.g. when the source of the TEI document was a web page in HTML, the emojis may
        occur only as an icon graphic in the source. In such a case, they may be encoded using
          <gi>figure</gi>. The corresponding Unicode character can then be recorded in the
          <gi>desc</gi> element by the encoder if desired.</p>
      <p>For example, the source text: <q>... ich überlege noch &#x1F648;</q> (English: <q>... I'm
          still thinking &#x1F648;</q>) might be encoded as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03"
            xml:id="cmc_post22"> ... ich überlege noch <figure type="emoji" generatedBy="template">
              <graphic url="fig1.png"/>
              <desc type="gloss" xml:lang="en">see no evil monkey</desc>
              <desc type="unicode">U+1F648</desc>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML></p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCgraphic">
      <head>Posts with Graphics</head>
      <p>A post in a CMC interaction may contain a graphic in addition to some text or even contain
        only a graphic (without any text). As explained in <ptr target="#CMCcmcpostatts"/>, the
        modality of such a post should be considered as <val>written</val>. To encode the graphic
        information, the <gi>figure</gi> element may be used at the appropriate place.</p>
        <p>In the following example a private chat post that contained
        only a screenshot of a google search result for a hairdresser
        is encoded as a <gi>post</gi> with a child <gi>figure</gi>. A
        link to the graphic file itself is not included presumably
        because this is a text-only corpus that does not include
        images.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#UND">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06" xml:id="cmc_post23">
            <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
              <desc>screenshot of the google search for hairdresser "Pasha's Haare'm" with the
                average google rating (4,5 of 5 stars), the address, the phone number, and the
                opening hours. </desc>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML>
        </p>
      <p>The following is an example of the encoding of a tweet which
      contains both text (including hashtags and mentions) and a
      graphic. The <gi>graphic</gi> element retains the URL of the
      graphic on the web just as in the source.
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <post type="tweet" modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t006"
            xml:id="cmc_post_1043823300479258624" who="#u1" xml:lang="de">
            <time generatedBy="system"> 16:24 </time> Bro Tri-Engel...so hab ich mir das
            vorgestellt!!! @AndreLo79 #bcrn18 #wikidach @Heiko komm' mal Twitter! #Engel <figure
              type="image" generatedBy="human">
              <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DnxnwN9XsAEHXw2.jpg:large"/>
            </figure>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCcirculation">
      <head>Circulation</head>
      <p>The following recommendations on how to encode features of
      the circulation of posts, such as IDs, re-posts (retweets),
      hashtags, and mentions use X (Twitter) posts (tweets) as an
      example; this phenomenon is not in any way unique to X
      (Twitter), however.</p>
      <p>In the following example, the type of post (in this case, a
      tweet) is recorded using the <att>type</att> attribute of
      <gi>post</gi>. If it were useful to record a particular
      sub-categorization of tweet, the <att>subtype</att> attribute
      could also be used. Furthermore, the original unique identifer
      of the tweet as supplied by X (Twitter) is recorded as part of
      the value of the <att>xml:id</att> attribute of the
      <gi>post</gi>.</p>
      <p>Also in the following example a retweet and its corresponding
      retweeted tweet are encoded as two separate posts each with its
      own set of attributes. The post representing the retweet itself
      does not contain or duplicate the content of the retweeted
      tweet. Instead it refers to the ID of the retweeted tweet via a
      <gi>ptr</gi> in the post content. All original content of the
      retweet goes in the content of the <gi>post</gi> element as
      well. In addition, the hashtags found in the body of the source
      tweets have been encoded using <gi>ref</gi> elements (with a
      <att>type</att> of <val>hashtag</val>), as they are links like
      any other hyperlink.</p>
      <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.tweets" xml:lang="de">
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" type="tweet" who="#u1"
          xml:id="cmc_post_1043796550101716993" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t004" xml:lang="de">
          <ptr type="retweet" target="#cmc_post_1043796093786566656"/> Ich mich auch? <ref
            type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dynamicduo?src=hash"
            >#dynamicduo</ref>
          <ref type="hashtag"
            target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wirk%C3%BCmmernunsauchumIhrenEmpfang?src=hash"
            >#wirkümmernunsauchumIhrenEmpfang</ref>
          <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash">#bcrn18</ref>
          <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wikidach?src=hash"
            >#wikidach</ref>
        </post>
        <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" type="tweet" who="#u2"
          synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t003" xml:lang="de" xml:id="cmc_post_1043796093786566656">
          <time generatedBy="system"> 14:35 </time> Immer wieder gerne. Kann ich mich schon für
          nächstes Jahr als Empfangs- <ref type="hashtag"
            target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Engel?src=hash">#Engel</ref> für das nächste
          BarCamp bewerben <w pos="EMO">&#x1F92A;</w>
          <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash">#bcrn18</ref>
          <trailer>
            <fs>
              <f name="favoritecount">
                <numeric value="4"/>
              </f>
            </fs>
          </trailer>
        </post>
      </egXML>
      <p>Note that in the above example <soCalled>CoMeRe</soCalled> style (cf. <ptr
      target="#BIB_CoMeRe"/>) encoding is used to represent the number of favorites. It would
      also be reasonable to use a TEI <gi>measure</gi> element instead of the <gi>fs</gi>.</p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCanalysis">
      <head>Linguistic Annotation</head>
      <p>For encoding linguistic analyses of CMC text, we may use the dedicated elements and
        attributes from the analysis module, which is described in <ptr target="#SA"/>. For example,
        the tokenization (segmentation into word-like units) of a CMC text should be encoded using
        the <gi>w</gi> element.</p>
      <p>Let us take, for example a posting that contains the content <q xml:lang="de">00:22 Bin
          soooooo im stress gewesen ich Armer lol</q> (in English: <q>I was soooooo stressed out
          poor me lol</q>). This may be encoded as follows. <!-- aus Dortmunder Chatkorpus Chat 1101004_Welcome_2004-11-08.tei.xml -->
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post generatedBy="human" rend="color:black" synch="#t010.a" who="#A03.a"
            xml:id="cmc_post_m16.a">
            <time>00:22</time>
            <w>Bin</w>
            <w>soooooo</w>
            <w>im</w>
            <w>stress</w>
            <w>gewesen</w>
            <w>ich</w>
            <w>Armer</w>
            <w>lol</w>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>In many CMC genres, especially in private chat, informal writing abounds
        including irregular spellings imitating spoken language, omitted word boundaries, and
        spurious boundaries leading to tokens separated in parts. For encoding these writing
        phenomena typical of CMC, the TEI attributes <att>norm</att> and <att>join</att> may be
        used.</p>
      <p>For example, the normalized spelling of an irregularly spelled word may be recorded using
        the <att>norm</att> attribute (from <ident type="class">att.linguistic</ident>):
        <!-- Note: the 2nd @norm in xmp below is correctly capitalized, because 
                   in German nouns are capitalized. —Syd, 2024-02-02 -->
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post generatedBy="human" rend="color:black" synch="#t010.b" who="#A03.b" xml:id="cmc_post_m16.b">
            <time> 00:22 </time>
            <w>Bin</w>
            <w norm="so">soooooo</w>
            <w>im</w>
            <w norm="Stress">stress</w>
            <w>gewesen</w>
            <w>ich</w>
            <w>Armer</w>
            <w>lol</w>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>When the boundaries between <gi>w</gi> elements are generally thought of as denoting word
        boundaries, we can keep track of boundaries not present in the source by using the
        <att>join</att> attribute, also from <ident type="class">att.linguistic</ident>. For
        example, for an original post that has nothing more than the token <q>Inmyoffice</q>, the
        following encoding demonstrates an interpretation that the single token represents the three
        words <q>In my office</q>:
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="en">
          <post>
            <w>In</w>
            <w join="left">my</w>
            <w join="left">office</w>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Alternatively, and especially when the normalization information pertains to more than one
        token, we can apply the notation using the elements <gi>reg</gi> and <gi>orig</gi>, related
        by a <gi>choice</gi> element as described in <ptr target="#COEDREG"/>. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post>
            <choice>
              <orig>
                <w pos="VAPPER" lemma="">hastes</w>
              </orig>
              <reg>
                <w pos="VAFIN" lemma="haben">hast</w>
                <w pos="PPER" lemma="du">du</w>
                <w pos="PPER" lemma="es">es</w>
              </reg>
            </choice>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>Other analysis attributes like <att>lemma</att> and <att>pos</att> (for part of speech) may
        be used as with traditional text. It is a matter of the tagset used to cater for POS
        categories that are appropriate for CMC. In the example below, for instance, the tag
          <val>AKW</val> stands for <gloss xml:lang="de" rend="italic">Aktionswort</gloss> (<gloss
          xml:lang="en">action word</gloss>, see <ptr type="cit" target="#STTS_IBK"/>).
          <!-- Note: the 2nd @norm in xmp below is correctly capitalized, because 
                     in German nouns are capitalized. —Syd, 2024-02-02 -->
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de">
          <post generatedBy="human" rend="color:black" synch="#t010.c" who="#A03.c" xml:id="cmc_post_m16.c">
            <time> 00:22 </time>
            <w lemma="sein" pos="VAFIN" xml:id="m16.t9">Bin</w>
            <w lemma="so" norm="so" pos="PTKIFG" xml:id="m16.t10">soooooo</w>
            <w lemma="in" pos="APPRART" xml:id="m16.t11">im</w>
            <w lemma="Stress" norm="Stress" pos="NN" xml:id="m16.t12">stress</w>
            <w lemma="sein" pos="VAPP" xml:id="m16.t13">gewesen</w>
            <w lemma="ich" pos="PPER" xml:id="m16.t14">ich</w>
            <w lemma="Armer" pos="NN" xml:id="m16.t15">Armer</w>
            <w lemma="lol" pos="AKW" xml:id="m16.t16">lol</w>
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
    <div xml:id="CMCnames">
      <head>Named Entities and Anonymization</head>
      <p>Named entities (NEs) may be marked up using <gi>name</gi> or the elements encoding different
        subcategories of names as described in <ptr target="#ND"/> such as <gi>surname</gi> or
          <gi>geogName</gi>, or <gi>rs</gi> for a general referencing string. In the following chat
        example (adapted from <ptr target="#BIB_DCK"/>), nicknames are linked to a <gi>person</gi>
        entry as shown in section <ptr target="#CMCParticipants"/> via the <att>ref</att> attribute.
          <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de" source="#BIB_DCK">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="system" rend="color:black" synch="#f2213001.t007"
            type="standard" who="#f2213001.A04" xml:id="f2213001.m27.eg35">
            <name ref="#f2213001.A04" type="NICK">
              <w lemma="Konstanze" pos="NE" xml:id="f2213001.m27.t1">Konstanze</w>
            </name>
            <w lemma="versuchen" pos="VVPP">versucht</w>
            <name ref="#f2213001.A03" type="NICK">
              <w lemma="Nasenloch" pos="NN">nasenloch</w>
            </name>
            <w lemma="die" pos="ART">den</w>
            <w lemma="Wunsch" pos="NN">wunsch</w>
            <w lemma="zu" pos="PTKZU">zu</w>
            <w lemma="erfüllen" pos="VVINF">erfüllen</w>
            <!-- ... -->
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>In the following version of the same chat snippet, the text strings with the nicknames
        have been replaced by category label strings for the purpose of anonymization. <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de" source="#BIB_DCK">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="system" rend="color:black" synch="#f2213001a.t007"
            type="standard" who="#f2213001a.A04" xml:id="f2213001a.m27.eg35">
            <name ref="#f2213001a.A04" type="NICK">
              <w pos="NE" xml:id="f2213001a.m27.t1">
                <gap reason="anonymization" unit="token" quantity="1"/>
                <supplied reason="anonymization">[_FEMALE-PARTICIPANT-A04_]</supplied></w>
            </name>
            <w lemma="versuchen" pos="VVPP">versucht</w>
            <name ref="#f2213001a.A03" type="NICK">
              <w pos="NN">
                <gap reason="anonymization" unit="token" quantity="1"/>
                <supplied reason="anonymization">[_PARTICIPANT-A04_]</supplied></w>
            </name>
            <w lemma="die" pos="ART">den</w>
            <w lemma="Wunsch" pos="NN">wunsch</w>
            <w lemma="zu" pos="PTKZU">zu</w>
            <w lemma="erfüllen" pos="VVINF">erfüllen</w>
            <!-- ... -->
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
      <p>In the preceding example, pairs of a <gi>gap</gi> and a <gi>supplied</gi> element encode
        the fact that some substring has been removed and replaced with another string for
        anonymization purposes. Note that in this example, the <gi>name</gi> and the <gi>w</gi>
        elements and their attributes also provide some categorical information about what has been
        removed. Using <gi>gap</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> to record the anonymization is especially
        recommendable when the original name or referencing string has been
          <soCalled>pseudonymized</soCalled>, i.e. replaced by a different referencing string of the
        same ontological category (such as replacing the female name
          <mentioned>Konstanze</mentioned> by the female name <mentioned>Kornelia.</mentioned>). In
        that case, the markup would be the only place where it can be seen that a pseudonymization
        has been carried out, as in the following version of the example.</p>
      <p>
        <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:lang="de" source="#BIB_DCK">
          <post modality="written" generatedBy="system" rend="color:black" synch="#f2213001p.t007"
            type="standard" who="#f2213001p.A04" xml:id="f2213001p.m27.eg35">
            <name ref="#f2213001p.A04" type="NICK">
              <w pos="NE" xml:id="f2213001p.m27.t1">
                <gap reason="pseudonymization" unit="token" quantity="1"/>
                <supplied reason="pseudonymization">Kornelia</supplied>
              </w>
            </name>
            <w lemma="versuchen" pos="VVPP">versucht</w>
            <!-- the rest of the post -->
          </post>
        </egXML>
      </p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div xml:id="CMCmodule">
    <head>The TEI CMC Module</head>
    <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components: <moduleSpec
        ident="cmc">
        <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2021-09-07">Computer-mediated communication</desc>
        <idno type="FPI">TEI-CMC</idno>
      </moduleSpec> The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
        <ptr target="#STIN"/>.</p>
    <specGrp xml:id="CMCincludes">
      <!-- att.cmc.xml and model.cmc.xml are included from ST -->
      <xi:include href="../../Specs/macro.specialPara.cmc.xml"/>
      <xi:include href="../../Specs/post.xml"/>
    </specGrp>
  </div>
</div>
