<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium.
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
-->

<?xml-model href="http://jenkins.tei-c.org/job/TEIP5-dev/lastSuccessfulBuild/artifact/P5/release/xml/tei/odd/p5.nvdl" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/nvdl/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" type="div1"
    xml:id="CMC">
    <head>Computer-mediated Communication</head>


    <div type="div2" xml:id="CMCoverview">

        <head>General Considerations and Overview</head>

        <p>This chapter describes the TEI encoding mechanisms available for textual data which
            represents discourse from genres of computer-mediated communication (CMC). It is
            intended to provide the basic framework needed to encode CMC corpora.</p>

        <p>While the term “computer-mediated communication”, in a broader sense, might be used to
            describe all sorts of communications between humans which are mediated by digital
            technologies (for example, text on web pages, dialogic written interaction in chats and
            forums, the spoken language in internet video meetings), herein we use the term to apply
            to forms of communication which share the following features:</p>
        <p>
            <list rend="bulleted">
                <item>they are <emph rend="italic">dialogic</emph>;</item>
                <item>they are organized in the form of interactional sequences so that each
                    communicative move determines the context for subsequent moves (taken by another
                    interlocutor) and reacts on the context created by a prior move;</item>
                <item>the communicative moves which may be put into practice as posts (cf. <ptr
                        target="#CMCcmcpost"/>), utterances, onscreen activities or bodily
                    activities exerted by a virtual avatar are created and displayed using <emph
                        rend="italic">computer technology</emph> (keyboard, mouse, speech-to-text
                    conversion software, monitor or screen) and mediated over a <emph rend="italic"
                        >computer network</emph> (typically the internet).</item>
            </list>
        </p>

        <p>Computer-mediated communication is conducted using</p>

        <list rend="simple">
            <item>communication technologies such as chats, messengers, online forums,</item>
            <item>social media platforms and applications such as Twitter, Facebook, Instagram or
                WhatsApp,</item>
            <item>the communication functions of collaborative platforms and projects (e.g. in the
                Wikipedia or in online learning environments),</item>
            <item>3D environments (e.g. Second Life, gaming environments),</item>
            <item>or similar technologies and services on the internet.</item>
        </list>

        <p>CMC is, by default, multimodal. Whereas early CMC systems (e.g. the prototypes of today’s
            chat and messaging applications or Usenet developed in the 70s and 80s) were completely
            ASCII-based, the lion’s share of contemporary CMC technologies and applications allows
            for the combination of different semiotic resources (e.g. written or spoken language
            with graphic icons and images) and even for the combined use of different CMC
            technologies in one and the same platform (e.g. combined use of an audio connection, a
            chat system and a 3D interface in which users control a virtual avatar as in many
            MMORPGs or in virtual worlds such as Second Life).</p>

    </div>

    <div type="div2">
        <head>Basic units of CMC</head>

        <p>This chapter describes the encoding mechanisms for the basic units of CMC and for their
            combined use to encode CMC data. </p>
        <p>We refer to units which are produced by an interlocutor to contribute to an ongoing CMC
            interaction or joint CMC activity as <emph rend="italic">basic CMC units</emph>.
            Contributions to an ongoing interaction are produced to perform a move as part of the
            further development of the interactional sequence, for instance in chats or forum
            discussions. In some cases contributions to joint CMC activities may not all directly be
            interactional but part of a collaborative project of the involved individuals, for
            instance editing activities in a shared text editor or whiteboard in parallel with an
            ongoing CMC interaction (chat, audio or video conference) in the same CMC environment in
            which these editing activities are discussed by the collaborators. </p>
        <p>Basic units to CMC can be described according to three criteria: (i) the temporal
            properties of how these contributions are produced by their creators, transmitted via
            CMC systems and made accessible for the recipients; (ii) whether the unit as a whole is
            realised in a verbal or nonverbal mode; (iii) for verbal units: whether the unit is
            realised in the written or spoken mode. A taxonomy of basic CMC units resulting from
            these criteria is given in Fig. <ptr target="Images/cmcunits-taxonomy.png"/>
        </p>

        <figure xml:id="cmcunits-taxonomy">
            <graphic url="Images/cmcunits-taxonomy.png"/>
            <head>Taxonomy of basic CMC units.<ptr type="cit"
                    target="BIB-Bibliography.xml/#BIB_CMC_Core"/></head>
        </figure>

        <p>Some further elaborations on the <ptr target="#cmcunits-taxonomy"/>:</p>

        <p>The most important distinction refers to the temporal nature of units exchanged via CMC
            technologies. The left part of the taxonomy describes units that are performed (=
            producer) and perceived (= recipient) as a continuous stream of behaviour. Units of that
            type can be performed as</p>

        <list rend="bulleted">
            <item><emph rend="bold">spoken utterances,</emph> i.e. stretches of speech which are
                produced to perform a speaker turn in a conversation,</item>
            <item><emph rend="bold">bodily activity,</emph> i.e. nonverbal behavior (gesture, gaze)
                produced to perform a speaker turn, either performed by the real body of an
                interlocutor (e.g. in a video conference) or through the virtual avatar of an
                interlocutor in a 3D environment, </item>
            <item><emph rend="bold">onscreen activities,</emph> i.e. non-bodily forms of behaviour
                that are transmitted to the group of interacting or coworking participants, for
                instance the editing of content in a shared text editor which can be perceived by
                the other parties simultaneously (as may be the case in learning or collaboration
                environments).</item>
        </list>

        <p>The right part of the taxonomy describes units in which the production, transmission and
            perception of contributions to CMC interactions are organised in a strictly consecutive
            order: The – verbal, nonverbal or multimodal – content of the contribution has to be
            produced before it can be transmitted via the internet and made available on the
            computer monitor or mobile screen of any other party as a preserved and persistent unit.
            We term this type of unit a <emph rend="italic">post</emph>. Posts occur in two
            different variants:</p>
        <list rend="bulleted">
            <item>as <emph rend="bold">written / multimodal posts,</emph> which are produced with an
                editor form that is designed for the composition of stretches of written text. Most
                of contemporary post-based CMC technologies provide features for the inclusion of
                graphic and audiovisual content (emoji graphics, images, videos) into posts and even
                to produce posts without verbal content (which then may exist only of emojis, an
                image or a video file). Written / multimodal posts are the standard format for user
                contributions in primarily text-based CMC genres and applications such as chat, SMS,
                WhatsApp, Instagram, Facebook, Twitter, online forums or Wikipedia talk
                pages.</item>
            <item>as <emph rend="bold">audio posts</emph>, which are produced using a recording
                function. In contrast to CMC units of the type <emph rend="italic">utterance</emph>
                which are produced and transmitted simultaneously, audio posts first have to be
                recorded as a whole and are then transmitted – as audio files – via the internet;
                the availability of the recording is indicated in the screen protocol by a
                template-generated, visual post; the recipients can play the recording (repeatedly)
                by activating the play button displayed in the post on the screen. Examples of CMC
                applications that implement audio posts are WhatsApp or RocketChat.</item>
        </list>

        <p>Three of the four basic CMC units described above can be represented with models that are
            described elsewhere in the TEI Guidelines:</p>

        <table>
            <row rend="underline">
                <cell>CMC unit</cell>
                <cell>Type of corpus data</cell>
                <cell> </cell>
                <cell>TEI P5 element</cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>utterance</cell>
                <cell>transcription of speech</cell>
                <cell>&#x21D2;</cell>
                <cell><gi>u</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>bodily activity</cell>
                <cell>texual description</cell>
                <cell>&#x21D2;</cell>
                <cell><gi>kinesic</gi></cell>
            </row>
            <row>
                <cell>onscreen activity</cell>
                <cell>textual description</cell>
                <cell>&#x21D2;</cell>
                <cell><gi>incident</gi></cell>
            </row>
        </table>

        <p><gi>u</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>, and <gi>incident</gi> are encoding elements which are not
            specific to CMC but which are used to encode textual transcriptions of spoken turns,
            bodily activity and onscreen activity that occur in CMC data. The unit post, which is
            specific to CMC, is introduced in Sect. <ptr target="#CMCcmcpost"/>.</p>
    </div>


    <div xml:id="CMCmeta">
        <head>Documenting CMC (and providing general meta data)</head>
        <?tei winita 
        Still an open issue. How to document the source (e.g. database dump, web scraping, query parameters) of the current CMC encodings
        * Source: made tag abuse for documenting the source: <biblStruct> or <recordingStmt>
        * Timeline: in textDesc/interaction/
        * Participant description (in profile description)
        ?>
    </div>


    <div xml:id="CMCcmc">
        <head>Encoding Unique to CMC</head>
        <?tei winita
            * Some introductory sentence
            * specList (will automatically insert post including its attributes)
            * Cf. https://tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-specList.html 
        ?>
        <p>This chapter describes elements, attributes, and models which are unique to CMC and the
            TEI CMC module.</p>
        <p>
            <specList>
                <specDesc key="post" atts="modality replyTo indentLevel"/>
            </specList></p>

        <div xml:id="CMCcmcpost">
            <head>CMC Posts</head>

            <p>The element <gi>post</gi> is unique to computer-mediated communication (CMC). A post
                is defined as a written (or spoken) contribution to an ongoing CMC interaction which
                has been composed (or recorded) by its author in its entirety as part of a private
                activity, and has been transmitted through the internet and is made available on the
                monitor or screen of the other parties en bloc. Posts occur in a broad range of
                written CMC genres, including (but not limited to) ‘messages’ in chats and WhatsApp
                dialogues, tweets in Twitter timelines, comments on Facebook pages, posts in forum
                threads, comments or contributions to discussions on Wikipedia talk pages or in the
                comments section of weblogs.</p>

            <p>Posts can be either written or spoken:</p>

            <list>
                <item><emph rend="bold">written/multimodal posts</emph>: In the majority of CMC
                    technologies they are composed as stretches of text using an entry form on the
                    screen and the keyboard or a speech-to-text conversion software. In many cases
                    the technology allows authors to include or embed graphics (emijos, images),
                    video files and hyperlinks into their posts.</item>
                <item><emph rend="bold">audio posts</emph>: A growing number of CMC technologies,
                    e.g. messenger software such as WhatsApp or RocketChat, allow for an
                    alternative, spoken production of posts providing a recording function which
                    allows users to record a stretch of spoken language and transmit the resulting
                    audio file to the other parties.</item>
            </list>

            <p> The element post may co-occur with <gi>u</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>, <gi>incident</gi>,
                or other existing TEI elements within a <gi>div</gi>, or directly within the
                    <gi>body</gi>, and may contain headings, paragraphs, openers, closers, or
                salutations.</p>

            <p>As a member of the TEI attribute classes <ident type="class">att.ascribed</ident>,
                    <ident type="class">att.canonical</ident>, <ident type="class"
                    >att.datable</ident>, <ident type="class">att.global</ident>, <ident
                    type="class">att.timed</ident>, and <ident type="class">att.typed</ident>, posts
                may take a variety of attributes. Common attributes used in conjunction with
                    <gi>post</gi> include <att>who</att>, <att>synch</att>, <att>type</att>,
                    <att>subtype</att>, <att>rend</att>, and <att>xml:id</att>.</p>

        </div>

        <div xml:id="CMCcmcpostatts">
            <head>Attributes specific to CMC <gi>post</gi></head>

            <p>Three attributes pertain specifically to <gi>post</gi>: <specList>
                    <specDesc key="post" atts="modality replyTo indentLevel"/>
                </specList> The <att>modality</att> attribute is required on the <gi>post</gi>
                element in order to describe the creation mechanism used in the CMC environment. The
                type of the content (i.e., whether the content of the post is written, an image, a
                video clip, etc.) is indicated by the child elements of the <gi>post</gi>. For
                example a written post from WhatsApp might include an audio-visual clip copied into
                the post, and in such case may not actually have any writing. Such a post is still
                considered in the “written” modality. <egXML
                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06"
                        xml:id="cmcEG01m12">
                        <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
                            <desc>Screenshot von der Google-Suche nach dem Friseur "Haarraum" mit
                                der Durchschnitts-Google-Bewertung (4,5 von 5 Sternen), der Adresse,
                                der Telefonnummer und den Öffnungszeiten</desc>
                        </figure>
                    </post>
                </egXML>
            </p>
            <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute is used to capture information drawn from the
                original metadata associated with a post that asserts to which previous post the
                current post is a response, or to which previous post it refers. This metadata is
                included by many, but not all, CMC environments, when the user executes a formal
                reply action (e.g., by clicking or tapping a reply button). This attribute should
                not be used to encode interpreted or inferred reply relations based on linguistic
                cues or discourse markers.</p>
            <p>The <att>replyTo</att> attribute indicates the replied-to or referred-to posts by
                providing one or more pointers to them. For example: <egXML
                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="p28"
                        who="#u7" replyTo="#p1" when-iso="2015-07-29T21:44">
                        <p>Es hat den Anschein, als wäre bei BER durchaus große Kompetenz am Bau,
                            allerdings nicht in Form von Handwerkern….</p>
                        <p>http://www.zeit.de/2015/29/imtech-flughafen-berlin-ber-verzoegerung/komplettansicht</p>
                    </post>
                    <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="p29"
                        who="#u8" replyTo="#p28" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:11">
                        <p>Nein Nein, an den Handwerkern kann es rein strukturel nicht gelegen
                            haben. Niemand lässt seine Handwerker auf der Baustelle derart allein.
                            Zudem gibt es höchstoffizielle “Abnahmen” von Bauabschnitten/phasen.
                            Welcher Mangel auch bestanden hatte, er hätte Zeitnah auffallen
                            müssen.</p>
                        <p>Uuups, für Imtek hab ich mal in einer Nachunternehmerfirma gearbeitet.
                            Imtek is offenbar ein universeler Bauträger, der alles baut.</p>
                    </post>
                    <post type="comment" modality="written" generatedBy="human" xml:id="p30"
                        who="#u8" replyTo="#p29" when-iso="2015-07-30T19:26">
                        <p>Stahlkunstruktionen dacht ich mal, was die bauen – oder bauen lassen.</p>
                        <p>Das ist schon ein übles Ding. Die Ausschreibungenund Angebote sind
                            unauffällig, aber wenn Unregelmässigkeiten auftreten (im Bauverlauf)
                            dann gibt es die saftigen Rechnungen. Da steht dann der Bauherr da und
                            fragt sich, wie er denn so schnell einen fähigen Ersatz herbekommt. Und
                            diese Frage erübrigt sich meist, weil der Markt der Baufirmen das nicht
                            hergibt – weil tendenziel 100 % Auslastung. (und noch schlimmer:
                            Absprachen) Was auch Folge des Marktdrucks gewesen war.</p>
                    </post>
                </egXML> Example: Three blog comments where, by the reply references in the source,
                the first is a reply to the initial blog post (not part of the example), the second
                is a reply to the first, and the third is a reply to the second. <?tei winitia
                    BIBL: should refer to the TEI encoding of a section of the blog page 
                    https://scilogs.spektrum.de/wild-dueck-blog/scheinzwerge-oder-viele-probleme-werden-groesser-wenn-man-sie-anpackt-griechenland/
                ?>
            </p>
            <p>In the CMC genre of Wiki talk, users insert their contribution to a discussion by
                modifying the wiki page of the discussion — the talk page. Since there is no
                technical reply action available in wiki software, users apply textual indentation
                in the wiki code to indicate a reply to a previous message, and a threaded structure
                is formed by a series of such indentations. The attribute <att>indentLevel</att>
                records the level of indentation, that is the nesting depth of the current post in
                such a thread-like structure (as defined by its author and in relation to the
                standard level of non-indentation which is to be encoded as
                    <code>indentLevel="0"</code>). It is used in wiki talk corpora but may also be
                used for other threaded genres e.g. when HTML was used as a source. <egXML
                    xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                    <div type="thread" xml:id="i.10031_19">
                        <head>[[WP:AUTO]]</head>
                        <post indentLevel="0" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-07T03:09+00"
                            who="#WU00010808" xml:id="i.10031_19_1">
                            <p> I would kindly request from Mr. Meyer to allow others to edit the
                                [...]</p>
                        </post>
                        <post indentLevel="1" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T03:49+00"
                            who="#WU00010804" xml:id="i.10031_19_2">
                            <p>I dont agree, this article is not about Dr. Meyer, [...]</p>
                        </post>
                        <post indentLevel="2" modality="written" when-iso="2006-09-08T04:16+00"
                            who="#WU00005520" xml:id="i.10031_19_3">
                            <p>Why don't you read the policy. [...]</p>
                        </post>
                        <post indentLevel="3" modality="written" when-iso="2006-11-01T22:58+00"
                            who="#WU00010815" xml:id="i.10031_19_4">
                            <p>Because the policy makes no sense, [...]</p>
                        </post>
                    </div>
                </egXML> Example: File 10031.tei.xml from the EFG Wikipedia corpus 2019. Exchange
                between four different users. (Page Talk:Eiffel (programming language) from the
                English Wikipedia) </p>
        </div>

        <div xml:id="CMCcmcatts">
            <head>Attributes for general CMC encoding</head>
            <?tei winita discussion of @generatedBy ?>

            <p>The attribute <att>generatedBy</att> is unique to CMC encoding, too. But unlike
                    <att>modality</att>, <att>replyTo</att>, and <att>indentLevel</att> as described
                above, it pertains not only to the <gi>post</gi> element, but to all its possible
                children as well. </p>

            <p>This means that <gi>post</gi> and all its possible child elements are members of the
                    <ident type="class">att.cmc</ident> class and share the attribute
                    <att>generatedBy</att>: <specList>
                    <specDesc key="att.cmc" atts="generatedBy"/>
                </specList>
            </p>

            <p><att>generatedBy</att> may indicate, for <gi>post</gi> or any of its children how its
                content was generated in a CMC environment i.e. whether it was created by a human
                user, whether it was generated by the respective CMC system (e.g. a status message,
                a timestamp), or whether the user activated a template that subsequently generated
                the textual content, such as in a signature. The attribute is optional, and it might
                not be appropriate to use it when all text content has been created in the same mode
                and no distinction needs to be made. A list of suggested values for
                    <att>generatedBy</att> follows: <list type="gloss">
                    <label>human</label>
                    <item>when then content of the respective element was “naturally” typed or
                        spoken by a human user (cf. the chat posts in Example <ptr
                            target="#ex.haarschnitt"/>)</item>
                    <label>template</label>
                    <item>when the content of the respective element was generated after a human
                        user activated a template for its insertion (cf. <gi>signed</gi> i.e.
                        signatures in wiki talk in Listing 2)</item>
                    <label>system</label>
                    <item>when the content of the respective element was generated by the system,
                        i.e. the CMC environment (cf. the system message in an IRC chat in Listing
                        6)</item>
                    <label>bot</label>
                    <item>when the content of the respective element was generated by a bot i.e. a
                        non-human agent, mostly external to the CMC environment</item>
                    <label>unspecified</label>
                    <item>when it is unspecified or unknown how the content of the respective
                        element was generated (cf. the <gi>post</gi> of the retweet p2 in Listing
                        5)</item>
                </list>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.haarschnitt">
                    <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t003" who="#A02"
                        xml:id="m8"> Da kostet ein Haarschnitt 50 € <figure type="emoji"
                            generatedBy="template">
                            <desc type="meaning">face screaming in fear</desc>
                            <desc type="unicode">U+1F631</desc>
                        </figure>
                    </post>
                </egXML>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.naturally">
                    <post mode="written" xml:id="p4" indentLevel="0" who="#u005" synch="#t005">
                        <p>I'm not sure that this is a proper criterium, or even what this means.
                            What if we set an explosion that breaks a comet into two pieces? What if
                            we build a moon? Cheers, </p><signed generatedBy="template"
                            rend="inline"><ref target="/wiki/User:Greenodd">Greenodd</ref> (<ref
                                target="/wiki/User_talk:Greenodd">talk</ref>) <time>01:00, 21 July
                                2011 (UTC)</time></signed>
                    </post>
                </egXML>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.grunzen">
                    <post mode="written" key="1043764753502486528" type="tweet" generatedBy="human"
                        synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t001" xml:id="p1" who="#u1" xml:lang="deu">
                        <time generatedBy="system"> 12:31 </time> Heute mit super Unterstützung, wir
                        grunzen, wenn die Zeit vorbei ist. <ref type="hashtag"
                            target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash">#bcrn18</ref>
                        <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wikidach?src=hash"
                            >#wikidach</ref> PS: Die beiden brauchen noch Namen. Hinweise dazu am
                        Empfang abgeben! <ref type="twitter-account"
                            target="https://twitter.com/AndreLo79">@AndreLo79</ref>
                        <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
                            <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DnwygdSW4AAoTUn.jpg:large"/>
                        </figure>
                    </post>
                </egXML>
                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.listPerson">
                    <listPerson>
                        <person xml:id="SYSTEM">
                            <persName>system</persName>
                        </person>
                        <!--  -->
                    </listPerson>
                    <!--  -->
                    <post type="event" generatedBy="system" who="#SYSTEM" rend="color:navy">
                        <p>
                            <name type="nickname" corresp="#A07">Interseb</name> betritt den Raum.
                        </p>
                    </post>
                </egXML>
            </p>
        </div>
    </div>


    <div xml:id="CMCrecs">
        <head>Recommendations for encoding CMC</head>
        <?tei winita
            Discussion of phenomena — short discussions, maybe with some code snippets, and references to the other chapters where the TEI encoding is introduced;
        ?>
        <div xml:id="CMCemos">
            <head>Emojis and Emoticons</head>
            <?tei winita add source for example in TEI <example> with ref to bibl element ?>


            <p>Emojis are iconic or symbolic, invariant graphic units which the users of social
                media applications such as WhatsApp, Instagram or Twitter can select from a menu or
                ‘emoji keyboard’ and embed into their written posts. Examples are &#x1F601;, &#x1F637;, &#xFE0F;, 
                &#x1F631;, or &#x1F648;🙈. An emoji is encoded by a single or several Unicode character(s) which is
                intended to be mapped directly to a pictorial symbol. </p>

            <p>Emoticons predate emojis and are created as combinations of ASCII punctuation and
                other characters using the keyboard. Examples are &lt;:-)&gt;, &lt;;-)&gt;,
                &lt;:-(&gt;, &lt;:-x&gt;, &lt;\O/&gt; or &lt;Oo&gt;. They first occured in newsgroup
                (cf. original newsgroup post by Scott Fahlman of 19-Sep-82) and then frequently in
                chat communication around the mid-1980s. An emoticon typically consists of several
                Unicode characters (from the ASCII subset) in a row, each of which has an intended
                use other than as part of an emoticon. </p>

            <p>Both emoticons and emojis may be simply transcribed as a sequence of characters. As
                with any other characters, they may be entered as numeric character entities if this
                is more convenient. (E.g., <mentioned>&#x01F637;</mentioned> might be transcribed as
                    <code>&amp;#x01F637;</code> in any XML document, including a TEI document; see
                    <ptr target="#D4-44"/>.)</p>

            <p> When the text of a post is being tokenized, e.g. for linguistic analysis, it may be
                useful to encode the emoticon or emoji as a separate token. In such cases elements
                like <gi>w</gi> and <gi>c</gi> may be used for tokenization, and the <att>pos</att>
                attribute may be used to indicate that the encoded string is an emoji or an
                emoticon. (See 18.1 Linguistic Segment Categories.) </p>

            <p>For example, the source post “da bin ich nicht so empfindlich ;-)” ends with an
                emoticon, and might be encoded as follows: </p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03"
                    xml:id="lscLB.m6a">   <w pos="ADV">Klar</w>   <w pos="EMOIMG">☺</w>
                </post>
            </egXML>


            <p>For example, the source post “da bin ich nicht so empfindlich ;)” ends with an
                emoticon, and might be encoded as follows:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post>
                    <w pos="ADV">da</w>
                    <w pos="VAFIN">bin</w>
                    <w pos="PPER">ich</w>
                    <w pos="PTKNEG">nicht</w>
                    <w pos="ADV">so</w>
                    <w pos="ADJD">empfindlich</w>
                    <w pos="EMOASC">;)</w>
                </post>
            </egXML>

            <p>Similarly, the source post “Klar☺” might be encoded as follows:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03"
                    xml:id="lscLB.m6a">
                    <w pos="ADV">Klar</w>
                    <w pos="EMOIMG">☺</w>
                </post>
            </egXML>

            <p>The values of <att>pos</att> in the above examples are from the STTS_IBK Tagset for
                German (see <ptr type="cit" target="#STTS_IBK"/>), which includes tags for
                interaction signs in CMC such as ‘EMOASC’ for an ASCII-based emoticon and ‘EMOIMG’
                for an icon-based emoji.</p>
            <p>Alternatively, e.g. when <gi>w</gi> is not regularly used to encode tokens in the TEI
                document, <gi>c</gi> can be used to mark an emoji. For example, the source post “Da
                kostet ein Haarschnitt 50 € &#x01F631;” might be encoded as follows:</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post xml:lang="de"> Da kostet ein Haarschnitt 50 € <c type="emoji" ana="#fsif"
                        generatedBy="template">&#x01F631;</c>
                </post>
            </egXML>

            <p>Sometimes, e.g. when the source of the TEI document was a web page in HTML, the
                emojis may occur only as an icon graphic in the source. In that case, they can be
                encoded in TEI using <gi>figure</gi>. The corresponding unicode character can then
                be recorded in the <gi>desc</gi> element by the encoder if desired. </p>

            <p>Source text: ... ich überlege noch &#x1F648;</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#lscLB.t004" who="#lscLB.A03"
                    xml:id="lscLB.m6b"> ... ich überlege noch <figure type="emoji"
                        generatedBy="template">
                        <graphic url="fig1.png"/>
                        <desc type="gloss">see no evil monkey</desc>
                        <desc type="unicode">U+1F648</desc>
                    </figure>
                </post>
            </egXML>
        </div>

        <div xml:id="CMCgraphic">

            <head>Post with graphics</head>

            <p>A post in a CMC interaction may contain a graphic in addition to some text or even
                contain only a graphic (without any text). As explained in [REF section on
                @modality], the modality of such a post should be considered as “written”. To encode
                the graphic information, the TEI element <gi>figure</gi> should be used in the
                appropriate place.</p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" source="#UND">
                <post modality="written" generatedBy="human" synch="#t005" who="#A06"
                    xml:id="cmcEG08m12">
                    <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
                        <desc>Screenshot von der Google-Suche nach dem Friseur "Haarraum" mit der
                            Durchschnitts-Google-Bewertung (4,5 von 5 Sternen), der Adresse, der
                            Telefonnummer und den Öffnungszeiten</desc>
                    </figure>
                </post>
            </egXML>
            <p>Example: A private chat post that contained only a screenshot of a google search
                result for a hairdresser. A link to the graphic file itself is not included because
                it has not been retained for the corpus. </p>
            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                <post type="tweet" key="1043823300479258624" modality="written" generatedBy="human"
                    synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t006" xml:id="p8" who="#u1" xml:lang="de">
                    <time generatedBy="system"> 16:24 </time> Bro Tri-Engel...so hab ich mir das
                    vorgestellt!!! @AndreLo79 #bcrn18 #wikidach @Heiko komm' mal Twitter! #Engel
                        <figure type="image" generatedBy="human">
                        <graphic url="https://pbs.twimg.com/media/DnxnwN9XsAEHXw2.jpg:large"/>
                    </figure>
                </post>
            </egXML>
            <p>Example: Encoding of a tweet that contains some text (including hashtags and
                mentions) and a graphic. The <gi>graphic</gi> element retains the url of the graphic
                on the web just as in the source. </p>
        </div>

        <div xml:id="CMCcirculation">
            <head>Circulation</head>
            <!-- ToDo: Check twi21 corpus -->
            <p>By the example of twitter posts (tweets), we would like to give some recommendations
                on how to encode features of the circulation of posts, such as IDs, re-posts
                (retweets), hashtags, and mentions.</p>
            <p>First, we encode the type of post ("tweet") in the global attribute <att>type</att>,
                and if it is a specific subtype of tweet, such as a retweet, that will be encoded in
                the attribute <att>subtype</att> at the <gi>post</gi> element accordingly</p>
            <p>Second, we distinguish between the ID that the post gets as part of the text
                collection (e.g. a corpus or a dataset), and the original Tweet-ID as supplied by
                twitter. The collection-related post ID should go in the global attribute
                    <att>xml:id</att>, while the original tweet ID should go in the canonical
                attribute <att>key</att>. </p>
            <p>Third, a retweet and its corresponding retweeted tweet are encoded as two separate
                posts each with its own set of attributes. The post representing the retweet itself
                is specified for <att>subtype</att>=<val>retweet</val> and does not contain or
                duplicate the content of the retweeted tweet. Instead it refers to the ID of the
                retweeted tweet via the pointing attribute <att>ref</att>. All original content of
                the retweet goes in the content of the <gi>post</gi> element. In the example <ptr
                    target="#ex.tweets"/>, the retweeted tweet happens to be a retweet itself. </p>
            <p>Fourth, hashtags occur on the in the body of tweets and are links like any other
                hyperlink and should be encoded using the element <gi>ref</gi>. The <att>type</att>
                attribute of the ref should contain the value <val>hashtag</val>, the
                    <att>target</att> attribute should contain the URL of the hashtag, and the
                content of <gi>ref</gi>should be the string of the hashtag itself.</p>

            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:id="ex.tweets">
                <post mode="written" key="1043796550101716993" generatedBy="human" type="tweet"
                    subtype="retweet" who="#u1" xml:id="p4" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t004" ref="#p5"
                    xml:lang="de"> Ich mich auch? <ref type="hashtag"
                        target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/dynamicduo?src=hash">#dynamicduo</ref>
                    <ref type="hashtag"
                        target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wirk%C3%BCmmernunsauchumIhrenEmpfang?src=hash"
                        >#wirkümmernunsauchumIhrenEmpfang</ref>
                    <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash"
                        >#bcrn18</ref>
                    <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/wikidach?src=hash"
                        >#wikidach</ref>
                </post>
                <post mode="written" key="1043796093786566656" generatedBy="human" type="tweet"
                    subtype="retweet" who="#u2" synch="#tweetsbcrn18.t003" xml:lang="de" xml:id="p5">
                    <time generatedBy="system"> 14:35 </time> Immer wieder gerne. Kann ich mich
                    schon für nächstes Jahr als Empfangs- <ref type="hashtag"
                        target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Engel?src=hash">#Engel</ref> für das
                    nächste BarCamp bewerben <figure type="emoji" generatedBy="template">
                        <desc type="meaning">zany face</desc>
                        <desc type="unicode">U+1F92A</desc>
                    </figure>
                    <ref type="hashtag" target="https://twitter.com/hashtag/bcrn18?src=hash"
                        >#bcrn18</ref>
                    <trailer>
                        <!-- CoMeRe Style encoding of the counts of favouriting and likes: -->
                        <fs>
                            <f name="favoritecount">
                                <numeric value="4"/>
                            </f>
                        </fs>
                    </trailer>
                </post>
            </egXML>
        </div>


    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMChow">
        <head>“Putting it all together” – genre specific examples</head>
        <?tei winita
        * Twitter
        * WhatsApp
        * Wikipedia talk
        * NB: not necessarily add complete examples (whole TEI file) but rather snippets
      ?>
    </div>

    <div xml:id="CMCmodule">
        <head>The TEI CMC Module</head>
        <p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:
                <moduleSpec ident="cmc">
                <desc xml:lang="en" versionDate="2021-09-07">Elements, Attributes, and Models for
                    Computer-mediated communication (CMC). This module collects all cmc-specific
                    extensions. Hence these will only be added to a TEI schema when this module is
                    selected in a customisation.</desc>
                <idno type="FPI">TEI-CMC</idno>
            </moduleSpec> The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described
            in <ptr target="#STIN"/>.</p>
        <specGrp xml:id="CMCincludes">
            <xi:include href="../../Specs/att.cmc.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="../../Specs/macro.specialPara.cmc.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="../../Specs/model.cmc.xml"/>
            <xi:include href="../../Specs/post.xml"/>
        </specGrp>
    </div>
</div>
