<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<div1 xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="Faisal" xml:id="COL">
<head>Colophon</head>
<p>The text of this manual was prepared electronically on a variety of
systems.  Most sections were originally drafted by members of the work
groups and working committees of the TEI; all have been revised by the
editors to achieve greater uniformity of style and greater consistency
in the tag set.</p>

<p>Tags from the schema documented here were introduced in the text by
the original drafters of the sections or by the editors, using
standard text editors on various systems over the years, include VMS,
VM/CMS, PC-DOS, Macintosh, Windows, Solaris and Linux systems.  The
resulting document fragments were validated using many different SGML
and XML tools over the years, starting with VM2 (a markup validator
distributed with the public-domain ARCSGML materials), sgmls (parser
built on the same engine), Markit, Checkmark, XGML Validator, James
Clark's nsgmls SGML/XML validator, Richard Tobin's rxp XML validator,
Michael Kay's Saxon XSLT implementation, and Daniel Veillard's
libxml2. The validated files, which contained both the prose
description of the tag set and the reference materials, were then
processed with ad hoc programs written originally in Spitbol and then
rewritten in XSLT to produce separate documents for the text of the
Guidelines, the reference section, and the schemas; the documentation
was then transformed to variously Waterloo GML, LaTeX, and XSL FO for
formatting and printing, and to HTML and XHTML for the web.</p>

<p>The camera ready copy of the 1992–1996 versions of
this document was produced by Waterloo Script
GML running on the IBM 3090 at the University of Illinois at Chicago
Academic Computer Center (to which thanks), and using a set of
macros extending the GML Starter Set of tags with specialized tags
designed for this document. Later interim versions were produced by a
translation to LaTeX.</p>

<p>The 2001 P4 release of the Guidelines was typeset by transforming
the TEI XML source to an XML file containing XSL Formatting Objects,
which was then formatted using the PassiveTeX implementation of XSL
Formatting Objects by David Carlisle and Sebastian Rahtz. The
underling engine was the pdfTeX extension of TeX by Han The Thanh. The
main font used was Times Roman, with Computer Modern Sans-serif and
Lucida-Sans Typewriter as needed.
<?odds date?>
</p>

<p>The 2006 P5 release of the Guidelines was formatted to XHTML
using a library of XSLT stylesheets, and PDF versions for printing
were producing by conversions to LaTeX markup, processing using
XeLaTeX.</p> 

</div1>
