<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<div1 xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="Faisal" xml:id="COL">
<head>Colophon</head>
<p>The text of this manual was prepared electronically on a variety of
systems.  Most sections were originally drafted by members of the work
groups and working committees of the TEI; all have been revised by the
editors to achieve greater uniformity of style and greater consistency
in the tag set.</p>
<p>SGML tags from a preliminary version of the tag set documented here were
introduced in the text by the original drafters of the sections or by
the editors, using standard text editors on VMS, VM/CMS, PC-DOS, and
Apple Macintosh systems.  The resulting SGML document fragments were
validated using VM2 (a markup validator distributed with the
public-domain ARCSGML materials), sgmls (a parser built on the same
engine), Markit, Checkmark, XGML Validator, and/or
Author/Editor.  The validated files, which contained both the prose
description of the tag set and the reference materials, were then
processed with ad hoc programs written in Spitbol to produce separate
SGML documents for the prose, the reference section, and the DTDs; these
SGML documents were then further translated by simple programs in Rexx
and Spitbol into either LaTeX or Waterloo GML for formatting and
printing.</p>
<p>In 2001–2002 the text of these guidelines was converted to
XML markup using a variety of Perl and XSLT scripts, and hand-editing.
The Gnu Emacs editor, with the PSGML package, was the mainstay of editing
from then on.  The resulting document was processed with XSLT
specifications to produce the DTD files, the HTML reference guide, and
the PDF version. James Clark's nsgmls SGML/XML validator, Richard
Tobin's rxp XML validator, Michael Kay's Saxon XSLT implementation,
and Daniel Veillard's libxml2 and libxslt were used extensively.</p>
<p>The camera ready copy of the 1992–1996 versions of
this document was produced by Waterloo Script
GML, version 89.1,
running on the IBM 3090 at the University of Illinois at Chicago
Academic Computer Center (to which thanks), and using a set of
macros extending the GML Starter Set of tags with specialized tags
designed for this document. Later interim versions were produced by a
translation to LaTeX.</p>
<p>The P4 release of the Guidelines was typeset by transforming
the TEI XML source to an XML file containing XSL Formatting Objects, which was 
then formatted using the PassiveTeX implementation of XSLFO by
David Carlisle and Sebastian Rahtz. The underling engine was the pdfTeX
extension of TeX by Han The Thanh.
</p>
<p>The current printed version is typeset in Times Roman, with
Computer Modern Sans-serif and Lucida-Sans Typewriter as needed.
<?odds date?>
</p>
</div1>
