<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="DS" n="7">
<head>Default Text Structure</head>
<p>This chapter describes the default high-level structure for TEI
documents. A full TEI document combines metadata describing
it, represented by a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element, with the document
itself, represented by a <gi>text</gi> element. This basic pair is
represented by a <gi>TEI</gi> element. The <gi>teiHeader</gi> element
is specified by the <ident type="module">header</ident> module, which is fully
described in chapter <ptr target="#HD"/>. The remainder of the present
chapter describes the <gi>text</gi> element and its high-level
constituents. </p>

<p>A variant on this basic form, the <gi>teiCorpus</gi>, is also
defined for the representation of language corpora, or other
collections of encoded texts. A <gi>teiCorpus</gi> consists of one or
more complete <gi>TEI</gi> elements, each combining a
<gi>teiHeader</gi> and a <gi>text</gi> which itself carries a
<gi>teiHeader</gi>. This permits the encoder to distinguish metadata
applicable to the whole collection of encoded texts, which is
represented by the outermost <gi>teiHeader</gi>, from that applicable
to each of the individual <gi>TEI</gi> elements within the
corpus. Further information about the organization and encoding of
language corpora is given in chapter <ptr target="#CC"/>. </p>

<p>In summary, when the default structure module is included in a
schema, the following elements are available for the
representation of the outermost structure of a TEI document:
<specList>
<specDesc key="TEI" atts="version"/>
<specDesc key="teiCorpus"/>
<specDesc key="teiHeader"/>
<specDesc key="text"/>
</specList>

As noted above, the <gi>teiHeader</gi> element is formally declared in
the <ident type="module">header</ident> module (see chapter <ptr target="#HD"/>). A TEI document may also contain elements from the
<ident type="class">model.resourceLike</ident> class (such as a
collection of facsimile images, or a feature system declaration) if
the appropriate module is included in a schema (see further <ptr target="#PHFAX"/> and <ptr target="#FD"/> respectively). By default,
however, this class is not populated and hence only the elements
<gi>TEI</gi>, <gi>text</gi>, and <gi>teiCorpus</gi> are available 
as major parts of a TEI document. These three elements are
provided by the <ident type="module">textstructure</ident> module
described by the present chapter.
<specGrp xml:id="DCOTOPELEMENTS">


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/TEI.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/teiCorpus.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/text.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</p>


<p>TEI texts may be regarded either as <term>unitary</term>, that is,
forming an organic whole, or as <term>composite,</term> that is,
consisting of several components which are in some important sense
independent of each other.  The distinction is not always entirely
obvious:  for example a collection of essays might be regarded as a
single item in some circumstances, or as a number of distinct items in
others.  In such borderline cases, the encoder must choose whether to
treat the text as unitary or composite; each may have advantages and
disadvantages in a given situation.
 </p>

<p>Whether unitary or composite, the text is marked with the
<gi>text</gi> tag and may contain front matter, a text body, and back
matter.  In unitary texts, the text body is tagged <gi>body</gi>; in
composite texts, where the text body consists of a series of subordinate
texts or groups, it is tagged <gi>group</gi>.  The overall structure of
any text, unitary or composite, is thus defined by the following
elements:
<specList><specDesc key="front"/><specDesc key="body"/><specDesc key="group"/><specDesc key="back"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>The overall structure of a unitary text is:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible"><TEI>
  <teiHeader> <!-- .... --> </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
<!-- front matter of copy text, if any, goes here -->
    </front>
    <body>
<!-- body of copy text goes here -->
    </body>
    <back>
<!-- back matter of copy text, if any, goes here -->
    </back>
  </text>
 </TEI></egXML></p>
<p>The overall structure of a composite text made up of two unitary
texts is:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible"><TEI>
  <teiHeader>   <!-- .... --> </teiHeader>
  <text>
    <front>
<!-- front matter for composite text -->
    </front>
    <group>
      <text>
        <front>
<!-- front matter of first unitary text, if any -->
        </front>
        <body>
<!-- body of first unitary text -->
        </body>
        <back>
<!-- back matter of first unitary text, if any -->
        </back>
      </text>
      <text>
        <body>
<!-- body of second unitary text -->
        </body>
      </text>
    </group>
    <back>
<!-- back matter for composite text, if any -->
    </back>
  </text>
 </TEI></egXML>
 </p>
<p>Finally, a <gi>floatingText</gi> element is provided for the case
where one text is embedded within another, but does not contribute to
its hierarchical organization, for example because it interrupts it,
or simply quoted within it. This is useful in such common literary contexts as
the <q>play within a play</q> or the narrative interrupted by other (often
deeply nested) multiple narratives. <specGrp xml:id="DDSTEXT">
<!--n="Top-level parts of default structure"-->


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/body.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/group.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/floatingText.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</p>
<p>Each of these elements is further described in the remainder of
this chapter.  Elements <gi>front</gi> and <gi>back</gi> are further
discussed in sections <ptr target="#DSFRONT"/> and <ptr target="#DSBACK"/>. The <gi>group</gi> and <gi>floatingText</gi>
elements, used for more complex or composite text structures, are
further discussed in section <ptr target="#DSGRPF"/>. Other textual
elements, such as paragraphs, lists or phrases, which nest within
these major structural elements, are discussed in chapter <ptr target="#CO"/>, in the case of elements which can appear in any kind
of document, or elsewhere in the case of elements specific to
particular kinds of document.
</p>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DSDIV"><head>Divisions of the Body</head>

<p>In some texts, the body consists simply of a sequence of low-level
structural items, referred to here as <term>components</term> or
<term>component-level elements</term> (see section <ptr target="#STEC"/>).  Examples in prose texts include paragraphs or
lists; in dramatic texts, speeches and stage directions; in
dictionaries, dictionary entries.  In other cases sequences of such
elements will be grouped together hierarchically into textual
divisions and subdivisions, such as chapters or sections.  The names
used for these structural subdivisions of texts vary with the genre
and period of the text, or even at the whim of the author, editor, or
publisher. For example, a major subdivision of an epic or of the Bible
is generally called a <soCalled>book</soCalled>, that of a report is
usually called a <soCalled>part</soCalled> or
<soCalled>section</soCalled>, that of a novel a
<soCalled>chapter</soCalled>—unless it is an epistolary novel, in
which case it may be called a <soCalled>letter</soCalled>.  Even texts
which are not organized as linear prose narratives, or not as
narratives at all, will frequently be subdivided in a similar way: a
drama into <soCalled>acts</soCalled> and <soCalled>scenes</soCalled>;
a reference book into <soCalled>sections</soCalled>; a diary or day
book into <soCalled>entries</soCalled>; a newspaper into
<soCalled>issues</soCalled> and <soCalled>sections</soCalled>, and so
forth.
 </p>

<p>Because of this variety, these Guidelines propose that all such
textual divisions be regarded as occurrences of the same neutrally named
elements, with an attribute <att>type</att> used to categorize elements
independently of their hierarchic level.  Two alternative styles are
provided for the marking of these neutral divisions:
<term>numbered</term> and <term>un-numbered</term>.  Numbered divisions
are named  <gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi>, etc., where the
number indicates the depth of this particular division within the
hierarchy, the largest such division being <q>div1</q>, any subdivision
within it being <q>div2</q>, any further sub-sub-division being
<q>div3</q> and so on.  Un-numbered divisions are simply named
<gi>div</gi>, and allowed to nest recursively to indicate their
hierarchic depth.  The two styles must <emph>not</emph> be combined
within a single <gi>front</gi>, <gi>body</gi>, or <gi>back</gi> element.
 </p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSDIV1"><head>Un-numbered Divisions</head>
<p>The following element is used to identify textual subdivisions in
the un-numbered style: <specList><specDesc key="div"/></specList> As a
member of the class <ident type="class">att.typed</ident>, this
element has the following additional attributes: <specList><specDesc key="att.typed" atts="type subtype"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>Using this style, the body of a text containing two parts, each
composed of two chapters, might be represented as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible"><body>
  <div type="part" n="1">
    <div type="chapter" n="1">
      <!-- text of part 1, chapter 1 -->
 </div>
    <div type="chapter" n="2">
      <!-- text of part 1, chapter 2 -->
    </div>
  </div>
  <div type="part" n="2">
    <div n="1" type="chapter">
      <!-- text of part 2, chapter 1 -->
    </div>
    <div n="2" type="chapter">
      <!-- text of part 2, chapter 2 -->
    </div>
  </div>
</body></egXML>
 </p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDSDIV">
<!-- n="Un-numbered divisions"-->


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSDIV2"><head>Numbered Divisions</head>
<p>The following elements are used to identify textual subdivisions
in the numbered style:
<specList>
<specDesc key="div1"/>
<specDesc key="div2"/>
<specDesc key="div3"/>
<specDesc key="div4"/>
<specDesc key="div5"/>
<specDesc key="div6"/>
<specDesc key="div7"/>
</specList>
As members of the class <ident type="class">att.typed</ident> these
elements all bear the following additional attributes:
<specList><specDesc key="att.typed" atts="type subtype"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>The largest possible subdivision of the body is <gi>div1</gi>
element and the smallest possible <gi>div7</gi>.  If numbered
divisions are in use, a division at any one level (say,
<gi>div3</gi>), may contain only numbered divisions at the next lowest
level (in this case, <gi>div4</gi>).</p>
<p>Using this style, the body of a text containing two parts, each
composed of two chapters, might be represented as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible"><body>
  <div1 type="part" n="1">
    <div2 type="chapter" n="1">
      <!-- text of part 1, chapter 1 -->
 </div2>
    <div2 type="chapter" n="2">
      <!-- text of part 1, chapter 2 -->
    </div2>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="part" n="2">
    <div2 n="1" type="chapter">
      <!-- text of part 2, chapter 1 -->
    </div2>
    <div2 n="2" type="chapter">
      <!-- text of part 2, chapter 2 -->
    </div2>
  </div1>
</body></egXML>

<!-- Changed example:  the point of the div1/div0             -->
	<!-- alternation in the body is to allow the scheme to        -->
	<!-- handle Chapters at a consistent level with or without    -->
	<!-- surrounding Parts, so the natural way to tag Part and    -->
	<!-- Chapter here is div0 div1, not div1 div2, or at least    -->
	<!-- so it seems to me.  -msm                                 -->
	<!-- tough if you then want sections too (LB) -->
	<!-- Also changed to agree with previous example in N values  -->
	<!-- and comments. -msm                                       -->
 </p>

<specGrp xml:id="DDSDIVN">
<!--n="Numbered divisions"-->


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div1.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div2.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div3.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div4.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div5.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div6.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/div7.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/divGen.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSDIV3"><head>Numbered or Un-numbered?</head>
<p>Within the same <gi>front</gi>, <gi>body</gi>, or <gi>back</gi>
element, all hierarchic subdivisions must be marked using either
nested <gi>div</gi> elements, or <gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi> etc.
elements nested as appropriate; the two styles must <emph>not</emph>
be mixed.
</p>
<p>The choice between numbered and un-numbered divisions will depend
to some extent on the complexity of the material: un-numbered
divisions allow for an arbitrary depth of nesting, while numbered
divisions limit the depth of the tree which can be constructed.  Where
divisions at different levels should be processed differently (for
example to ensure that chapters, but not sections, begin on a new
page), numbered divisions slightly simplify the task of defining the
desired processing for each level, though this distinction could also
be made by supplying this information on the <att>type</att> attribute
of an un-numbered <gi>div</gi>.  Some software may find numbered
divisions easier to process, as there is no need to maintain knowledge
of the whole document structure in order to know the level at which a
division occurs; such software may, however, find it difficult to cope
with some other aspects of the TEI scheme.  On the other hand, in a
collection of many works it may prove difficult or impossible to
ensure that the same numbered division always corresponds with the
same type of textual feature: a <soCalled>chapter</soCalled> may be at
level 1 in one work and level 3 in another. 
 </p>
<p>Whichever style is used, the global <att>n</att> and <att>xml:id</att>
attributes (section <ptr target="#STGA"/>) may be used to provide
reference strings or labels for each division of a text, where
appropriate. Such labels should be provided for each section
which is regarded as significant for referencing purposes (on
reference systems, see further section <ptr target="#CORS"/>).  
</p>

<p>As indicated above, the <att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att>
attributes provided by the <ident type="class">att.typed</ident> class
may be used to provide a name or description for the division.
Typical values might be <soCalled>book</soCalled>,
<soCalled>chapter</soCalled>, <soCalled>section</soCalled>,
<soCalled>part</soCalled>, or (for verse texts)
<soCalled>book</soCalled>, <soCalled>canto</soCalled>,
<soCalled>stanza</soCalled>, or (for dramatic texts)
<soCalled>act</soCalled>, <soCalled>scene</soCalled>. The following
extended example uses numbered divisions to indicate the structure of
a novel, and illustrates the use of the attributes discussed above.
It also uses some elements discussed in section <ptr target="#DSDTB"/>
and the <gi>p</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#COPA"/>.
<!-- a long example but an irresistible one... -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSDIV3-eg-22"><div1 type="book" n="I" xml:id="JA0100">
  <head>Book I.</head>
  <div2 type="chapter" n="1" xml:id="JA0101">
    <head>Of writing lives in general, and particularly of Pamela, with a word
      by the bye of Colley Cibber and others.</head>
    <p>It is a trite but true observation, that examples work more forcibly on
      the mind than precepts:  ... </p>
<!-- remainder of chapter 1 here -->
  </div2>
  <div2 type="chapter" n="2" xml:id="JA0102">
    <head>Of Mr. Joseph Andrews, his birth, parentage, education, and great
      endowments; with a word or two concerning ancestors.</head>  
    <p>Mr. Joseph Andrews, the hero of our ensuing history, was esteemed to
      be the only son of Gaffar and Gammar Andrews, and brother to the
      illustrious Pamela, whose virtue is at present so famous ... </p>
<!-- remainder of chapter 2 here -->
  </div2>
<!-- remaining chapters of Book 1 here -->
  <trailer>The end of the first Book</trailer>
</div1> 
<div1 type="book" n="II" xml:id="JA0200">
  <head>Book II</head>    
  <div2 type="chapter" n="1" xml:id="JA0201">
    <head>Of divisions in authors</head>
    <p>There are certain mysteries or secrets in all trades, from the highest
      to the lowest, from that of <term>prime-ministering</term>, to this of
      <term>authoring</term>, which are seldom discovered unless to members of
      the same calling ... </p>
    <p>I will dismiss this chapter with the following observation: that it
      becomes an author generally to divide a book, as it does a butcher to
      joint his meat, for such assistance is of great help to both the reader
      and the carver. And now having indulged myself a little I will endeavour
      to indulge the curiosity of my reader, who is no doubt impatient to know
      what he will find in the subsequent chapters of this book.</p>
  </div2>
  <div2 type="chapter" n="2" xml:id="JA0202">
    <head>A surprising instance of Mr. Adams's short memory, with the
      unfortunate consequences which it brought on Joseph.
    </head>
    <p>Mr. Adams and Joseph were now ready to depart different ways ... </p>
  </div2>
</div1></egXML>
<!--   Fielding, Joseph Andrews (ed Battestin, 1961) -->
 </p>

<p>As an alternative (or complement) to this use of the
<att>type</att> attribute to characterize neutrally named division
elements, the modification mechanisms discussed in section <ptr target="#MD"/> may be used to define new elements such as
<gi scheme="imaginary">chapter</gi>, <gi scheme="imaginary">part</gi>, etc. To make this simpler, a single
member model class is defined for each of the neutrally named division
elements: <ident type="class">model.divLike</ident> (containing
<gi>div</gi>), <ident type="class">model.div1Like</ident> (containing
<gi>div1</gi>), <ident type="class">model.div2Like</ident> (containing
<gi>div2</gi>), etc. For example, suppose that the body of a text
consists of a series of diary entries, each of which is potentially
divided into entries for the morning and the afternoon. This might be
represented in any of the following ways. First, using the un-numbered
style: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible"><body>
<div type="entry" n="1">
  <div type="morning" n="1.1"><p>....</p></div>
  <div type="afternoon" n="1.2"><p>....</p></div>
</div>
<div type="entry" n="2">
  <div type="morning" n="2.1"><p>....</p></div>
  <div type="afternoon" n="2.2"><p>....</p></div>
</div>
<!-- ...-->
</body></egXML>
Equivalently, using the numbered style:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><body>
<div1 type="entry" n="1">
  <div2 type="morning" n="1.1"><p>....</p></div2>
  <div2 type="afternoon" n="1.2"><p>....</p></div2>
</div1>
<div1 type="entry" n="2">
  <div2 type="morning" n="2.1"><p>....</p></div2>
  <div2 type="afternoon" n="2.2"><p>....</p></div2>
</div1>
<!-- ...-->
</body></egXML> 

Now, assuming a customization in which a new element
<gi scheme="imaginary">diaryEntry</gi> has been added to the <ident type="class">model.divLike</ident> class: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xmlns:my="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI" valid="feasible"><body>
<my:diaryEntry type="entry" n="1">
  <my:diaryEntry type="morning" n="1.1"><p>....</p></my:diaryEntry>
  <my:diaryEntry type="afternoon" n="1.2"><p>....</p></my:diaryEntry>
</my:diaryEntry>
<my:diaryEntry type="entry" n="1">
  <my:diaryEntry type="morning" n="1.1"><p>....</p></my:diaryEntry>
  <my:diaryEntry type="afternoon" n="1.2"><p>....</p></my:diaryEntry>
 </my:diaryEntry>
<!-- ...-->
</body></egXML>

And finally, assuming a customization in which three new elements have
been added: <gi scheme="imaginary">diaryEntry</gi> to the <ident type="class">model.div1</ident> class, and <gi scheme="imaginary">amEntry</gi> and
<gi scheme="imaginary">pmEntry</gi> both to the <ident
type="class">model.div2</ident> class: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
xmlns:my="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI"><body>
   <p><!-- .... --></p>
   <my:diaryEntry type="entry" n="1">
     <my:amEntry type="morning" n="1.1"><p>....</p></my:amEntry>
     <my:pmEntry type="afternoon" n="1.2"><p>....</p></my:pmEntry>
   </my:diaryEntry>
   <my:diaryEntry type="entry" n="1">
     <my:amEntry type="morning" n="1.1"><p>....</p></my:amEntry>
     <my:pmEntry type="afternoon" n="1.1"><p>....</p></my:pmEntry>
   </my:diaryEntry>
   <!-- ... -->
</body></egXML>
</p>
<p>More information about the customization techniques exemplified
here is provided in <ptr target="#MD"/>.
</p>


</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSDIV3X"><head>Partial and Composite Divisions</head>
<p>In most situations, the textual subdivisions marked by <gi>div</gi>
or <gi>div1</gi> (etc.) elements will be both complete and identically
organized with reference to the original source.  For some purposes
however, in particular where dealing with unusually large or unusually
small texts, encoders may find it convenient to present as textual
divisions sequences of text which are incomplete with reference to the
original text, or which are in fact an ad hoc agglomeration of tiny
texts.  Moreover, in some kinds of texts it is difficult or impossible
to determine the order in which individual subdivisions should be
combined to form the next higher level of subdivision, as noted below.
 </p>
<p>To overcome these problems, the following additional attributes are
defined for all elements in the <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident> class:
<specList><specDesc key="att.divLike" atts="org sample part"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>For example, an encoder might choose to transcribe only the first two
thousand words of each chapter from a novel.  In such a case, each
chapter might conveniently be regarded as a partial division, and tagged
with a <gi>div</gi> element in the following form:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div n="xx" sample="initial" part="Y" type="chapter">
  <p> ... </p>
</div></egXML>
where <val>xx</val> represents a number for the chapter, and the
<att>part</att> attribute takes the value <val>Y</val> to indicate
that this division is incomplete in some respect. Other possible
values for this attribute indicate whether material has been omitted
initially (I), finally 
(F), or in the middle (M) of the division, while the <gi>gap</gi>
element (<ptr target="#COEDADD"/>) may be used to indicate exactly
where material has been omitted: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div n="xx" part="M" type="chapter">
  <p> ... </p>
  <gap extent="2" reason="sampling"/>
  <p> ... </p>
</div></egXML>
The
<gi>samplingDecl</gi> element in the TEI Header should also be used to
record the principles underlying the selection of incomplete samples, as
further described in section <ptr target="#HD52"/>.
 </p>
<p>The following example demonstrates how a newspaper column composed of
very short unrelated snippets may be encoded using these attributes:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSDIV3X-eg-29"><div1 type="storylist" org="composite">
<head>News in brief</head>
<div2 type="story">
<head>Police deny <soCalled>losing</soCalled> bomb</head>
<p>Scotland Yard yesterday denied claims in the Sunday
Express that anti-terrorist officers trailing an IRA van
loaded with explosives in north London had lost track of
it 10 days ago.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="story">
<head>Hotel blaze</head>
<p>Nearly 200 guests were evacuated before dawn
yesterday after fire broke out at the Scandic
Crown hotel in the Royal Mile, Edinburgh.</p>
</div2>
<div2 type="story">
<head>Test match split</head>
<p>Test Match Special next summer will be split
between Radio 5 and Radio 3, after protests this
year that it disrupted Radio 3's music schedule.</p>
</div2>
</div1></egXML> 
<!-- Guardian 21 Dec 1992, p 2 -->
</p>
<p>The <att>org</att> attribute on the <gi>div1</gi> element is used
here to indicate that individual stories in this group, marked here as
<gi>div2</gi>, are really quite independent of each other, although they
are all marked as subdivisions of the whole group.  They can be read in
any order without affecting the sense of the piece; indeed, in some
cases, divisions of this nature are printed in such a way as to make it
impossible to determine the order in which they are intended to be read.
Individual stories can be added or removed without affecting the
existing components.
 </p>
<p>This method of encoding composite texts as composite divisions has
some limitations compared with the more general and powerful mechanisms
discussed in section <ptr target="#DSGRP"/>. However, it may be preferable
in some circumstances, notably where the individual texts are very
small.
 </p></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DSDTB"><head>Elements Common to All Divisions</head>
<p>The divisions of any kind of text may sometimes begin with a brief
heading or descriptive title, with or without a byline, an epigraph or
brief quotation, or a salutation such as one finds at the start of a
letter. They may also conclude with a brief trailer, byline,
postscript, or signature. Many of these (e.g. a byline) may appear
either at the start or at the end of a text division proper.</p>
<p>To support this heterogeneity, the TEI architecture defines five
classes, all of which are populated by this module:
<specList>
<specDesc key="model.divTop"/>
<specDesc key="model.divTopPart"/>
<specDesc key="model.divBottom"/>
<specDesc key="model.divBottomPart"/>
<specDesc key="model.divWrapper"/>
</specList></p>

<p>By default the class <ident type="class">model.divWrapper</ident>
provides the following special-purpose elements:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="argument"/>
  <specDesc key="byline"/>
  <specDesc key="dateline"/>
  <specDesc key="docAuthor"/>
  <specDesc key="docDate"/>
  <specDesc key="epigraph"/>
</specList>
</p>

<p>The class <ident type="class">model.divTop</ident> combines these
elements with the following elements, which populate the <ident type="class">model.divTopPart</ident> class:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="head"/>
  <specDesc key="salute"/>
  <specDesc key="opener"/>
</specList>
For further details of the <gi>head</gi> element, see section <ptr target="#DSHD"/>; for <gi>epigraph</gi> and <gi>argument</gi>, see
section <ptr target="#DSAE"/>; for <gi>opener</gi>, see section <ptr target="#DSOC"/>.</p>

<p>The class <ident type="class">model.divBottom</ident> combines
these elements with the following elements, which populate the <ident type="class">model.divBottomPart</ident> class:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="closer"/>
  <specDesc key="signed"/>
  <specDesc key="trailer"/>
  <specDesc key="postscript"/>
</specList>
For further details of the <gi>trailer</gi> element, see section <ptr target="#DSHD"/>; for the <gi>closer</gi> and <gi>signed</gi>
elements, section <ptr target="#DSOC"/>; for the <gi>postscript</gi>
element, section <ptr target="#DSAE"/>.</p>

<div type="div3" xml:id="DSHD"><head>Headings and Trailers</head>

<p>The <gi>head</gi> element is used to identify a heading prefixed to
the start of any textual division, at any level. A given division may
contain more than one such element, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSHD-eg-30"><div1 n="Etym">
<head>Etymology</head>
<head>(Supplied by a late consumptive usher to a
grammar school)</head>
<p>The pale Usher — threadbare in coat, heart,
body and brain; I see him now. He was ever
dusting his old lexicons and grammars, ...</p></div1></egXML>
<!-- H Melville, M.Dick -->
 </p>
<p>Unlike some other markup schemes, the TEI scheme does
<emph>not</emph> require that headings attached to textual
subdivisions at different hierarchic levels have different
identifiers. All kinds of heading are marked identically using the
<gi>head</gi> tag; the type or level of heading intended is implied by
the immediate parent of the <gi>head</gi> element, which may for
example be a <gi>div1</gi>, <gi>div2</gi>, etc., an un-numbered
<gi>div</gi>, or any member of the <ident type="class">model.listLike</ident> class.  However, as with
<gi>div</gi> elements, the encoder may choose to extend the <ident type="class">model.headLike</ident> class of which <gi>head</gi> is
the sole member to include other such elements if required. </p>
<p>In certain kinds of text (notably newspapers), there may be a need
to categorize individual headings within the sequence at the start of
a division, for example as <soCalled>main</soCalled> headings, or
<soCalled>detail</soCalled> headings: this may readily be done using the
<att>type</att> or <att>subtype</att> attribute. Specific elements are provided
for certain kinds of heading-like features, (notably <gi>byline</gi>,
<gi>dateline</gi>, and <gi>salute</gi>; see further section <ptr target="#DSOC"/>), but the <att>type</att> or <att>subtype</att>
attributes must be used to discriminate among other forms of
heading. These attributes are provided, as elsewhere, by the <ident type="class">att.typed</ident> attribute class of which the
<gi>head</gi> element is a member.
 </p>
<p>In the following example, taken from a British newspaper, the lead
story and its associated headlines have been encoded  as a <gi>div</gi>
element, with appropriate <ident type="class">model.divTop</ident> elements attached:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSHD-eg-31"><div type="story">
<head rend="underlined" type="sub">
President pledges safeguards for 2,400 British
troops in Bosnia</head>
<head rend="scream" type="main">
Major agrees to enforced no-fly zone</head>
<byline>By George Jones, Political Editor, in Washington</byline>
<p>Greater Western intervention in the conflict in
former Yugoslavia was pledged by President Bush ...</p></div></egXML>
<!-- Daily Telegraph 21 Dec 1992 -->
 </p>
<p>In older writings, the headings or <term>incipits</term> may be
longer than in modern works.
When heading-like material appears in the middle of a text, the encoder
must decide whether or not to treat it as the start of a new division.
If the phrase in question appears to be more closely connected with what
follows than with what precedes it, then it may be regarded as a
heading and tagged as the <gi>head</gi> of a new <gi>div</gi> element.
If it appears to be simply inserted or superimposed—as for example
the kind of <soCalled>pull quotes</soCalled> often found in newspapers
or magazines, then the <gi>quote</gi>, <gi>q</gi>, or <gi>cit</gi>
element may be more appropriate.
 </p>
<p>The <gi>trailer</gi> element, which can appear at the end of a
division only, is used to mark any heading-like feature appearing in
this position, as in this example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-01"><div type="book" n="I"><head>In the name of Christ here begins the
    first book of the ecclesiastical history of Georgius Florentinus,
    known as Gregory, Bishop of Tours.</head>
<div><head>Chapter Headings</head>
<list>
  <item><!-- chapter head --></item>
  <!-- further chapter heads omitted -->
</list>
</div>
  <div><head>In the name of Christ here begins Book I of the history.</head>
    <p>Proposing as I do ...</p>
    <p>From the Passion of our Lord until the death of Saint Martin four
      hundred and twelve years passed.</p>
    <trailer>Here ends the first Book, which covers five thousand, five
      hundred and ninety-six years from the beginning of the world down
      to the death of Saint Martin.</trailer>
  </div>
</div></egXML>
 </p>


</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSOC"><head>Openers and Closers</head>
<p>In addition to headings of various kinds, divisions sometimes include
more or less formulaic opening or closing passages, typically conveying
such information as the name and address of the person to whom the
division is addressed, the place or time of its production, a salutation
or exhortation to the reader, and so on.  Divisions in epistolary form
are particularly liable to include such features.  
Additional elements for the detailed encoding of personal names, dates,
and places are provided in chapter <ptr target="#ND"/>.
For simple cases, the following elements should be adequate:
<specList>
<specDesc key="byline"/>
<specDesc key="dateline"/>
<specDesc key="salute"/>
<specDesc key="signed"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>byline</gi> and <gi>dateline</gi> elements are used to encode
headings which identify the authorship and provenance of a division.
Although the terminology derives from newspaper usage, there is no
implication that <gi>dateline</gi> or <gi>byline</gi> elements apply
only to newspaper texts.  The following example illustrates use of the
<gi>dateline</gi> and <gi>signed</gi> elements at the end of the
preface to a novel:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSOC-eg-33"><div type="preface">
<head>To Henry Hope.</head>
<p>It is not because this volume was conceived and partly
executed amid the glades and galleries of the Deepdene,
that I have inscribed it with your name. ... I shall find a
reflex to their efforts in your own generous spirit and
enlightened mind.
</p>
<closer>
<signed xml:lang="el">D.</signed>
<dateline>Grosvenor Gate, May-Day, 1844</dateline>
</closer>
</div>
 </egXML>
<!-- B Disraeli, Coningsby (Nelson, nd) -->
 </p>
<p>Where a sequence of such elements appear together, either at the
beginning or end of an element, it may be convenient to group them
together using one of the following elements:
<specList><specDesc key="opener"/>
<specDesc key="closer"/>
</specList>
The following examples demonstrate the use of the <gi>opener</gi> and
<gi>closer</gi> grouping elements:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSOC-eg-34"><div type="narrative" n="6">
  <head>Sixth Narrative</head>
  <head>contributed by Sergeant Cuff</head>
  <div type="fragment" n="6.1">
	<opener>
	  <dateline>
		<name type="place">Dorking, Surrey,</name>
		<date>July 30th, 1849</date>
	  </dateline>
	  <salute>To <name>Franklin Blake, Esq.</name> Sir, —</salute>
	</opener>
	<p>I beg to apologize for the delay that has occurred in the
	  production of the Report, with which I engaged to furnish you. 
	  I have waited to make it a complete Report ...</p>
	<closer>
	  <salute>I have the honour to remain, dear sir, your
		obedient servant </salute>
	  <signed> <name>RICHARD CUFF</name> (late sergeant in the
		Detective Force, Scotland Yard, London). </signed>
	</closer>
  </div>
</div></egXML>
<!-- W. Collins, The Moonstone, Penguin, pp 503, 513 -->
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COHQHEG-eg-02"><div type="letter" n="14">
<head>Letter XIV: Miss Clarissa Harlowe to Miss Howe</head>
<opener> <dateline>Thursday evening, March 2.</dateline> </opener>
<p>On Hannah's depositing my long letter ...</p>
<p>An interruption obliges me to conclude myself 
in some hurry, as well as fright, what I must ever be,</p>
<closer>
<salute>Yours more than my own,</salute>
<signed>Clarissa Harlowe</signed>
</closer>
</div></egXML>
<!-- S. Richardson 'Clarissa', (Dent, EML, vol 1, p62,64 -->
 </p>
<p>For further discussion of the encoding of dates and of names of persons and places, see section <ptr target="#CONADA"/> and chapter <ptr target="#ND"/>.
 </p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSAE"><head>Arguments, Epigraphs, and Postscripts</head>
<p>The <gi>argument</gi> element may be used to encode the prefatory
list of topics sometimes found at the start of a chapter or
other division.  It is most conveniently encoded as a list, since this
allows each item to be distinguished, but may also simply be presented
as a paragraph.  The following are thus both equally valid ways of
encoding the same argument:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSAE-eg-36"><div type="chap" n="6">
  <argument>
    <p>Kingston — Instructive remarks on early English history
      — Instructive observations on carved oak and life in general
      — Sad case of Stivvings, junior — Musings on antiquity
      — I forget that I am steering — Interesting result
      — Hampton Court Maze — Harris as a guide.</p>
  </argument>
  <p>It was a glorious morning, late spring or early summer, as you
    care to take it ...</p>
</div></egXML>

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSAE-eg-36"><div type="chap" n="6">
  <argument>
    <list type="inline">
      <item>Kingston</item>
      <item>Instructive remarks on early English history</item>
      <item>Instructive observations on carved oak and life in
        general</item>
      <item>Sad case of Stivvings, junior</item>
      <item>Musings on antiquity</item>
      <item>I forget that I am steering</item>
      <item>Interesting result</item>
      <item>Hampton Court Maze</item>
      <item>Harris as a guide.</item>
    </list>
  </argument>
  <p>It was a glorious morning, late spring or early summer, as you
    care to take it ...</p>
</div></egXML>

 </p>
<p>An <term>epigraph</term> is a quotation from some other work, a
saying, or a motto,  appearing on a title page, or at the start of a
division.  It may be encoded using the special-purpose
<gi>epigraph</gi> element, as in the following example:
<egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSAE-eg-38a">
<titlePage>
<docAuthor>E. M. Forster</docAuthor>
<docTitle><titlePart>Howards End</titlePart></docTitle>
<epigraph><q>Only connect...</q></epigraph>
</titlePage>
</egXML>
When an epigraph contains a quotation, this may often be associated
with a bibliographic reference. In such cases, it is recommended
additionally to group the quotation and its source together using the
<gi>cit</gi> element, as in the following example: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSAE-eg-38"><div
n="19" type="chap"><head>Chapter 19</head>
 <epigraph>
 <cit><quote>I pity the man who can travel
     from Dan to Beersheba, and say <q>'Tis all
     barren;</q> and so is all the world to him
     who will not cultivate the fruits it offers.
     </quote>
     <bibl>Sterne: Sentimental Journey.</bibl>
 </cit></epigraph>
<p>To say that Deronda was romantic would be to
 misrepresent him: but under his calm and somewhat
 self-repressed exterior ...</p>
</div></egXML>
<!-- G. Eliot, D. Deronda, (1876) III.1 (Penguin, 1967, p. 245)  -->
 </p>
<p>For discussion of quotations appearing other than as epigraphs refer
to section <ptr target="#COHQQ"/>.
 </p><p>A <term>postscript</term> is a passage added after the signature of
a letter or, less frequently, the main portion of the body of a book,
article, or essay. In English a postscript is often abbreviated as
<mentioned>P.S.</mentioned> or <mentioned>PS</mentioned>, and
postscripts are often introduced by labels with one of these
abbreviations, as in the following example.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSAE-eg-39">
       <div type="letter">
        <opener>
          <dateline>
            <placeName>Newport</placeName>
            <date when="1761-05-27">May ye 27th 1761</date>
          </dateline>
          <salute>Gentlemen</salute>
        </opener>
        <p>Capt Stoddard's Business
          <lb/>calling him to Providence, have
          <lb/>got him to look at Hopkins brigantine
          <lb/>&amp; if can agree to Purchase her, shall
          <lb/>be much oblig'd for your further
          <lb/>assistance herein, &amp; will acquiesce with
          <lb/>whatever you &amp; he shall Contract
          <lb/>for — I Thank you for your
          <lb/><unclear>Line</unclear> respecting the brigantine &amp; Beg
          <lb/>leave to Recommend the Bearer
          <lb/>to you for your advice &amp; Friendship
          <lb/>in this matter</p>
        <closer>
          <salute>I am  your most  humble servant</salute>
          <signed>Joseph Wanton Jr</signed>
        </closer>
        <postscript>
	  <label>P.S.</label>
          <p>I have Mollases, Sugar,
          <lb/>Coffee &amp; Rum, which
          <lb/>will Exchange with you
          <lb/>for Candles or Oyl</p>
        </postscript>
      </div>
</egXML>
<!-- adapted from sajc000021.xml, which does not seem to be available on the website (http://dl.lib.brown.edu/slaveryandjustice/) -->
</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSCO"><head>Content of Textual Divisions</head>
<p>Other than elements from the <ident type="class">model.divWrapper</ident>, <ident type="class">model.divTop</ident>, or <ident type="class">model.divBottom</ident> classes, every textual division
(numbered or un-numbered) consists of a sequence of ungrouped <ident type="macro">macro.component</ident> elements (see <ptr target="#STEC"/>). The actual elements available will depend on the
modules in use; in all cases, at least the component-level structural
elements defined in the core will be available (paragraphs, lists,
dramatic speeches, verse lines and line groups etc.). If the drama
module has been selected, then other component- or phrase- level items
specialized for performance texts (for example, cast lists or camera
angles) will be available, as defined in
chapter <ptr target="#DR"/>) will be available. If the dictionary
module is in use, then dictionary entries, related entries, etc. (as
defined in chapter <ptr target="#DI"/>) will also be available; if the
module for transcribed speech is in use, then utterances, pauses,
vocals, kinesics, etc., as defined in chapter <ptr target="#TSBA"/>
will be available; and so on.</p>
<p>Where a text contains low-level elements from more than one
module these may appear at any point; there is no requirement that
elements from the same module be kept together.</p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDSDIVX">
<!-- n="Tags for start and end of divisions"-->


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/trailer.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/byline.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/dateline.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/argument.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/epigraph.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/opener.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/closer.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/salute.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/signed.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/postscript.xml"/>
</specGrp>

</div> 
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DSGRPF"><head>Grouped and Floating Texts</head>
<p>The <gi>group</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#DSGRP"/>
should be used to represent a collection of independent texts which is
to be regarded as a single unit for processing or other purposes.  The
<gi>floatingText</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#DSFLT"/>
should be used to represent an independent text which interrupts the
text containing it at any point but after which the surrounding text
resumes.  <specList><specDesc key="group"/><specDesc key="floatingText"/></specList>
</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="DSGRP"><head>Grouped Texts</head>
<p>
Examples of composite texts which should be represented using the
<gi>group</gi> element include
anthologies and other collections. The presence of common front matter
referring to the whole collection, possibly in addition to front matter
relating to each individual text, is a good indication that a given text
might usefully be encoded in this way; this structure may be found
useful in other circumstances too.
 </p>
<p>For example, the overall structure of a collection of
short stories might be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSGRP-eg-57">
  <text>
    <front>
      <docTitle><titlePart>
          The Adventures of Sherlock Holmes
        </titlePart></docTitle>
      <docImprint>First published in <title>The Strand</title>
        between July 1891 and December 1892</docImprint>
<!-- any other front matter specific to this collection -->
    </front>
    <group>
      <text>
        <front>
          <head rend="italic">Adventures of Sherlock
            Holmes</head>
          <docTitle><titlePart>Adventure I. —</titlePart>
            <titlePart>A Scandal in Bohemia</titlePart></docTitle>
          <byline>By A. Conan Doyle.</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
          <p>To Sherlock Holmes she is always
            <emph>the</emph> woman. ... </p>
<!-- remainder of A Scandal in Bohemia here -->
        </body>
      </text>
      <text>
        <front>
          <head rend="italic">Adventures of Sherlock Holmes</head>
          <docTitle><titlePart>Adventure II. —</titlePart>
            <titlePart>The Red-Headed League</titlePart></docTitle>
          <byline>By A. Conan Doyle.</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
	  <p>I had called upon my friend, Mr. Sherlock Holmes, one day
	  in the autumn of last year  and found him in deep conversation 
	  with a very stout, florid-faced, elderly gentleman with fiery red hair …
	  </p>
          <!-- remainder of The Red Headed League here -->
        </body>
      </text>
      <text>
        <front>
          <head rend="italic">Adventures of Sherlock Holmes</head>
          <docTitle><titlePart>Adventure XII. —</titlePart>
            <titlePart>The Adventure of the Copper Beeches</titlePart>
          </docTitle>
          <byline>By A. Conan Doyle.</byline>
        </front>
        <body>
          <p><q>To the man who loves art for its
            own sake,</q> remarked Sherlock Holmes ...

<!-- remainder of The Copper Beeches here -->

            ... she is now the head of a private school
            at Walsall, where I believe that she has
            met with considerable success.</p>
        </body>
      </text> <!-- end of The Copper Beeches -->
    </group>
  </text>  <!-- end of the Adventures of Sherlock Holmes -->
</egXML>
<!-- Original Illustrated Sherlock Holmes (Castle Books, 1989) -->
</p>
<p>A text which is a member of a group may itself contain groups. This
is quite common in collections of verse, but may happen in any kind of
text. As an example, consider the overall structure of a typical
collection, such as the <title>Muses Library</title> edition of
Crashaw's poetry. Following a critical
introduction and table of contents, this work contains the following
major sections:
<list type="simple">
<item><title>Steps to the Temple</title> (a collection of
verse first published in 1648)</item>
<item><title>Carmen deo Nostro</title> (a second collection,
published in 1652)</item>
<item><title>The Delights of the Muses</title> (a third
collection, published in 1648)</item>
<item><title>Posthumous Poems,</title> I (a collection of
fragments all taken from a single manuscript)</item>
<item><title>Posthumous Poems,</title> II (a further collection
of fragments, taken from a different manuscript)</item></list>
 </p>
<p>Each of the three collections published in Crashaw's lifetime has a
reasonable claim to be considered as a text in its own right, and may
therefore be encoded as such. It is rather more arbitrary as to
whether the two posthumous collections should be treated as two
groups, following the practice of the <title>Muses Library</title>
edition. An encoder might elect to combine the two into a single
group or simply to treat each fragment as an ungrouped unitary text.
 </p>
<p>The <title>Muses Library</title> edition reprints the whole of each
of the three original collections, including their original front
matter (title pages, dedications etc.). These should be encoded using
the <gi>front</gi> element and its constituents (on which see further
section <ptr target="#DSFRONT"/>), while the body of each collection
should be encoded as a single <gi>group</gi> element. Each individual
poem within the collections should be encoded as a distinct
<gi>text</gi> element. The beginning of the whole collection would
thus appear as follows (for further discussion of the use of the
elements <gi>div</gi> and <gi>lg</gi> for textual subdivision of
verse, see section <ptr target="#COVE"/> and chapter <ptr target="#VE"/>): <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-02" valid="feasible"><text>
  <front>
    <titlePage>
      <docTitle><titlePart>The poems of Richard Crashaw</titlePart></docTitle>
      <byline>Edited by J.R. Tutin</byline>
    </titlePage>    
    <div type="preface"><head>Editor's Note</head>
      <p>A few words are necessary ... </p>
    </div>
  </front>
  <group>
    <text>
      <front>
        <titlePage>
          <docTitle>
            <titlePart>Steps to the Temple, Sacred Poems</titlePart>
          </docTitle>
        </titlePage>
        <div type="address"><head>The Preface to the Reader</head>
          <p>Learned Reader, The Author's friend will not usurp much
            upon thy eye ... </p>
        </div>
      </front>
      <group>
        <text>
          <front>
            <docTitle><titlePart>Sospetto D'Herode</titlePart></docTitle>
          </front>
          <body>
            <div1 type="book" n="Herod I">
              <head>Libro Primo</head>
              <epigraph>
                <l>Casting the times with their strong signs</l>
              </epigraph>
              <lg n="I.1" type="stanza">
                <l>Muse! now the servant of soft loves no more</l>
                <l>Hate is thy theme and Herod whose unblest</l>
                <l>Hand (O, what dares not jealous greatness?) tore</l>
                <l>A thousand sweet babes from their mothers' breast,</l>
                <l>The blooms of martyrdom ...</l>
              </lg> </div1> </body> </text> 
        <text>
          <front><docTitle><titlePart>The Tear</titlePart></docTitle></front>
          <body>
            <lg n="I">
              <l>What bright soft thing is this</l>
              <l>Sweet Mary, thy fair eyes' expense?</l>
            </lg> </body> </text> 
	    <!-- remaining poems of the Steps to the Temple appear
	    here, each tagged as a distinct text element -->
      </group>  

      <back> <!-- back matter for the Steps to the Temple -->  </back>
    </text>
    <text> <!-- start of Carmen deo Nostro -->
      <front>  </front>
      <group>
        <text>  </text>
        <text>  </text>
	<!-- more texts here -->
      </group>
    </text>
    <text> <!-- start of The Delights of the Muses -->
      <group>
        <text>  </text>
        <text>  </text>
	<!-- more texts here -->
      </group>
    </text>
  </group>
  <back> <!-- back matter for the whole collection --> </back>
</text></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>group</gi> element may be used in this way to encode any kind
of collection of which the constituents are regarded by the encoder as
texts in their own right.  Examples include anthologies or collections
of verse or
prose by multiple authors, florilegia, or commonplace books,
journals, day books, etc.  As a fairly typical example, we consider
<title>The Norton Book of Travel</title>, an anthology edited by Paul
Fussell and published in 1987 by W. W. Norton.  This work comprises
the following major sections:
<list type="ordered">
<item>Front matter (title page, acknowledgments, introductory essay)</item>
<item>The Beginnings</item>
<item>The Eighteenth Century and the Grand Tour</item>
<item>The Heyday</item>
<item>Touristic Tendencies</item>
<item>Post Tourism</item>
<item>Back matter (permissions list, index)</item></list>
Each titled section listed above comprises a group of extracts or
complete texts from writers of a given historical period, preceded by an
introductory essay.  For example, the second group listed above
contains, inter alia, the following:
<list type="ordered">
<item>Prefatory essay</item>
<item>Five letters by Lady Mary Wortley Montagu</item>
<item>An extract from Swift's Gullivers Travels</item>
<item>Two poems by Alexander Pope</item>
<item>Two extracts from Boswell's Journal</item>
<item>A poem by William Blake</item></list>
Each group of writings by a single author is preceded by a brief
biographical notice.  Some of the extracts are quite lengthy, containing
several chapters or other divisions; others are quite short.  As the
above list indicates, the texts included range across all kinds of
material:  verse, prose, journals and letters.
 </p>
<p>The easiest way of encoding such an anthology is to treat each
individual extract as a text in its own right.  A sequence of texts by a
single author, together with the biographical note preceding it, can
then be treated as a single <gi>group</gi> element within the larger
<gi>group</gi> formed by the section.  The sequence of single or
composite texts making up a single section of the work is likewise
treated, together with its prefatory essay, as a single <gi>group</gi>
within the work.  Schematically:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-03" valid="feasible"><text> 
<!-- the whole anthology -->
  <front>
<!-- title page, acknowledgments, introductory essay -->
  </front>
  <group> <!-- body of anthology starts here -->
    <group><head>The Beginnings</head>
       <!-- sequence of texts or groups -->
    </group>
    <group> <!-- The Eighteenth Century and the Grand Tour -->
      <text> <!-- prefatory essay by editor --> </text>
      <group> <!-- Section on Lady Mary Wortley Montagu starts -->     
        <text> <!-- biographical notice by editor -->     </text>
        <text>  <!-- first letter -->    </text>
        <text>  <!-- second letter -->    </text>
	<!-- ... -->
      </group>     <!-- end of Montagu section -->
      <text>     <!-- single text by Jonathan Swift starts -->
        <front> <!-- biographical notice by editor -->  </front>
        <body>    </body>
      </text>  <!-- end of Swift section -->  
      <group>  <!-- Section on Alexander Pope starts -->
        <text> <!-- biographical notice by editor --> </text>
        <text>  <!-- first poem --> </text>
        <text>  <!-- second poem --> </text>
      </group> <!-- end of Pope section -->
    <!-- ... -->
    </group> <!-- end of 18th century section --> 
    <group><head>The Heyday</head>
    <!-- texts and subgroups -->
    </group>
<!-- ... -->
  </group> <!-- end of the anthology proper -->
  <back> <!-- back matter for anthology --> </back>
</text> </egXML>
 </p>
<p>Note that the editor's introductory essays on each author may be
treated as texts in their own right (as the essays on Lady Mary
Wortley Montagu and Alexander Pope have been treated above), or as
front matter to the embedded text, as the essay on Swift has been.
The treatment in the example is intentionally inconsistent, to allow
comparison of the two approaches. Consistency can be imposed either
by treating the Swift section as a <gi>group</gi> containing one text
by Swift and one by the editor, or by treating the Montagu and Pope
sections as <gi>text</gi> elements containing the editor's essays as
front matter. Marked in the second way, the Pope section of the book
would look like this:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible"><text>  <!-- Section on Alexander Pope starts -->
        <front> <!-- biographical notice by editor --> </front>
	<group>
	  <text>  <!-- first poem --> </text>
        <text>  <!-- second poem --> </text>
      </group>
      </text> <!-- end of Pope section-->   </egXML>
 </p>
<p>The essays on <q>The Eighteenth Century and the Grand Tour</q> and
other larger sections could also be tagged as <soCalled>front</soCalled>
matter in the same way, by treating the larger sections as <gi>text</gi>
elements rather than <gi>group</gi> elements.
 </p>
<p>Where, as in this case, an anthology contains different kinds of
text (for example, mixtures of prose and drama, or transcribed speech
and dictionary entries, or letters and verse), the elements to be
encoded will of course  be drawn from more than one  module.
The elements provided by the core module
described in chapter <ptr target="#CO"/> should however prove adequate
for most simple purposes, where prose, drama, and verse are combined
in a single collection.
 </p>
<p>For anthologies of short extracts such as commonplace books, it may
often be preferable to regard each extract not as a text in its own
right but simply as a quotation or <gi>cit</gi> element. The following
component-level elements may be used to encode quotations of this kind:
<specList><specDesc key="cit"/><specDesc key="quote"/></specList>
For example, the chapter of <soCalled>extracts</soCalled> which appears
in the front matter of Melville's <title>Moby Dick</title> might be
encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSHD-eg-30"><div n="2" type="chap">
  <head>Extracts</head>
  <head>(Supplied by a sub-sub-Librarian)</head>
  <p>It will be seen that this mere painstaking burrower and
	grubworm of a poor devil of a Sub-Sub appears to have gone
	through the long Vaticans and street-stalls of the earth,
	picking up whatever random allusions to whales he could
	anyways find ...
	Here ye strike but splintered hearts together — there,
	ye shall strike unsplinterable glasses!</p>
  <p>
	<cit>
	  <quote>And God created great whales.</quote>
	  <bibl>Genesis</bibl>
	</cit>
	<cit>
	  <quote>
		<l>Leviathan maketh a path to shine after him;</l>
		<l>One would think the deep to be hoary.</l>
	  </quote>
	  <bibl>Job</bibl>
	</cit>
	<cit>
	  <quote>By art is created that great Leviathan,
		called a Commonwealth or State — (in Latin,
		<mentioned xml:lang="la">civitas</mentioned>), which
		is but an artificial man.</quote>
	  <bibl>Opening sentence of Hobbes's Leviathan</bibl>
	</cit>
  </p>
</div></egXML>
For more information on the use of the <gi>quote</gi> and <gi>bibl</gi>
elements, see sections <ptr target="#COHQQ"/> and <ptr target="#COBI"/>
respectively.
 </p>

</div>
<div xml:id="DSFLT"><head>Floating Texts</head>
<p>An important characteristic of the unitary or composite text
structures discussed so far is that they can be regarded as forming what is
mathematically known as a <term>tesselation</term> covering the whole
of the available text (or text division) at each hierarchic
level. Just as an XML document has a single root element containing
a single tree, each node of which forms a properly nested sub-tree, so
it seems natural to think of the internal structure of a text as
decomposable hierarchically into subparts, each of which is a
properly nested subtree. While this is undoubtedly true of a large
number of documents, it is not true of all. In particular, it is not
true of texts which are only partly  tesselated at a given level. For
example, if a text A is contained by text B in such a way that part of
B precedes A and part follows it, we cannot tesselate the whole of B.
In such a case, we say that text A is a <q>floating</q> text. </p>

<p>The <gi>floatingText</gi> element is a member of the 
<ident type="class">model.divPart</ident> class, and can thus appear within
any division level element in the same way as a paragraph. For
example, texts such as the <title>Decameron</title> or the
<title>Arabian Nights</title> might be regarded as containing many
floating texts embedded within another single text, the framing
narrative, rather than as groups of discrete texts in which the
fragments of framing narrative are regarded as front or back matter.
</p>

<p>As an example, we consider an 18th century text <title>The Lining to
the <hi>Patch-Work Screen</hi></title>, by Jane Barker (1726). This 
lengthy narrative contains nearly a hundred distinct <q>tales</q>
embedded (as the title suggests) in a single patchwork. The work
begins by introducing the central character, Galecia, but within a few pages 
launches into a distinct narrative, the story of Captain Manly:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-04">
<p>Galecia one Evening setting alone in her Chamber by a clear Fire,
and a clean Hearth ...  reflected on the Providence of our
All-wise and Gracious Creator.... </p>
<p>She was thus ruminating, when a Gentleman enter'd the Room, the
Door being a jar...  calling for a Candle, she beg'd a thousand
Pardons, engaged him to sit down, and let her know, what had so long
conceal'd him from her Correspondence.
</p>
<pb n="5"/>
<floatingText><body><head>The Story of <hi>Captain Manly</hi></head>
<p>Dear Galecia, said he, though you partly know the loose, or rather
lewd Life that I led in my Youth; yet I can't forbear relating part of
it to you by way of Abhorrence...
<!-- Captain Manly's story here -->
I had lost and spent all I had in the World; in which I verified the
Old Proverb, That a Rolling Stone never gathers Moss,
</p></body></floatingText>
<pb n="37"/>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>Following the conclusion of Captain Manly's tale, we are
returned to Galecia, and almost immediately after that into two further
stories. <!--This second story opens within a paragraph, to cope with which
we could use the sample and part attribute discussed above for div -->
However, the Galecia narrative returns between each of the texts,
which is why we choose to represent them as <gi>floatingText</gi>s:

<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-04">
<p>The Gentleman having finish'd his Story, Galecia waited on him to
the Stairs-head; and at her return, casting her Eyes on the Table, she
saw lying there an old dirty rumpled Book, and found in it the
following story: </p>
<floatingText><body><p> IN the time of the Holy War when
Christians from all parts went into the Holy Land to oppose the Turks;
Amongst these there was a certain English Knight...</p>
<!-- rest of story here -->
<p>The King graciously pardoned the Knight; Richard was kindly receiv'd
into his Convent, and all things went on in good order: But from hence
came the Proverb, We must not strike <hi>Robert</hi> for
<hi>Richard.</hi></p></body></floatingText>
<pb n="43"/>      
<p>By this time Galecia's Maid brought up her Supper; after which she
cast her Eyes again on the foresaid little Book, where she found the
following Story, which she read through before she went to bed.
</p>
<floatingText><body><head>The Cause of the Moors Overrunning
<hi>Spain</hi></head>
<p>King ———— of Spain at his Death, committed the Government of his
Kingdom to his Brother Don ——— till his little Son should come of
Age ...</p>
<p>Thus the little Story ended, without telling what Misery
befel the King and Kingdom, by the Moors, who over ran the Country for
many Years after.  To which, we may well apply the Proverb,
<quote>
  <l>Who drives the Devil's Stages,</l>
  <l>Deserves the Devil's Wages</l>
</quote></p>
</body></floatingText>
<p>The reading this Trifle of a Story detained Galecia from her Rest
beyond her usual Hour; for she slept so sound the next Morning, that
she did not rise, till a Lady's Footman came to tell her, that his
Lady and another or two were coming to breakfast with her...
</p>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>In other multi-narrative texts, the individual nested tales may
have greater significance than the framing narratives, and it may
therefore be preferable to treat the fragments of framing narrative as
front or back matter associated with each nested tale. This is
commonly done, for example, in texts such as Chaucer's <title>Canterbury
Tales</title>, where each tale is typically presented with front matter in
which the teller of the tale is introduced, and back matter in which
the pilgrims comment on it.</p>

<p>It is important to distinguish between the uses of <gi>floatingText</gi> and <gi>quote</gi>. Whereas the semantics of <gi>quote</gi> suggest that its content derives from a source external to the current text, <gi>floatingText</gi> carries no such implication and is simply used whenever the richer content model that it provides is required to support the markup of a part of a text that is presented as a discrete <soCalled>inclusion.</soCalled> In some cases, such inclusions could be considered external (e.g., enclosures, attachments, etc.); often however, as in the examples above, the included text bears no signs of emanating from outside.</p>

<p><gi>floatingText</gi> and <gi>quote</gi> may be used in combination. For a text with rich internal structure that is quoted at length, <gi>floatingText</gi> might be used within <gi>quote</gi>. Also, like a unitary text, <gi>floatingText</gi> may include one or more quoted sections, each marked with a <gi>quote</gi> element.</p>

</div></div>

<div xml:id="DSVIRT"><head>Virtual Divisions</head>
<p>Where the whole of a division can be automatically generated, for
example because it is derived from
another part of this or another  document, an encoder may prefer not to represent it
explicitly but instead simply mark its location by means of a
processing instruction, or by using the special purpose
<gi>divGen</gi> element:
<specList><specDesc key="divGen"/></specList>
</p>
<p>This element is made available by the <ident type="class">model.divGenLike</ident> class of which it is the sole
element. The <gi>divGen</gi> element is a member of the
<ident type="class">att.typed</ident> class, from which it  inherits the
<att>type</att> and <att>subtype</att> attributes. It may appear
wherever a <gi>div</gi> or <gi>div1</gi> (<gi>div2</gi>, etc.)  element may appear.</p>



<p>For example, if the table of contents (toc) for a given work is simply
derived by copying  the first <gi>head</gi> element from each
<gi>div</gi> element in a text, it might be more easily encoded as
follows:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><divGen type="toc"/></egXML>
Similarly, in a digital edition combining a transcribed version
of some text with a translated version of it, it may be desired to
represent  the transcript, the translation, and an aligned version of
the two as three distinct divisions. This could be achieved by an
encoding like the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div>
<!-- transcript here--></div>
<div><!-- translation here --></div> <divGen type="alignment"/></egXML> The processing to be carried out when a
<gi>divGen</gi> element is rendered will be determined by the
application program or stylesheet in use: the function of the TEI
markup is simply to identify the location at which the virtual
division is to be generated, and also to provide some information
about the kind of division to be generated. As such it may be regarded
as a special kind of processing instruction, and could equally well be
represented by one.</p>

</div>


<div type="div2" xml:id="DSFRONT"><head>Front Matter</head>
<p>By <term>front matter</term> we mean distinct sections of a text
(usually, but not necessarily, a printed one), prefixed to it by way of
introduction or identification as a part of its production. Features
such as title pages or prefaces are clear examples; a less definite
case might be the prologue attached to a play.  The front matter of an
encoded text should not be confused with the TEI header described in
chapter <ptr target="#HD"/>, which serves as a kind of front matter for
the computer file itself, not the text it encodes.
 </p>
<p>An encoder may choose simply to ignore the front matter in a text,
if the original presentation of the work is of no interest, or for
other reasons; alternatively some or all components of the front matter
may be thought worth including with the text as components of the
<gi>front</gi> element.<note place="bottom">This decision should be recorded in the
<gi>samplingDecl</gi> element of the header.</note> With the exception of
the title page, (on which see section <ptr target="#DSTITL"/>), front
matter should be encoded using the same elements as the rest of a text.
As with the divisions of the text body, no other specific tags are
proposed here for the various kinds of subdivision which may appear
within front matter:  instead either numbered or un-numbered
<gi>div</gi> elements may be used.  The following suggested
values<note place="bottom">As with all lists of <soCalled>suggested
values</soCalled> for attributes, it is recommended that software
written to handle TEI-conformant texts be prepared to recognize and
handle these values when they occur, without limiting the user to the
values in this list.</note>
for the <att>type</att> attribute may be used to distinguish various
kinds of division characteristic of front matter:
<list type="gloss"><label><val>preface</val></label>
<item>A foreword or preface addressed to
    the reader in which the author or publisher explains the
    content, purpose, or origin of the text.</item><label><val>ack</val></label>
<item>A formal declaration of
    acknowledgment by the author in which persons and institutions
    are thanked for their part in the creation of a text.</item><label><val>dedication</val></label>
<item>A formal offering or dedication of
    a text to one or more persons or institutions by the author.</item><label><val>abstract</val></label>
<item>A summary of the content of a text as
    continuous prose.</item><label><val>contents</val></label>
<item>A table of contents, specifying the
    structure of a work and listing its constituents.
    The <gi>list</gi>
    element should be used to mark its structure.</item><label><val>frontispiece</val></label>
<item>A pictorial frontispiece,
    possibly including some text.</item></list>
 </p>
<p>The following extended example demonstrates how various parts of the
front matter of a text may be encoded.  The front part begins with a
title page, which is presented in section <ptr target="#DSTITL"/> below.
This is followed by a dedication and a preface, each of which is encoded
as a distinct <gi>div</gi>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-05"><div type="dedication">
  <p>To my parents, Ida and Max Fish</p>
</div>
<div type="preface"><head>Preface</head>
  <p>The answer this book gives to its title question is <q>there is
      and there isn't</q>.</p>
  <p>Chapters 1–12 have been previously published in the
    following journals and collections:
    <list>
      <item>chapters 1 and 3 in <title>New literary History</title></item>
      <item>chapter 10 in <title>Boundary II</title> (1980)</item>
    </list>.
    I am grateful for permission to reprint.</p>
  <signed>S.F.</signed>
</div></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The front matter concludes with another <gi>div</gi> element, shown
in the next example, this time containing a table of contents, which
contains a <gi>list</gi> element (as described in section 
<ptr target="#COLI"/>).  Note the use of the <gi>ptr</gi> element to provide
page-references:  the implication here is that the target identifiers
supplied (fish1, fish2, etc.) will correspond with identifiers used  for
the <gi>div</gi> elements containing chapters of the text itself. (For the
<gi>ptr</gi> element, see <ptr target="#COXR"/>.)  
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-05"><div type="contents">
  <head>Contents</head>
  <list>
	<item>Introduction, or How I stopped Worrying and Learned to Love
	  Interpretation <ptr target="#fish1"/></item>
	<item>
	  <list>
		<head>Part One: Literature in the Reader</head>
		<item n="1">Literature in the Reader: Affective Stylistics
		  <ptr target="#fish2"/></item>
		<item n="2">What is Stylistics and Why Are They Saying Such
		  Terrible Things About It? <ptr target="#fish3"/></item>
	  </list></item></list>
  </div>
<div xml:id="fish1"><head>Introduction</head>
<!-- .... -->
</div>
<div xml:id="fish2"><head>Literature in the Reader</head>
<!-- .... -->
</div>
<div xml:id="fish3"><head>What is stylistics?</head>
<!-- .... -->
</div>
</egXML>
Alternatively, the pointers in the index might link to the page breaks
at which a chapter begins, assuming that these have been included in
the markup:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><!-- .... -->
	<item n="1">Literature in the Reader: Affective Stylistics
		  <ref target="#fish-p24">24</ref></item>
<!-- .... -->
<div type="chapter"><head>Literature in the Reader</head>
<pb xml:id="fish-p24"/>
<!-- .... -->
</div>
<!-- .... -->
</egXML>
 </p>
<p>The following example uses numbered divisions to mark up the front
matter of a medieval text. 
Note that in this case no title page in the modern
sense occurs; the title is simply given as a heading at the start of the
front matter. Note also the use of the <att>type</att> attribute on the
<gi>div</gi> elements to indicate document elements comparatively
unusual in modern books such as the initial prayer:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSFRONT-eg-69"><front>
  <div1 type="incipit">
    <p>Here bygynniþ a book of contemplacyon, þe whiche 
      is clepyd <title>þE CLOWDE OF VNKNOWYNG</title>,
      in þe whiche a soule is onyd wiþ GOD.</p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="prayer">
    <head>Here biginneþ þe preyer on þe prologe.</head>
    <p>God, unto whom alle hertes ben open, &amp; unto whome alle wille
      spekiþ, &amp; unto whom no priue þing is hid: I beseche
      þee so for to clense þe entent of myn hert wiþ þe
      unspekable 3ift of þi grace, þat I may parfiteliche
      loue þee &amp; worþilich  preise þee. Amen.</p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="preface">
    <head>Here biginneþ þe prolog.</head> 
    <p>In þe name of þe Fader &amp; of þe Sone &amp;
      of þe Holy Goost.</p>
    <p>I charge þee &amp; I beseeche þee, wiþ as moche
      power &amp; vertewe as þe bonde of charite is sufficient
      to suffre, what-so-euer þou be þat þis book schalt
      haue in possession ...</p>
  </div1>
  <div1 type="contents">
    <head>Here biginneþ a table of þe chapitres.</head>
    <list>
      <label>þe first chapitre </label>
      <item>Of foure degrees of Cristen mens leuing; &amp; of þe
        cours of his cleping þat þis book was maad vnto.</item>
      <label>þe secound chapitre</label>
      <item>A schort stering to meeknes &amp; to þe werk of þis
        book</item>
      <label>þe fiue and seuenti chapitre</label>
      <item>Of somme certein tokenes bi þe whiche a man may proue
        wheþer he be clepid of God to worche in þis werk.</item>
    </list>
    <trailer>&amp; here eendeþ þe table of þe chapitres.</trailer>
  </div1>
</front></egXML>
<!-- Cloud of Unknowing, ed Phyllis Hodgson, EETS, 1944 -->
 </p>
<p>If, however, the table of contents can be automatically generated
from the remainder of the text, it may be preferable simply to mark
its presence, either by means of an empty  <gi>divGen</gi> element or
by using an appropriate processing instruction.</p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DSTITL"><head>Title Pages</head>
<p>Detailed analysis of the title page and other
<term>preliminaries</term> of older printed books and manuscripts is of
major importance in descriptive bibliography and the cataloguing of
printed books; such analysis may require a rather more detailed module
than that proposed here.<!--note place="bottom">Definition of such a module remains
a work item for the TEI; such modules for contemporary printed matter
already exist or are being created within the publishing industry, for
example the Majour (Modular Application for Journals) Project of the
European Workgroup on SGML. See for example <bibl><title>MAJOUR:
Modular Application for Journals: DTD for Article Headers</title>
([n.p.]: EWS, 1991).</bibl></note--> The following elements are
suggested as a means of encoding the major features of most title pages:
<specList>
<specDesc key="titlePage"/>
<specDesc key="docTitle"/>
<specDesc key="titlePart" atts="type"/>
<specDesc key="argument"/>
<specDesc key="byline"/>
<specDesc key="docAuthor"/>
<specDesc key="epigraph"/>
<specDesc key="imprimatur"/>
<specDesc key="docEdition"/>
<specDesc key="docImprint"/>
<specDesc key="docDate"/>
<specDesc key="graphic"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>Together with the <gi>figure</gi> element described in chapter <ptr target="#FT"/>, these elements constitute the <ident type="class">model.titlepagePart</ident> class. Any number of elements
from this class can appear grouped together within a
<gi>titlePage</gi> element. The <gi>figure</gi> element is included so
as to enable encoders to record the presence of complex non-textual
material on a title page. For simple cases such as printers'
ornaments or illustrations the <gi>graphic</gi> element discussed
in section <ptr target="#COGR"/> should be adequate.  </p>
<p>The elements listed above, together with the <gi>head</gi> element,
also constitute the class <ident type="class">model.pLike.front</ident>. The elements in this class can
appear within a minimal <gi>front</gi> element without any need to
group them together and encode a complete title page.</p>
<p>Encoders wishing to add new elements to either class may do so
using the methods described in section <ptr target="#MD"/>. Two
examples of the use of these elements follow. First, the title page of
the work discussed earlier in this section: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-05"><front>
  <titlePage>
    <docTitle>
      <titlePart type="main">Is There a Text in This Class?</titlePart>
      <titlePart type="sub">The Authority of Interpretive Communities</titlePart>
    </docTitle>
    <docAuthor>Stanley Fish</docAuthor>
    <docImprint>
	  <publisher>Harvard University Press</publisher>
      <pubPlace>Cambridge, Massachusetts</pubPlace>
      <pubPlace>London, England</pubPlace>
    </docImprint>
  </titlePage></front></egXML></p>
<p>Second, a characteristically verbose 17th century example. Note the
use of the <gi>lb</gi> tag to mark the line breaks of the original
where necessary:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DS-eg-06"><titlePage>
  <docTitle>
    <titlePart type="main">THE
      <lb/>Pilgrim's Progress 
      <lb/>FROM
      <lb/>THIS WORLD,
      <lb/>TO
      <lb/>That which is to come:</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="sub">Delivered under the Similitude of a
      <lb/>DREAM</titlePart>
    <titlePart type="desc">Wherein is Discovered,
      <lb/>The manner of his setting out,
      <lb/>His Dangerous Journey; And safe
      <lb/>Arrival at the Desired Countrey.</titlePart>
  </docTitle>
  <epigraph>
    <cit><quote>I have used Similitudes,</quote><bibl>Hos. 12.10</bibl></cit>
  </epigraph>
  <byline>By <docAuthor>John Bunyan</docAuthor>.</byline>
  <imprimatur>Licensed and Entred according to Order.</imprimatur>
  <docImprint>
    <pubPlace>LONDON,</pubPlace>
    Printed for <name>Nath. Ponder</name>
    <lb/>at the <name>Peacock</name> in the <name>Poultrey</name>
    <lb/>near <name>Cornhil</name>, <docDate>1678</docDate>.
  </docImprint></titlePage></egXML></p>
<p>Where, as here, it is considered important to encode salient
features of the way a title page was originally rendered,
the techniques exemplified in <ptr target="#HD57"/> may also be
useful. </p>

<specGrp xml:id="DDSTPAGE">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/titlePage.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/docTitle.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/titlePart.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/docAuthor.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/imprimatur.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/docEdition.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/docImprint.xml"/><include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/docDate.xml"/></specGrp>

<p>Where title pages are encoded, their physical rendition is
often of considerable importance.  One approach to this requirement
would be to use the <gi>seg</gi> tag, described in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>, to segment the typographic content of each part of the
title page, and then use the global <att>rend</att> attribute to specify
its rendition.  Another would be to use a module specialized for the
description of typographic entities such as pages, lines, rules, etc.,
bearing special-purpose attributes to describe line-height, leading,
degree of kerning, font, etc. Further discussion of these problems is
provided in chapter <ptr target="#PH"/>.
 </p>

<specGrp xml:id="DDSFRONT">


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/front.xml"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSTPAGE"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DSBACK"><head>Back Matter</head>
<p>Conventions vary as to which elements are grouped as back matter and
which as front.  For example, some books place the table of contents at
the front, and others at the back.  Even title pages may appear at the
back of a book as well as at the front.  The content model for
<gi>back</gi> and <gi>front</gi> elements are therefore identical.
 </p>
<p>The following suggested values may be used for the <att>type</att>
attribute on all division elements, in order to distinguish various
kinds of division characteristic of back matter:
<list type="gloss"><label><val>appendix</val></label>
<item>An ancillary self-contained section of
a work, often providing additional but in some sense extra-canonical
text.</item><label><val>glossary</val></label>
<item>A list of terms associated with definition texts
(<soCalled>glosses</soCalled>): this should be encoded as a <tag>list type="gloss"</tag>
(see section <ptr target="#COLI"/>).</item><label><val>notes</val></label>
<item>A section in which textual or
other kinds of notes are gathered together.</item><label><val>bibliogr</val></label>
<item>A list of bibliographic citations: this should be encoded
as a <gi>listBibl</gi> (see section <ptr target="#COBI"/>).</item><label><val>index</val></label>
<item>Any form of index to the work.</item><label><val>colophon</val></label>
<item>A statement appearing at the end of a book describing the
conditions of its physical production.</item></list>
 </p>
<p>No additional elements are proposed for the encoding of back matter
at present.  Some characteristic examples follow; first, an index (for
the case in which a printed index is of sufficient interest to merit
transcription):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSBACK-eg-83"><back>  
<div type="index">
  <head>Index</head>
  <list type="index">
  <item>Actors, public, paid for the contempt attending
    their profession, <ref>263</ref></item>
  <item>Africa, cause assigned for the barbarous state of
    the interior parts of that continent, <ref>125</ref></item>
  <item>Agriculture
    <list type="indexentry">
    <item>ancient policy of Europe unfavourable to, <ref>371</ref></item>
    <item>artificers necessary to carry it on, <ref>481</ref></item>
    <item>cattle and tillage mutually improve each other, <ref>325</ref></item>
    <item>wealth arising from more solid than that which proceeds
    from commerce <ref>520</ref></item>
    </list></item>
  <item>Alehouses, not the efficient cause of drunkenness, <ref>461</ref></item>
  </list>
</div>
</back></egXML>
<!-- Smith, Wealth of Nations, 1776; index to vol 1 -->
Note that if the page breaks in the original source have also been
explicitly encoded, and given identifiers, the references to them in the
above index can more usefully be recorded as links. For example,
assuming that the encoding of page 461 of the original source starts
like this:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><pb xml:id="P461"/></egXML>
then the last item above might be encoded more usefully in either
of the following forms:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">  <item>Alehouses, not
the efficient cause of drunkenness, <ref target="#P461">461</ref></item>
  <item>Alehouses, not the efficient cause of drunkenness, <ptr target="#P461"/></item>
</egXML></p>
<p>Next, a back-matter division in epistolary form:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#DSBACK-eg-86"><back>  
  <div type="letter">
    <head>A letter written to his wife, founde with this booke
      after his death.</head>
    <p>The remembrance of the many wrongs offred thee, and thy
      unreproued vertues, adde greater sorrow to my miserable state,
      than I can utter or thou conceiue. ...
      ... yet trust I in the world to come to find mercie, by the
      merites of my Saiuour to whom I commend thee, and commit
      my soule.</p>
    <signed>Thy repentant husband for his disloyaltie,
      <name>Robert Greene.</name></signed>
    <epigraph xml:lang="la"><p>Faelicem fuisse infaustum</p></epigraph>
    <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
  </div>
</back></egXML>
<!-- Greene, Groatsworth of witte, 1592 --></p>
<p>And finally, a list of corrigenda and addenda with pseudo-epistolary
features:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#SAPTEG-eg-3"><back>
  <div type="corrigenda">
    <head>Addenda</head>
    <salute xml:lang="la">M. Scriblerus Lectori</salute>
<p>Once more, gentle reader I appeal unto thee, from the shameful
ignorance of the Editor, by whom Our own Specimen of
<name>Virgil</name> hath been mangled in such miserable manner, that
scarce without tears can we behold it. At the very entrance, Instead
of <q xml:lang="grc">προλεγομενα</q>, lo! 
<q xml:lang="grc">προλεγωμενα</q> with an Omega! 
and in the same line <q xml:lang="la">consulâs</q> with a circumflex! 
In the next page thou findest <q xml:lang="la">leviter perlabere</q>, 
which his ignorance took to be the infinitive mood of 
<q xml:lang="la">perlabor</q> but ought to be 
<q xml:lang="la">perlabi</q> ... Wipe away all these
monsters, Reader, with thy quill.</p>
  </div>
</back></egXML>
<!-- Pope, Dunciad Variorum, 1729 -->
	<!--  end of draft -->
 </p>
<specGrp xml:id="DDSBACK">


<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/back.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="DSSTRUC">
<head>Module for Default Text Structure</head>
<p>The module described by the present chapter has the following
components:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DDS" ident="textstructure">
<altIdent type="FPI">Default Text Structure</altIdent><desc>Default
text structure</desc>
<desc xml:lang="fr">Structure textuelle par défaut</desc>
<desc xml:lang="zh-TW">預設文件結構</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Struttura standard del testo</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Estrutura do texto por defeito</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">テキスト構造モジュール</desc></moduleSpec>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSTEXT"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSDIV"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSDIVN"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSDIVX"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSBACK"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DDSFRONT"/>
The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/></p></div></div>
