<!-- needs rewritten -->
<!-- credit where credit is due -->

<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0"
      xml:id="FM1"><head>Introductory Note</head>
<p>The primary goal of this revision has been to make available a new
and corrected version of the TEI Guidelines which:
<list>
<item>is expressed in XML and conforms to a TEI-conformant XML
       DTD;</item>
<item>generates a set of DTD fragments that can be combined
       together to form either SGML or XML document type
       definitions;</item>
	  <item>corrects blatant errors, typographical mishaps, and other
		egregious editorial oversights;</item>
<item>can be processed and maintained using readily available XML
       tools instead of the special-purpose ad hoc software originally
       used for TEI P3.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>A second major design goal of this revision has been to ensure that the
      DTD fragments generated would not break existing documents: in
      other words, that any document conforming to the original TEI P3
      SGML DTD would also conform to the new XML version of
      it. Although full backwards compatibility cannot be guaranteed,
      we believe our implementation is consistent with that goal.
      </p>
<p>In most respects, the TEI Guidelines have stood the test of time remarkably
well. The present edition makes no substantial attempt to rewrite those few parts
of them which have now been rendered obsolete by changes since their
first publication, though an indication is given in the text of where such rewriting is
now considered necessary. Neither does the present version attempt to
address any of the many possible new areas of digital activity in which
the TEI approach to standardization may have something to offer. Both
these tasks require the existence of an informed and active TEI
Council to direct and validate such extension and maintenance work,
in response to the changing needs and priorities of the TEI user community. 
</p>
<p>Two exceptions to the above principles may be cited: firstly, the
chapter which originally provided a <soCalled>Gentle
Introduction</soCalled> to SGML has been completely rewritten to
provide a similarly gentle introduction to XML; secondly the chapter
on character sets has been completely revised in light of the
close connexion between Unicode and XML. The editors gratefully
acknowledge the assistance of the <foreign>ad hoc</foreign> workgroup chaired by Christian
Wittern, which undertook to provide expert advice and correction at
very short notice, in the latter task.</p>
<p>The preparation of this new version relied extensively on
preliminary work carried out by the former North American editor of
the TEI Guidelines, C.M. Sperberg-McQueen. In a TEI working paper
written in 1999<note place="foot"><title>TEI ED W69</title>, available
from the TEI website at <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw69.htm"/>.</note> he sketched
out a precise blueprint for the conversion of the TEI from SGML to
XML, which we have implemented, with only slight modification.</p>
<p>The Editors would also like to express thanks to the
team of volunteers from the TEI community who helped us with the task
of proof reading the first draft during the summer of 2001; and to 
      Sebastian Rahtz of Oxford University Computing Services, without
      whose skill and enthusiasm this new edition would not have been
      possible.
</p>
<p>A substantial proportion of the work of preparing this new edition was
funded with the assistance of a grant from the US National
Endowment for the Humanities, whose continued support of the TEI has
also been crucial to the effort of setting up the TEI Consortium.
</p>
<p>Finally, we would like to thank all our colleagues on the interim
management board of the TEI Consortium, in particular its Chairman
John Unsworth, for their continued support of
the TEI's work, and their willingness to devote effort to the
difficult task of overseeing its transition to a new organizational
infrastructure.</p>
<p>Summary details of the changes made in the present and previous
editions are given in their Prefatory Notes, all of which are now
reproduced in an Appendix to the present edition: see <ptr target="#PREFS"/>.
</p>
<signed>Lou Burnard and Syd Bauman (TEI Editors)
Oxford and Providence, March 2007.</signed>
</div>
