<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="FS" n="16"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Feature Structures</head>
<!-- this para is repeated at the start of ISO std -->
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">A <term>feature structure</term> is a general purpose data
structure which identifies and groups together individual
<term>features</term>, each of which associates a name with one or
more values.  Because of the generality of feature structures, they
can be used to represent many different kinds of information, but they
are of particular usefulness in the representation of linguistic
analyses, especially where such analyses are partial, or
<term>underspecified</term>. Feature structures represent the
interrelations among various pieces of information, and their
instantiation in markup provides a <term>metalanguage</term> for the
generic representation of analyses and interpretations.  Moreover,
this instantiation allows feature values to be of specific
<term>types</term>, and for restrictions to be placed on the values
for particular features, by means of <term>feature system
declarations</term>. <!-- , which are discussed in chapter <ptr
target="FD"/>. Such restrictions provide the basis for at least
partial validation of the feature-structure encodings that are
used.--><note place="foot">The recommendations of this chapter have
been adopted as ISO Standard 24610-1 <title>Language Resource
Management — Feature Structures — Part One: Feature Structure Representation</title></note>
</p>
<div type="div2"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Organization of this Chapter</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This chapter is organized as follows.  Following this introduction,
section <ptr target="#FSBI"/> introduces the elements <gi>fs</gi> and
<gi>f</gi>, used to represent feature structures and features
respectively, together with the elementary <term>binary</term> feature
value.  Section <ptr target="#FSSY"/> introduces elements for
representing other kinds of atomic feature values such as
<term>symbolic</term>, <term>numeric</term>, and <term>string</term>
values.  Section <ptr target="#FSFL"/> introduces the notion of
predefined <term>libraries</term> or groups of features or feature
values along with methods for referencing their components.  Section
<ptr target="#FSST"/> introduces complex values, in particular
feature-structures as values, thus enabling feature structures to be
recursively defined.  Section <ptr target="#FSSS"/> discusses other
complex values, in particular values which are collections, organized
as <term>set</term>s, <term>bag</term>s, and
<term>list</term>s. Section <ptr target="#FVE"/> discusses how
the operations of
alternation, negation, and collection of feature values may be represented.
Section <ptr target="#FSBO"/> discusses ways of representing
underspecified, default, or uncertain values.
Section <ptr target="#FSLINK"/> discusses how analyses may be linked to
other parts of an encoded text. Formal definitions for
all the elements introduced in this chapter are provided in section
<ptr target="#FSDEF"/>. <!-- KL says this shd be in Annex A Normative --></p>
<!-- &intro.odd; -->
<!-- intro moved to section 4 somewhere -->
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSBI"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Elementary Feature Structures and the Binary
Feature Value</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The fundamental elements used to represent a feature structure
analysis are <gi>f</gi> (for <term>feature</term>), which represents a
feature-value pair, and <gi>fs</gi> (for <term>feature
structure</term>), which represents a structure made up of such
feature-value pairs.  The <gi>fs</gi> element has an optional
<att>type</att> attribute which may be used to represent typed feature
structures, and may contain any number of <gi>f</gi> elements.  An
<gi>f</gi> element has a required <att>name</att> attribute and an
associated <term>value</term>. The value may be simple: that is, a
single binary, numeric, symbolic (i.e. taken from a restricted set of
legal values), or string value, or a collection of such values,
organized in various ways, for example, as a list; or it may be
complex, that is, it may itself be a feature structure, thus providing
a degree of recursion. Values may be under-specified or defaulted in
various ways.  These possibilities are all described in more detail in
this and the following sections.
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Feature and feature-value representations (including feature
structure representations) may be embedded directly at any point in an
XML document, or they may be collected together in special-purpose
feature or feature-value <term>libraries</term>. The components of
such libraries may then be referenced from other feature or
feature-value representations, using the <att>feats</att> or
<att>fVal</att> attribute as appropriate. </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">We begin by considering the simple case of a feature structure
which  contains binary-valued features only. The following three XML elements  are
needed to  represent such a feature structure: 
<specList>
<specDesc key="fs" atts="type feats"/>
<specDesc key="f" atts="name fVal"/>
<specDesc key="binary"/>
</specList>
The attributes <att>feats</att> and the <att>fVal</att> are not
discussed in this section: they provide an alternative way of
indicating the content of an element, as further discussed in  section
<ptr target="#FSFL"/>. 
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">An <gi>fs</gi> element containing <gi>f</gi> elements with binary
values can be straightforwardly used to encode the <term>matrices</term>
of feature-value specifications for phonetic segments, such as the
following for the English segment [s].<note place="foot">Adapted from 
Noam Chomsky and Morris Halle, <title>The Sound Pattern of English</title>.  
New York:  Harper &amp; Row, 1968, p. 415.</note>
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[+---          ---+
| consonantal +  |
| vocalic  -     |
| voiced  -      |
| anterior  +    |
| coronal  +     |
| continuant  +  |
| strident  +    |
+---          ---+]]></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This representation may be encoded in XML as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs type="phonological segments">
   <f name="consonantal"> <binary value="true"/>  </f>
   <f name="vocalic">     <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f name="voiced">      <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f name="anterior">    <binary value="true"/>  </f>
   <f name="coronal">     <binary value="true"/>  </f>
   <f name="continuant">  <binary value="true"/>  </f>
   <f name="strident">    <binary value="true"/>  </f>
</fs></egXML>
Note that <gi>fs</gi> elements may have an optional <att>type</att>
attribute to indicate the kind of feature structure in question,
whereas <gi>f</gi> elements must have a <att>name</att> attribute to
indicate the name of the feature. Feature structures need not be
typed, but features must be named. Similarly, the <gi>fs</gi> element may
be empty, but the <gi>f</gi> element must have (or reference) some content.</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The restriction of specific features to specific types of values
(e.g.  the restriction of the feature <mentioned>strident</mentioned>
to a binary value) requires additional validation, as does any
restriction on the features available within a feature structure of a
particular type (e.g. whether a feature structure of type
<mentioned>phonological segment</mentioned> necessarily contains a
feature <mentioned>voiced</mentioned>). Such validation may be carried
out at the document level, using special purpose processing, at the
schema level using additional validation rules, or at the declarative
level, using an additional mechanism such as the <term>feature-system
declaration</term> discussed in <!-- ref ref="#FD"--><ref>chapter FD
of the TEI Guidelines</ref>.
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Although we have used the term <term>binary</term> for this kind
of value, and its representation in XML uses values such as
<code>true</code> and <code>false</code> (or, equivalently,
<code>1</code> and <code>0</code>), it should be noted that such
values are not restricted to propositional assertions. As this example
shows, this kind of value is intended for use with any binary-valued
feature. </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Formal declarations for the <gi>fs</gi>, <gi>f</gi> and
<gi>binary</gi> elements are provided below in <ptr target="#FSDEF"/>.</p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSSY"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Other Atomic Feature Values</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Features may take other kinds of atomic value. In this section, we
define elements which may be used to represent: <term>symbolic
values</term>, <term>numeric values</term>, and <term>string
values</term>. The module defined by this chapter allows for the
specification of additional datatypes if necessary, by extending the
underlying class <ident type="class">class.singleVal</ident>. If this is done, it
is recommended that only the basic W3C datatypes should be used; more
complex datatyping should be represented as feature structures.
<specList>
<specDesc key="symbol" atts="value"/>
<specDesc key="numeric"/>
<specDesc key="string"/></specList>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>symbol</gi> element is used for the value of a feature when
that feature can have any of a small, finite set of possible values,
representable as character strings.  For example, the following might
be used to represent the claim that the Latin noun form
<mentioned>mensas</mentioned><!-- mentioned>the&#225;s</mentioned -->
(tables) has accusative case, feminine gender and
plural number:<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
   <f name="case">   <symbol value="accusative"/> </f>
   <f name="gender"> <symbol value="feminine"/> </f>
   <f name="number"> <symbol value="plural"/> </f>
</fs></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">More formally, this representation shows a structure in which three
features (<term>case</term>, <term>gender</term> and
<term>number</term>) are used to define morpho-syntactic properties of
a word. Each of these features can take one of a small number of
values (for example, case can be <code>nominative</code>,
<code>genitive</code>, <code>dative</code>, <code>accusative</code>
etc.)  and it is therefore appropriate to represent the values taken
in this instance as <gi>symbol</gi> elements.  Note that, instead of
using a symbolic value for grammatical number, one could have named
the feature <term>singular</term> or <term>plural</term> and given it
an appropriate binary value, as in the following example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs> 
  <f name="case"><symbol value="accusative"/></f>
  <f name="gender"><symbol value="feminine"/></f>
  <f name="singular"><binary value="false"/></f>
</fs></egXML>
Whether one uses a binary or symbolic value in situations like this is
largely a matter of taste. </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>string</gi> element is used for the value of a
feature when that value is a string drawn from a very large or potentially
unbounded set of possible strings of characters, so that it would be
impractical or impossible to use the <gi>symbol</gi> element.  The string
value is expressed as the content of the <gi>string</gi> element,
rather  than as an attribute value.  For example, one might encode a
street address as follows:
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
   <f name="address"><string>3418 East Third Street</string></f>
</fs></egXML> </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>numeric</gi> element is used when the value of a feature is a
numeric value, or a range of such values.  For example, one might wish
to regard the house number and the street
name as different features, using an encoding like the following:
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
   <f name="houseNumber"><numeric value="3418"/></f>
   <f name="streetName"><string>East Third Street</string></f>
</fs></egXML> </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If the numeric value to be represented falls within a specific
range (for example an address that spans several numbers), the
<att>max</att> attribute may be used to supply an upper limit:
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
   <f name="houseNumber"><numeric value="3418" max="3440"/></f>
   <f name="streetName"><string>East Third Street</string></f>
</fs></egXML> </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It is also possible to specify that the numeric value (or values)
represented should (or should not) be truncated. For example, assuming
that the daily rainfall in mm is a feature of interest for some
address, one might represent this by an encoding like the following:
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
   <f name="dailyRainFall"><numeric value="0.0" max="1.3" trunc="false"/></f>
</fs></egXML> This  represents any of the infinite
number of numeric values falling between 0 and 1.3; by contrast
 <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
   <f name="dailyRainFall"><numeric value="0.0" max="1.3" trunc="true"/></f>
</fs></egXML> represents only two possible values: 0 and 1.
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As noted above, additional processing is necessary to ensure that
appropriate values are supplied for particular features, for example
to ensure that the feature <code>singular</code> is not given a value
such as <tag>symbol value="feminine"/</tag>.  There are two
ways of attempting to ensure that only certain combinations of feature
names and values are used.  First, if the total number of legal
combinations is relatively small, one can predefine all of them in a
construct known as a <term>feature library</term>, and then reference
the combination required using the <att>feats</att> attribute in the
enclosing <gi>fs</gi> element, rather than give it explicitly.  This
method is suitable in the situation described above, since it requires
specifying a total of only ten (5 + 3 + 2) combinations of features
and values.  Similarly, to ensure that only feature structures
containing valid combinations of feature values are used, one can put
definitions for all valid feature structures inside a <term>feature
value library</term> (so called, since a feature structure may be the
value of a feature).  A total of 30 feature structures (5 × 3
× 2) is required to enumerate all the possible combinations of
individual case, gender and number values in the preceding
illustration.  We discuss the use of such libraries and their
representation in XML further in section <ptr target="#FSFL"/> below.
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">However, the most general method of attempting to ensure that only legal
combinations of feature names and values are used is to provide a
<term>feature-system declaration</term> discussed in <!--ref
ref="#FD"--><ref>chapter FD of the TEI Guidelines</ref>.
</p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSFL"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Feature and Feature-Value Libraries</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As the examples in the preceding section suggest, the direct
encoding of feature structures can be verbose.  Moreover, it is often
the case that particular feature-value combinations, or feature
structures composed of them, are re-used in different analyses. To reduce
the size and complexity of the task of encoding feature structures, one
may use the <att>feats</att> attribute of the <gi>fs</gi> element to point
to one or more of the feature-value specifications for that element.   This indirect method of
encoding feature structures presumes that the <gi>f</gi> elements are
assigned unique <att>xml:id</att> values, and are collected together in
<gi>fLib</gi> elements (<term>feature libraries</term>).  In the same way, feature
values of whatever type can be collected together in <gi>fvLib</gi> elements
(<term>feature-value libraries</term>). If a feature has as its
value a feature structure or other value which is predefined in this way,  the
<att>fVal</att> attribute may be used to point to it, as discussed in
the next section. The following elements  are used for representing feature,
and <!-- feature-structure and--> feature-value libraries:
<specList>
<specDesc key="fLib"/>
<specDesc key="fvLib"/></specList>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">For example, suppose a feature library for phonological feature
specifications is set up as follows.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fLib n="phonological features">
   <f xml:id="CNS1" name="consonantal"> <binary value="true"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="CNS0" name="consonantal"> <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="VOC1" name="vocalic">     <binary value="true"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="VOC0" name="vocalic">     <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="VOI1" name="voiced">      <binary value="true"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="VOI0" name="voiced">      <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="ANT1" name="anterior">    <binary value="true"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="ANT0" name="anterior">    <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="COR1" name="coronal">     <binary value="true"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="COR0" name="coronal">     <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="CNT1" name="continuant">  <binary value="true"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="CNT0" name="continuant">  <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="STR1" name="strident">    <binary value="true"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="STR0" name="strident">    <binary value="false"/> </f>
   <!-- ... -->
</fLib></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Then the feature structures that represent the analysis of the
phonological segments (phonemes) <code>/t/</code>, <code>/d/</code>,
<code>/s/</code>, and <code>/z/</code> may be defined as follows.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI0 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT0 #STR0"/><![CDATA[
]]><fs feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI1 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT0 #STR0"/><![CDATA[
]]><fs feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI0 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT1 #STR1"/><![CDATA[
]]><fs feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI1 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT1 #STR1"/></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The preceding are but four of the 128 logically possible fully
specified phonological segments using the seven binary features listed in
the feature library.  Presumably not all combinations of features
correspond to phonological segments (there are no strident vowels, for
example).  The legal combinations, however, can be collected together,
each one represented as an identifiable <gi>fs</gi> element within a
<term>feature-value library</term>, as in the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fvLib xml:id="fsl1" n="phonological segment definitions">
   <!-- ... -->
   <fs xml:id="T.DF" feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI0 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT0 #STR0"/>
   <fs xml:id="D.DF" feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI1 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT0 #STR0"/>
   <fs xml:id="S.DF" feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI0 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT1 #STR1"/>
   <fs xml:id="Z.DF" feats="#CNS1 #VOC0 #VOI1 #ANT1 #COR1 #CNT1 #STR1"/>
   <!-- ... -->
</fvLib></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Once defined, these feature structure values can also be reused.
Other <gi>f</gi> elements may invoke them by reference, using the
<att>fVal</att> attribute; for example, one might use them in a
feature value pair such as: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="dental-fricative" fVal="#T.DF"/><![CDATA[ ]]></egXML> rather than expanding the hierarchy of the
component phonological features explicitly.  </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Feature structures stored in this way  may also be associated with
the text which they are intended to annotate, either by a link from the text
(for example, using the TEI global <att>ana</att> attribute), or
by means of standoff annotation techniques (for example, using the TEI
<gi>link</gi> element): see further section <ptr target="#FSLINK"/>
below.
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Note that when features or feature structures are linked to in this
way, the result is effectively a copy of the item linked to into the
place from which it is linked. This form of linking should be distinguished  from
the phenomenon of <term>structure-sharing</term>, where it is desired
to indicate that some part of an annotation structure appears
simultaneously in two or more places within the structure. This kind
of annotation should be represented using the <gi>vLabel</gi> element, as
discussed in <ptr target="#FSVAR"/> below. </p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSST"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Feature Structures as Complex Feature Values</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Features may have complex values as well as atomic ones; the
simplest such complex value is represented by supplying a <gi>fs</gi>
element as the content of an <gi>f</gi> element, or (equivalently) by
supplying the identifier of an <gi>fs</gi> element as the value for
the <att>fVal</att> attribute on the <gi>f</gi>
element. Structures may be nested as deeply as appropriate, using this
mechanism.  For example, an <gi>fs</gi> element may contain or point
to an <gi>f</gi> element, which may contain or point to an <gi>fs</gi>
element, which may contain or point to an <gi>f</gi> element, and so
on.</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">To illustrate the use of complex values, consider the following
simple model of a word, as a structure combining surface form
information, a syntactic category, and semantic information. Each word
analysis is represented as a <gi>fs type='word'</gi> element,
containing three features named <code>surface</code>,
<code>syntax</code>, and <code>semantics</code>. The first of these
has an atomic string value, but the other two have complex values,
represented as nested feature structures of types
<code>category</code> and <code>act</code> respectively:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs type="word">
   <f name="surface"><string>love</string></f>
   <f name="syntax">
	<fs type="category">
	  <f name="pos"><symbol value="verb"/></f>
	  <f name="val"><symbol value="transitive"/></f>
	</fs>
   </f>
   <f name="semantics">
	<fs type="act">
	  <f name="rel"><symbol value="LOVE"/></f>
	</fs>
   </f>
</fs></egXML></p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This analysis does not tell us much about the meaning of the
symbols <code>verb</code> or <code>transitive</code>. It might be
preferable to replace these atomic feature values by feature
structures.  Suppose therefore that we maintain a feature-value
library for each of the major syntactic categories (N, V, ADJ, PREP):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fvLib n="Major category definitions">
<!-- ... -->
<fs xml:id="N" type="noun">
  <!--  noun features defined here -->
</fs>
<fs xml:id="V" type="verb">
  <!-- verb features defined here -->
</fs>
</fvLib><![CDATA[
]]></egXML>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This library allows us to use shortcut codes (<code>N</code>,
<code>V</code> etc.) to reference a complete definition for the
corresponding feature structure. Each definition may be explicitly
contained within the <gi>fs</gi> element, as a number of <gi>f</gi>
elements. Alternatively, the relevant features may be referenced by
their identifiers, supplied as the value of the <att>feats</att>
attribute, as in these examples:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[<!-- ... -->
<fs xml:id="ADJ" type="adjective" feats="#N1 #V1"/>
<fs xml:id="PREP" type="preposition" feats="#N0 #V0"/>
<!-- ... -->
]]></egXML>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This ability to re-use feature definitions within multiple feature
structure definitions is an essential simplification in any realistic
example.  In this case, we assume the existence of a feature library
containing specifications for the basic feature categories like the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fLib n="categorial features">
   <f xml:id="NN1" name="nominal"><binary value="true"/></f>
   <f xml:id="NN0" name="nominal"><binary value="false"/></f>
   <f xml:id="VV1" name="verbal"><binary value="true"/></f>
   <f xml:id="VV0" name="verbal"><binary value="false"/></f>
<!-- ... -->
</fLib><![CDATA[
]]></egXML>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">With these libraries in place, and assuming the availability of
similarly predefined feature structures for transitivity and
semantics, the preceding example could be considerably simplified:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs type="word">
<f name="surf"><string>love</string></f>
   <f name="syntax">
	<fs type="category">
	  <f name="pos" fVal="#V"/>
	  <f name="val" fVal="#TRNS"/>
	</fs>
   </f>
   <f name="semantics">
	<fs type="act">
	  <f name="rel" fVal="#LOVE"/>
	</fs>
   </f>
</fs><![CDATA[
]]></egXML></p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Although in principle the <att>fVal</att> attribute could  point to
any kind of feature value, its use is not recommended for simple
atomic values. </p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSVAR"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Re-entrant feature structures</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Sometimes the same feature value is required at multiple places
within a feature structure, in particular where the value is only
partially specified at one or more places. The <gi>vLabel</gi> element is
provided as a means of labelling each such re-entrancy point:
<specList>
<specDesc key="vLabel"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">For example, suppose one wishes to represent noun-verb agreement as
a single feature structure. Within the representation, the feature
indicating (say) number appears more than once. To represent the fact
that each occurrence is another appearance of the same feature (rather
than a copy) one could use an encoding like the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs xml:id="NVA">
<f name="nominal">
  <fs>
    <f name="nm-num">
     <vLabel name="L1">
       <symbol value="singular"/>
    </vLabel>
   </f>
   <!-- other nominal features -->
  </fs>
</f>
<f name="verbal">
  <fs>
    <f name="vb-num">
      <vLabel name="L1"/>
    </f>
  </fs>
   <!-- other verbal features -->
</f>
</fs></egXML>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In the above encoding, the features named <code>vb-num</code> and
<code>nm-num</code> exhibit structure sharing. Their values, given as
<code>vLabel</code> elements, are understood to be references to the same
point in the feature structure, which is labelled by their
<att>name</att> attribute. </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The scope of the names used to label re-entrancy points is that of the
outermost <gi>fs</gi> element in which they appear. When a feature
structure is imported from a feature value library, or referenced from
elsewhere (for example by using the <att>fVal</att> attribute) the
names of any
sharing points it may contain are implicitly prefixed by the identifier used
for the imported feature structure, to avoid name clashes. Thus, if
some other feature structure were to reference the <gi>fs</gi> element
given in the example above, for example in this way: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="class" fVal="#NVA"/></egXML> then
the labelled points in the example would be interpreted as if they had the
name <code>NVAL1</code>. </p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSSS"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Collections as Complex Feature Values</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Complex feature values need not always be represented as feature
structures. Multiple values may also be organized as as sets, bags (or
multisets), or lists of atomic values of any type. The <gi>vColl</gi>
element is provided to represent such cases:
<specList>
<specDesc key="vColl"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">A feature whose value is regarded  as a set, bag or list may have
any positive number of values as its content, or none at
all, (thus allowing for representation of the empty set, bag or list).
The items in a list are ordered, and need not be distinct. The items
in a set are not ordered, and must be distinct. The items in a bag are
neither ordered nor distinct. Sets and bags are thus distinguished
from lists in that the order in which the values are specified does
not matter for the former, but does matter for the latter, while sets
are distinguished from bags and lists in that repetitions of values do
not count for the former but do count for the latter.  
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If no value is specified for the <att>org</att> attribute, the
assumption is that the <gi>vColl</gi> defines a list of values. If the
<gi>vColl</gi> element is empty, the assumption is that it represents
the null list, set, or bag. <!--, unless the <att>feats</att> attribute is
used to specify its contents. If values are supplied  within a <gi>vColl</gi> element
which also specifies values on its <att>feats</att> attribute, the
implication is that the two sets of values are to be unified.--></p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">To illustrate the use of the <att>org</att> attribute, suppose that
a feature structure analysis is used to represent a genealogical tree,
with the information about each individual treated as a single feature
structure, like this: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs xml:id="p027" type="person">
   <f name="forenames">
     <vColl>
       <string>Daniel</string>
       <string>Edouard</string>
     </vColl>
   </f>
   <f name="mother" fVal="#p002"/>
   <f name="father" fVal="#p009"/>
   <f name="birthDate">
      <fs type="date" feats="#y1988 #m04 #d17"/>
   </f>
   <f name="birthPlace" fVal="#austintx"/>
   <f name="siblings">
       <vColl org="set">
        <fs copyOf="#pnb005"/>
        <fs copyOf="#prb001"/>
       </vColl>
   </f>
</fs></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">In this example, the <gi>vColl</gi> element is first used to supply
a list of <soCalled>name</soCalled> feature values, which together
constitute the <soCalled>forenames</soCalled> feature. Other features
are defined by reference to values which we assume are held in some
external feature value library (not shown here). For example, the
<gi>vColl</gi> element is used a second time to indicate that the
persons's siblings should be regarded as constituting a set rather
than a list. Each sibling is represented by a feature structure: in
this example, each feature structure is a copy of one specified in the
feature value library. </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If a specific feature contains only a single feature structure as
its value, the component features of which are organized as a set, bag
or list, it may be more convenient to represent the value as a
<gi>vColl</gi> rather than as a <gi>fs</gi>. For example, consider the
following encoding of the English verb form
<mentioned>sinks</mentioned>, which contains an
<mentioned>agreement</mentioned> feature whose value is a feature
structure which contains <mentioned>person</mentioned> and
<mentioned>number</mentioned> features with symbolic values.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs type="word">
  <f name="category"> <symbol value="verb"/> </f>
  <f name="tense"> <symbol value="present"/> </f>
  <f name="agreement">
    <fs>
      <f name="person"> <symbol value="third"/> </f>
      <f name="number"> <symbol value="singular"/> </f>
    </fs>
  </f>
</fs></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If the names of the features contained within
the <mentioned>agreement</mentioned> feature structure are
of no particular significance, the following simpler representation
may be used:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs type="word">
  <f name="word.oddss"> <symbol value="verb"/> </f>
  <f name="tense"> <symbol value="present"/> </f>
  <f name="agreement">
     <vColl org="set">
        <symbol value="third"/>
        <symbol value="singular"/>
     </vColl>
  </f>
</fs></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>vColl</gi> element is also useful in cases where an analysis
has several components. In the following example, the French
word <mentioned>auxquels</mentioned> has a two-part analysis,
represented as a list of two values. The first specifies that the word contains a
preposition; the second that it contains a masculine plural relative
pronoun: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
      <f name="lex">
	<symbol value="auxquels"/>
      </f>
      <f name="maf">
	<vColl org="list">
	  <fs>
	    <f name="cat"><symbol value="prep"/></f>
	  </fs>
	  <fs>
	    <f name="cat"><symbol value="pronoun"/></f>
	    <f name="kind"><symbol value="rel"/></f>
	    <f name="num"><symbol value="pl"/></f>
	    <f name="gender"><symbol value="masc"/></f>
	  </fs>
	</vColl>
      </f>
    </fs></egXML>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The set, bag or list which has no members is known as the null (or
empty) set, bag or list.  A <gi>vColl</gi> element with no content and
with no value for its <att>feats</att> attribute is interpreted as
referring to the null set, bag, or list, depending on the value of its
<att>org</att> attribute.</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If, for example, the individual described by the
feature structure with identifier <code>p027</code> (above) had no siblings, we might specify the
<mentioned>siblings</mentioned> feature as follows.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="siblings"><vColl org="set"/></f></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">A <gi>vColl</gi> element may also collect together one or more other
<gi>vColl</gi> elements, if, for example one of the members of a set is
itself a set, or if two lists are concatenated together. Note that
such collections pay no attention to the contents of the nested
<gi>vColl</gi> elements: if it is desired to produce the union of two
sets, the <gi>vMerge</gi> element discussed below should be used to
make a new collection from the two sets.  </p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FVE"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Feature Value Expressions</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">It is sometimes desirable to express the value of a feature as the
result of an operation over some other value (for example, as
<soCalled>not green</soCalled>, or as <soCalled>male or
female</soCalled>, or as the concatenation of two collections).  Three
special purpose elements are provided to represent disjunctive
alternation, negation, and collection of values:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="vAlt"/>
  <specDesc key="vNot"/>
  <specDesc key="vMerge"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FVALT"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Alternation</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>vAlt</gi> element can be used wherever a feature value can
appear. It contains two or more feature values, any one of which is to
be understood as the value required. Suppose, for example, that we are
using a feature system to describe residential property, using such
features as <mentioned>number.of.bathrooms</mentioned>. In a
particular case, we might wish to represent uncertainty as to whether
a house has two or three bathrooms. As we have already shown, one
simple way to represent this would be with a numeric maximum:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="number.of.bathrooms"><numeric value="2" max="3"/></f></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">A better, and more general, way would be to represent the
alternation explicitly, in this way:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="number.of.bathrooms"> <vAlt><numeric value="2"/><numeric value="3"/> </vAlt></f></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>vAlt</gi> element represents alternation over feature
values, not feature-value pairs. If therefore the uncertainty relates
to two or more feature value specifications, each  must be represented
as a feature structure, since a feature structure can always appear
where a value is required. For example, suppose that it is uncertain
as to whether the house being described has two bathrooms or two
bedrooms, a structure like the following may be used:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="rooms">
   <vAlt>
      <fs><f name="number.of.bathrooms"> <numeric value="2"/> </f></fs>
      <fs><f name="number.of.bedrooms"> <numeric value="2"/> </f></fs>
   </vAlt>
</f></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Note that alternation is always regarded as <term>exclusive</term>:
in the case above, the implication is that  having two bathrooms
excludes the possibility of having two bedrooms and vice versa. If
inclusive alternation is required, a <gi>vColl</gi> element may be
included in the alternation as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="rooms">
   <vAlt><fs><f name="number.of.bathrooms"> <numeric value="2"/> </f></fs>
          <fs><f name="number.of.bedrooms"> <numeric value="2"/> </f></fs>
      <vColl>
        <fs><f name="number.of.bathrooms"> <numeric value="2"/> </f></fs>
        <fs><f name="number.of.bedrooms"> <numeric value="2"/> </f></fs>
      </vColl>
   </vAlt>
</f></egXML>
This analysis indicates that the property may have two bathrooms, two
bedrooms, or both two bathrooms and two bedrooms.
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As the previous example shows, the <gi>vAlt</gi> element can also
be used to indicate alternations among values of features organized as
sets, bags or lists.  Suppose we use a feature
<code>selling.points</code> to describe items that are mentioned to
enhance a property's sales value, such as whether it has a pool or a
good view.  Now suppose for a particular listing, the selling points include
an alarm system and a good view, and either a pool or a jacuzzi (but
not both).  This situation could be represented, using the
<gi>vAlt</gi> element, as follows.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs type="real estate listing">
   <f name="selling.points"> 
      <vColl org="set">
      <string>alarm system</string>
      <string>good view</string>
      <vAlt>
         <string>pool</string>
         <string>jacuzzi</string>
      </vAlt>
      </vColl>
   </f>
</fs></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Now suppose the situation is like the preceding except that one is
also uncertain whether the property has an alarm system or a good
view.  This can be represented as follows.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs type="real estate listing">
   <f name="selling.points">
      <vColl org="set">
       <vAlt>
         <string>alarm system</string>
         <string>good view</string>
      </vAlt>
      <vAlt>
         <string>pool</string>
         <string>jacuzzi</string>
      </vAlt>
      </vColl>
   </f>
</fs></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If a large number of ambiguities or uncertainties need to be
represented, involving a relatively small number of features and
values, it is recommended that a stand-off technique, for example
using the general-purpose <gi>alt</gi> element discussed in <!--
section <ptr target="SAAT"/> of --> TEI P5, be used, rather than the
special-purpose <gi>vAlt</gi> element.
</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FVNOT"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Negation</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>vNot</gi> element can be used wherever a feature value can
appear. It contains any feature value and returns the complement of
its contents. For example, the feature
<mentioned>number.of.bathrooms</mentioned> in the following example
has any whole numeric value other than 2:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="number.of.bathrooms"> <vNot><numeric value="2"/> </vNot></f></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Strictly speaking, the effect of the <gi>vNot</gi> element is to
provide the complement of the feature values it contains, rather than
their negation. If a feature system declaration is available which defines the
possible values for the associated feature, then it is possible to say
more about the negated value. For example, suppose that the
available values for the feature <code>case</code> are declared to be
nominative, genitive, dative, or accusative, whether in a TEI feature
system declaration or
by some other means. Then the following two specifications are equivalent:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[ (i) ]]><f name="case">
      <vNot><symbol value="genitive"/></vNot></f><![CDATA[
(ii) ]]><f name="case">
      <vAlt>
       <symbol value="nominative"/>
       <symbol value="dative"/>
       <symbol value="accusative"/>
     </vAlt>
    </f></egXML>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If however no such system declaration is available, all that one
can say about a feature specified via negation is that its value is
something other than the negated value. </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Negation is always applied to a feature value, rather than to a
feature-value pair. The negation of an atomic value is the set of all
other values which are possible for the feature. </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Any kind of value can be negated, including collections
(represented by a <gi>vColl</gi> elements) or feature structures
(represented by <gi>fs</gi> elements). The negation of any complex
value is understood to be the set of values  which
cannot be unified with it. Thus, for example, the negation of the
feature structure F is understood to be the set of feature structures
which are not unifiable with F. In the absence of a constraint
mechanism such as the Feature System Declaration, the negation of a
collection is anything that is not unifiable with it, including
collections of different types and atomic values. It will generally be
more useful to require that the organization of the negated value be
the same as that of the original value, for example that a negated set
is understood to mean the set which is a complement of the set, but
such a requirement cannot be enforced in the absence of a constraint
mechanism. </p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="FVCOLL"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Collection of values</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The <gi>vMerge</gi> element can be used wherever a feature value can
appear. It contains two or more feature values, all of which are to be
collected together. The organization of the resulting collection is
specified by the value of the <att>org</att> attribute, which need
not necessarily be the same as that of its constituent values if these
are collections. For example, one can change a list to a set, or vice versa.</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As an example, suppose that we wish to represent the range of
possible values for a feature <soCalled>genders</soCalled> used to
describe some language. It would be natural to represent the possible
values  as a set, using the <gi>vColl</gi> element as in the following
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
<f name="genders">
   <vColl org="set">
       <symbol value="masculine"/>
       <symbol value="feminine"/>
   </vColl>
</f>
</fs><![CDATA[
]]></egXML>
</p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Suppose however that we discover for some language it is necessary
to add a new possible value, and to treat the value of the
feature as a list rather than as a set. The <gi>vMerge</gi> element can
be used to achieve this:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fs>
<f name="genders">
<vMerge org="list">
   <vColl org="set">
       <symbol value="masculine"/>
       <symbol value="feminine"/>
   </vColl>
   <symbol value="neuter"/>
</vMerge>
</f>
</fs><![CDATA[
]]></egXML>
</p> 
<!-- more examples needed, use from sect 4 -->
</div>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSBO"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Default Values</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The value of a feature may be underspecified in a number of
different ways. It may be null, unknown, or uncertain with respect to
a range of known possibilities, as well as being defined as a negation
or an alternation. As previously noted, the specification of the range
of known possibilities for a given feature is not part of the current
specification: in the TEI scheme, this information is conveyed by the
<term>feature system declaration</term>. Using this, or some other
system, we might specify (for example) that the range of values
for an element includes symbols for masculine, feminine, and neuter,
and that the default value is neuter. With such definitions available
to us, it becomes possible to say that some feature takes the default
value, or some unspecified value from the list. The following special
element is provided for this purpose:
<specList>
<specDesc key="default"/>
</specList>
</p> 
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The value of an empty <gi>f</gi> element which also lacks a <att>fVal</att>
attribute is understood to be the most general
case, i.e. any of the available values. Thus, assuming the feature
system defined above, the following two representations are equivalent. 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="gender"/><![CDATA[
]]><f name="gender">
   <vAlt>
      <symbol value="feminine"/>
      <symbol value="masculine"/>
      <symbol value="neuter"/>
   </vAlt>
</f></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">If, however, the value is explicitly stated to be the default one,
using the <gi>default</gi> element, then the  following two representations
are equivalent: 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="gender"> <default/> </f></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="gender"> <symbol value="neuter"/> </f></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Similarly, if the value is stated to be the negation of the
default, then the following two representations are equivalent:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="gender"> <vNot><default/></vNot> </f></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><f name="gender">    <vAlt>
      <symbol value="feminine"/>
      <symbol value="masculine"/>
</vAlt></f></egXML>
</p>
</div>
<!-- discussion of subsumption and nonsubsumption was here: removed to
     separate file for now -->
<!-- dogstoday example was here: removed to separate file pro tem -->
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSLINK"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Linking Text and Analysis</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Text elements can be linked with feature structures using any of
the linking methods discussed elsewhere in the Guidelines (see for
example sections <ptr target="#AIATTS"/> and <ptr target="#AILA"/>).
In the simplest case, the <att>ana</att> attribute may be used
to point from any element to an annotation of it, as in the following
example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><s n="00741">
   <w ana="#at0">The</w>
   <w ana="#ajs">closest</w>
   <w ana="#pnp">he</w>
   <w ana="#vvd">came</w>
   <w ana="#prp">to</w>
   <w ana="#nn1">exercise</w>
   <w ana="#vbd">was</w>
   <w ana="#to0">to</w>
   <w ana="#vvi">open</w>
   <w ana="#crd">one</w>
   <w ana="#nn1">eye</w>
   <phr ana="#av0">  
      <w>every</w>
      <w>so</w>
      <w>often</w>
   </phr>
   <c ana="#pun">,</c>
   <w ana="#cjs">if</w>
   <w ana="#pni">someone</w>
   <w ana="#vvd">entered</w>
   <w ana="#at0">the</w>
   <w ana="#nn1">room</w>
   <!-- ... -->
</s></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">The values specified for the <att>ana</att> attribute reference
components of a feature-structure library, which represents all of the
grammatical structures used by this encoding scheme. (For illustrative
purposes, we cite here only the structures needed for the first six
words of the sample sentence):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fvLib xml:id="C6" n="Claws 6 tags">
   <!-- ... -->
   <fs xml:id="ajs" type="grammatical structure" feats="#wj #ds"/>
   <fs xml:id="at0" type="grammatical structure" feats="#wl"/>
   <fs xml:id="pnp" type="grammatical structure" feats="#wr #rp"/>
   <fs xml:id="vvd" type="grammatical structure" feats="#wv #bv #fd"/>
   <fs xml:id="prp" type="grammatical structure" feats="#wp #bp"/>
   <fs xml:id="nnn" type="grammatical structure" feats="#wn #tc #ns"/>
 <!-- ... -->
</fvLib></egXML>
The components of each feature structure in the library are 
referenced in much the same way, using the
<att>feats</att> attribute to  identify one or more <gi>f</gi>
elements in the following feature library (again, only a few of the
available features are quoted here):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fLib>
   <!-- ... -->
   <f xml:id="bv" name="verbbase"> <symbol value="main"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="bp" name="prepbase"> <symbol value="lexical"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="ds" name="degree">   <symbol value="superlative"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="fd" name="verbform"> <symbol value="ed"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="ns" name="number">   <symbol value="singular"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="rp" name="prontype"> <symbol value="personal"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="tc" name="nountype"> <symbol value="common"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="wj" name="class">    <symbol value="adjective"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="wl" name="class">    <symbol value="article"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="wn" name="class">    <symbol value="noun"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="wp" name="class">    <symbol value="preposition"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="wr" name="class">    <symbol value="pronoun"/> </f>
   <f xml:id="wv" name="class">    <symbol value="verb"/> </f>
   <!-- ... -->
</fLib></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Alternatively, a stand-off technique may be used, as in the following
example, where a <gi>linkGrp</gi> element is used to link selected
characters in the text <mentioned>Caesar seized control</mentioned> with 
their phonological representations.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><![CDATA[
 ]]><s>
  <w xml:id="S1W1"><c xml:id="S1W1C1">C</c>ae<c xml:id="S1W1C2">s</c>ar</w>
  <w xml:id="S1W2"><c xml:id="S1W2C1">s</c>ei<c xml:id="S1W2C2">z</c>e<c xml:id="S1W2C3">d</c></w>
  <w xml:id="S1W3">con<c xml:id="S1W3C1">t</c>rol</w>.
</s><![CDATA[
  ]]><fvLib xml:id="FSL1" n="phonological segment definitions">
	<!-- as in previous example -->
  </fvLib><![CDATA[
  ]]><linkGrp type="phonology">
	<!-- ... -->
	<link targets="#S.DF #S1W3C1"/>
	<link targets="#Z.DF #S1W2C3"/>
	<link targets="#S.DF #S1W2C1"/>
	<link targets="#Z.DF #S1W2C2"/>
	<!-- ... -->
  </linkGrp></egXML>
 </p>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">As this example shows, a stand-off solution requires that every
component to be linked to must bear an identifier. To handle the
POS tagging example above, therefore, each annotated element would
need an identifier of some sort, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><s xml:id="mds09" n="00741">
   <w xml:id="mds0901">The</w>
   <w xml:id="mds0902">closest</w>
   <w xml:id="mds0903">he</w>
   <w xml:id="mds0904">came</w>
   <w xml:id="mds0905">to</w>
   <w xml:id="mds0906">exercise</w>
<!-- ... --></s></egXML>
It would then be possible to link each word to its intended
annotation in the feature library quoted above, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><linkGrp type="POS-codes">	<!-- ... -->
   <link targets="#mds0901 #at0"/><link targets="#mds0902 #ajs"/>
   <link targets="#mds0903 #pnp"/><link targets="#mds0904 #vvd"/>
   <link targets="#mds0905 #prp"/><link targets="#mds0906 #nn1"/>
   <link targets="#mds0907 #vbd"/><link targets="#mds0908 #to0"/>
   <link targets="#mds0909 #vvi"/><link targets="#mds0910 #crd"/>
	<!-- ... -->
  </linkGrp></egXML>
</p>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="FSDEF"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Formal Definition and Implementation</head>
<p xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">This elements discussed in this chapter constitute a module of the
TEI scheme which is formally defined as follows:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DFS" ident="iso-fs">
<altIdent type="FPI">Feature Structures</altIdent>
<desc>Feature structures</desc></moduleSpec>
<!--publicID:  -//TEI P5//DTD Additional Module for Feature Structure Representation//EN-->

The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
<specGrp>
&fs;
&f;
&binary;
&symbol;
&numeric;
&string;
&vLabel;
&vColl;
&default;
&vAlt;
&vNot;
&vMerge;
&fLib;
&fvLib;
</specGrp></p>
<!--<p>In a TEI conformant document, this module is selected as described
in <ref target="#STIN">TEI P5, chapter ST</ref></p>
-->
</div>
</div>
