<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Licensed under the GNU General Public License. 
See the file COPYING for details.
$Date$
$Author$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="PH" n="18"><head xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">Representation of Primary Sources</head>

<p>This chapter defines a module intended for use in the
representation of primary sources, in particular manuscripts or other
unique instances of written materials. Section <ptr target="#FAX"/>
provides elements for the encoding of digital facsimiles or images of
such materials, while the remainder of the chapter discusses ways of
encoding detailed transcriptions of such materials. It is expected
that this module will also be useful in the preparation of critical
editions, but the module defined here is distinct from that defined in
chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>, and may be used independently of
it. Detailed metadata relating to primary sources of any kind may be
recorded using the elements defined by the manuscript description
module discussed in chapter <ptr target="#MS"/>, but again the present
module may be used independently if such data is not required.
</p>
<p>It should be noted that this chapter focuses primarily upon
problems associated with manuscript materials,
and that consequently problems of codicology and other matters peculiar to
early printed materials are not specifically addressed
here. Nevertheless, many of the recommendations presented may —
mutatis mutandis — also be applied in the encoding of printed
matter or indeed any form of  written source, including
monumental inscriptions.</p>
<p>Many of the descriptions below use terms like
<soCalled>scribe</soCalled>, <soCalled>author</soCalled>,
<soCalled>editor</soCalled>,
<soCalled>annotator</soCalled>,
<soCalled>corrector</soCalled>,
<soCalled>transcriber</soCalled>,
and <soCalled>encoder</soCalled>, to make
clear how they apply in cases where these roles are distinct.  To the
extent that these roles are not distinct (for example, in authorial
manuscripts where the author and the scribe are the same person) the
interpretation of the markup should be adjusted appropriately.
Many of the elements defined here apply (within limits) also in
cases of printed materials, so <soCalled>compositor</soCalled>, etc.,
may also be understood as applying where appropriate.</p>



<div xml:id="FAX">
<head>Digital Facsimiles</head>

<p>These Guidelines are mostly concerned with the preparation of
digital texts, in which a pre-existing text is transcribed or
otherwise converted into character form, and marked up in
XML. However, it is also very common practice to make a different form
of <soCalled>digital text</soCalled>, which is instead composed of
digital images of the original source, typically one per page, or
other written surface. We call such a resource a <term>digital
facsimile</term>. A digital facsimile may, in the simplest case, just
consist of a collection of images, with some metadata to identify them
and the source materials portrayed. It may sometimes contain a
variety of images of the same source pages, for example of different
resolutions, or of different kinds. And it may also be complemented by
a trancribed or encoded version of the original source, which may be
linked to the page images. In this section we present elements
designed to support these various possibilities and discuss the
associated mechanisms provided by these Guidelines.</p>

<p>The following elements are used to represent components of a
digital facsimile:
<specList>
<specDesc key="facsimile"/>
<specDesc key="surface" atts="xMax yMax start"/>
<specDesc key="zone" atts="start"/>
</specList>
</p>

<p>The <gi>facsimile</gi> element is used to represent a digital
facsimile. It appears within a TEI document along with, or instead of,
the <gi>text</gi> element introduced in section <ptr
target="#DS"/>. When this module is selected therefore, a
legal TEI document may thus comprise any of the following:-
<list>
<item>a TEI Header and a text element</item>
<item>a TEI Header and a facsimile element</item>
<item>a TEI Header, a facsimile element, and a text element</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>Like the <gi>text</gi> element, a <gi>facsimile</gi> element may
also contain an optional <gi>front</gi> or <gi>back</gi> element, used
in the same way as described in sections <ptr target="#DSFRONT"/> and
<ptr target="#DSBACK"/>. </p>
  
<p>In the simplest case, a facsimile just contains a series of
<gi>graphic</gi> elements, each of which identifies an image file:

<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<facsimile>
  <graphic url="page1.png"/>
  <graphic url="page2.png"/>
  <graphic url="page3.png"/>
  <graphic url="page4.png"/>
</facsimile>
</egXML>

If desired, the <gi>binaryObject</gi> element described in <ptr
target="#COGR"/> can be used instead of a <gi>graphic</gi></p>

<p>In this simple case, the four page images are understood to
represent the complete facsimile, and are to be read in the sequence
given. Suppose, however, that the second page of this particular work
is available both as an ordinary photograph and as an infra-red image,
or in two different resolutions. The <gi>surface</gi> element may be
used to indicate that there are two image files corresponding with the
same area of the work:

<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<facsimile>
  <graphic url="page1.png"/>
  <surface>
   <graphic url="page2-highRes.png"/>
   <graphic url="page2-lowRes.png"/>
  </surface>
  <graphic url="page3.png"/>
  <graphic url="page4.png"/>
</facsimile>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>When this module is included in a schema, the class
<ident>att.global</ident> is extended to include a new pointer
attribute <att>facs</att>. This attribute may be used to associate any
element in a transcribed text with an image of it, by means of the
usual pointing mechanism. For example, suppose that the page
represented by the graphic <ident>page1.png</ident> contains text
which is encoded as a <gi>div</gi> element in the <gi>text</gi>
element corresponding with this <gi>facsimile</gi>. We can represent
the alignment as follows:
<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<TEI>
<teiHeader> <!-- ... --></teiHeader>
<facsimile>
  <graphic xml:id="Page1" url="page1.png"/>
  <!-- more graphics here -->
</facsimile>
<text>
  <div facs="#Page1">
    <!-- text contained on page 1 is encoded here -->
  </div>
</text>
</TEI>  
</egXML>
</p>

<p>In this very simple case the image and the structural encoding
correspond — that is, all and only the text contained by the
<gi>div</gi> element is represented in the graphic (and vice
versa). Of course, in real life this will rarely be the case,
particularly when the source in question is a printed book or
codex. As discussed elsewhere (see for example <ptr
target="#CORS5"/>), these Guidelines recommend the use of empty
milestone elements to delimit the boundary points of the stretches of
encoded text which correspond with an image. </p>

<p>For example, suppose that page 2 of some source is represented by
the graphic in <ident>page2.png</ident>, and that this page contains
the end of chapter one of a novel, and the start of chapter
two. The simplest way of encoding this would be to use  a
<gi>pb</gi> milestone to indicate where the page changes:
<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<facsimile>
  <graphic xml:id="Page2" url="page2.png"/>
  <!-- more graphics here -->
</facsimile>
<text>
  <div><head>Chapter one</head>
  <p>  <!-- text --> </p>
  <p> <!-- more text -->
    <pb n="234" facs="#Page2"/>
 <!-- more text -->
  </p>
  </div>
  <div><head>Chapter two</head>
  <!-- etc -->
  </div>
</text>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>Other milestone elements may be used in the same way. In the
following example, each image corresponds to a column in a manuscript
scroll:

<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
  <graphic xml:id="col1" url="column1.png"/>
  <graphic xml:id="col2" url="column2.png"/>
  <!-- more graphics here -->
</facsimile>
<text>
  <cb n="1" facs="#col1"/>
  <div>
  <p>.....</p>
  <p> ...
  <cb n="2" facs="#col2"/>
  </p>
  </div>
</text>
</egXML>
</p>

<p>If a facsimile contains only one image per page or column (or
similar unit), and no more complex mapping between text and image is
envisaged, then it may be preferred to use the <att>facs</att>
attribute to point directly to the graphic resource itself, rather
than to a <gi>graphic</gi> or other element within a
<gi>facsimile</gi>:

<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<TEI>
<teiHeader> ...</teiHeader>
<text>
  <pb facs="page1.png"/>
    <!-- text contained on page 1 is encoded here -->
  <pb facs="page2.png"/>
    <!-- text contained on page 2 is encoded here -->
</text>
</TEI>  
</egXML>

The value of the <att>facs</att> attribute can be any URI, and may
thus indicate graphic elements directly without their being included
in a <gi>facsimile</gi> element:

<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <pb facs="http://example.com/myImages/page1.png"/>
</egXML>
This approach is not generally recommended, since it does not scale
well and may lead to interchange problems, but may be found
appropriate for very simple applications. </p>

<p>In the more general case, an encoder may wish to record arbitrary
planar co-ordinates of textual elements on any kind of written surface
and to link such elements with digital facsimile images of
them. Typical applications include the provision of full text search
in <soCalled>digital facsimile editions</soCalled>, and ways of
annotating graphics, for example so as to identify individuals
appearing in a group portraits and link them to data about the person
represented. To support such requirements a more complex encoding is
necessary, for which the elements <gi>surface</gi> and <gi>zone</gi>
are provided.</p>


<p>The <gi>surface</gi> element mentioned above may be used to
represent any physical surface forming part of the source
material. This might be a sheet of paper or parchment, a face of a
monument, a billboard, a scroll, or indeed any two-dimensional
surface, of any size. The actual dimensions of the object represented
are not documented by the <gi>surface</gi> element; it defines a
co-ordinate space with its own dimensions.
</p>

<p>A <gi>surface</gi> may contain one or more <gi>graphic</gi>
elements, each providing a graphic representation of exactly the same
co-ordinate space. This space is defined by the attributes
<att>xMax</att> and <att>yMax</att>, which supply an upper bound for
the horizontal and vertical dimensions of this space respectively. The
units in which these dimensions are measured are not significant: the
object is to define a grid superimposed on the image indicated by the
first child <gi>graphic</gi> element of the <gi>surface</gi>. </p>

<p>A <gi>surface</gi> may  also contain one or more <gi>zone</gi>
elements, each of which represents a rectangular region or
<term>bounding box</term> within the co-ordinate space defined by the
parent <gi>surface</gi> element. This provides a unit of analysis
which may be used to define any rectangular region of interest, such
as a detail or illustration, or some part of the surface which is to
be aligned with a particular text element. If the image being mapped
represents something outside the written part of the surface (for
example a binding or the surface of a desk on which the page rests),
the <gi>surface</gi> element may also need to define a zone of
interest. The <att>box</att>
attribute is used to supply the co-ordinates of a zone. </p>



<p>In the following example, we discuss a hypothetical digital edition
of an early 16th century French work, Charles de Bouelles
<title>Geometrie Pratique</title>. In this edition, each page has been
digitized as a separate file: for example, recto page 49 is stored in
a file called <ident>Boulles-49r.png</ident>. In the
<gi>facsimile</gi> element used to contain the whole set of pages, we
define a 
<gi>surface</gi> element  for this page, to which we attach a co-ordinate
scale running from 0 to 200 in the x (horizontal) axis, and 0 to 300 in
the y (vertical) axis. <note place="foot">A co-ordinate scale may be
thought of as a grid superimposed on a rectangular space. Rectangular
areas of the grid are defined as four numbers a b c d: the first two
identify the grid point which is at the upper left corner of the
rectangle; the second two give the grid point located at the lower
right corner of the rectangle. The grid point a b is understood to be
the point which is located a points from the origin along the x
(horizontal) axis, and b points from the origin along the y (vertical)
axis.</note>  No units need be specified; the relationship between
this scale and the physical size of the original page is not relevant
to the encoding. However, in practice, it will usually be convenient
if the scale is expressed in terms of the pixel resolution of the
digital image itself.  </p>
<p>The <gi>surface</gi> element  contains a
<gi>graphic</gi> element pointing to the image: <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface xMax="200" yMax="300">
  <graphic url="Boulles-49r.png"/>
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML> We can now identify distinct zones within the
page image using the co-ordinate scale defined for the surface. In
<ptr target="#facs-fig1"/> we show the upper part of the page, with
boxes indicating four such zones. Each of these will be represented by
a  <gi>zone</gi> element, given within the <gi>surface</gi>
element already defined, and specified in terms of the same
co-ordinate system. 
<figure xml:id="facs-fig1">
  <graphic url="Images/facs-fig1.png"/>
</figure>
The following encoding defines each of the four zones identified in
the figure.
 <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface xMax="200" yMax="300">
  <graphic url="Boulles-49r.png"/>
  <zone box="25 25 180 60"/> 
    <!-- contains the title -->
  <zone box="28 75 175 178"/> 
    <!-- contains the paragraph in italics -->
  <zone box="105 76 175 160"/> 
    <!-- contains the figure -->
  <zone box="45 125 60 130"/>
    <!-- contains the word "pendans" -->
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML> 
Note that the location of each zone is defined
independently but using the same co-ordinate system, so that they may
overlap freely. Zones need not  nest within each other; they must
however be rectangular.</p>
<p>Generally, a <gi>zone</gi> element will be empty, as in the above
example. However, it is also possible to include within it a
further <gi>graphic</gi> element, if for example a detailed image is
available. Since all <gi>zone</gi> elements use the same co-ordinate
system (that defined by their parent <gi>surface</gi>, there is no
need to demonstrate enclosure of one zone within another by means of
nesting. To continue the current example, supposing that we have an
additional image called 
<ident>Boulles49r-detail.png</ident> containing  an
additional image of the figure in the third zone above, we might
encode that zone as follows:
<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
  <zone box="105 76 175 160"> 
    <graphic url="Boulles49r-detail.png"/>
  </zone>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>Now suppose that we wish to align a transcription of this page
with the zones identified above. The first step is to give each
relevant part of the facsimile an identifier:

 <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface xml:id="B49r" xMax="200" yMax="300">
  <graphic url="Boulles-49r.png"/>
  <zone xml:id="B49rHead" box="25 25 180 60"/> 
    <!-- contains the title -->
  <zone xml:id="B49rPara2" box="28 75 175 178"/> 
    <!-- contains the paragraph in italics -->
  <zone xml:id="B49rFig1" box="105 76 175 160"/> 
    <!-- contains the figure -->
  <zone xml:id="B49rW457" box="45 125 60 130"/>
    <!-- contains the word "pendans" -->
</surface>
</facsimile></egXML> 
The alignment between transcription and image is made, as usual, by
means of the <att>facs</att> attribute:
<egXML  xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<pb facs="#B49r"/>
<fw>De Geometrie 49</fw>
<head facs="#B49rHead">
DU SON ET ACCORD DES CLOCHES ET <lb/> des alleures des chevaulx,
chariotz &amp; charges, des fontaines:&amp; <lb/> encyclie du monde,
&amp; de la dimension du corps humain.</head>
<head>Chapitre septiesme</head>
<div n="1">
<p>Le son &amp; accord des cloches pendans en ung mesme <lb/> axe, est
faict en contraires parties.</p>
<p rend="it" facs="#B49rPara2">LEs cloches ont quasi fi<lb/>gures de rondes
pyra<lb/>mides imperfaictes &amp; <lb/> irregulieres: &amp; leur
accord se <lb/> fait par reigle geometrique. Com<lb/>me si les deux
cloches C &amp; D <lb/> sont <w facs="#B49rW457">pendans</w> à ung
mesme axe <lb/> ou essieu A B: je dis que leur ac<lb/>cord se fera en
co<expan>n</expan>traires parties<lb/> co<expan>m</expan>me voyez icy
figuré. Car qua<expan>n</expan>d <lb/> lune sera en hault, laultre
declinera embas. Aultrement si elles decli<lb/>nent toutes deux
ensembles en une mesme partie, elles seront discord, <lb/> &amp; sera
leur sonnerie mal plaisante à oyr.<figure facs="#B49rFig1"><graphic
url="Boulles49r-detail.png"/> </figure></p>
</div>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>Further discussion of the principals underlying the encoding
choices made in the above transcription are provided in the remainder
of this chapter. </p>

<p>It is also possible to point in the other direction, from a
<gi>surface</gi> or <gi>zone</gi> to the corresponding text. This is
the function of the <att>start</att> attribute, which supplies the
identifier of the element containing the transcribed text found within
the surface or zone concerned. Thus, another way of linking this page
with its transcription would be simply <egXML
xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><facsimile>
<surface start="#PB49R" >
  <graphic url="Boulles-49r.png"/>
</surface>
</facsimile>
<text>
<!-- ... -->
<pb xml:id="PB49R"/>
<fw>De Geometrie 49</fw>
<!-- ... -->
</text>
 </egXML></p>

<p>The elements and classes defined by this section are formally
defined as follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DPFACS">
&facsimile;
&att.global.facs;
&surface;
&att.coordinated;
&zone;
&model.resourceLike;
</specGrp>
</p>

</div>


<div><head>Scope of Transcriptions</head>

<p>When transcribing a primary source, scholars may wish to record
information concerning individual readings of letters, words or larger
units, whether the object is simply a <soCalled>neutral</soCalled>
transcription or a critical edition.  In either case they  may also
wish to include other editorial material, such
as comments on the status or possible origin of particular readings,
corrections, or text supplied to fill lacunae.  Further, it is
customary in transcriptions to register certain features of the
source, such as ornamentation, underlining, deletion, areas of damage
and lacunae. This chapter provides ways of encoding such information:
<list type="bullets">
<item>first, the problem of recording editorial or other alterations to
the text, such as expansion of abbreviations, corrections, conjectures,
etc. (section <ptr target="#PHCH"/>)</item>
<item>then, methods of describing important extra-linguistic phenomena
in the source: unusual spaces, lines, page and line breaks, change of
manuscript hand, etc. (section <ptr target="#PHPH"/>)</item>
<item>finally, a method of recording material such as running heads,
catch-words, and the like (section <ptr target="#PHSK"/>)</item></list></p>
<p>These recommendations are not intended to meet every
transcriptional circumstance likely to be faced by any scholar.
Rather, they should be regarded as a base which can be elaborated if necessary by different scholars in different disciplines<!-- , with
distinct scholarly domains eventually developing their own document
types.  In time, the feature structure notation developed in chapter
<ptr target="#FS"/>, may also permit scholars to tailor the encoding
of complex transcriptional information in ways not here anticipated-->.
 <!-- We are conscious that a great deal of work remains to done in
these areas, and that the encoder will need to take even more
individual responsibility than usual in applying the recommendations
of this chapter in such contexts, but believe that these
recommendations form a good basis for such future work.-->
</p><p>As a rule, all elements which may be used in the course of a
transcription of a single witness may also be used in a critical
apparatus, i.e. within the elements proposed in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>.
This can generally be achieved by nesting a
particular reading containing tagged elements from a particular witness
within the <gi>rdg</gi> element in an <gi>app</gi> structure.
	</p>
<p>Just as a critical apparatus may contain transcriptional elements
within its record of variant readings in various witnesses, one may
record variant readings in an individual witness by use of the apparatus
mechanisms <gi>app</gi> and <gi>rdg</gi>.  This is discussed in
section <ptr target="#TCTR"/>.
	</p>
<p>This module makes available the following components:

<moduleSpec xml:id="DPH" ident="transcr"><altIdent type="FPI">Transcription of Primary Sources</altIdent><desc>Transcription of primary sources</desc></moduleSpec><!--publicID:  -//TEI P5//ELEMENTS Additional Element Set for Transcription of Primary Sources//EN-->


The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>
<p>The module is organized as follows:
<specGrpRef target="#DPFACS"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCAD"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DPHCD"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DPHOM"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DPHHD"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DPHDA"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DPHSP"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCHD"/>
</p>
<!-- this extension never referenced by DTD, so removed -->
<!--
<p>This tag set modifies the element class
<ident type="class">model.pPart.edit</ident> by declaring two extra attributes
for members of the class:
<module xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xml:id="DPHENT" n="Attributes for Transcription of Primary Sources" ident="transcr-decl" type="decls"><publicID>-//TEI P5//ENTITIES Element Classes for Transcription of Primary Sources//EN</publicID>
&editph.cla;
    </module></p>
-->
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="PHCH"><head>Altered, Corrected, and Erroneous Texts</head>
<p>In the detailed transcription of any source, it may prove necessary
to record various types of actual or potential alteration of the text:
expansion of abbreviations, correction of the text (either by author, 
scribe, or later hand, or by previous or current editors or scholars), addition, deletion, or
substitution of material, and the like.  The sections below describe how
such phenomena may be encoded using either elements defined in the core
module (defined in chapter <ptr target="#CO"/>) or specialized elements
available only when the module described in this chapter is
available.</p>
<!-- add and del for things added and removed
     supplied by later editor  (add suppress, or use gap) -> ed for
     emendation in general (DO, MD, LB to discuss) -->

<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCO"><head>Use of Core Tags for Transcriptional Work</head>
<p>In transcribing individual sources 
of any type, encoders may record their corrections, normalizations,
expansions of abbreviations, additions, and omissions
using the elements described in section <ptr target="#COED"/>.
Those particularly relevant to this chapter include:
<specList><specDesc key="abbr"/><specDesc key="expan"/><specDesc key="sic"/><specDesc key="corr"/><specDesc key="add"/><specDesc key="del"/><specDesc key="hi"/><specDesc key="gap"/></specList>
	</p>

<p>When the module for transcription of primary sources is selected,
these elements all gain two specialized attributes for specifying who
is responsible for certain aspects of the interpretation and markup,
and the certainty attributed to the interpretation:
<specList><specDesc key="model.pPart.edit"/></specList>
The specific aspect of the markup described by these attributes differs
on different elements; for further discussion, see the relevant sections
below, especially section <ptr target="#PHHR"/>.</p>
<p>The following sections describe how the core elements just named may
be used in the transcription of primary source materials. Examples of
more complex application in scholarly transcriptions of these core
elements are given, and of their extension by linkage with the
<gi>note</gi>, <gi>respons</gi>, and <gi>certainty</gi> elements. Where the
core elements do not satisfy the needs of scholarly transcription,
additional elements are defined.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHAB"><head>Abbreviation and Expansion</head>
<p>The writing of manuscripts by hand lends itself to the use of
abbreviation to shorten scribal labour. Commonly occurring letters,
groups of letters, words or even whole phrases, may be represented by
significant marks. This phenomenon of manuscript abbreviation is so
widespread and so various that no taxonomy of it is here attempted.
Instead, methods are shown which allow abbreviations to be encoded using
the core elements mentioned above.</p>
<p>A manuscript abbreviation may be viewed in two ways. One may
transcribe it as a particular sequence of letters or marks upon the
page: thus, a <q>p with a bar through the descender</q>, a
<q>superscript hook</q>, a <q>macron</q>. One may also interpret the
abbreviation in terms of the letter or letters it is seen as standing
for: thus, <q>per</q>, <q>re</q>, <q>n</q>. Both of these views are
supported by these Guidelines. The entity reference system allows the
encoder to declare whatever entities are needed, using entity names
like <ident type="ge">p-underbar</ident>, <ident type="ge">sup-hook</ident>, or <ident type="ge">macron</ident>.
Furthermore, each entity reference may be linked to an image of the
abbreviation itself, so that the reader might see a rendering of the
text's appearance. Alternatively, the encoder may transcribe the
letter or letters he or she believes the abbreviation stands for, as
the content of an <gi>expan</gi> element: thus
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><expan>per</expan> <expan>re</expan> <expan>n</expan></egXML>
</p>
<p>These two methods of coding abbreviation may also be combined. An
encoder may record, for any abbreviation, both the sequence of letters
or marks which constitutes it, and its sense, that is, the letter or
letters for which it is believed to stand. For example, the
abbreviations of <mentioned>euery persone</mentioned> in the following
fragment<note place="foot">From <bibl><title level="a">The Manere of
Good Lyuynge</title>, fol 126v of Bodleian MS Laud Misc. 517, plate
8(ii) in <title>English Cursive Book Hands 1250–1500</title> by
M. B. Parkes (Clarendon Press: Oxford, 1969)</bibl>.</note> may be
expanded in transcription:  
<eg><![CDATA[eu<expan>er</expan>y
<expan>per</expan>sone that
loketh after heuen hath a place in this ladder]]></eg>
Alternatively, the encoding may represent only the fact of abbreviation:
<eg><![CDATA[eu<abbr>&er;</abbr>y
<abbr >&p-underbar;</abbr>sone that
loketh after heuen hath a place in this ladder]]></eg></p>
<!-- removed resp="#mp" as not relevant for now LB -->
<p>The choice between the <gi>expan</gi> and <gi>abbr</gi>
elements is left to the encoder. As a rule, the <gi>abbr</gi> element
should be preferred where it is wished to signify that the content of
the element is an abbreviation, without necessarily indicating what the
abbreviation may stand for. The <gi>expan</gi> element should be used
where it is wished to signify that the content of the element is an
expanded text, without necessarily indicating the abbreviation used in
the original. The decision as to which (<gi>abbr</gi> or
<gi>expan</gi>) to use may vary from abbreviation to abbreviation; there
is no requirement that the one system be used throughout a
transcription. However, processing may be simplified if one only of
these is used throughout a transcription. The choice is likely to be a
matter of editorial policy, which might be applied consistently
throughout. If the highest priority is to transcribe the text
literatim, while indicating the presence of abbreviations, the choice
will be to use <gi>abbr</gi> throughout. If the highest priority is to
present a reading transcription, while indicating that some letters or
words are expansions of abbreviations, the choice will be to use
<gi>expan</gi> throughout.</p>
<p>Further information may be attached to instances of these elements by
the <gi>note</gi> element, on which see section <ptr target="#CONO"/>, and
by use of the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes. In this
instance from the English <title>Brut</title>,<note place="foot">On fol
65v of Bodleian MS. Rawlinson Poetry 32; in Parkes 12(ii).</note>
a note is attached to an editorial expansion of the tail on the final d
of <mentioned>good</mentioned> to <mentioned>goode</mentioned>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For alle the while that I had
good<expan xml:id="exp01">e</expan>
I was welbeloued</egXML>
 <!--  abbr="&#x027d;" -->
Then the note:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><note target="#exp01">The stroke added to 
the final d could signify the plural ending (-es, -is, -ys&gt;)
but the singular <hi rend="it">good</hi> was used with the meaning
<q>property</q>, <q>wealth</q>, at this time (v. examples
quoted in OED, sb. Good, C. 7, b, c, d and 8 spec.)</note></egXML>
The editor might declare a degree of certainty for this expansion, based
on the OED examples, and state the responsibility for the expansion:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For alle the while that I had
good<expan resp="#mp" cert="high">e</expan>
I was welbeloued</egXML>
The value supplied for the <att>resp</att> attribute may point to any
other element. The intention is that it should indicate in one
place the name of the editor responsible for this and possibly other
interventions; an appropriate element therefore might be a
<gi>respStmt</gi> element in the header like the following:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<respStmt xml:id="mp">
<resp>Editorial emendations</resp>
<name>Malcom Parks</name>
</respStmt></egXML>.  
Observe that the <att>cert</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes may be
used with the <gi>expan</gi> element only to indicate respectively
confidence in the content of the element (i.e. the expansion), and
responsibility for suggesting this expansion. </p>
<p>The <gi>choice</gi> element may be used to indicate that the
proposed expansion is one way of encoding what might equally well be
represented as an abbreviation, represented by the hooked D, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For alle the while that I had
good<choice><abbr>ɽ</abbr><expan resp="#mp" cert="high">e</expan></choice>
I was welbeloued</egXML>
If it is desired to express aspects of certainty and responsibility for
some other aspect of the use of these elements, then the mechanisms
discussed in chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> should be used. See also <ptr target="#PHHR"/> for discussion of the issues of certainty and
responsibility in the context of transcription.</p>
<p>If more than one expansion for the same abbreviation is to be
recorded, multiple notes may be supplied. It may also be appropriate
to use the markup for critical apparatus; an example is given in
section <ptr target="#TCTR"/>.</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCC"><head>Correction and Conjecture</head>
<p>The <gi>sic</gi>, <gi>corr</gi>, and <gi>choice</gi> elements, defined in the Common Core module
may be used to register authorial or scribal corrections within a
witness. For example, in the manuscript of William James's <title>A
Pluralistic Universe</title>, edited by Fredson Bowers (Cambridge:
Harvard University Press, 1977) a sentence first written
<q rend="display">One must have lived longer with this system,
to appreciate its advantages.</q>
has been modified by James to begin <q>But one must ...</q>, without the
inital capital O having been reduced to lowercase. This non-standard
orthography could be recorded thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">But <sic>One</sic> must have lived ...</egXML>
or corrected:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">But <corr>one</corr> must have lived ...</egXML>
or the two possibilities might be represented as a choice:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">But <choice><sic>One</sic><corr>one</corr></choice> must have lived ...</egXML></p>
<p>In this example from Albertus Magnus,<note place="foot"><title>De
Nutrimento et Nutribili, Tractatus 1</title>, fol 217r col b of Merton
College Oxford MS O.2.1 (Parkes pl. 16).</note>
both a manuscript error <mentioned>angues</mentioned> and its correction
<mentioned>augens</mentioned> are registered within a  <gi>choice</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Nos autem iam ostendimus quod nutrimentum
et <choice><sic>angues</sic><corr>augens</corr></choice>.</egXML>
</p> 
<!-- dropped example for the moment, pending clarification of when to -->
	<!-- use supplied etc,. LB -->
	<!--
In this example, from George Moore's draft of additional materials for
<q>Memoirs of My Dead Life</q>,<note place="foot">In Pierpont Morgan MA
  3421, from <title>British Literary Manuscripts/Series II:  from 1800
  to 1914</title>, by V. Klinkenborg, H.Cahoon and C. Ryskamp (New York:
  Pierpont Morgan Library, 1981).</note>
the transcriber supplies the word <mentioned>we</mentioned> omitted by the author:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">You see that I avoid the word create for we
create nothing <sic corr="we"/> develope.</egXML>
Or with reverse use of the <gi>corr</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">You see that I avoid the word create for we
create nothing <corr sic="">we</corr> develope.</egXML>
(N.B. when the additional tag set defined in this chapter is selected,
the <gi>supplied</gi> element should normally be used in preference
to <gi>sic</gi> or <gi>corr</gi> for such supplied text.)</p>
-->
<p>As with <gi>expan</gi> and <gi>abbr</gi>, the
choice as to whether to record simply that there is an apparent error,
or simply that a correction has been applied, or to record both
possible readings within a  <gi>choice</gi> element is
left to the encoder. The choice is likely to be a matter of editorial policy,
which might be applied consistently throughout or decided case by case.
If the highest priority is to present an uncorrected transcription while
noting perceived errors in the original, the choice will typically
be to use only <gi>sic</gi> throughout. If the highest priority is to
present a reading transcription, while indicating that perceived errors
in the original have been corrected, the choice will be to use
only <gi>corr</gi> throughout.</p>
<p>Further information may be attached to instances of these elements by
the <gi>note</gi> element and <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes. Here, two separate corrections in Dudo of S. Quentin<note place="foot"><title>De moribus et actis primorum Normannie ducum</title>,
in fol 4v of British Library MS Harley 3742, Parkes pl 6(i).</note>
are assigned the same note. First the correction is represented within
a <gi>choice</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">quamuis <choice xml:id="sic01"><sic>mens</sic><corr>iners</corr></choice> que nutu dei
gesta sunt ... unde esset uiriliter
<choice xml:id="sic02"><corr>uegetata</corr><sic>negata</sic></choice></egXML>
then the note, linked to the <att>xml:id</att> of the two <gi>choice</gi> elements
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><note target="#sic01 #sic02">Substitution of a more
familiar word which resembles graphically what the
scribe should be copying but which
does not make sense in the context.</note></egXML></p>
<p>The <att>cert</att> attribute may also be used with the <gi>corr</gi>
element to signify the conjectural status of a particular editorial
reading, with the <att>resp</att> attribute used to identify the scholar
responsible for the conjecture by pointing to them. For example,
assuming that some element in the header or elsewhere exists to identify
Donaldson himself, then editorial confidence
in E. Talbot Donaldson's emendation of the Hengwrt manuscript reading
<mentioned>wight</mentioned> to <mentioned>wright</mentioned> in line 117 of Chaucer's
<title>The Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> may be marked as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<!-- ... --> <name xml:id="ETD">E Talbot Donaldson</name> <!-- ... -->
Telle me also, to what conclusioun
Were membres maad, of generacioun
And of so parfit wis a 
<choice xml:id="corr117"><sic>wight</sic><corr resp="#ETD" cert="medium">wright</corr></choice>
ywroght?
</egXML>
The editor might also conveniently add a note referring to Donaldson's
discussion of this passage:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><note target="#corr117">This emendation of the Hengwrt copy text,
based on a Latin source and on the reading of three late
and usually unauthoritative manuscripts, was proposed
by E. Talbot Donaldson in <bibl><title>Speculum</title> 40 (1965)
626–33.</bibl></note></egXML></p>
<p>Alternative corrections within a transcription of a single witness
may be held within an <gi>app</gi> structure, in the same way that
alternative expansions are so grouped in the example given in section
<ptr target="#TCTR"/>. Here, Donaldson's conjectured emendation of the
Hengwrt manuscript may be recorded not only alongside the editorial
transcription but also alongside another conjecture:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">And of so parfit wis a
<app>
  <rdg wit="#Hg">wight</rdg>
  <rdg wit="#Ln #Ry2 #Ld" resp="#ETD"> <corr>wright</corr> </rdg>
  <rdg wit="#Gg" resp="#mp"> <corr>wyf</corr> </rdg>
</app></egXML></p>
<p>Observe that no <att>resp</att> attribute is necessary for the base
transcription:  by default, responsibility is assigned to the scholar(s)
responsible for the transcription, as identified in the TEI header.  The
conjectures are held within <gi>corr</gi> elements, contained within the
<gi>rdg</gi> elements. The <att>resp</att> attribute identifying
responsibility for each correction is attached to the outer
<gi>rdg</gi>, and inherited by the inner <gi>corr</gi> element. Note
too that the support for these conjectures in other manuscripts can be
noted in the <att>wit</att> attribute in the <gi>rdg</gi> element.</p>
<p>The <att>cert</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes may be used with
the <gi>corr</gi> element only to indicate respectively confidence in
the content of the element (i.e. the correction), and confidence in the
responsibility for suggesting this correction or conjecture. <!-- In the
case of the use of these attributes with the <gi>sic</gi> element, the
<att>cert</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes are defined as indicating
respectively confidence in the conjecture held in the <att>corr</att>
attribute and the responsibility for suggesting this conjecture. The
above example could be encoded using the <gi>sic</gi> element as
follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">And of so parfit wis a
<sic corr="wright" resp="#etd" cert="70">wight</sic>
ywroght?</egXML>
--> 
If it is desired to express aspects of certainty and responsibility for
some other aspect of the use of these elements, then the mechanisms
discussed in chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> should be used. See also <ptr target="#PHHR"/> for discussion of the issues of certainty and
responsibility in the context of transcription.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHAD"><head>Additions and Deletions</head>
<p>Additions and deletions to a text may be described using the
following elements:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="add"/>
  <specDesc key="addSpan"/>
  <specDesc key="del"/>
  <specDesc key="delSpan"/>
</specList>
Of these, <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> are included in the core tag
set, while <gi>addSpan</gi> and <gi>delSpan</gi> are available only when
using the module defined in this chapter.</p>
<p>As described in section <ptr target="#COED"/>, the <gi>add</gi> element
indicating material added may be used to signify manuscript additions or
insertions, be they authorial or scribal. In the autograph manuscript
of Max Beerbohm's <title>The Golden Drugget</title>,<note place="foot">In
  Pierpont Morgan MA 3391 (Klinkenborg 123).</note>
the author's addition of "do ever" may be recorded as follows, with the
<att>hand</att> attribute indicating that the addition was Beerbohm's
by referencing a <gi>hand</gi> element defined elsewhere in the document:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Some things are best at first sight. Others — and
here is one of them — <add hand="#mb">do ever</add>
improve by recognition ....
<hand xml:id="mb" scribe="Max Beerbohm holograph"/>
</egXML>
Similarly, the <gi>del</gi> element indicating material deleted may be
used to signify manuscript deletions. In the autograph manuscript of D.
H. Lawrence's <title>Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani</title><note place="foot">In Pierpont
Morgan MA 1892, (Klinkenborg 129).</note>, the author's deletion of
<mentioned>my</mentioned> may be recorded as follows. As well as the
<att>hand</att> attribute indicating that the deletion was Lawrence's,
the <att>rend</att> attribute indicates that the deletion was by
strike-through:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For I hate this <del rend="strikethrough" hand="#dhl">my</del> body,
which is so dear to me
...
<hand xml:id="dhl" scribe="holograph"/>
</egXML>
If deletions are classified systematically, the <att>type</att>
attribute should normally
be used to indicate the classification; when they
are classified by the manner in which they were effected, or by their
appearance, however,
this will lead to a certain arbitrariness in deciding
whether to use the <att>type</att> or the <att>rend</att> attribute
to hold the information. In general, it is recommended that the
<att>rend</att> attribute be used for description of the appearance
or method of deletion, and that the <att>type</att> attribute be
reserved for higher level or more abstract classifications.</p>
<p>Further characteristics of the addition and deletion, e.g. the date,
or ink, may be needed for detailed transcription of manuscripts. Such
characteristics may conveniently be recorded as attributes of the
<gi>add</gi> or <gi>del</gi> element. The specific attributes required
may be added to the formal declaration of these elements by using the
techniques described in chapter <ptr target="#MD"/>.</p>
<p>The <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi> elements defined in the core tag
set available in all TEI documents will suffice for describing typically
brief additions and deletions in the text being transcribed. On
occasion, it will be necessary to record an addition or deletion which
crosses a structural boundary in the text being encoded, for example the
addition or deletion from a manuscript of a section containing several
distinct structural subdivisions, such as poems or prose items. These
are most conveniently encoded using the <gi>addSpan</gi> and
<gi>delSpan</gi> elements, available in the module defined
in this chapter. In this example of the use of <gi>addSpan</gi>, the
insertion of a gathering containing four neo-Eddic poems into
<title>Landsbókasafn</title><note place="foot">In Reykjavík, Lbs 1562 4to</note> by Helgi
Ólafsson is recorded as follows.  
<!-- added clarificatory sentence -->
A <gi>hand</gi> element is
first declared, within the header of the document, to associate
the identifier <ident>heol</ident> with Helgi. In the body of the
text, an <gi>addSpan</gi> element
is placed to mark the beginning of the span of added text.  The
<att>hand</att> attribute ascribes the responsibility for the addition
to the manuscript to Helgi, and the <att>to</att> attribute declares the
identifier for the anchor which marks the end of the added text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><hand xml:id="heol" n="Helgi Ólafsson"/>
<addSpan n="added gathering" hand="#heol" spanTo="#p025"/>
<anchor xml:id="p025"/>
</egXML></p>
<p>In this example of the use of the <gi>delSpan</gi> element, a full
two lines of Thomas Moore's autograph of the second version of
<title>Lalla Rookh</title><note place="foot">In Pierpont Morgan MA 310,
(Klinkenborg 23).</note> are marked for omission by vertical
strike-through. The two lines cross the structural line division marked
<tag>l n='2'</tag>, so it would not be possible to use a single
<gi>del</gi> element, since it would have to span the <gi>l</gi> marker.
The lines also themselves include a further deletion and addition.  The
<gi>delSpan</gi> element indicates the begining of the span marked for
deletion, with the <att>to</att> attribute giving the identifier
<val>#delend01</val> for an <gi>anchor</gi> element which marks the end of the span of text so
marked:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l n="1">
   <delSpan rend="vertical strike" spanTo="#delend01"/>
   Tis moonlight <del>upon</del> <add>over</add> Oman's sky</l>
<l n="2">Her isles of pearl look lovelily<anchor xml:id="delend01"/></l></egXML></p>
<p>The text deleted must be at least partially legible, in order for
the encoder to be able to transcribe it.  If it is not legible at all,
the <gi>gap</gi> element should be used to signal that the text was
not transcribed, because it could not be; the <att>reason</att>
attribute can give the cause of the omission from the transcription as
<q>deletion, illegible</q>.  <!-- The <gi>gap</gi> element may optionally
be enclosed by a <gi>del</gi> element, if it is thought useful to
record the deletion explicitly using this element.-->  If the deleted
text is partially legible, the <gi>unclear</gi> element described in
section <ptr target="#PHDA"/> should be used to signal the areas of
text which cannot be read with confidence; it too may be enclosed
within a <gi>del</gi> element.  See further section <ptr
target="#PHOM"/> and section <ptr target="#PHDA"/>.</p>
<p>The elements <gi>add</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, and <gi>gap</gi> are defined
in the Common Core module and are available in all TEI documents.  The
elements <gi>addSpan</gi> and <gi>delSpan</gi> have the following formal
declarations:
<specGrp xml:id="DTCAD" n="Added and Deleted Spans">
&addSpan;
&delSpan;
</specGrp></p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHSU"><head>Substitutions</head>
<p>Substitution of one word or phrase for another is
perhaps the most common of all phenomena requiring special treatment
in transcription of primary textual sources.
It may be simply one word overwriting another, or
deletion of one word and its replacement by another written above it by
the same hand at the one time; the deletion and replacement may be done
by different hands at different times; there may be a long chain of
substitutions on the one stretch of text, with uncertainty as to the
order of substitution and as to the final reading.</p>
<p>Three different methods may be used to express substitution of one
stretch of text by another:
<list type="bullets">
<item>the <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi> elements, either individually
to encode a single substitution or nested to encode a sequence of
substitutions;</item>
<item>the <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> elements, used in sequence to
show that text was first deleted then other text inserted;</item>
<item>the <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> elements, used within an
<gi>app</gi> structure (as defined in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>) to
indicate that the deleted and added text within the individual reading
elements making up the <gi>app</gi> structure are variants of one
another.</item></list>
The use of all three of these is illustrated in the following encodings
of the second line of <title>Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani</title> from
the Lawrence manuscript mentioned above.  Lawrence first wrote <q>How it
galls me, what a galling shadow</q>.  Subsequently, he deleted
<mentioned>galls</mentioned> and wrote <mentioned>dogs</mentioned> above the deletion.</p>
<p>This substitution could be registered using the first method outlined
above, as a correction using the <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi>
elements within a <gi>choice</gi> element.
Note the use of the <att>resp</att> attribute on the <gi>corr</gi>
element to assign the correction to Lawrence.  (For further information
on the <att>hand</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes, see section
<ptr target="#PHHR"/>.) 
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">How it <choice><sic>galls</sic><corr resp="#DHL">dogs</corr></choice>
me, what a galling shadow</egXML>
This substitution could be registered using the second method outlined
above, using the <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> elements in sequence to
reflect the fact that text was first deleted then other text inserted:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">How it <del type="overstrike" hand="#dhl">galls</del>
<add place="supralinear" hand="#dhl">dogs</add>
me, what a galling shadow</egXML>
This substitution could be registered using the third method outlined
above, using the <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> elements within an
<gi>app</gi> structure to indicate that the deleted and added texts are
variants of one another.  Note that within the <gi>app</gi> structure
the <att>hand</att> attribute is moved from the inner <gi>del</gi> and
<gi>add</gi> elements to the outer <gi>rdg</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">How it
  <app>
    <rdg hand="#dhl"> <del type="overstrike"> galls</del> </rdg>
    <rdg hand="#dhl"> <add place="supralinear"> dogs</add> </rdg>
  </app>
me, what a galling shadow</egXML>
Each of these three methods has its particular advantages and
disadvantages.  The first method (use of <gi>sic</gi> and <gi>corr</gi>)
is compact and indicates clearly that one text is a substitute for
another.  However, it provides no clear means of stating how the
substitution is effected:  whether by deletion through strike-through, or
underdotting, or erasure, followed by interlinear insertion, or marginal
insertion.  (The global <att>rend</att> attribute might conceivably be
used, but this may not be thought an obvious place to put such
information.)  In a transcription where this information is not felt to
be important, however, this method will suffice to indicate simple cases
of direct substitution of one text for another.</p>
<p>The second method (use of a <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> sequence)
is also compact and provides means for exact declaration of how the
deletion and insertion are effected.  However, it does not indicate
explicitly that one text is a substitute for another.  It is left for
the reader or the application to infer from the <gi>del</gi> and
<gi>add</gi> sequence that the insertion is to be taken as a
substitution for the deletion.  In many transcriptions, the inference
may be safely drawn for simple cases of direct substitution of one text
for another.  In other transcriptions, for example of complex authorial
manuscripts, this inference may prove fragile; those who desire
to express clearly that an adjacent addition and deletion are not
independent but constitute a single act of substitution will therefore
wish to avoid this method.  Others, of course, may prefer it for
precisely the same reason, namely that it avoids prejudging the issue of
whether adjacent deletions and additions are independent or joined.</p>
<p>The third method (use of the <gi>del</gi> and <gi>add</gi> elements
within an <gi>app</gi> structure) provides means both for exact
declaration of how the deletion and insertion are effected and for
explicit indication that one text is a substitute for another.  Further,
the exact sequence of readings may also be declared by use of the
<att>varSeq</att> attribute on the <gi>rdg</gi> element, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">How it
  <app>
    <rdg varSeq="1" hand="#dhl"> <del>galls</del> </rdg>
    <rdg varSeq="2" hand="#dhl"> <add>dogs</add> </rdg>
  </app>
me, what a galling shadow</egXML>
Here, the combination of the <att>hand</att> and <att>varSeq</att>
attributes suffices to inform the reader of the authorial substitution
of <mentioned>dogs</mentioned> for <mentioned>galls</mentioned>.</p>
<p>Similarly, the <att>varSeq</att> attribute might be used in a
transcription of the manuscripts of James Joyce's <title>Ulysses</title>
to indicate the sequence of Joyce's corrections which is implicit in
Hans Walther Gabler's reconstruction of the <q>overlay</q> levels of
Joyce's transcriptions.  This third method is the most powerful and
unambiguous of the three methods and enables the widest range of
processing possibilities, at the expense of introducing a heavier
burden of markup into the text. Production of such documents should
therefore not be undertaken without markup-aware editors.  
Applications of some
sophistication may be needed to make full use of all the information
that may be held within an <gi>app</gi> structure.  In the absence of
such applications, scholars may feel that the present cost of the more
informative coding using <gi>app</gi> structures outweighs the future
benefits.  In making such decisions, it should however be kept in mind
that the capabilities of software at the time a project begins will often
be wholly irrelevant when the project is completed some years later.</p>
<p>The Lawrence example above shows the three methods used for encoding
a single substitution of one reading for another.  <!--The same three
methods may also be used to encode longer sequences of substitutions.-->
In the example from William James, first written out by James as <q>One
must have lived longer with this system, to appreciate its
advantages</q> the word <mentioned>this</mentioned> is first replaced by
<mentioned>such a</mentioned> and this is then replaced by <mentioned>a</mentioned>.
<note place="foot">The manuscript contains several other substitutions,
ignored here for the sake of clarity.</note> 
<!-- This may be encoded using
the first method, with the sequence of substitutions shown by the
nesting of <gi>corr</gi> elements:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">One must have lived longer with
<choice>
<sic>this</sic>
<corr sic="such a">a</corr></corr> system,
to appreciate its advantages.</egXML></p>
-->
It may be encoded using the second method, with the two changes being
treated as a sequence of additions and deletions:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">One must have lived longer with
<del>this</del> <del><add>such a</add></del>
<add>a</add> system, to appreciate its advantages.</egXML>
Note the nesting of an <gi>add</gi> element within a <gi>del</gi> to
record text first added, then deleted in the source.</p>
<p>It may be encoded using the third method, with each reading in the
series contained in a <gi>rdg</gi> element within an <gi>app</gi>
structure:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">One must have lived longer with
  <app>
    <rdg varSeq="1"><del>this</del></rdg>
    <rdg varSeq="2"><del><add>such a</add></del></rdg>
    <rdg varSeq="3"><add>a</add></rdg>
  </app>
system, to appreciate its advantages.</egXML>
The three encodings of this slightly more complex example illustrate the
general truth that the more information involving substitutions there is
to be encoded, the clearer become the advantages of the use of the
<gi>app</gi> method over the other two methods.  As a rule, it is
recommended that the <gi>app</gi> method be used for encoding
substitutions of any complexity.  It is also desirable that the one
method be used throughout any one transcription.  Accordingly, the
<gi>app</gi> method is recommended for text critical transcription of
primary textual materials requiring encoding of instances of other than
straightforward substitution.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCD"><head>Cancellation of Deletions and Other Markings</head>
<p>An author or scribe may mark a word or phrase in some way, and then
on reflection decide to cancel the marking.  For example, text may be
marked for deletion and the deletion then cancelled, thus restoring the
deleted text.  Such cancellation may be indicated by the
<gi>restore</gi> element:
<specList><specDesc key="restore" atts="type  hand "/></specList></p>
<p>Presume that Lawrence decided to restore <mentioned>my</mentioned> to the
phrase of <title>Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani</title> first written
<q>For I hate this my body</q>, with the <mentioned>my</mentioned> first deleted
then restored by writing <q>stet</q> in the margin.  This may be
encoded:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For I hate this
<restore hand="#dhl" means="marginalStetNote"><del>my</del></restore>
body</egXML></p>
<p>The <gi>restore</gi> element is defined as follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DPHCD" n="Cancelled Deletions">
&restore;
</specGrp>
	</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHOM"><head>Text Omitted from or Supplied in the Transcription</head>
<p>Where text is not transcribed, whether because of damage to the
original, or because it is illegible, or because of editorial policy,
the <gi>gap</gi> core element should be used to register the omission;
where text not present in the source is supplied (whether
conjecturally or from other witnesses) to fill an apparent gap in the
text, it should be marked using the <gi>supplied</gi> element provided
by the module defined in this chapter.
<specList><specDesc key="gap" atts="reason hand agent"/><specDesc key="supplied" atts="reason hand agent source"/></specList></p>
<p>By its nature, the <gi>gap</gi> element must have no content.  It
should be used wherever an authorial or scribal erasure is so
successful, or the text is so illegible, that nothing can be read.  In
the Beerbohm manuscript of <title>The Golden Drugget</title> cited
above, for example, the author has erased several passages by inking
them over completely:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Others <gap
reason="cancelled" hand="#mb" extent="10" unit="cm"/>—and
here is one of them...</egXML></p>
<p>In an autograph letter of Sydney Smith in the Pierpont Morgan
library,<note place="foot">In Klinkenborg 11</note> three words in the signature are quite illegible:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I am dr Sr yr <gap
reason="illegible" extent="3" unit="word"/>Sydney Smith</egXML>
It is possible, but not always necessary, to provide measurements
precise to the millimeter or even to the printer's point.  The degree of
precision attempted will vary with the purpose of the encoding and the
nature of the material.</p>
<p>In cases where there is damage, or a degree of illegibility, but the
text is nevertheless legible and is transcribed, the <gi>gap</gi>
element should not be used.  Instead, the passage should be marked using
one or more of the elements <gi>damage</gi> and <gi>unclear</gi>, which
are described in section <ptr target="#PHDA"/>.</p>
<p>If the source text is completely illegible or missing, and new text
is supplied to fill the gap, it should be marked as <gi>supplied</gi>.
If another (imaginary) copy of the letter above preserved the signature
as reading <q>I am dear Sir your very humble Servt Sydney Smith</q>, the
text illegible in the autograph might be supplied in the transcription:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I am dr Sr yr
<supplied reason="illegible" resp="#RW" source="amanuensis copy">very
humble Servt</supplied> Sydney Smith</egXML>
Both <gi>gap</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> may be used in combination with
<gi>unclear</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, and other elements; for
discussion, see section <ptr target="#PHCOMB"/>.</p>
<p>As noted, <gi>gap</gi> is defined in the Common Core module.  The
<gi>supplied</gi> element is declared thus:
<specGrp xml:id="DPHOM" n="Supplied Text">
&supplied;
</specGrp></p></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="PHPH"><head>Non-Linguistic Phenomena in the Source</head>
<p>This section describes methods for recording a number of
non-linguistic characteristics of the source text which are often of
particular interest in the transcription of primary sources:  points at
which one scribe takes over from another, or at which ink, pen, or other
characteristics of the writing change; points at which the source is
damaged or imperfectly legible; and unusual spaces or lines in the
source.  A discussion of the usage of the <att>hand</att>,
<att>resp</att>, and <att>cert</att> attributes is also included.
Methods for recording page breaks, column breaks, and line breaks in the
source are described in section <ptr target="#COXR"/>.</p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHDH"><head>Document Hands</head>
<p>For many text-critical purposes it is important to signal the person
responsible (the <term>hand</term>) for the writing of a whole document, a
stretch of text within a document, or a particular feature within the
document.  The hand may be of a known and named scribe or author, as
<mentioned>DHL</mentioned>, or may be described by an anonymous formula, as <mentioned>hand
one</mentioned>.  Where the hand is associated with a particular feature tagged
within a document, this may be indicated by the value of the
<att>hand</att> attribute on that feature.  The examples given above of
the use of the <att>hand</att> attribute with coding of additions and
deletions illustrate this. </p>
<p>In other cases, it may be necessary to identify a document hand
without there being any association of that hand with any specific
tagged document feature.  The <gi>handList</gi> and <gi>hand</gi>
elements are used in the TEI header (in the <gi>profileDesc</gi>
element) to define each unique hand or scribe distinguished by the
encoder in the document.  One such element must appear within the header
for each hand distinguished in the text, and each such element should
bear a distinct identifier as the value of its global
<att>xml:id</att> attribute.<!-- note place="foot">In earlier version of these Guidelines an attribute
<ident>hand</ident> was used on the <gi>hand</gi> element to carry
the same information as the existing <att>xml:id</att> attribute. The <att>hand</att> attribute is
retained in the current version of these Guidelines only for backwards compatibility and will be removed at the next release.</note-->
Each location where a change
of hands occurs may then be marked in the text by the empty
<gi>handShift</gi> element, which specifies the hand concerned by
giving the same identifier.
<specList>
<specDesc key="hand"/><specDesc key="handList"/>
<specDesc key="handShift"/></specList>
</p><p>The  <att>new</att> attribute on the
<gi>handShift</gi> element is used to indicate the hand applicable to
the material following the <gi>handShift</gi>.  This will
ordinarily, but not necessarily, be the order in which the material was
originally written.  The <att>writing</att> attribute will be most often
used to encode descriptive shifts which the transcriber perceives within
a manuscript but which are not judged to indicate a change of hand.   The particular values encoded will depend
upon the needs of the transcriber. <!-- Where many values are to be encoded,
feature structures provide an alternative means of encoding these. --><!-- might be better to allow for
nested desc?-->  </p>
<p>A single hand may employ different writing styles and inks within a
document, or may change character.  For example, the writing style might
shift from <q>anglicana</q> to <q>secretary</q>, or the ink from blue to
brown, or the character of the hand may change.  Any such changes should
be indicated by assigning a new value to the appropriate attribute
within the <gi>handShift</gi> element.  The one hand may employ
different renditions within the one writing style, for example medieval
scribes indicating a structural division by emboldening all the words
within a line.  These should be indicated by use of the <att>rend</att>
attribute on an element, in the same manner as underlining, emboldening,
font shifts, etc., in transcription of a printed text, rather than by
introducing a new <gi>handShift</gi> element.</p>
<p>In this example<note place="foot">From the Wiltshire Record Office,
Dean of Sarum Churchwardens' presentments, 1731, Hurst; the
transcription was provided by Donald A. Spaeth.</note> first the
document hands are declared in the header:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
   <profileDesc>
    <handList>
      <hand xml:id="h1" style="copperplate" ink="brown" writing="regular" first="true" resp="#das"/>
      <hand xml:id="h2" style="print" ink="brown" writing="unschooled" resp="#das"/>
    </handList>
  </profileDesc>
 </egXML>
<!-- teiheader def will need to be modified PR   --></p>
<p>Then the change of hand is indicated in the text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><handShift new="#h1" resp="#das"/>... and that good Order Decency and regular worship
may be once more introduced and Established in this
Parish according to the Rules and Ceremonies of the
Church of England and as under a good Consciencious
and sober Curate there would and ought to be
<handShift new="#h2" resp="#das"/>
and for that purpose the parishioners pray</egXML></p>
<p>In this example<note place="foot">From folio 52 recto of the Holkham
manuscript of Chaucer's <title>Canterbury Tales</title>.</note> there is
a change of ink within the one hand.  This is indicated by a new value
for the <att>ink</att> attribute on the <gi>handShift</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l>When wolde the cat dwelle in his ynne</l>
<handShift new="#h2" ink="black"/>
<l>And if the cattes skynne be slyk and gaye</l></egXML></p>
<p>These elements are declared as follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DPHHD" n="Hand Shifts">
&hand;
&handShift;
&handList;
</specGrp></p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHHR"><head>Hand, Responsibility, and Certainty Attributes</head>
<p>The <att>hand</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes have similar, but
not identical, meanings.  Observe their distinctive uses in the
following encoding of the William James passage mentioned above in
section <ptr target="#PHCC"/>.  In this example, the <mentioned>But</mentioned>
inserted by James is tagged as an <gi>add</gi>, and the consequent
editorial correction of <mentioned>One</mentioned> to <mentioned>one</mentioned> treated
separately:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><add place="supralinear" resp="#FB" hand="#WJ">But</add>
<choice><sic>One</sic><corr resp="#FB">one</corr></choice> must have
lived ...
<!-- elsewhere -->
<respStmt xml:id="FB">
<resp>editorial changes</resp>
<name>Fredson Bowers</name>
</respStmt>
<respStmt xml:id="WJ">
<resp>authorial changes</resp>
<name>William James</name>
</respStmt>
</egXML>
As in this example, <att>hand</att> should be reserved for indicating
the hand of any form of marking—here, addition but also deletion,
correction, annotation, underlining, etc.—within the primary text
being transcribed.  The scribal or authorial responsibility for this
marking may be inferred from the value of the <att>hand</att> attribute.
The value of the <att>hand</att> attribute should be one of the hand
identifiers declared in the document header (see section <ptr target="#PHDH"/>).</p>
<p>As in this example, the <att>resp</att> on a particular element
should be used only to indicate the particular aspect of responsibility
defined in these <title>Guidelines</title> as appropriate to the
<att>resp</att> attribute for that element.  In the case of the
<gi>add</gi> element, the <att>resp</att> attribute is defined as
signifying the responsibility for identifying the hand of the
addition:  here, Bowers' identification of the hand as that of William
James.  In the case of the <gi>corr</gi> element, the <att>resp</att>
attribute is defined as signifying the responsibility for supplying the
intellectual content of the correction reported in the transcription:
here, Bowers' correction of <q>One</q> to <q>one</q>.</p>
<p>As these examples show, the field of application of the
<att>resp</att> attributes varies from element to element.  In some
cases, it applies to the content of the element (<gi>corr</gi> and
<gi>expan</gi>); in others it applies to the value of a particular
attribute (<gi>sic</gi>, <gi>abbr</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, etc.).  In all
cases where both the <att>cert</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes are
defined for a particular element, the two attributes refer to the same
aspect of the markup.  The one indicates who is intellectually
responsible for some item of information, the other indicates the degree
of confidence in the information.  Thus, for a
correction, the <att>resp</att> attribute signifies the person
responsible for supplying the correction, while the <att>cert</att>
attribute signifies the degree of editorial confidence felt in that
correction.  For the expansion of an abbreviation, the
<att>resp</att> attribute signifies the person responsible for supplying
the expansion and the <att>cert</att> attribute signifies the degree of
editorial confidence felt in the expansion.</p>
<p>This close definition of the use of the <att>resp</att> and
<att>cert</att> attributes with each element is intended to provide for
the most frequent circumstances in which encoders might wish to make
unambiguous statements regarding the responsibility for and certainty of
aspects of their encoding.  The <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes, as so defined, give a convenient mechanism for this.
However, there will be cases where it is desired to state responsibility
for and certainty concerning other aspects of the encoding.  For
example, one may wish in the case of an apparent addition to state the
responsibility for the use of the <gi>add</gi> element, rather than the
responsibility for identifying the hand of the addition.  It may also be
that one editor may make an electronic transcription of another editor's
printed transcription of a manuscript text — here, one will wish to
assign layers of responsibility, so as to allow the reader to determine
exactly what in the final machine-readable transcription was the
responsibility of each editor.  In these complex cases of divided
editorial responsibility for and certainty concerning the content,
attributes and application of a particular element, the more general
mechanisms for representing certainty and responsibility described in
chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> should be used.</p>
<p>The fields of reference of the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes for each element have been chosen to enable what are felt as
the most frequent likely statements an encoder may wish to make
concerning the areas of responsibility and certainty related to that
element.  It is open to each local transcription scheme to vary the use
of the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes on particular
elements where it is felt convenient.  This practice should be
documented in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> element in the file header.
Further, it is recommended that before interchange any such local usage
of these attributes be converted to conformancy with the definitions of
the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes given in these
<title>Guidelines</title>.  Use of the <att>resp</att> and
<att>cert</att> in interchange documents in ways not here defined may
lead to unpredictable results.</p>
<p>It should be noted that the certainty and responsibility mechanisms
described in chapter <ptr target="#CE"/> replicate all the functions of the
<att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes on particular elements.
For example, the encoding of Donaldson's conjectured emendation of
<mentioned>wight</mentioned> to <mentioned>wright</mentioned> in line 117 of Chaucer's
<title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> (see <ptr target="#PHCC"/>) may be
encoded as follows using the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att>
attributes on the <gi>corr</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<choice><sic>wight</sic><corr resp="#ETD" cert="medium">wright</corr></choice></egXML>
Exactly the same information could be conveyed using the certainty
and responsibility mechanisms, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<choice><corr xml:id="c117">wright</corr><sic>wight</sic></choice>
<certainty target="#c117" locus="transcribedContent" degree="0.7"/>
<respons target="#c117" locus="transcribedContent" resp="#ETD"/></egXML>
The choice of which mechanism to use is left to the encoder.  In
transcriptions where only such statements of responsibility and
certainty are made as can be accommodated within the <att>resp</att> and
<att>cert</att> attributes of particular elements, it will be economical
to use the <att>resp</att> and <att>cert</att> attributes of those
elements.  Where many statements of responsibility and certainty are
made which cannot be so accommodated, it may be economical to use the
<gi>respons</gi> and <gi>certainty</gi> elements throughout.</p>
<p>The above discussion supposes that in each case an encoder is able to
specify exactly what it is that one wishes to state responsibility for
and certainty about.  Situations may arise when an encoder wishes to
make a statement concerning certainty or responsibility but is unable or
unwilling to specify so precisely the domain of the certainty or
responsibility.  In these cases, the <gi>note</gi> element may be used
with the <att>type</att> attribute set to <q>cert</q> or <q>resp</q>
and the content of the note giving a prose description of the state of
affairs.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHDA"><head>Damage, Illegibility, and Supplied Text</head>
<p>The <gi>gap</gi> and <gi>supplied</gi> elements described above
(section <ptr target="#PHOM"/>) should be used with appropriate attributes
where the degree of damage or illegibility in a text is such that
nothing can be read and the text must be either omitted or supplied
either conjecturally or from one or more other sources.  In many cases, however,
despite damage or illegibility, the text may yet be read with reasonable
confidence.  In these cases, the following elements should be used:
<specList><specDesc key="damage" atts="type  hand agent degree extent"/><specDesc key="unclear" atts="reason  hand agent"/></specList></p>
<p>The following examples refer to the recto of folio 5 of the unique
manuscript of the Elder Edda.<note place="foot">Codex Regius, ed.  L. F.
A. Wimmer and F. Jónsson (Copenhagen 1891).</note> Here, the
manuscript of <title>Vóluspá</title> has been damaged
through irregular rubbing so that letters in various places are obscured
and in some cases cannot be read at all.  The existence of the damage
may be registered in general for this leaf by use of the <gi>damage</gi>
element.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><damage extent="whole leaf" agent="rubbing"> ... </damage></egXML>
However, in fact the damage crosses structural divisions, so the
<gi>damage</gi> element does not nest properly within the containing
<gi>div</gi> elements.  The simplest method to solve this problem is to
split the element into two fragments, one within each structural
division:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><p>
  <pb n="5r"/>
  <damage agent="rubbing" extent="whole leaf">
  </damage>
</p>
<p>
  <damage agent="rubbing" extent="whole leaf">
  </damage>
  <pb n="5v"/>
</p></egXML>
For other techniques of handling non-nesting information, see chapter
<ptr target="#NH"/>.</p>
<p>In the first line of this leaf, the transcriber may believe that the
last three letters of <mentioned>daga</mentioned> can be read clearly despite
the damage:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">um aldr d<damage>aga</damage> yndisniota</egXML></p>
<p>Alternatively, the letters in question may be only imperfectly
legible on account of the damage; this state of affairs may be indicated
simply by using the <gi>unclear</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">um aldr d<unclear reason="damage">aga</unclear> yndisniota</egXML></p>
<p>If it is desired to supply more information about the kind of
damage, it is also possible to nest an <gi>unclear</gi> element within
the <gi>damage</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">um aldr d<damage agent="rubbing"><unclear>aga</unclear></damage> yndisniota</egXML></p>
<p>Alternatively, the transcriber may not feel able to read the last
three letters of <mentioned>daga</mentioned> but may wish to supply them by
conjecture. Note the use of the <att>source</att> attribute to assign
the conjecture to Finnur Jónsson:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">um aldr d<supplied reason="rubbing" source="FJ">aga</supplied> yndisniota</egXML>
The <gi>supplied</gi> element may if desired be enclosed within a
<gi>damage</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">um aldr d<damage agent="rubbing"><supplied source="FJ">aga</supplied></damage> yndisniota</egXML></p>
<p>Contrast the use of <gi>gap</gi> in the next line, where the
transcriber believes that four letters cannot be read at all because
of the damage:
<eg><![CDATA[&Thorn;ar k&hook-o;mr inn dimmi dreki fliugandi na&thorn;r frann
ne&thorn;an <gap reason="illegible" agent="rubbing" extent="4"/>]]></eg>
As with <gi>supplied</gi>, this <gi>gap</gi> might be enclosed by a
<gi>damage</gi> element.</p>
<p>In these examples, various phenomena of illegibility and conjecture
all result from the one cause, an area of damage to the text — rubbing
at various points — which is not continuous in the text, affecting it
at irregular points.  In these cases, the <gi>join</gi> element may be
used to indicate which tagged features are part of the same physical
phenomenon.  (See chapter <ptr target="#SA"/> for more details.)</p>
<p>The above examples record imperfect legibility due to damage.  When
imperfect legibility is due to some other reason (typically because the
handwriting is ill-formed), the <gi>unclear</gi> element should be used
without any enclosing <gi>damage</gi> element.  In Robert Southey's
autograph of <title>The Life of Cowper</title>,<note place="foot">In
Pierpont Morgan MA 412 (Klinkenborg 15).</note> the final six letters
of <mentioned>attention</mentioned> are difficult to read because of the haste
of the writing, though reasonably certain from the context.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">and from time to time invited in like manner
his att<unclear>ention</unclear></egXML>
The <att>cert</att> attribute on the <gi>unclear</gi> element may be
used to indicate the level of editorial confidence in the reading
contained within it.</p>
<p>The <gi>damage</gi> element is defined formally as follows:
<specGrp xml:id="DPHDA" n="Damage and Illegiblity">
&damage;
</specGrp>
The <gi>unclear</gi> element is defined in section <ptr target="#COED"/>.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHCOMB"><head>Use of the Gap, Del, Damage, Unclear and Supplied Tags in Combination</head>
<p>The <gi>gap</gi>, <gi>damage</gi>, <gi>unclear</gi>,
<gi>supplied</gi>, and <gi>del</gi> elements may be closely allied in
their use.  For example, an area of damage in a primary source might
be encoded with any one of the first four of these elements, depending on
how far the damage has affected the readability of the text.
Further, certain of the elements may nest within one another. The
examples given in the last sections illustrate something of how these
elements are to be distinguished in use.  This may be formulated as
follows:
<list type="bullets">
<item>where the text has been rendered completely illegible by
deletion or damage and no text is supplied by the editor in place of
what is lost: place an empty <gi>gap</gi> element at the point of
deletion or damage.  Use the <att>reason</att> attribute to state the
cause (damage, deletion, etc.) of the loss of text.</item>
<item>where the text has been rendered completely illegible by
deletion or damage and text is supplied by the editor in place of
what is lost: surround the text supplied at the point of deletion or
damage with the <gi>supplied</gi> element.  Use the <att>reason</att>
attribute to state the cause (damage, deletion, etc.) of the loss of
text leading to the need to supply the text.</item>
<item>where the text has been rendered partly illegible by deletion
or damage so that the text can be read but without perfect
confidence: transcribe the text and surround it with the
<gi>unclear</gi> element.  Use the <att>reason</att> attribute to state
the cause (damage, deletion, etc.) of the uncertainty in transcription
and the <att>cert</att> attribute to indicate the confidence in the
transcription.</item>
<item>where there is deletion or damage but the text can be read with
perfect confidence: transcribe the text and surround it with the
<gi>del</gi> element (for deletion) or the <gi>damage</gi> element (for
damage).  Use appropriate attribute values to indicate the cause and
type of deletion or damage.  Observe that the <att>degree</att>
attribute on the <gi>damage</gi> element permits the encoding to show
that a letter, word or phrase is not perfectly preserved, though it
may be read with confidence.</item>
<item>where there is an area of deletion or damage and parts of the
text within that area can be read with perfect confidence, other
parts with less confidence, other parts not at all: in transcription,
surround the whole area  with the <gi>del</gi> element (for deletion; or
the <gi>delSpan</gi> element where it crosses a structural boundary); or
the <gi>damage</gi> element (for damage).  Text within the damaged area
which can be read with perfect confidence needs no further tagging.
Text within the damaged area which can not be read with perfect
confidence may be surrounded with the <gi>unclear</gi> element.  Places
within the damaged area where the text has been rendered completely
illegible and no text is supplied by the editor may be marked with
the <gi>gap</gi> element. For each element, one may use appropriate
attribute values to indicate the cause and type of deletion or damage
and the certainty of the reading.</item></list></p>
<p>The rules for combinations of the <gi>add</gi> and <gi>del</gi>
elements, and for the interpretation of such combinations, are
similar:
<list type="bullets">
<item>if one <gi>add</gi> element (with identifier <ident>ADD1</ident>)
contains another (with identifier <ident>ADD2</ident>), then
the addition <ident>ADD1</ident> was first
made to the text, and later a second addition (<ident>ADD2</ident>) was
made within that added text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">This is the text
<add xml:id="ADD1">with some added
   <add xml:id="ADD2">(interlinear!)</add>
material</add>
as written.</egXML></item>
<item>if one <gi>del</gi> element (with identifier <ident>DEL1</ident>)
contains another (with identifier <ident>DEL2</ident>), then
the deletion <ident>DEL2</ident> was first
made, and later a second deletion (<ident>DEL1</ident>)
removed the entire passage:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del n="DEL1">This sentence contains
some <del n="DEL2">redundant</del> unnecessary
verbiage.</del></egXML></item>
<item>if a <gi>del</gi> element contains an <gi>add</gi> element, the normal
interpretation will be that an addition was made within a passage
which was later
deleted in its entirety:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><del>This sentence was deleted
<add>originally</add> from the text.</del></egXML></item>
<item>if an <gi>add</gi> element contains a <gi>del</gi> element, the
normal interpretation will be that a
deletion was made from  a passage which had earlier been added:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><add>This sentence was added
<del>eventually</del> to the text.</add></egXML></item>
</list></p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHSP"><head>Space</head>
<p>The presence of significant space in the text being transcribed may
be indicated by the <gi>space</gi> element.  The author or scribe may
have left space for a word, or for an initial capital, and for some
reason the word or capital was never supplied and the space left empty.
This element should not be used to mark normal inter-word space or the
like.
<specList><specDesc key="space" atts="resp"/></specList></p>
<p>In line 694 of Chaucer's <title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> in
the Holkham manuscript the scribe has left a space for a word where
other manuscripts read <mentioned>preestes</mentioned>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">By god if wommen had writen storyes
As <space quantity="7" unit="char"/> han within her oratoryes</egXML>
The <gi>supplied</gi> element discussed in the previous section may be
used to supply the text presumed missing:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">By god if wommen had writen storyes
As <supplied reason="space" resp="#ES" source="Hg">preestes</supplied>
han within her oratoryes</egXML>
Here, the fact of the space within the manuscript is indicated by the
value of the <att>reason</att> attribute.  The source of the supplied
text is shown by the value of the <att>source</att> attribute as the
Hengwrt manuscript; the transcriber responsible for supplying the text
is ES.
The <gi>space</gi> element is formally defined thus:
<specGrp xml:id="DPHSP" n="Spaces in the source">
&space;
</specGrp>	</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="PHLN"><head>Lines</head>
<p>The most common form of marking of text in manuscripts is by lines
written under, beside or through the text.  The lines themselves may be
of various types:  they may be solid, dashed or dotted, doubled or
tripled, wavy or straight, or a combination of these and other
renderings.  The line may be used for emphasis, or to mark a foreign or
technical term, or to signal a quotation or a title, etc.:  the elements
<gi>emph</gi>, <gi>foreign</gi>, <gi>term</gi>, <gi>mentioned</gi>,
<gi>title</gi> may be used for these.  Frequently, a scholar may judge
that a line is used to delete text:  the <gi>del</gi> element is
available to indicate this.  In all these cases, the <att>rend</att>
attribute may be used on these or other elements to indicate that the
text is marked by a line and the style of the line.  Thus, Lawrence's
deletion by strike-through of <mentioned>my</mentioned> in the autograph of
<title>Eloi, Eloi, lama sabachthani</title> is noted:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">For I hate this
<del rend="strikethrough" hand="#dhl">my</del> body,
which is so dear to me</egXML></p>
<p>There will be instances, however, where a scholar wishes only to
register the occurrence of lines in the text, without making any
judgement as to what the lines signify.  In these the <gi>hi</gi>
element may be used, with the <att>rend</att> attribute to mark the
style of line.  In the manuscript of a letter by Robert Browning to
George Moulton-Barrett,<note place="foot">Pierpont Morgan MA 310, Klinkenborg 23</note> the
underlining of the phrase <mentioned>had obtained all the letters to Mr Boyd</mentioned>
may be marked-up as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I have once — by declaring I would prosecute
by law — hindered a man's proceedings who
<hi rend="underline">had obtained all the letters
to Mr Boyd</hi></egXML></p>
<p>The above examples presume the common case where a single word or
phrase is marked by a line, with no doubt as to where the marking begins
or ends and with no overlapping of the area of text with other marked
areas of text.  Where there is doubt, the <gi>certainty</gi> element may
be used to record the doubt.  In the Browning example cited above the
underlining actually begins half-way under <mentioned>who</mentioned>, and this
uncertainty could be remarked as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">I have once — by declaring I would prosecute
by law — hindered a man's proceedings who
<hi xml:id="cstart1" rend="underline">had obtained all
the letters to Mr Boyd</hi>
<!-- ... -->
<certainty target="#cstart1" locus="startLoc" degree="0.70">
<desc>may begin with previous word</desc>
</certainty></egXML></p>
<p>Where the area of text marked overlaps other areas of text, for
example crossing a structural division, one of the span mechanisms
outlined in these Guidelines may be used.  Where the line is thought to
mark a deletion, the <gi>delSpan</gi> element may be used.  Where it is
desired simply to record the marking of a span of text in circumstances
where it is not possible to surround the text with a <gi>hi</gi>
element, the <gi>span</gi> element may be used with the <att>rend</att>
attribute indicating the style of line-marking.</p>
<p>More work needs to be done on clarifying the treatment of other
textual features marked by lines which might so overlap or nest.  For
example, in many Middle English manuscripts (e.g. the Jesus and Digby
verse collections) marginal sidebars may indicate metrical structure:
couplets may be linked in pairs, with the pairs themselves linked
into stanzas. Or, marginal sidebars may indicate emphasis, or may
point out a region of text on which there is some annotation: in many
manuscripts of Chaucer's <title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> lines
655–8 are marked with nesting parentheses against which the scribe
has written <mentioned>nota</mentioned>.</p>
<p>At the lowest level, all such features could be captured by use of
the <gi>note</gi> element, containing a prose description of the
manuscript at this point.  It is not yet clear how best to mark up such
phenomena so as to
obtain more usefully structured encodings.  For example,
in the Chaucer example just cited, one may wish to record that the
<mentioned>nota</mentioned> is written in the Hengwrt manuscript in the right
margin against a single large left parenthesis bracketing the four
lines, with two right parentheses in the right margin bracketing two
overlapping pairs of lines:  the first and third, the second and fourth.
The <gi>note</gi> element allows us to record that the scribe wrote
<mentioned>nota</mentioned>, but is not well-adapted to show that the
<mentioned>nota</mentioned> points both at all four lines and at two pairs of
lines within the four lines.  </p></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="PHSK"><head>Headers, Footers, and Similar Matter</head>
<p>As a rule, matter associated with the page break (signature,
catchword, page number) should be drawn into the <gi>pb</gi> element
as attributes:  see section <ptr target="#CORS"/>.  In text-critical
situations where these elements need tagging in their own right (for
instance, when the catch-word presents a variant reading, or spacing
in the header or footer is significant for compositor identification),
the element <gi>fw</gi> may be used:
<specList><specDesc key="fw"/></specList>
The name <mentioned>fw</mentioned> is short for <q>forme work</q>. It
may be used  to encode any of
the unchanging portions of a page forme, such as:
<list type="bullets">
<item>running heads (whether repeated on every page, or changing on
every page)</item>
<item>running footers</item>
<item>page numbers</item>
<item>catch-words</item>
<item>other material repeated from page to page, which falls outside the
stream of the text</item></list>
It should not be used for marginal glosses, annotations, or textual
variants, which should be tagged using <gi>gloss</gi>, <gi>note</gi>, or
the text-critical tags described in chapter <ptr target="#TC"/>,
respectively.</p>
<p>For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><fw type="head" place="top-centre">Poëms.</fw>
<fw type="pageNum" place="top-right">29</fw>
<fw type="sig" place="bot-centre">E3</fw>
<fw type="catch" place="bot-right">TEMPLE</fw></egXML>
<!-- Donne, Poems 1633, p. 29 -->
	<!-- [Need several examples, all fuller than this one.     -->
	<!-- Take from DOSL materials? -MSM]                          --></p>
<p>The formal declaration for the <gi>fw</gi> element is
this:
<specGrp xml:id="DTCHD" n="Headers and footers">
&fw;
</specGrp></p></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="PHTRXX"><head>Other Primary Source Features not Covered in These Guidelines</head>
<p>We repeat the advice given at the beginning of this chapter, that
these recommendations are not intended to meet every transcriptional
circumstance ever likely to be faced by any scholar.  They are intended
rather as a base to enable encoding of the most common phenomena found
in the course of scholarly transcription of primary source materials.
These guidelines particularly do not address the encoding of physical
description of textual witnesses:  the materials of the carrier, the
medium of the inscribing implement, the layout of the inscription upon
the material, the organisation of the carrier materials themselves (as
quiring, collation, etc.), authorial instructions or scribal markup,
etc.  Some of these issues may be covered in future editions of these
guidelines.</p></div></div>
