<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xml:id="PREFS"><head>Prefatory Notes</head>
<p>This Appendix contains (in reverse chronological
order) the <soCalled>Introductory Notes</soCalled> prefixed to each 
revision of the TEI Guidelines since its first publication in 1994. 
</p>

<div xml:id="p4pf02"><head>Prefatory Note (March 2002)</head>
<p>The primary goal of this revision has been to make available a new
and corrected version of the TEI Guidelines which:
<list type="simple">
<item>is expressed in XML and conforms to a TEI-conformant XML
       DTD;</item>
<item>generates a set of DTD fragments that can be combined
       together to form either SGML or XML document type
       definitions;</item>
	  <item>corrects blatant errors, typographical mishaps, and other
		egregious editorial oversights;</item>
<item>can be processed and maintained using readily available XML
       tools instead of the special-purpose ad hoc software originally
       used for TEI P3.</item>
</list>
</p>
<p>A second major design goal of this revision has been to ensure that the
      DTD fragments generated would not break existing documents: in
      other words, that any document conforming to the original TEI P3
      SGML DTD would also conform to the new XML version of
      it. Although full backwards compatibility cannot be guaranteed,
      we believe our implementation is consistent with that goal.
      </p>
<p>In most respects, the TEI Guidelines have stood the test of time remarkably
well. The present edition makes no substantial attempt to rewrite those few parts
of them which have now been rendered obsolete by changes since their
first publication, though an indication is given in the text of where such rewriting is
now considered necessary. Neither does the present version attempt to
address any of the many possible new areas of digital activity in which
the TEI approach to standardization may have something to offer. Both
these tasks require the existence of an informed and active TEI
Council to direct and validate such extension and maintenance work,
in response to the changing needs and priorities of the TEI user community. 
</p>
<p>Two exceptions to the above principles may be cited: firstly, the
chapter which originally provided a <soCalled>Gentle
Introduction</soCalled> to SGML has been completely rewritten to
provide a similarly gentle introduction to XML; secondly the chapter
on character sets has been completely revised in light of the
close connexion between Unicode and XML. The editors gratefully
acknowledge the assistance of the <foreign>ad hoc</foreign> workgroup chaired by Christian
Wittern, which undertook to provide expert advice and correction at
very short notice, in the latter task.</p>
<p>The preparation of this new version relied extensively on
preliminary work carried out by the former North American editor of
the TEI Guidelines, C.M. Sperberg-McQueen. In a TEI working paper
written in 1999<note place="bottom"><title>TEI ED W69</title>, available
from the TEI web site at <ptr target="http://www.tei-c.org/Vault/ED/edw69.htm"/>.</note> he sketched
out a precise blueprint for the conversion of the TEI from SGML to
XML, which we have implemented, with only slight modification.</p>
<p>The Editors would also like to express thanks to the
team of volunteers from the TEI community who helped us with the task
of proofreading the first draft during the summer of 2001; and to 
      Sebastian Rahtz of Oxford University Computing Services, without
      whose skill and enthusiasm this new edition would not have been
      possible.
</p>
<p>A substantial proportion of the work of preparing this new edition was
funded with the assistance of a grant from the US National
Endowment for the Humanities, whose continued support of the TEI has
also been crucial to the effort of setting up the TEI Consortium.
</p>
<p>Finally, we would like to thank all our colleagues on the interim
management board of the TEI Consortium, in particular its Chairman
John Unsworth, for their continued support of
the TEI's work, and their willingness to devote effort to the
difficult task of overseeing its transition to a new organizational
infrastructure.</p>
<p>Summary details of the changes made in the present and previous
editions are given in their Prefatory Notes, all of which are now
reproduced in an Appendix to the present edition: see <ptr target="#PREFS"/>.
</p>
<signed>Lou Burnard and Syd Bauman (TEI Editors)
Oxford and Providence, March 2002.</signed>
</div>



<div xml:id="p4pf01"><head>Introductory Note (November 2001)</head>
<p>To complete the work started in June of this year, the TEI Editors
asked for volunteers from the TEI community to proofread the preliminary XML
version. 24 volunteers responded to this call during August, and gave invaluable help both by identifying
a number of previously un-noticed errors, and by suggesting areas in
which more substantial revision should be undertaken in the
future. The Editors gratefully acknowledge the assistance of the following
individuals during this exercise:
</p>
<p rend="display">
Jimmy Adair,
Syd Bauman,
Michael Beddow,
Steven Bird,
Lisa Charlong, 
Matthew Driscoll,
Patrick Durusau,
Tomaz Erjavec,
Nick Finke,
Tim Finney,
Julia Flanders,
Mike Fraser,
Pankaj Kamthan,
François Lachance,
Terry Langendoen,
Anne Mahoney,
Gregory Murphy,
Daniel Pitti,
Rafal Prinke,
Laurent Romary,
Stewart Russell,
Gary Simons,
Elisabeth Solopova,
Christian Wittern, 
Martin Wynne.
</p>
<p>In addition to error correction, and clear delineation of those sections in
which substantial revision is yet to be undertaken for TEI P5, the
present draft differs from earlier ones in the following respects:
<list type="simple">
<item>Formal Public Identifiers have been introduced as a means of
constructing TEI DTDs and an SGML Open Catalog is now included with the
standard release; </item>
<item>Some systematic errors and omissions in the reference section
have been removed; the format of this  section  has been substantially changed, we
hope for the better;</item>
<item>The chapters on obtaining the TEI DTDs and WSDs have been
brought up to date; the chapter on modification has been expanded to
include a discussion of the TEI Lite customization;</item>
<item>All examples and cited markup has been checked for XML validity
against the published DTDs, and corrected where faulty; examples have
been formatted in a (more or less) consistent style.</item>
</list>
</p>
<signed>Lou Burnard and Syd Bauman (Editors)</signed>
<signed>Oxford and Providence, November 2001.</signed>
</div>
<div xml:id="PPF2"><head>Introductory Note (June 2001)</head>
<p>This is a preliminary version of a revised and fully XML-compliant
edition of the TEI Guidelines. Although work on revising and
correcting the text of the document is incomplete, by making
available this preliminary version we hope to facilitate testing of
the XML document type declarations which it describes by as wide a
range of TEI users as possible. </p>
<p>The primary goal of this revision is to make available the
corrected (May 1999) edition of the Guidelines in a new version which:
<list type="simple">
<item>is expressed  in XML and itself conforms to a TEI-conformant XML
       DTD;</item>
<item>generates a set of XML DTD fragments that can be combined
       together in the same way as the existing TEI (P3) SGML DTD
       fragments to form true TEI XML DTD fragments without loss of functionality;</item>
<item>can be processed and maintained using readily available XML
       tools instead of the special-purpose ad hoc software originally
       used for TEI P3.</item>
</list>
As noted elsewhere, a number of errors were corrected in
the May 1999 edition. A (much) smaller number of errors have also been
corrected in this edition, but no new material has been added. We
expect the expansion and modification of the Guidelines to become
a real possibility in the context of the newly formed TEI Consortium,
which has funded the preparation of this present edition.</p>
<p>A major design goal of both this and the previous revision has been
      to ensure that the DTD fragments generated would not break
      existing documents: in other words, that any document conforming
      to the original TEI P3 SGML DTD would also conform to the new
      XML version of it. Although full backwards compatibility cannot
     be guaranteed, we believe our implementation is consistent with
      that goal.  </p>
<p>In making this new version, we relied extensively on preliminary
      work carried out by the outgoing North American editor of the
      TEI Guidelines, Michael Sperberg-McQueen. In a TEI working paper
      written in 1999, TEI ED
      W69, Michael sketched out a precise blueprint for the
      conversion of the TEI from SGML to XML, which we have
      implemented, with only slight modification. The current TEI
      editors wish to express here our admiration for the detailed
      care put into that paper, without which our task would have been
      forbiddingly difficult, if not impossible. We would also like to
      express our thanks to Sebastian Rahtz of Oxford University
      Computing Services, for his invaluable assistance in preparing
      this new edition.</p>
<p>We list here in summary form all the changes made in the present
edition. Full technical details are provided in documents TEI EDW69
and TEI EDW70, available from the TEI web site. 
<list type="ordered">
<item>A new keyword <ident type="pe">TEI.XML</ident> has been added. By setting
its value to <val>INCLUDE</val>, rather than the default <val>IGNORE</val>,
the user can request generation of an XML rather than an SGML DTD;</item>
<item>The content models of all elements have been checked, and, where
necessary, changed so that they are equally valid as SGML or as
XML; </item>
<item>The declared value for all attributes has been changed to a form
which is equally valid as SGML or as XML;</item>
<item>All the examples have been checked for conformance and converted to
use XML syntax, where possible. (This process is currently incomplete.)</item>
<item>Some errors and duplications in the class
membership of elements from the names and dates tagsets have been corrected. </item></list></p>
<p>To implement the first of these, we have parameterized the
<term>tag omissibility</term> indicators <q>- o</q> and <q>- -</q>
used within element declarations in the DTD. When XML is to be
generated, the parameter entities concerned are redeclared with the null
string as their value. </p>
<p>The second change was achieved by removing SGML-specific features
(ampersand connectors, inclusion and exclusion exceptions, various
types of attribute content) from the DTD and revising the syntax of
the DTD to conform to XML requirements (specifically in the
representation of mixed-content models, and by removing redundant
parentheses). In making these changes, we took care to ensure that the
resulting content model would continue to accept existing valid
documents, though in the nature of things it could not be guaranteed
to reject the same set of documents. As further discussed in EDW69 and
EDW70, some constraints (exclusion exceptions, for example) which
could be carried out by a generic SGML parser using TEI P3 will have
to be implemented by a special purpose TEI validator using TEI
P4. </p>
<p>Much work remains to be done, firstly in testing the new DTD
fragments against as wide a range of TEI materials as possible,
secondly in revising the discussion of markup theory and practice
within the text to reflect current thinking. A few sections of the
current text (the Gentle Introduction to SGML and the discussion of
Extended Pointer syntax are two examples) will need substantial
rewriting. For the most part, however, we think the Guidelines have
stood the test of time well and can be recommended to a new generation of
text encoders scarcely born at the time they were first formulated.
</p>
<p>Lou Burnard and Steve De Rose (Editors)</p>
<p>Oxford and Providence, May 2001.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="ppf">
<head>Introductory Note (May 1999)</head>
<p>No work of the size and complexity of the TEI
<title>Guidelines</title> could reasonably be expected to be error-free on
publication, nor to remain long uncorrected. It has however taken rather longer
than might have been anticipated to complete production of the present
corrected reprint of the first edition, for which we present our apologies,
both to the many individuals and institutions whose enthusiastic adoption and
promotion of the TEI encoding scheme have ensured its continued survival in the
rapidly changing world of digital scholarship, and also to the many helpfully
critical users whose assiduous uncovering and reporting of our errors have made
possible the present revision. </p>
<p>At its first meeting in Bergen, in June 1996, the TEI Technical Review
Committee (TRC) approved the setting up of a small working committee to oversee the
production of a revised edition of the TEI
<title>Guidelines</title>, to include corrections of as many as possible of the
`corrigible errors' notified to the editors since publication
of the first edition in May 1994, the bulk of which are summarized in a TEI
working paper (TEI EDW67, available from the TEI web site). </p>
<p>During the spring of 1997, this TRC Core Subcommittee reviewed nearly 200
comments and proposals which the editors had collected from public debate and
discussion over the preceding two years, and provided invaluable technical
guidance in disposition of them. We are glad to take this opportunity of
expressing our thanks to this subcommittee, whose members were Elli Mylonas,
Dominic Dunlop, and David T. Barnard. </p>
<p>The work of making the corrections and regenerating the text proceeded
  rather fitfully during 1998 and 1999, largely because of increasing demands on
  the editors' time from their other responsibilities. With the
  establishment of the new TEI Consortium, it is be hoped that maintenance of the
  Guidelines will be placed on a more secure footing. Some specific areas in which we
  anticipate future revisions being carried out are listed below. </p>
<div xml:id="ppf-tcm">
<head>Typographic corrections made</head>
<list type="simple">
  <item>examples of TEI markup throughout the text were all checked against the
	 relevant DTD fragment and an embarassingly large number of tagging errors
	 corrected;</item>
  <item>various minor typographic and spelling errors were corrected;</item>
  <item>the <soCalled>corrigible errors</soCalled> listed in working paper TEI EDW67 were all
	 corrected: some of these required specific changes to the DTD which are listed
	 in the next section.</item>
</list>
</div>
<div xml:id="ppf-spc">
<head>Specific changes in the DTD</head>
<p>A major goal of this revision was to avoid changes which might invalidate
  existing data, even where existing constructs seemed erroneous in retrospect.
  To that end, wherever changes have been made in content models for existing
  elements, they have as far as possible been made so that the DTD will now
  accept a superset of what was previously legal. Only one new element
  (<gi>ab</gi>) has been added.</p>
<p>Where possible, a few content models have been changed in such a way as to
  facilitate conversion to XML, but XML compatibility is
  <emph>not</emph> a goal
  of this revision.</p>
<p>Brief details of all changes made in the DTD follow:
<list type="simple">
  <item>Several changes were made in class membership, in order to correct
	 unreachability problems. Specifically:
	 <list type="simple">
		<item>elements <gi>geogName</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>,
		  <gi>placeName</gi> were added to the <ident type="class">m.data</ident> class; </item>
		<item><gi>geogName</gi> and <gi>placeName</gi> were removed from the
		  <ident type="class">m.placepart</ident> class;</item>
		<item>the elements <gi>addSpan</gi>, <gi>delSpan</gi>, <gi>gap</gi>, were
		  added to the <ident type="class">m.Edit</ident> class; </item>
		<item>a new class <ident type="class">m.editIncl</ident> was defined, with members
		  <gi>addSpan</gi>, <gi>delSpan</gi>, and <gi>gap</gi>; this class was then added
		  to the global inclusion class
<ident type="class">m.globIncl</ident> along with
		  <gi>anchor</gi> (erroneously a member of the
<ident type="class">m.Seg</ident>  class, from
		  which it is now removed), <ident type="class">m.metadata</ident> and <ident type="class">m.refsys</ident>;
		  </item>
	 </list></item>
  <item>added <gi>name</gi> element to <ident type="class">m.addrPart</ident> class;</item>
  <item>added <gi>dateline</gi> to <ident type="class">m.divtop</ident> and 
     <ident type="class">m.divbot</ident> classes;</item>
  <item>added <gi>epilogue</gi> and <gi>castList</gi> to
     <ident type="class">m.dramafront</ident> class;</item>
  <item>added <gi>divGen</gi> to <ident type="class">m.front</ident> class;</item>
  <item>added <gi>dateline</gi> to <ident type="class">m.divtop</ident> and
	 <ident type="class">m.divtop</ident> classes;</item>
  <item>added <gi>u</gi> element to <ident type="class">a.declaring</ident> class;</item>
  <item>defined new class <ident type="class">m.fmchunk</ident> (front matter chunk),
	 comprising <gi>argument</gi>, <gi>byline</gi>, <gi>docAuthor</gi>,
	 <gi>docDate</gi>, <gi>docEdition</gi>, <gi>docImprint</gi>, <gi>docTitle</gi>,
	 <gi>epigraph</gi>, <gi>head</gi>, and <gi>titlePart</gi> for use in
	 simplification of the content model for <gi>front</gi> element;</item>
  <item>defined new element <gi>ab</gi> (anonymous block), and added it to the
	 <ident type="class">m.chunk</ident> class;</item>
  <item>corrected an error whereby global attributes were not properly defined
	 for elements specifying a non-default value for any of the
	 <ident type="class">a.global</ident> attributes: elements affected include: <gi>foreign</gi>,
	 <gi>hi</gi>, <gi>del</gi>, <gi>pb</gi>, <gi>lb</gi>, <gi>cb</gi>,
	 <gi>language</gi>, <gi>anchor</gi>, and <gi>when</gi>;</item>
  <item>changed content models to permit empty <gi>list</gi> and empty
	 <gi>availability</gi> elements;</item>
  <item>changed content model for <gi>series</gi> element to permit #PCDATA;
  </item>
  <item>changed content model for <gi>setting</gi> element to permit
	 <gi>date</gi> element as a direct child; </item>
  <item>added a <att>key</att> attribute to the <gi>distance</gi> element,
	 for consistency with other elements in its class;</item>
  <item>changed content model for <gi>orgName</gi> element to make it more
	 consistent with e.g. <gi>persName</gi>;</item>
  <item>changed content model for <gi>opener</gi> element to include
	 <gi>argument</gi>, <gi>byline</gi>, and <gi>epigraph</gi>;</item>
  <item>changed content models for <gi>app</gi>, <gi>rdgGrp</gi>, and
	 <gi>wit</gi> elements;</item>
  <item>revised attributes on <gi>hand</gi> element.</item></list></p>
<p>A number of content models were changed with a view to
easing the creation of an XML compatible version of the
Guidelines. Specifically:
<list type="simple"><item> removed ampersand connectors from  <gi>cit</gi>,
<gi>respStmt</gi>, <gi>publicationStmt</gi>, and <gi>graph</gi>;</item>
<item>changed the mixed content models for <gi>sense</gi>, <gi>re</gi>, <gi>persName</gi>,
<gi>placeName</gi>, <gi>geogName</gi>, <gi>dateStruct</gi>, <gi>timeStruct</gi>, and <gi>dateline</gi>
to make them XML-conformant.</item></list>
</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="ppf-err">
<head>Outstanding errors</head>
<p>A small number of other known problems remain uncorrected in this version
  and are briefly listed below. Please watch the TEI mailing list for
  announcements of their correction.</p>
<list type="simple">
<item>elements of class <ident type="class">inter</ident> don't always behave
        as they should (e.g. one cannot insert a <gi>table</gi> before
        anything else in a <gi>div</gi>);
  </item>
  <item>some mixed-content problems consequent on the definition of
         <ident type="macro">macro.specialPara</ident> need to be addressed systematically;
         in particular, the treatment of list items or notes which contain
         several paragraphs continues to surprise many users:  no 
         whitespace is allowed between the paragraphs;</item>
  <item>the <att>resp</att> attributes on editorial elements are not
         consistently defined; </item>
  <item>the discussions of DTD invocation, and the DTD itself, all use
        system identifiers instead of formal public identifiers.</item>
</list>
<p>Our next priority however will be the production of a fully XML-compliant version
  of the TEI DTD, work on which is already well advanced.</p>
<signed>C.M. Sperberg McQueen and Lou Burnard, May 1999</signed>
</div>
</div>
<div xml:id="PF"><head>Preface (April 1994)</head>
<p>These Guidelines are the result of over five years' effort by
members of the research and academic community within the
framework of an international cooperative project called the Text
Encoding Initiative (TEI), established in 1987 under the joint
sponsorship of the Association for Computers and the Humanities,
the Association for Computational Linguistics, and the Association
for Literary and Linguistic Computing.
 </p>
<p>The impetus for the project came from the humanities computing
community, which sought a common encoding scheme for complex textual
structures in order to reduce the diversity of existing encoding
practices, simplify processing by machine, and encourage the sharing of
electronic texts. It soon became apparent that a sufficiently flexible
scheme could provide solutions for text encoding problems generally. The
scope of the TEI was therefore broadened to meet the varied encoding
requirements of any discipline or application. Thus, the TEI became the
only systematized attempt to develop a fully general text encoding model
and set of encoding conventions based upon it, suitable for processing
and analysis of any type of text, in any language, and intended to serve
the increasing range of existing (and potential) applications and use.
 </p>
<p>What is published here is a major milestone in this effort. It
provides a single, coherent framework for all kinds of text encoding
which is hardware-, software- and application-independent. Within this
framework, it specifies encoding conventions for a number of key text
types and features. The ongoing work of the TEI is to extend the
scheme presented here to cover additional text types and features, as
well as to continue to refine its encoding recommendations on the
basis of extensive experience with their actual application and use.
 </p>
<p>We therefore offer these Guidelines to the user community for use in
the same spirit of active collaboration and cooperation with which
they have so far been developed. The TEI is committed to actively
supporting the wide-spread and large-scale use of the Guidelines
which, with the publication of this volume, is now for the first time
possible. In addition, we anticipate that users of the TEI Guidelines
will in some instances adapt and extend them as necessary to suit
particular needs; we invite such users to engage in the further
development of the Guidelines by working with us as they do so.
 </p>
<p>Like any standard which is actually used, these Guidelines do not
represent a static finished work, but rather one which will evolve
over time with the active involvement of its community of users. We
invite and encourage the participation of the user community in
this process, in order to ensure that the TEI Guidelines become and
remain useful in all sorts of work with machine-readable texts.
 </p>
<p>This document was made possible in part by financial support from
the U.S. National Endowment for the Humanities, an independent federal
agency; Directorate General XIII of the Commission of the European
Communities; the Andrew W. Mellon Foundation; and the Social Science
and Humanities Research Council of Canada.  Direct and indirect
support has also been received from the University of Illinois at
Chicago, the Oxford University Computing Services, the University of
Arizona, the University of Oslo and Queen's University (Kingston,
Ont.), Bellcore (Bell Communications Research), the Istituto di
Linguistica Computazionale (C.N.R.) Pisa, the British Academy, and
Ohio State University, as well as the employers and host institutions
of the members of the TEI working committees and work groups listed in
the acknowledgments.
 </p>
<p>The production of this document has been greatly facilitated by the
willingness of many software vendors to provide us with evaluation
versions of their products. Most parts of this text have been processed
at some time by almost every currently available SGML-aware software
system. In particular, we gratefully acknowledge the
assistance of the following vendors:
<list type="simple">
<item>Berger-Levrault AIS s.a. (for Balise);</item>
<item>E2S n.v. (for E2S Advanced SGML Editor);</item>
<item>Electronic Book Technology (for DynaText);</item>
<item>SEMA Group and Yard Software (for Mark-It and Write-It);</item>
<item>Software Exoterica (for CheckMark and Xtran);</item>
<item>SoftQuad, Inc., (for Author/Editor and RulesBuilder);</item>
<item>Xerox Corporation (for Ventura Publisher).</item></list>
 </p>
<p>Details of the software actually used to produce the current document
are given in the colophon at the end of the work.</p>
</div>
<div xml:id="WG"><head>Acknowledgments</head>
<p>Many people have given of their time, energy, expertise, and support
in the creation of this document; it is unfortunately not possible to
thank them all adequately.  Below are listed those who have served as
formal members of the TEI's Work Groups and Working Committees during
its six-year history; others not so officially enfranchised also
contributed much to the quality of the result.</p>
<p>The editors take this opportunity to acknowledge our debt to those
who have patiently endured and corrected our misunderstandings of their
work; we hope that they will feel the wait has not been in vain.  For
any errors and inconsistencies remaining, we must accept responsibility;
any virtue in what is here presented, we gladly ascribe to the energies
of the keen intellects listed below.</p>
<p>C. M. Sperberg McQueen and Lou Burnard</p>
<div xml:id="WGWC"><head>TEI Working Committees (1990-1993)</head><note place="inline">Not all members listed were able to serve throughout the development
of the Guidelines.</note>
<list type="gloss"><label>Committee on Text Documentation:</label>
<item>
<p>Chair:  Dominik Wujastyk (Wellcome Institute for the History of
Medicine)</p>
<p>Members 1990–1992:  J. D. Byrum (Library of Congress);
Marianne Gaunt (Rutgers University);
Richard Giordano (Manchester University);
Barbara Ann Kipfer (Independent Consultant);
Hans Jørgen Marker (Danish Data Archive, Odense);
Marcia Taylor (University of Essex);</p></item><label>Committee on Text Representation</label>
<item>
<p>Chair:  Stig Johansson (University of Oslo)</p>
<p>Members 1990–1992:  Roberto Cencioni (Commission of the European
Communities);
David R. Chesnutt (University of South Carolina);
Robin C. Cover (Dallas Theological Seminary);
Steven J. DeRose (Electronic Book Technology Inc);
David G. Durand (Boston University);
Susan M. Hockey (Oxford University Computing Service);
Claus Huitfeldt (University of Bergen);
Francisco Marcos-Marin (University Madrid);
Elli Mylonas (Harvard University);
Wilhelm Ott (University of Tübingen);
Allen H. Renear (Brown University);
Manfred Thaller (Max-Planck-Institut für Geschichte,
Göttingen)</p></item><label>Committee on Text Analysis and Interpretation</label>
<item>
<p>Chair:  D. Terence Langendoen (University of Arizona)</p>
<p>Members 1990–1992:
Robert Amsler (Bell Communications Research);
Stephen Anderson (Johns Hopkins University);
Branimir Boguraev (IBM T. J. Watson Research Center);
Nicoletta Calzolari (University of Pisa);
Robert Ingria (Bolt Beranek Newman Inc);
Winfried Lenders (University of Bonn);
Mitch Marcus (University of Pennsylvania);
Nelleke Oostdijk (University of Nijmegen);
William Poser (Stanford University);
Beatrice Santorini (University of Pennsylvania);
Gary Simons (Summer Institute of Linguistics);
Antonio Zampolli, University of Pisa.</p></item><label>Committee on Metalanguage and Syntax</label>
<item>
<p>Chair:  David T. Barnard (Queen's University)</p>
<p>Members 1990–1994: David G. Durand (Boston University);
Jean-Pierre Gaspart (Associated Consultants and
Software Engineers sa/nv);
Nancy M. Ide (Vassar College);
Lynne A. Price (Software Exoterica / Xerox PARC);
Frank Tompa (University of Waterloo);
Giovanni Battista Varile (Commission of the European Communities).</p></item></list>
<p>In addition, the two TEI editors served ex officio on each
committee.</p>
<p>Following publication of the first draft of the TEI Guidelines (P1)
in November 1990, a number of specialist work groups were charged with
responsibility for drafting revisions and extensions, which, together
with material already presented in P1, constitute the basis of the
present work.</p>
<p>In addition, many members of the work groups listed below met on
three occasions to review the emerging proposals in detail at
technical review meetings convened by the TEI Steering Committee.
These meetings, held in Myrdal, Norway (November 1991), Chicago (May
1992) and Oxford (May 1993), were largely responsible for the
technical content and organization of the present work.  Attendants at
these meetings are starred in the list below.
<list type="gloss"><label>TR1 Character sets</label>
<item>Chair:  Harry Gaylord* (University of Groningen);
Syun Tutiya* (Chiba University).</item><label>TR2 Text criticism</label>
<item>Chair:  Peter Robinson* (Oxford University);
David Chesnutt* (University of South Carolina);
Robin Cover* (Dallas Theological Seminary);
Robert Kraft (University of Pennsylvania);
Peter Shillingsburg (Mississippi State University).</item><label>TR3 Hypertext and hypermedia</label>
<item>Chair:  Steven J. DeRose* (Electronic Book Technologies Inc);
David Durand (Boston University);
Edward A. Fox (Virginia State University); Eve Wilson (University of
Kent).</item><label>TR4 Formulæ, Tables, figures, and graphics</label>
<item>Chair:  Paul Ellison* (University of Exeter);
Anders Berglund (Independent Consultant); Dale Waldt (Thompson
Professional Publishing).</item><label>TR6 Language corpora</label>
<item>Chair:  Douglas Biber* (University of Northern Arizona);
Jeremy Clear (Birmingham University);
Gunnel Engwall (University of Stockholm).</item><label>TR9 Manuscripts and codicology</label>
<item>Chair:  Claus Huitfeldt* (University of Bergen);
Dino Buzzetti (University of Bologna);
Jacqueline Hamesse (University of Louvain);
Mary Keeler (Georgetown University);
Christian Kloesel (Indiana University);
Allen Renear* (Brown University);
Donald Spaeth (Glasgow University).</item><label>TR10 Verse</label>
<item>Chair:  David Robey* (University of Manchester);
Elaine Brennan* (Brown University);
David Chisholm (University of Arizona);
Willard McCarty (University of Toronto).</item><label>TR11 Drama and performance texts</label>
<item>Chair:  Elli Mylonas* (Harvard University);
John Lavagnino* (Brandeis University);
Rosanne Potter (University of Iowa).</item><label>TR12 Literary prose</label>
<item>Chair Thomas N. Corns* (University of Wales);
Christian Delcourt (University of Liège).
	</item><label>AI1 Linguistic description</label>
<item>Chair:  D. Terence Langendoen* (University of Arizona);
Stephen R. Anderson (Johns Hopkins University);
Nicoletta Calzolari (University of Pisa);
Geoffrey Sampson* (University of Sussex);
Gary Simons* (Summer Institute of Linguistics).</item><label>AI2 Spoken text</label>
<item>Chair: Stig Johansson* (University of Oslo);
Jane Edwards (University of California at Berkeley);
Andrew Rosta (University College London).</item><label>AI3 Literary studies</label>
<item>Chair: Paul Fortier* (University of Manitoba);
Christian Delcourt  (University of Liège;);
Ian Lancashire  (University of Toronto);
Rosanne Potter (University of Iowa);
David Robey* (University of Manchester).</item>
<label>AI4 Historical studies</label>
<item>Chair: Daniel Greenstein* (University of Glasgow);
Peter Denley (Queen Mary Westfield College, London);
Ingo Kropac (University of Graz);
Hans Jørgen Marker (Danish Data Archive, Odense);
Jan Oldervoll (University of Tromsø);
Kevin Schurer (University of Cambridge);
Donald Spaeth (Glasgow University);
Manfred Thaller (Max-Planck-Institut für Geschichte,
Göttingen).<note place="bottom">This Workgroup was jointly
sponsored by the Association for History and Computing.</note></item>
<label>AI5 Print dictionaries</label>
<item>Chairs: Robert Amsler* (Bell Communications Research) and
Nicoletta Calzolari (University of Pisa);
Susan Armstrong-Warwick (University of Geneva);
John Fought (University of Pennsylvania);
Louise Guthrie (University of New Mexico);
Nancy M. Ide* (Vassar College);
Frank Tompa (University of Waterloo);
Carol Van Ess-Dykema (US Department of Defense);
Jean Veronis (University of Aix-en-Provence).</item><label>AI6 Machine lexica</label>
<item>Chair:  Robert Ingria* (Bolt Beranek Newman Inc);
Susan Armstrong-Warwick (University of Geneva);
Nicoletta Calzolari (University of Pisa).</item><label>AI7 Terminological data</label>
<item>Chair:  Alan Melby* (Brigham Young University)
Gerhard Budin (University of Vienna);
Gregory Shreve (Kent State University);
Richard Strehlow (Oak Ridge National Laboratory);
Sue Ellen Wright (Kent State University).</item></list></p></div>
<div xml:id="WGAB"><head>Advisory Board</head>
<p>Members of the TEI Advisory Board during the lifetime of the
project are listed below, grouped under the name of the organization
represented.
<list rend="compact" type="gloss"><label>American Anthropological Association:</label>
<item>Chad McDaniel (University of Maryland).</item><label>American Historical Association:</label>
<item>Elizabeth A. R. Brown (Brooklyn College, CUNY).</item><label>American Philological Association:</label>
<item>Jocelyn Penny Small (Rutgers University).</item><label>American Philosophical Association:</label>
<item>Allen Renear (Brown University).</item><label>American Society for Information Science:</label>
<item>Clifford A. Lynch (University of California).</item><label>Association for Computing Machinery, Special Interest Group for
Information Retrieval:</label>
<item>1989–93:  Scott Deerwester (University of Chicago); 1993- :
Martha Evens (Illinois Institute of Technology).</item><label>Association for Documentary Editing:</label>
<item>David Chesnutt (University of South Carolina).</item><label>Association for History and Computing:</label>
<item>1989–91:  Manfred Thaller, Max-Planck-Institut für
Geschichte, Göttingen; 1991- :  Daniel Greenstein (Glasgow
University).</item><label>Association Internationale Bible et Informatique</label>
<item>1989–93:  Wilhelm Ott (University of Tübingen); 1993- :
Winfried Bader (University of Tübingen).</item><label>Canadian Linguistic Association:</label>
<item>Anne-Maria di Sciullo (Université du Québec
à Montréal)</item><label>Dictionary Society of North America:</label>
<item>Barbara Ann Kipfer (Independent Consultant).</item><label>AAP Electronic Publishing Special Interest Group:</label>
<item>1989–92:  Betsy Kiser (OCLC); 1992- :
Deborah Bendig and Andrea Keyhani (OCLC).</item><label>International Federation of Library Associations and
Institutions:</label>
<item>J. D. Byrum Jr. (The Library of Congress).</item><label>Linguistic Society of America:</label>
<item>Stephen Anderson (The Johns Hopkins University)</item><label>Modern Language Association:</label>
<item>Randall Jones (Brigham Young University) and
Ian Lancashire (University of Toronto).</item></list></p></div>
<div xml:id="WGSC"><head>Steering Committee Membership</head>
<p>Members of the Steering Committee of the TEI during the preparation
of this work were:
<list type="gloss"><label>Association for Computational Linguistics:</label>
<item>
<list type="simple">
<item>1987–1993:  Robert A. Amsler (Bell Communications Research);</item>
<item>1987–1993:  Donald E. Walker (Bell Communications Research);</item>
<item>1993–1994:  Susan Armstrong-Warwick (University of Geneva);</item>
<item>1994–1999:  Judith Klavans (Columbia University).</item></list></item><label>Association for Computers and the Humanities:</label>
<item>
<list type="simple">
<item>1987–1999:  Nancy M. Ide (Vassar College);</item>
<item>1987–1994:  C. M. Sperberg-McQueen (University of Illinois at
Chicago);</item>
<item>1994–1999:  David Barnard (Queen's University).</item></list></item><label>Association for Literary and Linguistic Computing:</label>
<item>
<list type="simple">
<item>1987–1999:  Susan M. Hockey (Center for Electronic Texts in the
Humanities);</item>
<item>1987–1999:  Antonio Zampolli (University of Pisa).</item></list></item></list></p></div></div>
</div>
