<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="ST" n="3">

  <head>The TEI Infrastructure</head>

  <p>This chapter describes the infrastructure for the encoding scheme defined by these Guidelines.
    It introduces the conceptual framework within which the following chapters are to be understood,
    and the means by which that conceptual framework is implemented. It assumes some familiarity
    with XML and XML schemas (see chapter <ptr target="#SG"/>) but is intended to be accessible to
    any user of these Guidelines. Other chapters supply further technical details, in particular
    chapter <ptr target="#TD"/> which describes the XML schema used to express the Guidelines
    themselves, and chapter <ptr target="#USE"/> which combines a discussion of modification and
    conformance issues with a description of the intended behaviour of an ODD processor; these
    chapters should be read by anyone intending to implement a new TEI-based system.</p>

  <p>The TEI encoding scheme consists of a number of <term>modules</term>, each of which declares
    particular XML elements and their attributes. Part of an element's declaration includes its
    assignment to one or more element <term>classes</term>. Another part defines its possible
    content and attributes with reference to these classes. This indirection gives the TEI system
    much of its strength and its flexibility. Elements may be combined more or less freely to form a
      <term>schema</term> appropriate to a particular set of requirements. It is also easy to add
    new elements which reference existing classes or elements to a schema, as it is to exclude some
    of the elements provided by any module included in a schema.</p>

  <p>In principle, a TEI schema may be constructed using any combination of modules. However,
    certain TEI modules are of particular importance, and should always be included in all but
    exceptional circumstances: the module <ident type="module">tei</ident> described in the present
    chapter is of this kind because it defines classes, macros, and datatypes which are used by all
    other modules. The <ident type="module">core</ident> module, defined in chapter <ptr
      target="#CO"/> contains declarations for elements and attributes which are likely to be needed
    in almost any kind of document, and is therefore recommended for global use. The <ident
      type="module">header</ident> module defined in chapter <ptr target="#HD"/> provides
    declarations for the metadata elements and attributes constituting the TEI Header, a component
    which is required for TEI conformance, while the <ident type="module">textstructure</ident>
    module defined in chapter <ptr target="#DS"/> declares basic structural elements needed for the
    encoding of most book-like objects. Most schemas will therefore need to include these four
    modules.<!--, but are free to mix and match them
with others.--></p>

  <p>The specification for a TEI schema is itself a TEI document, using elements from the module
    described in chapter <ptr target="#TD"/>: we refer to such a document informally as an
      <term>ODD</term> document, from the design goal originally formulated for the system: <q>One
      Document Does it all</q>. Stylesheets for maintaining and processing ODD documents are
    maintained by the TEI, and these Guidelines are also maintained as such a document. As further
    discussed in <ptr target="#IM"/>, an ODD document can be processed to generate a schema
    expressed using any of the three schema languages currently in wide use: the XML DTD language,
    the ISO RELAX NG language, or the W3C Schema language, as well as to generate documentation such
    as the <title>Guidelines</title> and their associated web site.</p>

  <p>The bulk of this chapter describes the TEI infrastructure module itself. Although it may be
    skipped at a first reading, an understanding of the topics addressed here is essential for
    anyone planning to take full advantage of the TEI customization techniques described in chapter
      <ptr target="#MD"/>.</p>

  <p>The chapter begins by briefly characterizing each of the modules available in the TEI scheme.
    Section <ptr target="#STIN"/> describes in general terms the method of constructing a TEI schema
    in a specific schema language such as XML DTD language, RELAX NG, or W3C Schema.</p>

  <p>The next and largest part of the chapter introduces the attribute and element classes used to
    define groups of elements and their characteristics (section <ptr target="#STEC"/>).</p>

  <p>Finally, section <ptr target="#STmacros"/> introduces the concept of <term>macros</term>, which
    are used to express some commonly used content models, and lists the <term>datatypes</term> used
    to constrain the range of legal values for TEI attributes (section <ptr target="#DTYPES"/>). </p>


  <div type="div2" xml:id="STMA">
    <head>TEI Modules</head>

    <p>These Guidelines define several hundred elements and attributes for marking up documents of
      any kind. Each definition has the following components: <list type="simple">
        <item>a prose description</item>
        <item>a formal declaration, expressed using a special-purpose XML vocabulary defined by
          these Guidelines in combination with elements taken from the ISO schema language RELAX
          NG</item>
        <item>usage examples</item>
      </list></p>
    <p>Each chapter of the Guidelines presents a group of related elements, and also defines a
      corresponding set of declarations, which we call a <term>module</term>. All the definitions
      are collected together in the reference sections provided as an appendix. Formal declarations
      for a given chapter are collected together within the corresponding module. For convenience,
      each element is assigned to a single module, typically for use in some specific application
      area, or to support a particular kind of usage. A module is thus simply a convenient way of
      grouping together a number of associated element declarations. In the simple case, a TEI
      schema is made by combining together a small number of modules, as further described in
      section <ptr target="#STIN"/> below.</p>


    <p>The following table lists the modules defined by the current release of the Guidelines: <!-- table can be re-autogenerated from modules.xsl LB 20-xii-05 -->
      <table xml:id="tab-mods">
        <row role="label">
          <cell>Module name</cell>
          <cell>Formal public identifier</cell>
          <cell>Where defined</cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>analysis</cell>
          <cell>Analysis and Interpretation</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#AI"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>certainty</cell>
          <cell>Certainty and Uncertainty</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#CE"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>core</cell>
          <cell>Common Core</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#CO"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>corpus</cell>
          <cell>Metadata for Language Corpora</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#CC"/></cell>
        </row>
        <!--<row><cell>declarefs</cell><cell>Feature System Declaration</cell><cell><ptr target="#FD"/></cell></row>-->
        <row>
          <cell>dictionaries</cell>
          <cell>Print Dictionaries</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#DI"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>drama</cell>
          <cell>Performance Texts</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#DR"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>figures</cell>
          <cell>Tables, Formulae, Figures</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#FT"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>gaiji</cell>
          <cell>Character and Glyph Documentation</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#WD"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>header</cell>
          <cell>Common Metadata</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#HD"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>iso-fs</cell>
          <cell>Feature Structures</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#FS"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>linking</cell>
          <cell>Linking, Segmentation, and Alignment</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#SA"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>msdescription</cell>
          <cell>Manuscript Description</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#MS"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>namesdates</cell>
          <cell>Names, Dates, People, and Places</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#ND"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>nets</cell>
          <cell>Graphs, Networks, and Trees</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#GD"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>spoken</cell>
          <cell>Transcribed Speech</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#TS"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>tagdocs</cell>
          <cell>Documentation Elements</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#TD"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>tei</cell>
          <cell>TEI Infrastructure</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#ST"/></cell>
        </row>
        <!--row><cell>terminology</cell><cell>terminology</cell><cell><ptr target="#TE"/></cell></row-->
        <row>
          <cell>textcrit</cell>
          <cell>Text Criticism</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#TC"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>textstructure</cell>
          <cell>Default Text Structure</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#DS"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>transcr</cell>
          <cell>Transcription of Primary Sources</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#PH"/></cell>
        </row>
        <row>
          <cell>verse</cell>
          <cell>Verse</cell>
          <cell><ptr target="#VE"/></cell>
        </row>
      </table>
    </p>

    <p>For each module listed above, the corresponding chapter gives a full description of the
      classes, elements, and macros which it makes available when it is included in a schema. Other
      chapters of these Guidelines explore other aspects of using the TEI scheme.</p>
  </div>


  <div type="div2" xml:id="STIN">
    <head>Defining a TEI Schema</head>

    <p>To determine that an XML document is valid (as opposed to merely well-formed), its structure
      must be checked against a schema, as discussed in chapter <ptr target="#SG"/>. For a valid TEI
      document, this schema must be a conformant TEI schema, as further defined in chapter <ptr
        target="#CF"/>. Local systems may allow their schema to be implicit, but for interchange
      purposes the schema associated with a document <emph>must</emph> be made explicit. The method
      of doing this recommended by these Guidelines is to provide explicitly or by reference a TEI
      schema specification against which the document may be validated.</p>

    <p>A TEI-conformant schema is a specific combination of TEI modules, possibly also including
      additional declarations that modify the element and attribute declarations contained by each
      module, for example to suppress or rename some elements. The TEI provides an
      application-independent way of specifying a TEI schema by means of the <gi>schemaSpec</gi>
      element defined in chapter <ptr target="#TD"/>. The same system may also be used to specify a
      schema which extends the TEI by adding new elements explicitly, or by reference to other XML
      vocabularies. In either case, the specification may be processed to generate a formal schema,
      expressed in a variety of specific schema languages, such as XML DTD language, RELAX NG, or
      W3C Schema. These output schemas can then be used by an XML processor such as a validator or
      editor to validate or otherwise process documents. Further information about the processing of
      a TEI formal specification is given in chapter <ptr target="#USE"/>.</p>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="STINsimpleExample">
      <head>A Simple Customization</head>
      <p>The simplest customization of the TEI scheme combines just the four recommended modules
        mentioned above. In ODD format, this schema specification takes this form: <egXML
          xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
          <schemaSpec ident="TEI-minimal" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="header"/>
            <moduleRef key="core"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
          </schemaSpec>
        </egXML></p>
      <p>This schema specification contains references to each of four modules, identified by the
          <att>key</att> attribute on the <gi>moduleRef</gi> element. The schema specification
        itself is also given an identifier (<ident>TEI-minimal</ident>). An ODD processor will
        generate an appropriate schema from this set of declarations, expressed using the XML DTD
        language, the ISO RELAX NG language, the W3C Schema language, or in principle any other
        adequately powerful schema language. The resulting schema may then be associated with the
        document instance by one of a number of different mechanisms, as further described in
        chapter <ptr target="#SG"/>.<!-- somewhere --> The start point (or root element) of document
        instances to be validated against the schema is specified by means of the <att>start</att>
        attribute. Further information about the processing of an ODD specification is given in <ptr
          target="#IM"/>. </p>
    </div>

    <div type="div3" xml:id="STINlargerExample">
      <head>A Larger Customization</head>

      <p>These Guidelines introduce each of the modules making up the TEI scheme one by one, and
        therefore, for clarity of exposition, each chapter focusses on elements drawn from a single
        module. In reality, of course, the markup of a text will draw on elements taken from many
        different modules, partly because texts are heterogenous objects, and partly because
        encoders have different goals. Some examples of this heterogeneity include: <list
          type="simple">
          <item>a text may be a collection of other texts of different types: for example, an
            anthology of prose, verse, and drama;</item>
          <item>a text may contain other smaller, embedded texts: for example, a poem or song
            included in a prose narrative;</item>
          <item>some sections of a text may be written in one form, and others in a different form:
            for example, a novel where some chapters are in prose, others take the form of
            dictionary entries, and still others the form of scenes in a play; </item>
          <item>an encoded text may include detailed analytic annotation, for example of rhetorical
            or linguistic features; </item>
          <item>an encoded text may combine a literal transcription with a diplomatic edition of the
            same or different sources; </item>
          <item>the description of a text may require additional specialized metadata elements, for
            example when describing manuscript material in detail.</item>
        </list></p>

      <p>The TEI provides mechanisms to support all of these and many other use cases. The
        architecture permits elements and attributes from any combination of modules to co-exist
        within a single schema. Within particular modules, elements and attributes are provided to
        support differing views of the <soCalled>granularity</soCalled> of a text, for example:
          <list type="simple">
          <item>a definition of a corpus or collection as a series of <gi>TEI</gi> documents,
            sharing a common TEI header (see chapter <ptr target="#CC"/>)</item>
          <item>a definition of composite texts which combine optional front- and back-matter with a
            group of collected texts, themselves possibly composite (see section <ptr
              target="#DSGRP"/>)</item>
          <item>an element for the representation of <term>embedded texts</term>, where one
            narrative appears to <soCalled>float</soCalled> within another (see section <ptr
              target="#DSFLT"/>)</item>
        </list></p>
      <p>Subsequent chapters of these Guidelines describe in detail markup constructs appropriate
        for these and many other possible features of interest. The markup constructs can be
        combined as needed for any given set of applications or project.</p>

      <p>For example, a project aiming to produce an ambitious digital edition of a collection of
        manuscript materials, to include detailed metadata about each source, digital images of the
        content, along with a detailed transcription of each source, and a supporting biographical
        and geographical database might need a schema combining several modules, as follows: <egXML
          xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><schemaSpec ident="TEI-PROJECT" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="header"/>
            <moduleRef key="core"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
            <moduleRef key="msdescription"/>
            <!-- manuscript description -->
            <moduleRef key="transcr"/>
            <!-- transcription of primary sources -->
            <moduleRef key="figures"/>
            <!-- figures and tables -->
            <moduleRef key="namesdates"/>
            <!-- names, dates, people, and places -->
          </schemaSpec></egXML></p>

      <p>Alternatively, a simpler schema might be used for a part of such a project: those preparing
        the transcriptions, for example, might need only elements from the <ident type="module"
          >core</ident>, <ident type="module">textstructure</ident>, and <ident type="module"
          >transcr</ident> modules, and might therefore prefer to use a simpler schema such as that
        generated by the following: <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
            ><schemaSpec ident="TEI-TRANSCR" start="TEI">
            <moduleRef key="tei"/>
            <moduleRef key="core"/>
            <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>
            <moduleRef key="transcr"/>
          </schemaSpec></egXML>
      </p>

      <p>The TEI architecture also supports more detailed customization beyond the simple selection
        of modules. A schema may suppress elements from a module, suppress some of their attributes,
        change their names, or even add new elements and attributes. Detailed discussion of the kind
        of modification possible in this way is provided in <ptr target="#MD"/> and conformance
        rules relating to their application are discussed in <ptr target="#CF"/>. These facilities
        are available for any schema language (though some features may not be available in all
        languages). The ODD language also makes it possible to combine TEI and non-TEI modules into
        a single schema, provided that the non-TEI module is expressed using the RELAX NG schema
        language (see further <ptr target="#ST-aliens"/>).</p>
    </div>
  </div>


  <div type="div2" xml:id="STEC">
    <head>The TEI Class System</head>

    <p>The TEI scheme distinguishes about five hundred different elements. To aid comprehension,
      modularity, and modification, the majority of these elements are formally classified in some
      way. Classes are used to express two distinct kinds of commonality among elements. The
      elements of a class may share some set of attributes, or they may appear in the same locations
      in a content model. A class is known as an <term>attribute class</term> if its members share
      attributes, and as a <term>model class</term> if its members appear in the same locations. In
      either case, an element is said to <term>inherit</term> properties from any classes of which
      it is a member. </p>

    <p>Classes (and therefore elements which are members of those classes) may also inherit
      properties from other classes. For example, supposing that class A is a member (or a
        <term>subclass</term>) of class B, any element which is a member of class A will inherit not
      only the properties defined by class A, but also those defined by class B. In such a
      situation, we also say that class B is a <term>superclass</term> of class A. The properties of
      a superclass are inherited by all members of its subclasses. </p>


    <p>A basic understanding of the classes into which the TEI scheme is organized is strongly
      recommended and is essential for any successful customization of the system.</p>



    <div type="div2" xml:id="STECAT">
      <head>Attribute Classes</head>

      <p>An attribute class groups together elements which share some set of common attributes.
        Attribute classes are given names composed of the prefix <code>att.</code>, often followed
        by an adjective. For example, the members of the class <ident type="class"
          >att.canonical</ident> have in common a <att>key</att> and a <att>ref</att> attribute,
        both of which are inherited from their membership in the class rather than individually
        defined for each element. These attributes are said to be defined by (or inherited from) the
          <ident type="class">att.canonical</ident> class. If another element were to be added to
        the TEI scheme for which these attributes were considered useful, the simplest way to
        provide them would be to make the new element a member of the <ident type="class"
          >att.canonical</ident> class. Note also that this method ensures that the attributes in
        question are always defined in the same way, taking the same default values etc., no matter
        which element they are attached to.</p>

      <p>Some attribute classes are defined within the <ident type="module">tei</ident>
        infrastructural module and are thus globally available. Other attribute classes are specific
        to particular modules and thus defined in other chapters. Attributes defined by such classes
        will not be available unless the module concerned is included in a schema.</p>

      <p>The attributes provided by an attribute class are those specified by the class itself,
        either directly, or by inheritance from another class. For example, the attribute class
          <ident type="class">att.pointing.group</ident> provides attributes <att>domains</att> and
          <att>targFunc</att> to all of its members. This class is however a subclass of the <ident
          type="class">att.pointing</ident> class, from which its members also inherit the
        attributes <att>target</att>, <att>targetLang</att> and <att>evaluate</att>. Members of the
        class <ident type="class">att.pointing</ident> will thus have these three attributes, while
        members of the class <ident type="class">att.pointing.group</ident> will have all five.</p>


      <p>Note that some modules define superclasses of an existing infrastructural class. For
        example, the global attribute class <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident> makes attributes
          <att>org</att> and <att>sample</att> available, while the <ident
          type="class">att.metrical</ident> class, which is specific to the <ident type="module"
          >verse</ident> module, provides attributes <att>met</att>, <att>real</att>, and
          <att>rhyme</att>. Because <ident type="class">att.metrical</ident> is defined as a
        superclass of <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident>, all five of these attributes are
        available to elements; the declaration for <ident type="class">att.metrical</ident> adds its
        three attributes to the three already defined by <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident>
        when the <ident type="module">verse</ident> module is included in a schema. If, however,
        this module is not included in a schema, then the <ident type="class">att.divLike</ident>
        class supplies only the two attributes first mentioned.</p>


      <p>Attributes specific to particular modules are documented along with the relevant module
        rather than in the present chapter. One particular attribute class, known as <ident
          type="class">att.global</ident>, is common to all modules, and is therefore described in
        some detail in the next section. A full list of all attribute classes is given in <ptr
          target="#REF-CLASSES-ATTS"/> below. </p>

      <div type="div2" xml:id="STGA">
        <head>Global Attributes</head>

        <p>The following attributes are defined for every TEI element. <specList>
            <specDesc key="att.global"
              atts="xml:id n xml:lang rend style
rendition xml:base xml:space"/>
          </specList>
        </p>

        <p>These attributes are optionally available for any TEI element; none of them is required.
          Their usage is discussed in the following subsections. </p>

        <div xml:id="STGAid">
          <head>Element Identifiers and Labels</head>

          <p>The value supplied for the <att>xml:id</att> attribute must be a legal
              <term>name</term>, as defined in the World Wide Web Consortium's <ref
              target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml">XML Recommendation</ref>. This means that it
            must begin with a letter, or the underscore character (<q>_</q>), and contain no
            characters other than letters, digits, hyphens, underscores, full stops, and certain
            combining and extension characters.<note place="bottom">The colon is also by default a
              valid name character; however, it has a specific purpose in XML (to indicate namespace
              prefixes), and may not therefore be used in any other way within a name.</note></p>
          <p>In XML names (and thus the values of <att>xml:id</att> in an XML TEI document)
            uppercase and lowercase letters are distinguished, and thus
              <mentioned>partTime</mentioned> and <mentioned>parttime</mentioned> are two distinctly
            different names, and could (though perhaps unwisely) be used to denote two different
            element occurrences.</p>
          <p>If two elements are given the same identifier, a validating XML parser will signal a
            syntax error. The following example, therefore, is <emph>not</emph> valid: <egXML
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#STGA-eg-4">&lt;p
              xml:id="PAGE1"&gt;&lt;q&gt;What's it going to be then, eh?&lt;/q&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p
              xml:id="PAGE1"&gt;There was me, that is Alex, and my three droogs, that is Pete,
              Georgie, and Dim, ... &lt;/p&gt;</egXML>
          </p>
          <p>For a discussion of methods of providing unique identifiers for elements, see section
              <ptr target="#CORS2"/>.</p>
          <p>The <att>n</att> attribute also provides an identifying name or number for an element,
            but in this case the information need not be a legal <att>xml:id</att> value. Its value
            may be any string of characters; typically it is a number or other similar enumerator or
            label. For example, the numbers given to the items of a numbered list may be recorded
            with the <att>n</att> attribute; this would make it possible to record errors in the
            numeration of the original, as in this list of chapters, transcribed from a faulty
            original in which the number 10 is used twice, and 11 is omitted: <egXML
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><list type="ordered">
                <item n="1">About These Guidelines</item>
                <item n="2">A Gentle Introduction to XML</item>
                <item n="9">Verse</item>
                <item n="10">Drama</item>
                <item n="10">Spoken Materials </item>
                <item n="12">Dictionaries</item>
              </list></egXML> The <att>n</att> attribute may also be used to record non-unique names
            associated with elements in a text, possibly together with a unique identifier as in the
            following example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#STGA-eg-6"
                ><div type="book" n="one" xml:id="TXT0101">
                <!-- ... -->
                <div type="stanza" n="xlii">
                  <!-- ... -->
                </div>
              </div></egXML>
          </p>
          <p>As noted above there is no requirement to record a value for either the
              <att>xml:id</att> or the <att>n</att> attribute. Any XML processor can identify the
            sequential position of one element within another in an XML document without any
            additional tagging. An encoding in which each line of a long poem is explicitly labelled
            with its numerical sequence such as the following <egXML xml:lang="und"
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l n="1"><!-- ... --></l>
              <l n="2"><!-- ... --></l>
              <l n="3"><!-- ... --></l>
              <!-- ... -->
              <l n="100"><!-- ... --></l>
            </egXML> is therefore probably redundant.</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="STGAla">
          <head>Language Indicators</head>

          <p>The <att>xml:lang</att> attribute indicates the natural language and writing system
            applicable to the content of a given element. If it is not specified, the value is
            inherited from that of the immediately enclosing element. As a rule, therefore, it is
            simplest to specify the base language of the text on the <gi>TEI</gi> element, and allow
            most elements to take the default value for <att>xml:lang</att>; the language of an
            element then need be explicitly specified only for elements in languages other than the
            base language. For this reason, it is recommended practice to supply a default value for
            the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute, either on the <gi>TEI</gi> root element, or on both the
              <gi>teiHeader</gi> and the <gi>text</gi> element. The latter is appropriate in the not
            uncommon case where the text element in a TEI document uses a different default language
            from that of the TEI Header attached to it. Other language shifts in the source should
            be explicitly identified by use of the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute on an element at an
            appropriate level wherever possible. </p>
          <p>In the following example schematic, an English language TEI header is attached to an
            English language text: <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
              valid="feasible">
              <TEI xml:lang="en">
                <teiHeader>
                  <!-- ... -->
                </teiHeader>
                <text>
                  <!-- ... -->
                </text></TEI></egXML>
          </p>
          <p>The same effect would be obtained by specifying the default language for both header
            and text: <egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
              valid="feasible">
              <TEI>
                <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
                  <!-- ... -->
                </teiHeader>
                <text xml:lang="en">
                  <!-- ... -->
                </text></TEI></egXML>
          </p>
          <p>The latter approach is necessary in the case where the two differ: for example, where
            an English language header is applied to a French text: <egXML xml:lang="und"
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible">
              <TEI>
                <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
                  <!-- ... -->
                </teiHeader>
                <text xml:lang="fr">
                  <!-- ... -->
                </text></TEI></egXML>
          </p>
          <p>The same principle applies at any hierarchic level. In the following example, the
            default language of the text is French, but one section of it is in German: <egXML
              xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="feasible">
              <TEI>
                <teiHeader xml:lang="en">
                  <!-- ... -->
                </teiHeader>
                <text xml:lang="fr">
                  <body>
                    <div>
                      <!-- chapter one is in French -->
                    </div>
                    <div xml:lang="de">
                      <!-- chapter two is in German -->
                    </div>
                    <div>
                      <!-- chapter three is French -->
                    </div>
                    <!-- ... -->
                  </body>
                </text></TEI></egXML>
          </p>

          <p>Similarly, in the following example the <att>xml:lang</att> attribute on the
              <gi>term</gi> element allows us to record the fact that the technical terms used are
            Latin rather than English; no <att>xml:lang</att> attribute is needed on the <gi>q</gi>
            element, by contrast, because it is in the same language as its parent. <egXML
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#STGA-eg-10"><p xml:lang="en">The
                constitution declares <q>that no bill of attainder or <term xml:lang="la">ex post
                    facto</term> law shall be passed.</q> ...</p></egXML>
          </p>
          <p>Note that in cases where it is advisable or necessary to identify the language of the
            text that is pointed at, the (non-global) attribute <att>targetLang</att> should be
            used, for example in <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><ptr target="x12"
                targetLang="fr"/></egXML> the pointer references text written in French.</p>
          <p>The values used for the <att>xml:lang</att> and <att>targetLang</att>attributes must be
            constructed in a particular way, using values from standard lists. See further <ptr
              target="#CHSH"/>.</p>
          <p>Additional information about a particular language may be supplied in the
              <gi>language</gi> element within the header (see section <ptr target="#HD41"/>).</p>
        </div>
        <div xml:id="STGAre">
          <head>Rendition Indicators</head>
          <p>The <att>rend</att>, <att>rendition</att>, and <att>style</att> attributes are all used
            to give information about the physical presentation of the text in the source. In the
            following example, <att>rend</att> is used to indicate that both the emphasized word and
            the proper name are printed in italics: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
              corresp="#STGA-eg-11"><p> ... Their motives <emph rend="italics">might</emph> be pure
                and pious; but he was equally alarmed by his knowledge of the ambitious <name
                  rend="italics">Bohemond</name>, and his ignorance of the Transalpine chiefs:
                ...</p></egXML> The same effect might be achieved using the <att>style</att>
            attribute, as follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"
              corresp="#STGA-eg-11"><p> ... Their motives <emph style="font-style: italic"
                  >might</emph> be pure and pious; but he was equally alarmed by his knowledge of
                the ambitious <name style="font-style: italic">Bohemond</name>, and his ignorance of
                the Transalpine chiefs: ...</p></egXML> If all or most <gi>emph</gi> and
              <gi>name</gi> elements are rendered in the text by italics, it will be more convenient
            to register that fact in the TEI header once and for all (using the <gi>rendition</gi>
            element discussed below) and specify a <att>rend</att> or <att>style</att> value only
            for any elements which deviate from the stated rendition. </p>
          <p>The main difference between <att>rend</att> attribute and <att>style</att> is that the
            value used for the former may contain one or more tokens from any vocabulary devised by
            the encoder, separated by space characters, whereas the value used for the latter must
            be a single string taken from a formally-defined style definition language such as CSS. 
	The <att>rend</att> attribute values are sequence-indeterminate set of
            whitespace-separated tokens, whereas <att>style</att> values allow whitespace and
            sequence relationships as part of the formally-defined style definition language.</p>
          <p>The <gi>rendition</gi> element defined in <ptr target="#HD57"/> may be used to hold
            repeatedly-used format descriptions. A <gi>rendition</gi> element can then be associated
            with any element, either by default, or by means of the global <att>rendition</att>
            attribute. For example: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <tagsDecl>
                <!-- define italic style using CSS -->
                <rendition xml:id="IT" scheme="css">font-style: italic</rendition>
                <!-- define a serif font family -->
                <rendition xml:id="FontRoman" scheme="css">font-family: serif</rendition>
                <!-- set italic style as default for the emph and hi elements -->
                <namespace name="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
                  <tagUsage gi="emph" render="#IT"/>
                  <tagUsage gi="hi" render="#IT"/>
                  <!-- set the default font-family for the text element -->
                  <tagUsage gi="text" render="#FontRoman"/>
                </namespace>
              </tagsDecl>
              <!-- ... -->
              <text><body>
                  <div>
                    <p rendition="#IT"
                      ><!-- this paragraph uses the seriffed font, but is in italic--></p>
                    <p>
                      <!-- this paragraph uses the seriffed font, but is not in
   italic --></p>
                  </div></body></text>
            </egXML>
          </p>

          <p>The <att>rendition</att> attribute always points to one or more <gi>rendition</gi>
            elements, each of which defines some aspect of the rendering or appearance of the text
            in its original form. These details may most conveniently be described using a formal
            style definition language, such as CSS (<ptr target="#CSS1"/>) or XSL-FO (<ptr
              target="#XSL11"/>); in some other formal language developed for a specific project; or
            even informally in running prose. Although languages such as CSS and XSL-FO are
            generally used to describe document output to screen or print, they nonetheless provide
            formal and precise mechanisms for describing the appearance of source documents,
            especially print documents, but also many aspects of manuscript documents. For example,
            both CSS and XSL-FO provide mechanisms for describing typefaces, weight, and styles;
            character and line spacing; and so on.</p>
          <p>As noted above, the <att>style</att> attribute is provided for encoders wishing to
            describe the appearance of individual source elements using a language such as CSS
            directly rather than by reference to a <gi>rendition</gi> element. Its value may be any
            expression in the chosen formal style definition language. </p>
          <p>Formal definition languages such as CSS typically identity a series of
              <term>properties</term> (such as font-style or margin-left) for which
              <term>values</term> are specified. A sequence of such property-value pairs makes up a
            stylesheet. The TEI uses such languages simply to describe the appearance of a source
            document, rather than to control how it should be formatted. </p>
          <p>In the TEI scheme, it is possible to supply information about the appearance of
            elements within a source document in the following distinct ways: <list type="ordered">
              <item>One or more properties may be specified as the default for all elements of a
                given type, using the <att>render</att> attribute to point to <gi>rendition</gi>
                elements ;</item>
	      <item>One or more properties may be specified for individual element occurrences, 
                using the <att>rend</att> attribute with any convenient set of one or more sequence-indeterminate tokens; </item> 
<item>One or more properties may be specified for individual element occurrences,
                using the <att>rendition</att> attribute to point to <gi>rendition</gi> elements; </item>
              <item>One or more properties may be supplied explicitly for individual element
                occurrences, using the <att>style</att> attribute. </item>
            </list>
          </p>
          <p>If the same property is specified in more than one of the above ways, the one with the
            highest number in the list above is understood to be applicable. The resulting
            properties from each way are then combined to provide the full set of property-value
            pairs applicable to the given element, and (by default) to all of its children. </p>
          <p>For simplicity of processing, the same formal style definition should be used
            throughout; however, the architecture does permit this to be varied, by using the
              <att>scheme</att> attribute to indicate a different language for one or more
              <gi>rendition</gi> elements. Care should be taken to ensure that such values can be
            meaningfully combined. Similar considerations apply to the use of the <att>rend</att>
            attribute, if this is used in combination with either <att>rendition</att> or
              <att>style</att>. </p>

          <p>Note that these TEI attributes always describe the rendition or appearance of the
            source document, <emph>not</emph> intended output renditions, although often the two may
            be closely related. </p>

        </div>

        <div xml:id="STGAba">
          <head>Evaluation of links</head>
          <p>Several TEI elements carry attributes whose values are
	  defined as <code>anyURI</code>, meaning that such attributes
	  supply a link or pointer, typically expressed as a URL. Like
	  other XML applications, the TEI allows use of a special
	  attribute to set the context within which relative URLs are
	  to be evaluated. The global attribute <att>xml:base</att> is defined as part
            of the XML specification and belongs to the XML namespace rather than the TEI namespace.
            We do not describe it in detail here: reference
	    information about <att>xml:base</att> is
            provided by <ptr target="#XMLBASE"/> </p>

          <p>In essence <att>xml:base</att> is used to set a context for all relative URLs
            within the scope of the element on which it is specified. For example: <egXML
              xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
              <body>
                <div xml:base="http://www.example.org/somewhere.xml">
                  <p><!--... -->
                    <ptr target="#p1"/>
                    <!--... -->
                  </p>
                </div>
                <div>
                  <p><!--... -->
                    <ptr target="#p1"/>
                    <!--... -->
                  </p>
                </div>
              </body></egXML>The first <gi>ptr</gi> element here is within the scope of a
              <gi>div</gi> which supplies a value for <att>xml:base</att>; its target is therefore
            to be found at <code>http://www.example.org/somewhere.xml#p1</code>. The second
              <gi>ptr</gi>, however, is within the scope of a <gi>div</gi> which does not change the
            default context, and its target is therefore some element within the current document
            with the value <code>p1</code> for its <att>xml:id</att> attribute. Further discussion
            of this element and its effect on TEI linking methods is provided in chapter <ptr
              target="#SA"/>. </p>
</div>
<div xml:id="STGAxs">
<head>XML Whitespace</head>
<p>The global attribute <att>xml:space</att> provides a mechanism for
indicating to systems processing
an XML file how they should treat whitespace, that is, any sequences
of consecutive tab (#x09), space
(#x20), carriage return (#x0D) or linefeed (#x0A) characters. Like
<att>xml:id</att> this attribute is defined as part           of the XML specification and belongs to the XML
namespace rather than the TEI namespace. Complete information about
this attribute is provided by  <ref
target="http://www.w3.org/TR/REC-xml/#sec-white-space">section 2.10 of the XML
Specification</ref>; here we provide a summary of how
its use affects users of the TEI scheme.</p>
<p>The <att>xml:space</att> attribute has  only two permitted values: <val>preserve</val> and
<val>default</val>. The first indicates that whitespace in a text
node—every
carriage return, every tab, etc.—should be maintained as is when the
document is processed. The
second (which is implied when the attribute is not supplied),
indicates that whitespace should be
handled <soCalled>as appropriate</soCalled>. Exactly what is deemed appropriate is left unspecified by
the XML Recommendation. </p>
<p>These Guidelines assume one of two different ways of processing
whitespace will apply in a given case, depending on an element's
content model. For an element that can
contain only other elements with no
intervening non-whitespace characters, 
whitespace is considered to have no semantic significance, and should
therefore be discarded by a processor. For example, in a <gi>choice</gi> element, such as 
   <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<choice>
<sic>1724</sic>
<corr>1728</corr>
</choice>
</egXML>
since non-whitespace text  is not permitted  between  the
<gi>choice</gi>
start-tag and  the <gi>sic</gi> tags or between the <gi>sic</gi> and
<gi>corr</gi> tags, 
any whitespace found there has no significance and can be ignored
completely by a processor.</p>
<p>Similarly,  the <gi>address</gi> element has a content model
containing only elements: any punctuation or
whitespace required between the
lines of an address must therefore be supplied by the processor, as
any whitespace present in the input document will be ignored. </p>

<p>Elements with content models of this type are comparatively unusual
in the TEI: a list of them is provided in the TEI release file
<ident type="file">stripspace.xsl.model</ident>, formatted there for use as an
<gi>xsl:strip-space</gi>
command for XSL stylesheets.</p>
<p>Most TEI elements permit what is known as mixed-content: that is,
they can contain both text and other elements. Here the assumption of
these Guidelines is
that whitespace
will be normalized. This means that all space, carriage return, linefeed,
and tab characters are converted into spaces, all consecutive spaces are
then deleted and replaced by one space, and then space immediately after a
start-tag or immediately before an end-tag is deleted. The result is that
this encoding,
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<persName>
<forename>Edward</forename>
<forename>George</forename>
<surname type="linked">Bulwer-Lytton</surname>,
<roleName>Baron Lytton of
<placeName>Knebworth</placeName>
</roleName>
</persName>
</egXML>
would be rendered as <q>Edward George Bulwer-Lytton, Baron Lytton of Knebworth</q>.
The space before his name has been removed, a space is included between his
forenames, the comma is preserved, and the newlines within his name have all been removed.
</p>

<!--
<p>The <gi>persName</gi> element is a mixed-content element; punctuation
such as the
comma in the above example lies outside any of the child elements. The
<gi>address</gi> element, on the other hand, is like <gi>list</gi> and
<gi>choice</gi>, a
structured element. (These three are included in stripspace.xsl.model.) No
punctuation is allowed outside the elements within <gi>address</gi>, and
the
presumed processing behavior is that any space between its components will
get removed. An application processing an <gi>address</gi> element is then
responsible for adding any necessary space or punctuation between the
components of the address. Treating a structured element as a
mixed-content
one, or vice versa, should be done with care. </p>
-->

<p>If the default treatment described above is not appropriate for a
mixed content element, the processing required may be described in the
<gi>encodingDesc</gi> element of the TEI header, but generic XML processing
tools may not take note of this. </p>
<p>Alternatively, the <att>xml:space</att> attribute may be supplied
with a value of <val>preserve</val> in order to
indicate that every space, tab, carriage return and linefeed character
found within that element in the document being processed is significant. Typically, the result of that processing will be to retain
the whitespace characters in the output. Thus if the above example
began  
<tag>persName xml:space="preserve"</tag>, the resulting text would
most likely be rendered over
five lines, indented, and with a blank line following. </p>
<p>The
<code>xml:space=”preserve”</code> attribute is rarely used in TEI
documents because such layout features are generally captured with
less risk and more precision by using native TEI elements such as
<gi>lb</gi> or <gi>space</gi>, or by using the renditional attributes
described in section  <ptr target="#STGAre"/>.</p>


          <specGrp xml:id="DSTECAT" n="Attribute classes">


            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.ascribed.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.canonical.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.ranging.xml"/>
            <!-- must come before att.dimensions -->
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.dimensions.xml"/>
            <!-- must come before att.damaged -->
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.damaged.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.breaking.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.cReferencing.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
              href="../../Specs/att.datable.custom.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.datable.w3c.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.datable.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.datcat.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.declarable.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.declaring.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
		     href="../../Specs/att.fragmentable.xml"/>
<!-- must come before att.divLike -->
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.divLike.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.docStatus.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.duration.w3c.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.duration.iso.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.duration.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
              href="../../Specs/att.responsibility.xml"/>
            <!-- referenced by att.editLike, att.interpLike, att.testCritical -->
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.editLike.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.global.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.handFeatures.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.internetMedia.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.media.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.resourced.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.interpLike.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.measurement.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
              href="../../Specs/att.milestoneUnit.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.naming.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.placement.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.typed.xml"/>
            <!-- must precede pointing.group -->
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.pointing.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.pointing.group.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.readFrom.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.scoping.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.segLike.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.sortable.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.edition.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.spanning.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.styleDef.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
              href="../../Specs/att.tableDecoration.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.timed.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
              href="../../Specs/att.transcriptional.xml"/>
            <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/att.translatable.xml"/>
            <!--&att.xmlspace;-->



          </specGrp>
	</div>
      </div>
    </div>

    <div type="div2" xml:id="STECCM">
      <head>Model Classes</head>

      <p>As noted above, the members of a given TEI model class share the property that they can all
        appear in the same location within a document. Wherever possible, the content model of a TEI
        element is expressed not directly in terms of specific elements, but indirectly in terms of
        particular model classes. This makes content models simpler and more consistent; it also
        makes them much easier to understand and to modify.</p>

      <p>Like attribute classes, model classes may have subclasses or superclasses. Just as elements
        inherit from a class the ability to appear in certain locations of a document (wherever the
        class can appear), so all members of a subclass inherit the ability to appear wherever any
        superclass can appear. To some extent, the class system thus provides a way of reducing the
        whole TEI galaxy of elements into a tidy hierarchy. This is however not entirely the
        case.</p>

      <p>In fact, the nature of a given class of elements can be considered along two dimensions: as
        noted, it defines a set of places where the class members are permitted within the document
        hierarchy; it also implies a semantic grouping of some kind. For example, the very large
        class of elements which can appear within a paragraph comprises a number of other classes,
        all of which have the same structural property, but which differ in their field of
        application. Some are related to highlighting, while others relate to names or places, and
        so on. In some cases, the <soCalled>set of places where class members are
          permitted</soCalled> is very constrained: it may just be within one specific element, or
        one class of element, for example. In other cases, elements may be permitted to appear in
        very many places, or in more than one such set of places.</p>

      <p>These factors are reflected in the way that model classes are named. If a model class has a
        name containing <val>part</val>, such as <ident type="class">model.divPart</ident> or <ident
          type="class">model.biblPart</ident> then it is primarily defined in terms of its
        structural location. For example, those elements (or classes of element) which appear as
        content of a <gi>div</gi> constitute the <ident type="class">model.divPart</ident> class;
        those which appear as content of a <gi>bibl</gi> constitute the <ident type="class"
          >model.biblPart</ident> class. If, however, a model class has a name containing
          <val>like</val>, such as <ident type="class">model.biblLike</ident> or <ident type="class"
          >model.nameLike</ident>, the implication is that its members all have some additional
        semantic property in common, for example containing a bibliographic description, or
        containing some form of name, respectively. These semantically-motivated classes often
        provide a useful way of dividing up large structurally-motivated classes: for example, the
        very general structural class <ident type="class">model.pPart.data</ident> (<soCalled>data
          elements that form part of a paragraph</soCalled>) has four semantically-motivated member
        classes (<ident type="class">model.addressLike</ident>, <ident type="class"
          >model.dateLike</ident>, <ident type="class">model.measureLike</ident>, and <ident
          type="class">model.nameLike</ident>), the last of these being itself a superclass with
        several members.</p>

      <p>Although most classes are defined by the <ident type="module">tei</ident> infrastructure
        module, a class cannot be populated unless some other specific module is included in a
        schema, since element declarations are contained by modules. Classes are not declared
          <soCalled>top down</soCalled>, but instead gain their members as a consequence of
        individual elements' declaration of their membership. The same class may therefore contain
        different members, depending on which modules are active. Consequently, the content model of
        a given element (being expressed in terms of model classes) may differ depending on which
        modules are active. </p>

      <p>Some classes contain only a single member, even when all modules are loaded. One reason for
        declaring such a class is to make it easier for a customization to add new member elements
        in a specific place, particularly in areas where the TEI does not make fully elaborated
        proposals. For example, the TEI class <ident type="class">model.rdgLike</ident>, initially
        empty, is expanded by the <ident type="module">textcrit</ident> module to include just the
        TEI <gi>rdg</gi> element. A project wishing to add an alternative way of structuring
        text-critical information could do so by defining their own elements and adding it to this
        class.</p>

      <p>Another reason for declaring single-member classes is where the class members are not
        needed in all documents, but appear in the same place as elements which are very frequently
        required. For example, the specialized element <gi>g</gi> used to represent a non-Unicode
        character or glyph is provided as the only member of the <ident type="class"
          >model.gLike</ident> class when the <ident type="module">gaiji</ident> module is added to
        a schema. References to this class are included in almost every content model, since if it
        is used at all the <gi>g</gi> must be available wherever text is available; however these
        references have no effect unless the gaiji module is loaded.</p>

      <p>At the other end of the scale, a few of the classes
      predefined by the tei module are subsequently populated with
      very many members. For example, the class <ident type="class"
      >model.pPart.edit</ident> groups all the classes of elementfor
      simple editorial correction and transcription which can appear
      within a <gi>p</gi> or paragraph element. The <ident
      type="module">core</ident> module alone adds more than fifty
      elements to this class; the <ident
      type="module">namesdates</ident> module adds another twenty, as
      does the <ident type="module">tagdocs</ident> module. Since the
      <gi>p</gi> element is one of the basic building blocks of a TEI
      document it is not surprising that each module will need to add
      elements to it. The class system here provides a very convenient
      way of controlling the resulting complexity. Typically, elements
      are not added directly to these very general classes, but via
      some intermediate semantically-motivated class. </p>

      <p>Just as there are a few classes which have a single member, so there are some classes which
        are used only once in the TEI architecture. These classes, which have no superclass and
        therefore do not fit into the class hierarchy defined here, are a convenient way of
        maintaining elements which are highly structured internally, but which appear from the
        outside to be uniform objects like others at the same level.<note place="bottom">In former
          editions of these Guidelines, such elements were known metaphorically as
            <soCalled>crystals</soCalled>.</note> Members of such classes can only ever appear
        within one element, or one class of elements. For example, the class <ident type="class"
          >model.addrPart</ident> is used only to express the content model for the element
          <gi>address</gi>; it references some other classes of elements, which can appear
        elsewhere, and also some elements which can only appear inside an address.</p>

      <div xml:id="STBTC">
        <head>Informal element classifications </head>

        <p>Most TEI elements may also be informally classified as belonging to one of the following
          groupings: <list type="gloss">
            <label><term>divisions</term></label>

            <item>high level, possibly self-nesting, major divisions of texts. These elements
              populate such classes as <ident type="class">model.divLike</ident> or <ident
                type="class">model.div1Like</ident>, and typically form the largest component units
              of a text. </item>

            <label><term>chunks</term>
            </label>
            <item>elements such as paragraphs and other paragraph-level elements, which can appear
              directly within texts or within divisions of them, but not (usually) within other
              chunks. These elements populate the class <ident type="class">model.divPart</ident>,
              either directly or by means of other classes such as <ident type="class"
                >model.pLike</ident> (paragraph-like elements), <ident type="class"
                >model.entryLike</ident>, etc.</item>

            <label><term>phrase-level elements</term>
            </label>
            <item>elements such as highlighted phrases, book titles, or editorial corrections which
              can occur only within chunks, but not between them (and thus cannot appear directly
              within a division). These elements populate the class <ident type="class"
                >model.phrase</ident>.<note place="bottom">Note that in this context,
                  <term>phrase</term> means any string of characters, and can apply to individual
                words, parts of words, and groups of words indifferently; it does not refer only to
                linguistically-motivated phrasal units. This may cause confusion for readers
                accustomed to applying the word in a more restrictive sense.</note></item>
          </list>
        </p>
        <p>The TEI also identifies two further groupings derived from these three: <list
            type="gloss">
            <label><term>inter-level elements</term></label>
            <item>elements such as lists, notes, quotations, etc. which can appear either between
              chunks (as children of a <gi>div</gi>) or within them; these elements populate the
              class <ident type="class">model.inter</ident>. Note that this class is not a superset
              of the <ident type="class">model.phrase</ident> and <ident type="class"
                >model.divPart</ident> classes but rather a distinct grouping of elements which are
              both chunk-like and phrase-like. However, the classes <ident type="class"
                >model.phrase</ident>, <ident type="class">model.pLike</ident>, and <ident
                type="class">model.inter</ident> are all disjoint.</item>

            <label><term>components</term>
            </label>
            <item>elements which can appear directly within texts or text divisions; this is a
              combination of the inter- and chunk- level elements defined above. These elements
              populate the class <ident type="class">model.common</ident>, which is defined as a
              superset of the classes <ident type="class">model.divPart</ident>, <ident type="class"
                >model.inter</ident>, and (when the dictionary module is included in a schema)
                <ident type="class">model.entryLike</ident>.</item>
          </list> Broadly speaking, the front, body, and back of a text each comprises a series of
          components, optionally grouped into divisions. </p>

        <p>As noted above, some elements do not belong to any model class, and some model classes
          are not readily associated with any of the above informal groupings. However, over
          two-thirds of the 500+ elements defined in the present edition of these Guidelines are
          classified in this way, and future editions of these recommendations will extend and
          develop this classification scheme.</p>

        <p>A complete alphabetical list of all model classes is provided in <ptr
            target="#REF-CLASSES-MODEL"/>.</p>

        <!-- all model class declarations: nb order is critical -->
        <!-- inline things -->

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.nameLike.agent.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.segLike.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.hiLike.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.emphLike.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.highlighted.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.dateLike.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.dimLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.measureLike.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.egLike.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.graphicLike.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.offsetLike.xml"/>


        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.pPart.msdesc.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.pPart.editorial.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.pPart.transcriptional.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.pPart.edit.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.linePart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.ptrLike.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.lPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.global.meta.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.milestoneLike.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.gLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.oddDecl.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.oddRef.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.phrase.xml.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.specDescLike.xml"/>
        <!-- inter level -->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.biblLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.headLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.labelLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.listLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.noteLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.lLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.pLike.xml"/>
        <!-- used by model.divPart -->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.stageLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.featureVal.complex.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.featureVal.single.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.entryPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.entryPart.top.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.global.edit.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.global.spoken.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divPart.xml"/>


        <!-- <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.persTraitLike.xml"/> -->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.persStateLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.persEventLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.personLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.personPart.xml"/>
        <!-- <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.placeTraitLike.xml"/> -->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.placeNamePart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.placeStateLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.placeEventLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.orgPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.publicationStmtPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.availabilityPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.certLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.descLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.glossLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.quoteLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.qLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.rdgLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.respLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divWrapper.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divTopPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divTop.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.frontPart.drama.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.pLike.front.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divBottomPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divBottom.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.titlepagePart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.msQuoteLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.msItemPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.choicePart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.recordingPart.xml"/>
        <!-- in TS-->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.imprintPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.catDescPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.settingPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.textDescPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.castItemPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.physDescPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.addressLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.nameLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.persNamePart.xml"/>
        <!-- from ND -->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.global.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.featureVal.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.biblPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.frontPart.xml"/>
        <!--<p>These classes refer only to level 1 or to primitive lowlevel
classes or to elements</p>-->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.addrPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.pPart.data.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.inter.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.common.xml"/>
        <!-- needs model.inter -->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.phrase.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.limitedPhrase.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divGenLike.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.div1Like.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.div2Like.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.div3Like.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.div4Like.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.div5Like.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.div6Like.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.div7Like.xml"/>

        <!-- remainder are left overs -->
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.applicationLike.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.teiHeaderPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.sourceDescPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.encodingDescPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.editorialDeclPart.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/model.profileDescPart.xml"/>

      </div>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="STmacros">
    <head>Macros</head>
    <p>The infrastructure module defined by this chapter also declares a number of
        <term>macros</term>, or shortcut names for frequently occurring parts of other declarations.
      Macros are used in two ways in the TEI scheme: to stand for frequently-encountered content
      models, or parts of content models (<ptr target="#STECST"/>); and to stand for attribute
      datatypes (<ptr target="#DTYPES"
      />).<!--Macros are implemented
as patterns in the RELAX NG schema fragments, and as parameter
entities in the XML DTD fragments.--></p>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="STECST">
      <head>Standard Content Models</head>
      <p>As far as possible, the TEI schemas use the following set of frequently-encountered content
        models to help achieve consistency among different elements. <specList>
          <specDesc key="macro.paraContent"/>
          <specDesc key="macro.limitedContent"/>
          <specDesc key="macro.phraseSeq"/>
          <specDesc key="macro.phraseSeq.limited"/>
          <specDesc key="macro.schemaPattern"/>
          <specDesc key="macro.specialPara"/>
          <specDesc key="macro.xtext"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>The present version of the TEI Guidelines includes some 500 different elements. <ptr
          target="#tab-content-models"/> shows, in descending order of frequency, the seven most
        commonly used content models.<table xml:id="tab-content-models" rend="display">
          <row role="label">
            <cell>Content model</cell>
            <cell>Number of elements using this</cell>
            <cell>Description</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>macro.phraseSeq</cell>
            <cell>83</cell>
            <cell>any combination of text with elements from the <ident type="class"
                >model.gLike</ident>, <ident type="class">model.global</ident>, or <ident
                type="class">model.phrase</ident> classes</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>macro.paraContent</cell>
            <cell>49</cell>
            <cell>macro.phraseSeq with the addition of <ident type="class"
              >model.inter</ident></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>empty</cell>
            <cell>39</cell>
            <cell> elements that have no content</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>macro.specialPara</cell>
            <cell>24</cell>
            <cell>macro.paraContent with the addition of <ident type="class"
              >model.divPart</ident></cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>macro.phraseSeq.limited</cell>
            <cell>24</cell>
            <cell>a subset of <ident type="class">model.phrase</ident> appropriate for use in
              non-transcriptional contexts</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>text</cell>
            <cell>21</cell>
            <cell>plain untagged text</cell>
          </row>
          <row>
            <cell>macro.xtext</cell>
            <cell>19</cell>
            <cell>any combination of text with elements from the <ident type="class"
                >model.gLike</ident> class </cell>
          </row>
        </table></p>
      <specGrp>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/macro.paraContent.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/macro.limitedContent.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/macro.phraseSeq.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/macro.phraseSeq.limited.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/macro.specialPara.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/macro.xtext.xml"/>
      </specGrp>
    </div>
    <div type="div3" xml:id="DTYPES">
      <head>Datatype Macros</head>
      <p>The values which attributes may take in a TEI schema are defined, for the most part, by
        reference to a TEI <term>datatype</term>. Each such datatype is defined in terms of other
        primitive datatypes, derived mostly from <ref target="http://www.w3.org/TR/xmlschema-2/">W3C
          Schema Datatypes</ref>, literal values, or other datatypes. This indirection makes it
        possible for a TEI application to set constraints either globally or in individual cases, by
        redefining the datatype definition or the reference to it respectively. In some cases, the
        TEI datatype includes additional usage constraints which cannot be enforced by existing
        schema languages, although a TEI-compliant processor should attempt to validate them (see
        further discussion in chapter <ptr target="#CF"/>).</p>
      <p>Where literal values or name tokens are used in a datatype definition, an associated value
        list supplies definitions for the significance of suggested or (in the case of closed lists)
        all possible values.</p>
      <!-- but can we put a valList in a macroSpec ? -->
      <p>TEI-defined datatypes may be grouped into those which define normalized values for numeric
        quantities, probabilities, or temporal expressions, those which define various kinds of
        shorthand codes or keys, and those which define pointers or links.</p>
      <p>The following datatypes are used for attributes which are intended to hold normalized
        values of various kinds. First, expressions of quantity or probability: <specList>
          <specDesc key="data.certainty"/>
          <specDesc key="data.probability"/>
          <specDesc key="data.numeric"/>
          <specDesc key="data.count"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Examples of attributes using the <ident type="datatype">data.probability</ident> datatype
        include <att>degree</att> on <gi>damage</gi> or <gi>certainty</gi>; examples of <ident
          type="datatype">data.numeric</ident> include <att>quantity</att> on members of the <ident
          type="class">att.measurement</ident> class or <att>value</att> on <gi>numeric</gi>;
        examples of <ident type="datatype">data.count</ident> include <att>cols</att> on
          <gi>cell</gi> and <gi>table</gi>.</p>
      <specGrp xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xml:id="DTYPES-1"
        n="Numeric Datatypes">
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.certainty.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.probability.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.numeric.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.count.xml"/>
      </specGrp>
      <p>Next, the datatypes used for attributes which are intended to hold normalized dates or
        times, durations, or truth values: <specList>
          <specDesc key="data.duration.w3c"/>
          <specDesc key="data.duration.iso"/>
          <specDesc key="data.temporal.w3c"/>
          <specDesc key="data.temporal.iso"/>
          <specDesc key="data.truthValue"/>
          <specDesc key="data.xTruthValue"/>
          <specDesc key="data.language"/>
          <specDesc key="data.sex"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <p>Note that in each of these cases the values used are those recommended by existing
        international standards: ISO 8601 as profiled by <title>XML Schema Part 2: Datatypes Second
          Edition</title> in the case of durations, times, and date; W3C Schema datatypes in the
        case of truth values; BCP 47 in the case of language; and ISO 5218 in the case of sex.</p>
      <specGrp xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xml:id="DTYPES-2"
        n="Normalized Datatypes">
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.temporal.w3c.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.duration.w3c.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.truthValue.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.xTruthValue.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.language.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.sex.xml"/>
      </specGrp>
      <p>The following datatypes have more specialized uses: <specList>
          <specDesc key="data.outputMeasurement"/>
          <specDesc key="data.namespace"/>
          <specDesc key="data.pattern"/>
          <!-- only one usage -->
          <specDesc key="data.point"/>
          <specDesc key="data.pointer"/>
          <specDesc key="data.version"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <specGrp xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xml:id="DTYPES-3"
        n="Notation and pointer datatypes">
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.namespace.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude"
          href="../../Specs/data.outputMeasurement.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.pattern.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.point.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.pointer.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.version.xml"/>
      </specGrp>
      <p>By far the largest number of TEI attributes take values which are coded values or names of
        some kind. These values may be constrained or defined in a number of different ways, each of
        which is given a different name, as follows: <specList>
          <!--specDesc key="data.key"/-->
          <specDesc key="data.word"/>
          <specDesc key="data.text"/>
          <specDesc key="data.name"/>
          <specDesc key="data.enumerated"/>
          <specDesc key="data.code"/>
        </specList>
      </p>
      <!-- <p>The attributes <att>key</att> provided by the <ident type="class">att.canonical</ident> class is currently the only attribute
of type <ident type="datatype">data.key</ident>. It is used to supply
an externally-defined identifier, such as a database key or
filename. Because such identifiers are externally-defined, no
constraints are placed on their possible values: any string of Unicode
characters may be used. Any constraints on their values, such as the
rules for constructing a valid database key in a particular system,
may be documented by a <gi>tagUsage</gi> element in the TEI Header,
but are not enforced by the datatype as defined here. Such
system-specific constraints may however be added to a TEI schema by
using the customization techniques methods described in <ptr
target="#MD"/>.</p>-->
      <!-- removed as we don't now use data.key LB 2012-06-17-->
      <p>Attributes of type <ident type="datatype">data.word</ident>, such as <att>age</att> on
          <gi>person</gi>, are used to supply an identifier expressed as any kind of single token or
        word. The TEI places a few constraints on the characters which may be used for this purpose:
        only Unicode characters classified as letters, digits, punctuation characters, or symbols
        can appear in an attribute value of this kind. Note in particular that such values cannot
        include whitespace characters. Legal values include <val>cholmondeley</val>, <val>été</val>,
          <val>1234</val>, <val>e_content</val>, or <val>xml:id</val>, but not <val>grand
          wazoo</val>. Attributes of this kind are sometimes used to associate (by co-reference)
        elements of different types.</p>
      <p>Where identifiers are defined externally, for example as part of a database or file system,
        the inability to include whitespace or other special characters in a value may be
        problematic. In other cases, it may also be simply more convenient to supply a short
        sequence of natural language words including spaces as a single value. For these reasons, we
        also provide a datatype <ident>data.text</ident> which does permit whitespace and indeed any
        other Unicode character. Legal values include <val>cholmondeley</val>, <val>été</val>,
          <val>1234</val>, <val>e-content</val>, <val>xml:id</val>, and <val>grand wazoo</val>. This
        datatype should be used with care since XML will not normalise whitespace characters within
        it: for example the values <code>n="a b"</code> (two spaces) and <code>n="a b"</code> (three
        spaces) would be considered distinct. This case should be distinguished from that of an
        attribute permitting multiple values, each of which may be separated by whitespace which
          <emph>will</emph> be normalised (see further <ptr target="#TD-datatypes"/>). </p>
      <p>Attributes of type <ident type="datatype">data.name</ident> are similar to those of type
          <ident type="datatype">data.word</ident>, but with the additional constraint that they
        must be legal XML identifiers, as defined by the XML 1.0 specification, or successors.
        Hence, they may not begin with digits or punctuation characters. Legal identifiers include
          <val>cholmondeley</val>, <val>été</val>, <val>e_content</val>, or <val>xml:id</val>, but
        not <val>grand wazoo</val> or <val>1234</val>. Attributes of this kind are typically used to
        represent XML element or attribute names.</p>
      <p>Attributes of type <ident type="datatype">data.enumerated</ident>, such as <att>new</att>
        on <gi>shift</gi> or <att>evidence</att> supplied by <ident type="class"
          >att.editLike</ident>, have the same definition as <ident type="datatype"
          >data.word</ident> above, with the added constraint that the word supplied is taken from a
        specific list of possibilities. In each case, the element or class specification which
        includes the definition for the attribute will also contain a list of possible values,
        together with a prose description of their intended significance. This list may be open (in
        which case the list is advisory), or closed (in which case it determines the range of legal
        values). In this latter case, the datatype will not be <ident type="datatype"
          >data.enumerated</ident>, but an explicit list of the possible values.</p>
      <p>Attributes of type <ident type="datatype">data.code</ident> are similar in function, in
        that they also supply encoded names for values which are defined in more detail elsewhere.
        In this case, however, the full definition is supplied as content of another XML element,
        typically but not necessarily in the same document, and it is referenced by means of a
        pointer.</p>
      <specGrp xmlns:rng="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0" xml:id="DTYPES-4"
        n="Coded value datatypes">
        <!--<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.key.xml"/>-->

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.word.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.text.xml"/>
        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.code.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.name.xml"/>

        <include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/data.enumerated.xml"/>
      </specGrp>
      <p>An attribute may, of course, take more than one value of a given type, for example a list
        of pointer values, or a list of words. In the TEI scheme, this information is regarded as a
        property of the <gi>datatype</gi> element used to document the attribute in question rather
        than as a distinct <soCalled>datatype</soCalled>. See further <ptr target="#TD-datatypes"
        />.</p>
    </div>
  </div>
  <div type="div2" xml:id="STOV">
    <head>The TEI Infrastructure Module</head>
    <p>The <ident type="module">tei</ident> module defined by this chapter is a required component
      of any TEI schema. It provides declarations for all datatypes, and initial declarations for
      the attribute classes, model classes, and macros used by other modules in the TEI scheme. Its
      components are listed below in alphabetical order:<moduleSpec xml:id="DSTTEI2" ident="tei"
        type="core">
        <altIdent type="FPI">TEI Infrastructure</altIdent>
        <desc>Declarations for classes, datatypes, and macros available to all TEI modules</desc>
        <desc xml:lang="fr">Infrastructure de la TEI</desc>
        <desc xml:lang="zh-TW">所有TEI模組可用的元素集、資料類型、巨集指令之宣告</desc>
        <desc xml:lang="it">Dichiarazione di classi, tipi di dati (datatype)e macro disponibili in
          tutti i moduli TEI</desc>
        <desc xml:lang="pt">Declaraçoes de classes, tipos de dados, e macros disponíveis em todos os
          módulos TEI </desc>
        <desc xml:lang="ja">全TEIモジュールで使用可能なデータ型，クラス，マクロ．</desc>
      </moduleSpec>
    </p>
    <p>The order in which declarations are made within the infrastructure module is critical, since
      several class declarations refer to others, which must therefore precede them. Other
      constraints on the order of declarations derive from the way in which the modularity of the
      TEI scheme is implemented in different schema languages. The XML DTD fragment implementing
      this TEI module makes extensive use of <term>parameter entities</term> and <term>marked
        sections</term> to effect a kind of conditional construction; the RELAX NG schema fragment
      similarly predeclares a number of patterns with null (<soCalled>notAllowed</soCalled>) values.
      These issues are further discussed in chapter <ptr target="#IM"/>.</p>

  </div>
</div>
