<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="TC" n="19">
<head>Critical Apparatus</head>
<p>Scholarly editions of texts, especially texts of great antiquity or
importance, often record some or all of the known variations among
different <term>witnesses</term> to the text.  Witnesses to a text may
include authorial or other manuscripts, printed editions of the work,
early translations, or quotations of a work in other texts.
Information concerning variant readings of a text may be accumulated in
highly structured form in a critical apparatus of variants.  This
chapter defines a module for use in encoding such an
apparatus of variants, which may be used in conjunction with any of the
modules defined in these Guidelines.  It also defines an element
class which provides extra attributes for some elements of the core tag
set when this module is selected.</p>

<p>Information about variant readings (whether or not represented by a
critical apparatus in the source text) may be recorded in a series of
<term>apparatus entries</term>, each entry documenting one
<term>variation</term>, or set of readings, in the text.  Elements for the
apparatus entry and readings, and for the documentation of the witnesses
whose readings are included in the apparatus, are described in
section <ptr target="#TCAPLL"/>. Special tags for fragmentary witnesses are
described in section <ptr target="#TCAPMI"/>.  The available methods for
embedding the apparatus in the rest of the text, or for linking an
external apparatus to the base text, are described in section <ptr target="#TCAPLK"/>.  Finally, several extra attributes for some tags of the
core tag set, made available when the additional tag set for text
criticism is selected, are documented in section <ptr target="#PHCO"/>.
	</p>

<p>Many examples given in this chapter refer to the following texts
of the opening (usually just line 1) of Chaucer's <title>Wife of
Bath's Prologue</title>, as it appears in each of the four different
manuscripts
<list type="simple">
<item>Ellesmere, Huntingdon Library 26.C.9 (<label>El</label>)
<!--<q rend="display">Experience though noon Auctoritee /
Were in this world, were right ynogh to me /
To speke of wo that is in mariage; ...</q>--></item>
<item>Hengwrt, National Library of Wales, Aberystwyth,
Peniarth 392D (<label>Hg</label>)
<!--<q rend="display">Experience thogh noon Auctoritee /
Were in this world, is right ynogh for me /
To speke of wo that is in mariage; ...</q>--></item>
<item> British Library Lansdowne 851 (<label>La</label>)
<!--<q rend="display">Experiment thouh none auctorite /
Were in this world, is right ynohe for me /
To speke of wo that is in mariage; ...</q>--></item>
<item>Bodleian Library Rawlinson Poetic 149 (<label>Ra2</label>)
<!--<q rend="display">Eryment though none auctorite /
Were in this world, it is right ynow for me /
To speke of wo that is in mariage; ...</q>-->
</item></list></p>

<div type="div2" xml:id="TCAPLL"><head>The Apparatus Entry, Readings, and Witnesses</head>
<p>This section introduces the fundamental markup methods used to encode
textual variations:
<list type="simple">
<item>the <gi>app</gi> element for entries in the critical apparatus:
see section <ptr target="#TCAPEN"/>.</item>
<item>elements for identifying individual readings: see section <ptr target="#TCAPLR"/>.</item>
<item>ways of grouping readings together: see section <ptr target="#TCAPSU"/>.</item>
<item>methods of identifying which witnesses support a particular
reading, and for describing the witnesses included in the
apparatus: see section <ptr target="#TCAPLW"/>.</item>
<item>elements for indicating which portions of a text are covered by
fragmentary witnesses: see section <ptr target="#TCAPMI"/>.</item></list></p>
<p>The <gi>app</gi> element is in one sense a more  sophisticated and
complex version of the <gi>choice</gi> element introduced in <ptr target="#COEDCOR"/> as a way of marking points where the encoding of a passage
in a single source may be carried out in more than one way. Unlike
<gi>choice</gi>, however, the <gi>app</gi> element allows for the
representation of many different versions of the same passage taken
from different sources.</p>

<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPEN"><head>The Apparatus Entry</head>
<p>Individual textual variations are encoded using the <gi>app</gi>
element, which groups together all the readings constituting the
variation.  The identification of discrete textual variations or
apparatus entries is not a purely mechanical process; different editors
may group readings differently.  No rules are given here as to how to
group readings into apparatus entries; the tags given here may be used
to group readings in whatever way the editor finds most perspicuous or
useful.</p>
<p>The individual apparatus entry is encoded with the <gi>app</gi>
element:
<specList><specDesc key="app" atts="type from to loc"/></specList></p>
<p>The attributes <att>loc</att>, <att>from</att>, and <att>to</att>,
are used to link the apparatus entry to the base text, if present.  In
such cases, several methods
may be used for such linkage, each involving a slightly different usage
for these attributes.  Linkage between text and apparatus is described
below in section <ptr target="#TCAPLK"/>. For the use of the
<gi>app</gi> element without a base text, see <ptr target="#TCAPPS"/>. </p>
<p>Each <gi>app</gi> element comprises one or more readings, which in
turn are encoded using the <gi>rdg</gi> or other elements, as described
in the next section.  A very simple partial apparatus for the first line
of the <title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> might take a form
something like this:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app>
   <rdg wit="#El">Experience though noon Auctoritee</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#La">Experiment thouh noon Auctoritee</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment though none auctorite</rdg>
</app></egXML>
Of course, in practice the apparatus will be somewhat more complex.
Specifically, it may be desired to
record more obviously that manuscripts El and La agree on the
words <q>noon Auctoritee</q>, to indicate a preference for one
reading, etc.  The following sections on
readings, subvariation, and witness information describe some of the
more important complications which can arise.</p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTCAPEN" n="Apparatus entry">










&app;





</specGrp></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPLR"><head>Readings</head>
<p>Individual readings are the crucial elements in any critical
apparatus of variants.  The following elements should be used to tag
individual readings within an apparatus entry:
<specList><specDesc key="lem"/><specDesc key="rdg"/></specList>
N.B. the term <term>lemma</term> is used here in the text-critical
sense of <q>the reading accepted as that of the original or of the
base text</q>. This sense differs from that in which the word is used
elsewhere in the Guidelines, for example as in the attribute
<att>lemma</att> where the intended sense is <q>the root form of
an inflected word</q>, or  <q>the heading
of an entry in a reference book, especially a dictionary</q>. <!-- nor with
<q>a subsidiary proposition introduced in the proof of some other
proposition; a helping theorem.</q>--></p>
<p>In recording readings within an apparatus entry, the <gi>rdg</gi>
element may always be used; each <gi>app</gi> must contain at least one
<gi>rdg</gi>.</p>
<p>The <gi>lem</gi> element may also be used, under some circumstances,
to record the base text of the source edition, to mark the readings of a
base witness, to indicate the preference of an editor or encoder for a
particular reading, or to make clear, in cases of ambiguity, precisely
which portion of the main text the variation applies to.  Those who
prefer to work without the notion of a base text may prefer not to use
it at all.  How it is used depends in part on the method chosen for
linking the apparatus to the text; for more information, see section
<ptr target="#TCAPLK"/>.</p> 
<p>Readings may be encoded individually, or grouped for perspicuity
using the <gi>rdgGrp</gi> element described in section <ptr target="#TCAPSU"/>.</p>
<p>As members of the attribute class <ident type="class">att.textCritical</ident>,
both of these elements inherit the following attributes.  Some of
these attributes are intelligible only if the reading is ascribed to a
single witness; others have no such restriction.
<specList><specDesc key="att.textCritical" atts="wit type cause varSeq
hand"/></specList>
This class also inherits the following attributes from the <ident
type="class">att.responsibility</ident> class: 
<specList><specDesc key="att.responsibility" atts="resp cert"/></specList>
As elsewhere, these attributes may be used to indicate the 
person responsible for the editorial decision being recorded, and also
the degree of certainty associated with that decision by the person
carrying out the encoding. 

</p>
<p>The <att>wit</att> attribute identifies the witnesses which have the
reading in question.  It is required if the apparatus gathers together
readings from different witnesses, but may be omitted in an apparatus
recording the readings of only one witness, e.g. substitutions,
divergent opinions on what is in the witness or on how to expand
abbreviations, etc.  Even in such a one-witness apparatus, however,
the <att>wit</att> attribute may still be useful when it is desired to
record the occurrence of a particular reading in some other witness.
For other methods of identifying the witnesses to a reading, see
section <ptr target="#TCAPLW"/>.
	</p>
<p>The <att>type</att> attribute allows the encoder to classify readings
in any convenient way, for example as substantive variants of the lemma:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app>
   <lem wit="#El #Hg">Experience</lem>
   <rdg wit="#La" type="substantive">Experiment</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Ra2" type="substantive">Eryment</rdg>
</app></egXML>
or as orthographic variants:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app>
   <lem wit="#El #Ra2">though</lem>
   <rdg wit="#La" type="orthographic">thouh</rdg>
</app></egXML></p>
<p>The <att>varSeq</att> and <att>cause</att> attributes may be used to
convey information on the sequence and cause of variation.  In the
following apparatus fragment, the reading <mentioned>Eryment</mentioned> is
tagged as sequential to (derived from) the reading
<mentioned>Experiment</mentioned>, and the cause
is given as loss of the abbreviation for <mentioned>per</mentioned>.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app>
   <rdg wit="#La" varSeq="1">Experiment</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Ra2" cause="abbreviation_loss" varSeq="2">Eryment</rdg>
</app></egXML></p>
<p>If a manuscript is written in several hands, and it is desired to
report which hand wrote a particular reading, the <att>hand</att>
attribute should be used.  For example, in the Munich manuscript
containing the <title>Carmina Burana</title>,
the word <mentioned>alle</mentioned> has been changed
to <mentioned>allen</mentioned>:
<egXML xml:lang="gmh" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COBICOR-eg-251"><l>Swaz hi gât umbe</l>
<l>daz sint alle megede,</l>
<l>die wellent ân man</l>
<l>
   <app>
      <rdg wit="#Mu" varSeq="1" hand="#m1">alle</rdg>
      <rdg wit="#Mu" cause="nachgetragen" varSeq="2" hand="#m2">allen</rdg>
   </app>
disen sumer gân.</l>
</egXML>
<!-- Des Minnesangs Fr&uuml;hling, ed.  Hugo Moser and        -->
	<!-- Helmut Tervooren (Stuttgart:  Hirzel, 1977), I, 20.      -->
	<!-- (Anonymous VI).                                          --></p>
<p>Similarly, if a witness is hard to decipher, it may be desired to
indicate responsibility for the claim that a particular reading is
supported by a particular witness.  In line 2212a of
<title>Beowulf</title>, for example, the manuscript is read in different
ways by different scholars; the editor Klaeber prints one text, using
parentheses to indicate his expansion, and
records in the apparatus two different accounts of the manuscript
reading, by Zupitza and Chambers:<note place="bottom">For the sake of
legibility in the example, long marks
over vowels are omitted. </note>
<egXML xml:lang="ang" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TCAPLR-eg-11"><l>se ðe on
  <app>
     <rdg wit="#Kl">hea(um) h(æþ)e</rdg>
     <rdg wit="#ms" resp="#Z">heaðo hlæwe</rdg>
     <rdg wit="#ms" resp="#Cha">heaum hope</rdg>
  </app></l>
<l>hord beweotode,</l></egXML>
<!-- He also records the fact that Holthausen, editions 1-5,  -->
	<!-- and Sch&uuml;cking follow Zupitza's reading of the ms.   -->
	<!-- So in 'real life' this will require a witDetail          -->
	<!-- element, I think.                                        --></p>
<p>The <att>hand</att> and <att>resp</att> attributes are intelligible
only on an element recording a reading from a single witness, and should
not be used if more than one witness is given on the same <gi>rdg</gi>
or <gi>lem</gi> element.  If more than one witness is given for the
reading, they are undefined.  To convey this information when the
witness is one among several, the <gi>witDetail</gi> element should be
used; see section <ptr target="#TCAPLW"/>.</p>
<p>Where there is a greater weight of editorial discussion and
interpretation than can conveniently be expressed through the attributes
provided on these elements (for example where there are multiple
witnesses for a single reading or
multiple editorial responsibility for an emendation) this information
can be attached to the apparatus in a note, or recorded in the feature
structure notation defined in chapter <ptr target="#FS"/>.  In particular,
such recurring text-critical situations as palaeographic confusion of
particular letters, or homœoarchy or homœoteleuton involving specific
character groups, may lend themselves to feature structure treatment.
Information concerning these recurrent situations may be encoded into
database-like fragments within the text which would then be available to
sophisticated computer-assisted analysis.  Further work remains to be
done on such mechanisms, however, and so no examples are given here of
the use of feature structures in text-critical apparatus.</p>
<p>The <gi>note</gi> element may also be used to record the specific
wording of notes in the apparatus of the source edition, as here in
a transcription of Friedrich Klaeber's note on <title>Beowulf</title>
2207a:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TCAPLR-eg-11"><l n="2207a">syððan Beowulfe
<note resp="#Kl" place="app">Fol. 179a <mentioned>beowulfe</mentioned>.
  Folio 179, with the last page (Fol. 198b), is the worst part of the
  entire MS. It has been freshened up by a later hand, but not always
  correctly. Information on doubtful readings is in the notes of
  Zupitza and Chambers.</note></l>
<l n="2207b">brade rice</l>
</egXML>
<!-- Klaeber, app. to 2207.                                   -->
Notes providing details of the reading of one particular witness should
be encoded using the specialized <gi>witDetail</gi> element described in
section <ptr target="#TCAPLW"/>.</p>
<p>Encoders should be aware of the distinct fields of use of the
attribute values <att>wit</att>, <att>hand</att>, and <att>resp</att>.
Broadly, <att>wit</att> identifies the physical entity in which the
reading is found (manuscript, clay tablet, papyrus, printed edition);
<att>hand</att> refers to the agent responsible for inscribing that
reading in that physical entity (scribe, author, inscriber, hand 1, hand
2); <att>resp</att> indicates the scholar responsible for asserting the
existence of that reading in that physical entity.  In some cases, the
categories may blur:  a scholar may produce an edition introducing
readings for which he or she is responsible; that edition may itself
become a witness in a later critical apparatus.  Thus, readings
introduced as corrections in the earlier edition will be seen in the
later apparatus as witnessed by the earlier edition.  As observed in the
discussion concerning the discrimination of <att>hand</att> and
<att>resp</att> in transcription of primary sources in section <ptr target="#PHHR"/>, the division of layers of responsibility through various
scholars for particular aspects of a particular reading may require the
more complex mechanisms for assigning responsibility described in
chapter <ptr target="#CE"/>.</p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTCAPLR" n="Readings">










&lem;















&rdg;





</specGrp></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPSU"><head>Indicating Subvariation in Apparatus Entries</head>
<p>The <gi>rdgGrp</gi> element may be used to group readings, either
because they have identical values on one or more attributes, or because
they are seen as forming a self-contained variant sequence, or for some
other reason.  This grouping of readings is entirely optional:  no such
grouping of readings is required.
<specList><specDesc key="rdgGrp"/></specList></p>
<p>The <gi>rdgGrp</gi> element is a member of class <ident type="class">att.textCritical</ident> and therefore can carry the
<att>wit</att>, <att>type</att>, <att>cause</att>, <att>varSeq</att>,
<att>hand</att>, and <att>resp</att> attributes described in the
preceding section.  When values for any of these attributes are given
on a <gi>rdgGrp</gi> element, the values given are inherited by the
<gi>rdg</gi> or <gi>lem</gi> elements nested within the reading group,
unless overridden by a new specification on the individual reading
element.</p>
<p>To indicate that both Hg and La vary only orthographically from the
lemma, one might tag both readings <tag>rdg type='orthographic'</tag>,
as shown in the preceding section.  This fact can be expressed more
perspicuously, however, by grouping their readings into a
<gi>rdgGrp</gi>, thus:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app>
   <lem wit="#El #Ra2">though</lem>
   <rdgGrp type="orthographic">
      <rdg wit="#La">thogh</rdg>
      <rdg wit="#Hg">thouh</rdg>
   </rdgGrp>
</app></egXML></p>
<p>Similarly, <gi>rdgGrp</gi> may be used to organize the substantive
variants of an apparatus entry.  Editors may need to indicate that each
of a group of witnesses may be taken as all supporting a particular
reading, even though there may be variation concerning the exact form of
that reading in, or the degree of support offered by, those witnesses.
For example:  one may identify three substantive variants on the first
word of Chaucer's <title>Wife of Bath's Prologue</title> in the
manuscripts:  these might be expressed in regularized spelling as
<mentioned>Experience</mentioned>, <mentioned>Experiment</mentioned>, and <mentioned>Eriment</mentioned>.  In fact, the
manuscripts display many different spellings of these words, and a
scholar may wish both to show that the manuscripts have all these
variant spellings and that these variant spellings actually support only
the three regularized spelling forms.  One may term these variant
spellings as <soCalled>subvariants</soCalled> of the regularized
spelling forms.</p>
<p>This subvariation can be expressed within an <gi>app</gi> element
by gathering the readings into three groups according to the
normalized form of their reading.  All the readings within each group
may be accounted subvariants of the main reading for the group, which
may be indicated by tagging it as a <gi>lem</gi> element or as
<tag>rdg type='groupBase'</tag>.</p>
<p>In this example, the different subvariants on <mentioned>Experience</mentioned>,
<mentioned>Experiment</mentioned>, and <mentioned>Eriment</mentioned> are held within three
<gi>rdgGrp</gi> elements nested within the enclosing <gi>app</gi>
element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app type="substantive">
    <rdgGrp type="subvariants">
         <lem wit="#El #Hg">Experience</lem>
        <rdg wit="#Ha4">Experiens</rdg>
     </rdgGrp>
    <rdgGrp type="subvariants">
        <lem wit="#Cp #Ld1">Experiment</lem>
        <rdg wit="#La">Ex<g ref="#per"/>iment</rdg>
    </rdgGrp>
    <rdgGrp type="subvariants">
        <lem>Eriment<wit>[unattested]</wit></lem>
        <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
     </rdgGrp>
</app></egXML>
From this, one may deduce that the regularized reading <mentioned>Experience</mentioned>
is supported by all three manuscripts El Hg Ha4, although the spelling
differs in Ha4, and that the regularized reading <mentioned>Eriment</mentioned> is
supported by Ra2, even though the form differs in that manuscript.
Accordingly, an application which recognizes that these apparatus
entries show subvariation may then assign all the witnesses instanced as
attesting the sub-variants on that lemma as actually supporting the
reading of the lemma itself at a higher level of classification.  Thus,
Ha4 here supports the reading <mentioned>Experience</mentioned> found in El and Hg, even
though it is spelt slightly differently in Ha4.</p>
<p>Reading groups may nest recursively, so that variants can be
classified to any desired depth.  Because apparatus entries may also
nest, the <gi>app</gi> element might also be used to group readings in
the same way.  The example above is substantially identical to the
following, which uses <gi>app</gi> instead of <gi>rdgGrp</gi>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app n="a1" type="substantive">
   <rdg wit="#El #Hg #Ha4">        
      <app n="a2" type="orthographic">
         <lem wit="#El #Hg">Experience</lem>
         <rdg wit="#Ha4">Experiens</rdg>
      </app>
   </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Cp #Ld1 #La">        
      <app n="a3" type="orthographic">
         <lem wit="#Cp #Ld1">Experiment</lem>
         <rdg wit="#La">Ex<g ref="#per"/>iment</rdg>
      </app>
   </rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Ra2">        
      <app n="a4" type="orthographic">
         <lem>Eriment<wit>[unattested]</wit></lem>
         <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
      </app>
   </rdg>
</app></egXML>
This expresses even more clearly than the previous encoding of this
material that at the highest level of classification (apparatus entry
A1), this variation has three normalized readings, and that the first of
these is supported by manuscripts El, Hg, and Ha4; the second by Cp,
Ld1, and La; and the third by Ra2.  Some encoders may find the use of
nested apparatus entries less intuitive than the use of reading groups,
however, so both methods of classifying the readings of a variation are
allowed.</p>
<p>Reading groups may also be used to bring together variants which form
an apparent developmental sequence, and to make clear that other
readings are not part of that sequence, as in the following example,
which makes clear that the variant sequence <mentioned>experiment</mentioned> to
<mentioned>eriment</mentioned> says nothing about the relative priority of
<mentioned>experiment</mentioned> and <mentioned>experience</mentioned>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app type="substantive">
    <rdgGrp type="subvariants">
        <lem wit="#El #Hg">Experience</lem>
        <rdg wit="#Ha4">Experiens</rdg>
    </rdgGrp>
    <rdgGrp type="sequence">
        <rdgGrp varSeq="1" type="subvariants">
            <lem wit="#Cp #Ld1">Experiment</lem>
            <rdg wit="#La">Ex<g ref="#per"/>iment</rdg>
        </rdgGrp>
        <rdgGrp varSeq="2" cause="abbreviation_loss" >
            <lem>Eriment<wit>[unattested]</wit></lem>
            <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
        </rdgGrp>
    </rdgGrp>
</app></egXML></p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTCAPSU" n="Reading Groups">










&rdgGrp;





</specGrp></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPLW"><head>Witness Information</head>
<p>A given reading is associated with the set of witnesses attesting it
by listing the witnesses in the <att>wit</att> attribute on the
<gi>rdg</gi>, <gi>lem</gi>, or <gi>rdgGrp</gi> element.  Special
mechanisms, described in the following sections, are needed to associate
annotation on a reading with one specific witness among several
(section <ptr target="#TCAPWD"/>), to transcribe witness information verbatim from a
source edition (section <ptr target="#TCSCWL"/>), and to identify the
formal lists of witnesses typically provided in the front matter of
critical editions (section <ptr target="#TCAPWL"/>).</p>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TCAPWD"><head>Witness Detail Information</head>
<p>When it is desired to give additional information about a particular
witness or witnesses for the reading, the information may be given in a
<gi>witDetail</gi> element. This is a specialized form of note, which
can be linked to both a reading and to one or more of the witnesses
for that reading. The former linkage is effected by the
<att>target</att> attribute which <gi>witDetail</gi> inherits from the
attribute class <ident type="class">att.pointing</ident>, and the
latter by the  <att>wit</att> attribute. 
<specList><specDesc key="att.pointing" atts="target"/>
<specDesc key="witDetail" atts="wit"/></specList></p>
<p>Unlike <gi>note</gi>, <gi>witDetail</gi>
cannot be included in the text at the point of attachment; it must point to
the reading(s) being annotated by means of its <att>target</att> attribute.  To
indicate, on the authority of editor PR, that the Ellesmere manuscript
has an ornamental capital in the word <mentioned>Experience</mentioned>, for
example, one might write:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app type="substantive">
    <rdgGrp type="subvariants">
        <lem xml:id="W026" wit="#El #Hg">Experience</lem>
        <rdg wit="#Ha4">Experiens</rdg>
    </rdgGrp>
</app>
<witDetail target="#W026" wit="#El" resp="#PR">Ornamental capital.</witDetail></egXML>
This encoding makes clear that the ornamental capital mentioned is in
the Ellesmere manuscript, and not in Hengwrt or Ha4. The <att>resp</att> attribute assigns responsibility to PR.</p>
<p>Like <gi>note</gi>, <gi>witDetail</gi> may be used to
record the specific wording of information in the source text, even when
the information itself is captured in some more formal way elsewhere.
The example from the <title>Carmina Burana</title> above (section <ptr target="#TCAPLR"/>), for example, might be extended thus, to record the
wording of the note explaining the variant:
<egXML xml:lang="gmh" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COBICOR-eg-251"><l>Swaz hi gât umbe</l>
<l>daz sint alle megede,</l>
<l>die wellent ân man</l>
<l>
   <app>
      <rdg wit="#Mu" hand="#m1">alle</rdg>
      <rdg xml:id="anon.6.4" wit="#Mu" hand="#m2">allen</rdg>
   </app>
disen sumer gân.</l>
<witDetail target="#anon.6.4" wit="#Mu">
   <ref>allen</ref>
   <mentioned>n</mentioned> nachgetragen.
</witDetail></egXML>
<!-- Des Minnesangs Fr&uuml;hling, ed.  Hugo Moser and        -->
	<!-- Helmut Tervooren (Stuttgart:  Hirzel, 1977), I, 20.      -->
	<!-- (Anonymous VI).                                          --></p>
<p>Observe that a single witness detail element may be linked to several
different readings (noting, for example, a recurrent phenomenon in a
particular manuscript) by having the <att>target</att> attribute point
at all the readings in question.  Similarly, feature structures
containing information about the text in a witness (whether
retroversion, regularization, or other) can also be linked to specific
<gi>lem</gi> and <gi>rdg</gi> instances.  See chapter <ptr target="#FS"/>.</p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTCAPWD" n="Witness Details">
&witDetail;
</specGrp></div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TCSCWL"><head>Witness Information in the Source</head>
<p>In the transcription of printed critical editions, it may be
desirable to retain for future reference the exact form in which the
source edition records the witnesses to a particular reading; this is
particularly important in cases of ambiguity in the information, or
uncertainty as to the correct interpretation.  The <gi>wit</gi>
element may be used to transcribe such lists of witnesses to a
particular reading.
<specList><specDesc key="wit"/></specList>
The <gi>wit</gi> list may appear following a <gi>rdg</gi>,
<gi>rdgGrp</gi>, or <gi>lem</gi> element in any apparatus entry, and
should be used only to transcribe the witness information in the form
found in the source.<!-- In particular, it should not be used as a substitute     -->
	<!-- for the <att>wit</att> attribute:  where present, the    -->
	<!-- information in the <gi>wit</gi> element and the          -->
	<!-- <att>wit</att> attribute should agree, unless the        -->
	<!-- encoder is uncertain about the interpretation of the     -->
	<!-- witness information in the source, or the encoder has    -->
	<!-- corrected an error in the source.                        -->
The advantage of holding witness information in the <att>wit</att>
attribute of <gi>lem</gi> or <gi>rdg</gi> is that <!-- this may make
it more convenient for -->an application can check that every
sigil<note place="foot">We use the term sigil as the English
equivalent of the Latin term <foreign>siglum</foreign> (sign)
traditionally used for the brief identifier associated with a
particular document.</note>  for the
identifier has been declared elsewhere in the document. Because the
<att>wit</att> attribute has declared datatype of one or more <ident type="datatype">data.pointer</ident> values, a check can be made that
readings are assigned only to witness sigla which have been identified
(using the <att>xml:id</att> attribute) within a <gi>listWit</gi>
element (see section <ptr target="#TCAPWL"/>). Such checking is more
difficult for witness sigla held as the content of a <gi>wit</gi>
element. <!--: an application program can check them, but parsers will
not.--> For this reason, it is recommended that encoders always hold
witness information in the <att>wit</att> attribute of <gi>lem</gi>
and <gi>rdg</gi>, where possible. Thus, as in the examples below, even
when a reference to a witness is exactly reproduced in the
<gi>wit</gi> element, the corresponding sigil for that witness can be
written into the <att>wit</att> attribute of the matching <gi>rdg</gi> or
<gi>lem</gi>. However, in cases where it is uncertain  how the witness
reference contained in the <gi>wit</gi> element should be interpreted,
or where no witness exists, the <att>wit</att> attribute on the
matching <gi>rdg</gi> or <gi>lem</gi> may be left empty. <egXML
   xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COBICOR-eg-251" xml:lang="gmh"><lg type="stanza"> <l xml:id="Diet1.1">Slăfest du, vriedel ziere?</l>
    <l xml:id="Diet1.2">wan wecket uns leider schiere;</l>
    <l xml:id="Diet1.3">ein vogellīn sŏ wol getăn</l>
    <l xml:id="Diet1.4">daz ist der linden an daz zwī gegăn.</l>
    </lg>
<app type="secondary" loc="Diet.1.1">
    <rdg wit="#Kb">slăfst</rdg> <wit>K(Ba)</wit>
    </app>
<app type="secondary" loc="Diet.1.2">
    <rdg wit="#Kv">Man</rdg> <wit>K(V)</wit>
    <rdg wit="#K">weckt</rdg> <wit>K (Wackernagel 401)</wit>
    <rdg wit="#Ju">Ich waen ez taget uns schiere</rdg>
    <wit>Jungbluth, Festschr. Pretzel 1963, 122.</wit>
    </app>
</egXML>
<!-- MF 39,18, ed. Moser/Tervooren, p. 66.                    -->
Of course, the sigil used for a particular witness in the source, as
recorded in the <gi>wit</gi> element, may well differ from that used
to indicated the same witness in the <att>wit</att> attribute, as
shown particularly in the apparatus for the second line of the poem
(Diet.1.2).</p>

<specGrp xml:id="DTCSCWL" n="Sourcetext Witness Lists in Apparatus">










&wit;





</specGrp></div>
<div type="div4" xml:id="TCAPWL"><head>The Witness List</head>
<p>A list of all identified witnesses should normally be supplied in
the front matter of the edition, or in the <gi>sourceDesc</gi> element
of its header. This may be given either as a simple bibliographic
list, using the <gi>listBibl</gi> element described in <ptr target="#COBI"/>, or as  a <gi>listWit</gi> element, which 
contains a series of <gi>witness</gi> elements.  Each <gi>witness</gi>
element may contain a brief characterisation of the witness, given as
one or more prose paragraphs. If more detailed information about
a manuscript witness is available, it should be represented using the
<gi>msDesc</gi> element provided by the <ident type="module">msdescription</ident>
module; a <gi>msDesc</gi> may appear within a <gi>listBibl</gi>. </p>
<p>Whether information about a particular witness is supplied by
means of a <gi>bibl</gi>, <gi>msDesc</gi>, or <gi>witness</gi>
element, a unique sigil for this source should always be
supplied,  using the global <att>xml:id</att> attribute. This
identifier can then be used
elsewhere to refer to this particular witness.  <specList><specDesc key="listWit"/><specDesc key="witness"/><specDesc key="msDesc"/><specDesc key="bibl"/><specDesc key="listBibl"/></specList></p>
<p>The minimal information provided by a witness list is thus the set of
sigla for all the witnesses named in the apparatus.  For example, the
witnesses referenced by the examples of this
chapter might simply be listed  thus:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><listWit>
   <witness xml:id="Chi3"/>
   <witness xml:id="Ha4"/>
   <witness xml:id="Ju"/> 
   <witness xml:id="K"/>  
   <witness xml:id="Kb"/>  
   <witness xml:id="Kl"/> 
   <witness xml:id="Kv"/>  
   <witness xml:id="Ld"/>
   <witness xml:id="Ld1"/> 
   <witness xml:id="Ln"/>
   <witness xml:id="Mu"/>  
   <witness xml:id="Ry2"/>
   <witness xml:id="Wa"/>  
   <witness xml:id="X"/>   
</listWit></egXML></p>
<p>It is more helpful, however, for witness lists to be somewhat
more informative:  each <gi>witness</gi> element should contain at
least a brief prose
description of the witness, perhaps including a bibliographic
citation, as in the following examples:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><listWit>
  <witness xml:id="El">Ellesmere, Huntingdon Library 26.C.9</witness>
  <witness xml:id="Hg">Hengwrt, National Library of Wales,
    Aberystwyth, Peniarth 392D</witness>
  <witness xml:id="Ra2">Bodleian Library Rawlinson Poetic 149
(see further <ptr target="http://example.com/msDescs#MSRP149"/>)</witness>
</listWit></egXML>
As the last example shows, the witness description here may be complemented
by a reference to a full
description of the manuscript supplied elsewhere, typically as the
content of a <gi>msDesc</gi> or <gi>bibl</gi> element. 
Alternatively, it may contain a whole paragraph of
commentary for each witness :
<egXML xml:lang="de" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#COBICOR-eg-251"><listWit>
   <witness xml:id="A">die sog. <soCalled>Kleine (oder alte)
      Heidelberger Liederhandschrift</soCalled>.
      <bibl>Universitätsbibliothek Heidelberg col. pal.
      germ. 357. Pergament, 45 Fll. 18,5 × 13,5 cm.</bibl>
      Wahrscheinlich die älteste der drei großen Hss. Sie
      <quote>datiert aus dem 13. Jahrhundert, etwa um 1275. Ihre Sprache
      weist ins Elsaß, evtl. nach Straßburg. Man geht wohl nicht
      fehl, in ihr eine Sammlung aus dem Stadtpatriziat zu sehen</quote>
      (<bibl><author>Blank</author>, [vgl. <ref>Lit. z. Hss. Bd. 2,
      S. 39</ref>] S. 14</bibl>). Sie enthält 34 namentlich
      genannte Dichter. <quote>Zu den Vorzügen von A gehört, daß
      sie kaum je bewußt geändert hat, so daß sie für
      manche Dichter ... oft den besten Text liefert</quote> (so wohl mit
      Recht <bibl><author>v. Kraus</author></bibl>).</witness>
   <witness xml:id="a">Bezeichnung <bibl><author>Lachmann</author>
      </bibl>s für die von einer 2. Hand auf bl. 40–43
      geschriebenen Strophen der Hs. A.</witness>
   <witness xml:id="B">die <soCalled>Weingartner (Stuttgarter)
      Liederhandschrift</soCalled>. <bibl>Württembergische
      Landesbibliothek Stuttgart, HB XIII poetae germanici 1.
      Pergament, 156 Bll. 15 × 11,5 cm; 25 teils ganzseitig,
      teils halbseitige Miniaturen.</bibl> Kaum vor 1306 in Konstanz
      geschrieben. Sie enthält Lieder von 25 namentlich genannten
      Dichtern. (Dazu kommen Gedichte von einigen ungenannten
      bzw. unbekannten Dichtern, ein Marienlobpreis und eine
      Minnelehre.)</witness>
</listWit></egXML>
<!-- Moser/Tervooren II: 39-40; the last bit of the entry for A omits some stuff -->
</p>
<p>It would however generally be preferable to represent such detailed
information using an appropriately structured <gi>msDesc</gi> element,
as discussed in chapter <ptr target="#MS"/>. Note also that if the
witnesses being recorded are not manuscripts but printed works, it
may be preferable to document them using the standard <gi>bibl</gi> or
<gi>biblStruct</gi> elements described in <ptr target="#COBI"/>, as in
this example:
<egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listBibl> 
<bibl xml:id="bcn_1482">T. Kempis, De la imitació de Jesuchrist e del
menyspreu del món (trad. Miquel Peres); Barcelona, 1482, Pere
Posa. Editio princeps.</bibl>
<bibl xml:id="val_1491">T. Kempis, Del menyspreu del món (trad. Miquel
Peres); València, 1491.</bibl>
<bibl xml:id="bcn_1518">T. Kempis, Libre del menysprey del món e de la
imitació de nostre senyor Déu Jesucrist, (trad. Miquel Peres);
Barcelona, 1518, Carles Amorós. </bibl>
</listBibl>
</egXML>
</p>
<p>In text-critical work it is customary to refer to frequently occurring
groups of witnesses by means of a single common sigil.  Such sigla may
be documented as pseudo-witnesses in their own right by including a
nested witness list within 
the witness list, which uses the sigil for the group as its
identifier, and supplies a fuller name for the group in its optional child
<gi>head</gi> element, before
 listing the other witnesses contained by the group. <!-- In this example, the group of
manuscripts of the <title>Canterbury Tales</title> which make up <soCalled>Constant
Group C</soCalled> are themselves first allocated sigla in individual
<gi>witness</gi> elements, and then those sigla are given as the
<att>included</att> value of a further <gi>witness</gi> element. --> 
For example, the Constant Group C of manuscripts comprising witnesses Cp, La,
and S12, might be represented as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<listWit>
<witness xml:id="Ellesmere">Ellesmere, Huntingdon Library 26.C.9</witness>
<!-- ... -->
<listWit xml:id="Con">
   <head>Constant Group C</head>
   <witness xml:id="Cp">Corpus Christi Oxford MS 198</witness>
   <witness xml:id="La">British Library Lansdowne 851</witness>
   <witness xml:id="Sl2">British Library Sloane MS 1686</witness>
</listWit>
</listWit></egXML>
<!--   <witness xml:id="c" included="#Cp #La #Sl2">Constant Group c</witness>-->
That the reading <mentioned>Experiment</mentioned> occurs in all three manuscripts
can now be indicated simply as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><rdg wit="#Con">Experiment</rdg></egXML>
<!-- What happens if both 'c' and 'La' are given, on two      -->
	<!-- different readings?  Needs clarification for next        -->
	<!-- revision.  Allow single-ms readings to override a        -->
	<!-- group?  What, then, about groups of groups, or about     -->
	<!-- overlapping groups?  Perhaps better to say that 'c'      -->
	<!-- *always* is the same as 'Cp La Sl2', with no             -->
	<!-- exceptions.  (msm)
	-->
Note that a single witness cannot  appear more than once in a witness list,
and therefore cannot be assigned to more than one group of witnesses.
</p>


<p>Situations commonly arise where there are many more or less
fragmentary witnesses, such that there may be quite distinct groups of
witnesses for different parts of a text or collection of texts.  One
may treat this with distinct <gi>listWit</gi> elements for each
different part.  Alternatively, one may have a single <gi>listWit</gi>
element at the beginning of the file or in its header listing all the
witnesses, partial and complete, for the text, with the attestation of
fragmentary witnesses indicated within the apparatus by use of the
<gi>witStart</gi> and <gi>witEnd</gi> elements described in section
<ptr target="#TCAPMI"/>.</p>
<p>If a witness list is provided, it may be unnecessary to give, in each
apparatus entry, an exhaustive list of the witnesses which agree with
the base text.  An application program can — in principle — compare
the witnesses given for each variant found with those given in the full
list of witnesses, subtracting from this list all the witnesses not
active at this point (perhaps because of lacuna, or because they contain
a variation on a different, overlapping lemma) and thence calculate all
the manuscripts agreeing with the base text.  In practice, encoders may
find it less error-prone to list all witnesses explicitly in each
apparatus entry.</p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTCAPLW" n="Witness Lists in Front Matter">










&listWit;















&witness;





</specGrp></div></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPMI"><head>Fragmentary Witnesses</head>
<p>If a witness is incomplete (whether a single fragment, a series of
fragments, or a relatively complete text with one or more lacunae), it
is usually desirable to record explicitly where its preserved portions
begin and end.  The following empty tags, which may occur within any
<gi>lem</gi> or <gi>rdg</gi> element, indicate the beginning or end of a
fragmentary witness or of a lacuna within a witness:
<specList><specDesc key="witStart"/><specDesc key="witEnd"/><specDesc key="lacunaStart"/><specDesc key="lacunaEnd"/></specList>
These elements constitute the class <ident type="class">model.rdgPart</ident>, members of which are permitted
within the elements <gi>lem</gi> and <gi>rdg</gi> when the module
defined by this chapter is included in a schema.</p>
<p>Suppose a fragment of a manuscript X of the <title>Wife of Bath's
Prologue</title> has a physical lacuna, and the text of the manuscript
begins with <mentioned>auctorite</mentioned>.  In an apparatus this might appear
thus, distinguished from the reading of other manuscripts by the
presence of the <gi>lacunaEnd</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app>
   <lem wit="#El #Hg">Auctoritee</lem>
   <rdg wit="#La #Ra2">auctorite</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#X"><lacunaEnd/>auctorite</rdg>
</app></egXML>
In some cases, the apparatus in the source may commence recording the
readings for a particular witness without its being clear whether the
previous absence of readings for this witness is due to a lacuna, or to
some other reason.  The <gi>witStart</gi> element may be used in this
circumstance:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app>
   <lem wit="#El #Hg">Auctoritee</lem>
   <rdg wit="#La #Ra2">auctorite</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#X"><witStart/>auctorite</rdg>
</app></egXML></p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTCFW" n="Fragmentary witnesses">










&witStart;















&witEnd;















&lacunaStart;















&lacunaEnd;





</specGrp></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="TCAPLK"><head>Linking the Apparatus to the Text</head>
<p>Three different methods may be used to link a critical
apparatus to the text:
<list type="ordered">
<item>the location-referenced method,</item>
<item>the double-end-point-attached method, and</item>
<item>the parallel segmentation method.</item></list></p>
<p>Both the location-referenced and the double end-point methods may be
used with either <term>in-line</term> or <term>external</term>
apparatus, the former dispersed within the base text, the latter held in
some separate location, within or outside the document with the base
text.  The parallel segmentation method does not use the concept of a
base text and may only be used for in-line apparatus.</p>
<p>Any document containing <gi>app</gi> elements requires a
<gi>variantEncoding</gi> declaration in the <gi>encodingDesc</gi>
element of its TEI header, thus:
<specList><specDesc key="variantEncoding" atts="method location"/></specList></p>

<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPLO"><head>The Location-referenced Method</head>
<p>The location-referenced method of encoding apparatus provides a
convenient method for encoding printed apparatus; in this method as in
most printed editions, the apparatus is linked to the base text by
indicating explicitly only the block of text on which there is a variant
(noted usually by a canonical reference scheme, or by line number in the
edition, such as <val>A 137</val> or <mentioned>Page 15 line 1</mentioned>).</p>
<p>If the location-referenced method is used for an apparatus stored
externally to the base text, the TEI header must have the
declaration:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><variantEncoding method="location-referenced" location="external"/></egXML></p>
<p>In the <gi>body</gi> of the document, the base text (here El) will
appear:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><text>
  <body> 
    <div n="WBP" type="prologue">
      <head>The Prologe of the Wyves Tale of Bathe</head>
      <l n="1">Experience though noon Auctoritee</l>
      <l>Were in this world ...</l>
    </div>
  </body>
</text></egXML></p>
<p>Elsewhere in the document, or in a separate file, the apparatus will
appear. On each <gi>app</gi> element, the <att>loc</att> attribute
should be specified to indicate where the variant occurs in the base
text.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app loc="WBP 1">
   <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
</app></egXML></p>
<p>If the same text is encoded using in-line storage, the apparatus is
dispersed through the base text block to which it refers.  In this case,
the location of the variant can be read from the line in which it
occurs.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><variantEncoding method="location-referenced" location="internal"/>
<!-- ... -->
<l n="1">Experience
  <app>
    <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
    <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
  </app>
  though noon Auctoritee</l>
<l>Were in this world ...</l></egXML></p>
<p>Since the location is not required to be exact, the apparatus for
a line might also appear at the end of the line:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l n="1">Experience though noon Auctoritee
  <app>
    <rdg wit="#La"> Experiment</rdg>
    <rdg wit="#Ra2"> Eryment</rdg>
  </app></l>
<l>Were in this world ...</l></egXML></p>
<p>When the apparatus is linked to the text by means of location
references, as shown here, it is not possible to find automatically the
precise portion of text varied by the readings.  In order to show
explicitly what portion of the base text is replaced by the variant
readings, the <gi>lem</gi> element may be used:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l n="1">Experience though noon Auctoritee
  <app>
    <lem wit="#El">Experience</lem>
    <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
    <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
  </app></l>
<l>Were in this world ...</l></egXML>
Often the lemma will have no attributes, being simply the
<soCalled>base text reading</soCalled> and requiring no qualification,
but it may optionally carry the normal attributes, as shown here.  Some
text critics prefer to abbreviate or elide the lemma, in order to save
space or trouble; such practice is not forbidden by these Guidelines,
but no recommendations are made for conventions of abbreviating the
lemma, whether abbreviation of each word, or suppression of all but the
first and last word, etc.</p>
<p>Where it is intended that the apparatus be complete enough to allow
the reconstruction of the witnesses (or at least of
their non-orthographic variations), simple location-reference methods
are unlikely to be as successful as the other two methods, which allow the
unambiguous reconstruction of the lemma from the encoding. The use of
(for example) an XPath expression denoting a text range rather than a
simple pointer may however obviate this necessity.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPDE"><head>The Double End-Point Attachment Method</head>
<p>In the double end-point attachment method, the beginning and end of
the lemma in the base text are both explicitly indicated.  It thus
differs from the location-referenced method, in which only the larger
span of text containing the lemma is indicated.  Double end-point
attachment permits unambiguous matching of each variant reading against
its lemma.  It or the parallel-segmentation method should be used in all
cases where this is desired, for example where the apparatus is intended
to enable full reconstruction of the text, or of the substantives, of
every witness.</p>
<p>When the double end-point attachment method is used, the
<att>from</att> and <att>to</att> attributes of the <gi>app</gi> element
are used to indicate the beginning and ending points of the reading in
the base text: their values are identifiers which occur at the
locations in question.  If no other markup is present there, the
beginning and ending points should be marked using the <gi>anchor</gi>
element defined in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.  In cases where it is not
possible to insert anchors within the base text (e.g. where the text is
on a read-only medium) the beginning and end of the lemma may be
indicated by using the <soCalled>indirect pointing</soCalled> mechanisms
discussed in chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.  Explicit anchors are more likely
to be reliable, and are therefore to be preferred.</p>
<p>The double end-point attachment method may be used with in-line or
external apparatus.  In the latter case, the base text (here El) will
appear with <gi>anchor</gi> elements inserted at every place where a
variant begins or ends (unless some element with an identifier
already begins or ends at that point):
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
    <variantEncoding method="double-end-point" location="external"/>
<!-- ... -->
      <div n="WBP" type="prologue"><head>The Prologe ... </head>
        <l n="1" xml:id="WBP.1">Experience<anchor xml:id="WBP-A2"/> though noon Auctoritee</l>
        <l>Were in this world ...</l> 
      </div> 
</egXML>
The apparatus will be separately encoded:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app from="#WBP.1" to="#WBP-A2">
   <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
</app></egXML>
No <gi>anchor</gi> element is needed at the beginning of the line, since
the <att>from</att> attribute can use the identifier for the
line as a whole; the lemma is assumed to run from the beginning of the
element indicated by the <att>from</att> attribute, to the end of that
indicated by the <att>to</att> attribute.  If no value is
given for <att>to</att>, the lemma runs from the beginning to the end of
the element indicated by the <att>from</att> attribute.</p>
<p>When the apparatus is encoded in-line, it is dispersed through the
base text.  Only the beginning of the lemma need be marked with an
<gi>anchor</gi>, since the <gi>app</gi> is inserted at the end of the
lemma, and itself therefore marks the end of the lemma.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><variantEncoding method="double-end-point" location="internal"/>
<!-- ... -->
<l n="1" xml:id="wbp.1">Experience
   <app from="#wbp.1">
      <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
      <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
   </app>
   though noon Auctoritee</l>
<l>Were in this world ...</l></egXML></p>
<p>The lemma need not be repeated within the <gi>app</gi> element in
this method, as it may be extracted reliably from the base text.  If an
exhaustive list of witnesses is available, it will also not be necessary
to specify just which manuscripts agree with the base text to enable
reconstruction of witnesses.  An application will be able to determine
the manuscripts that witness the base reading, by noting which witnesses
are attested as having a variant reading, and inferring the base text
reading for all others after adjusting for fragmentary witnesses and for
witnesses carrying overlapping variant readings.</p>
<p>Alternatively, if it is desired to make an explicit record of the
attestation of the base text, the <gi>lem</gi> element may be embedded
within <gi>app</gi>, carrying the witnesses to the base. Thus
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><app from="#WBP.1" to="#WBP-A2">
   <lem wit="#El #Hg">Experience</lem>
   <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
   <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
</app></egXML></p>
<p>This method is designed to cope with <soCalled>overlapping
lemmata</soCalled>. For example, at line 117 of the Wife of Bath's
Prologue, the manuscripts Hg (Hengwrt), El (Ellesmere), and Ha4 (British
Library Harleian 7334) read:
<list type="gloss">
<label>Hg</label><item>And of so parfit wys a wight ywroght</item>
<label>El</label><item>And for what profit was a wight ywroght</item>
<label>Ha4</label><item>And in what wise was a wight ywroght</item></list></p>
<p>In this case, one might wish to record <mentioned>in what wise was</mentioned> in Ha4
as a single variant for <mentioned>of so parfit wys</mentioned> in Hg, and <mentioned>was a
wight</mentioned> in El and Ha4 as a variant on <mentioned>wys a wight</mentioned> in Hg.  This method
can readily cope with such difficult situations, typically found in
large and complex traditions:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l xml:id="WBP.117" n="117"> And
  <anchor xml:id="WBP-A117.1"/> of so parfit
  <anchor xml:id="WBP-A117.2"/> wys
  <anchor xml:id="WBP-A117.3"/> a wight
  <anchor xml:id="WBP-A117.4"/> ywroght
  <app from="#WBP-A117.1" to="#WBP-A117.3">
    <lem wit="#Hg">of so parfit wys</lem>
    <rdg wit="#Ha4">in what wise was</rdg>
  </app>
  <app from="#WBP-A117.2" to="#WBP-A117.4">
    <lem wit="#Hg">wys a wight</lem>
    <rdg wit="#El #Ha4">was a wight</rdg>
  </app></l></egXML>
The parallel segmentation method, to be discussed next, cannot handle
overlaps among variants, and would require the individual variants to be
split into pieces.</p>
<p>Because creation and interpretation of double end-point attachment
apparatus will be lengthy and difficult it is likely that they will
usually be created and examined by scholars only with mechanical
assistance.</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TCAPPS"><head>The Parallel Segmentation Method</head>
<p>This method differs from the double end-point attachment method in
that all variants at any point of the text are expressed as variants
on one another.  In this method, no two variations can overlap,
although they may nest.  Thus, the concepts of a base text and of a
lemma become unnecessary:  the texts compared are divided into
matching segments all synchronized with one another.  This permits
direct comparison of any span of text in any witness with that in
any other witness.  It is also very easy with this method for an
application to extract the full text of any one witness from the
apparatus.</p>
<p>This method will (by definition) always be satisfactory when there
are just two texts for comparison (assuming they are in the same
language and script).  It will also be useful where editors do not wish
to privilege a text as the <soCalled>base</soCalled> or when editors
wish to present parallel texts.  It will become less convenient as
traditions become more complex and tension develops between the need to
segment on the largest variation found and the need to express the
finest detail of agreement between witnesses.</p>
<p>In the parallel segmentation method, each segment of text on which
there is variation is marked by an <gi>app</gi> element; each reading is
given in a <gi>rdg</gi> element; if it is desired to single out one
reading as preferred, it may be tagged <gi>lem</gi>:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><variantEncoding method="parallel-segmentation" location="internal"/>
<!-- ... -->
  <l n="1">
    <app><lem wit="#El #Hg">Experience</lem>
         <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
         <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg></app>
    though noon Auctoritee</l>
  <l>Were in this world ...</l></egXML></p>
<p>This method cannot be used with external apparatus:  it must be used
in-line.  Note that apparatus encoded with this method may be translated
into the double end-point attachment method and back without loss of
information.  Where double-end-point-attachment encodings have no
overlapping lemmata, translation of these to the parallel segmentation
encoding and back will also be possible without loss of information.</p>
<p>For economy, the witnesses to the reading most widely attested need
not be stated.  Since all manuscripts must be represented in all
apparatus entries, it will be possible for an application to read a
<gi>listWit</gi> declaring all the witnesses to the text and then
calculate which witnesses have not been named.  In the example below,
only La and Ra2 are identified explicitly with a reading; an application
might successfully infer from this that <mentioned>Experience</mentioned>,
whose witnesses are not given, must be attested by El and Hg.  To avoid
confusion, however, witnesses may be omitted only for a single reading.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l n="1">    
   <app>
      <lem>Experience</lem>
      <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
      <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
   </app>
   though noon Auctoritee</l>
<l>Were in this world ...</l></egXML></p>
<p>Alternatively, the witnesses for every reading may be stated, as in
the first example.</p>
<p>As noted, apparatus entries may nest in this method:  if an imaginary
fifth manuscript of the text read <mentioned>Auctoritee, though none
experience</mentioned>, the variation on the individual words of the line would
nest within that for the line as a whole:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><l n="1">
   <app>
      <rdg wit="#Chi3">Auctoritee, though none experience</rdg>
      <rdg>    
         <app>
            <rdg wit="#El #Hg">Experience</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#La">Experiment</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#Ra2">Eryment</rdg>
         </app>
         <app>
            <rdg wit="#El #Ra2">though</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#Hg">thogh</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#La">thouh</rdg>
         </app>
         <app>
            <rdg wit="#El #Hg">noon Auctorite</rdg>
            <rdg wit="#La #Ra2">none auctorite</rdg>
         </app>
      </rdg>
   </app>
</l></egXML></p>
<p>Parallel segmentation cannot, however, deal very gracefully with
variants which overlap without nesting:  such variants must be broken up
into pieces in order to keep all witnesses synchronized.
 </p></div></div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="TCTR"><head>Using Apparatus Elements in Transcriptions</head>
<p>It is often desirable to record different transcriptions of one
stretch of text.  These variant transcriptions may be grouped within a
single <gi>app</gi> element.  An application may then construct
different <soCalled>views</soCalled> of the transcription by extraction of the
appropriate variant readings from the apparatus elements embedded in the
transcription.</p>
<p>For example, alternative expansions can be recorded in several
different <gi>expan</gi> elements, all grouped within an <gi>app</gi>
element.  Consider, for example, the three different transcriptions
given below of line 105 of the Hengwrt manuscript of Chaucer's
<title>The Wife of Bath's Prologue</title>.  The last word of the line
<mentioned>Virginite is grete perfection</mentioned> is written <mentioned>perfectio</mentioned>
followed by two minims over which a bar has been drawn, which has been
read in different ways by different scholars.  The first
transcription, by Elizabeth Solopova, represents the two minims with
bar above as a special composite character using the <gi>g</gi> element.  This
transcription notes this as a mark of abbreviation but gives no
expansion for it.  A second transcriber, F. J. Furnivall, regards the
bar as an abbreviation of <mentioned>u</mentioned>, and therefore reads the two minims as
an <mentioned>n</mentioned>.  A third transcriber, P. G. Ruggiers, regards the
bar as an abbreviation of <mentioned>n</mentioned>, reading the minims as
<mentioned>u</mentioned>.  This information may be held within an <gi>app</gi>
structure, as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Virginite is grete
<app>
  <rdg resp="#ES">perfectio<am><g ref="#ii"/></am></rdg>
  <rdg resp="#FJF">perfectio<ex>u</ex>n</rdg>
  <rdg resp="#PGR">perfectiou<ex>n</ex></rdg>
</app></egXML>
This example uses special purpose elements <gi>am</gi> and <gi>ex</gi>
used to represent abbreviation marks and editorial expansion
respectively; these elements are provided by the <ident type="module">transcr</ident> module documented in chapter <ptr target="#PH"/>, which should be consulted for further discussion of
methods of representing multiple readings of a source.

<!-- This example illustrates the adaptation of the <gi>rdg</gi> aelement for
use within the transcription of a particular witness.  The
<att>wit</att> attribute, which may be compulsory in recording variant
readings of many witnesses within a critical apparatus, is redundant
when recording variant readings relating to a single witness.  However,
it may be desirable to specify the editorial responsibility for a
particular reading within a transcription.  For all three readings, the
<att>resp</att> attribute on <gi>rdg</gi> assigns this responsibility.
Using this system, it will be straightforward for an application to
extract from the one file the three different transcriptions done by
these scholars.  To do this, the application need look only at the
<att>resp</att> attribute on each <gi>rdg</gi> element.</p>
<p>Observe too that in this example the <att>resp</att> attribute is
attached to the outer <gi>rdg</gi> element and is not repeated for the
inner <gi>expan</gi> elements.  There is no need for repetition of the
<att>resp</att> attribute values, as the <gi>expan</gi> elements
contained within each <gi>rdg</gi> element will inherit the value of the
<att>resp</att> from the outer <gi>rdg</gi> element.  Thus, the
processor will know that the responsibility for the expansion
<mentioned>perfectioun</mentioned> lies with <ident>FJF</ident>, as
<ident>FJF</ident> was responsible for the reading containing this expansion.
This simplifies the processing of the information, as the application
has only to look at the attribute values for each reading in turn and
not for those for elements nested within.--></p>
<p>Editorial notes may also be attached to <gi>app</gi> structures
within transcriptions.  Here, editorial preference for Ruggiers'
expansion and an explanation of that preference is given:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">Virginite is grete
<app>
  <rdg resp="#ES">perfecti<am><g ref="#ii"/></am></rdg>
  <rdg xml:id="f105" resp="#FJF">perfectio<ex>u</ex>n</rdg>
  <rdg xml:id="r105" resp="#PGR">perfectiou<ex>n</ex></rdg>
</app>
<!-- ... <note> appearing elsewhere in the document ... -->
<note target="#r105 #f105">Furnivall's expansion implies that the bar
  is an abbreviation for 'u'. There are no certain instances of
  this mark as an abbreviation for 'u' in these manuscripts and it is
  widely used as an abbreviation for 'n'. Ruggiers' expansion is to
  be accepted.</note></egXML>
</p>
<p>In most cases, elements used to indicate features of a primary
textual source may be represented within an <gi>app</gi> structure
simply by nesting them within its readings, just as the <gi>am</gi>
and <gi>ex</gi> elements are nested within the <gi>rdg</gi> elements
in the example just given.  However, in cases where the tagged feature
extends across a span of text which might itself contain variant
readings which it is desired to represent by <gi>app</gi> structures,
some adaptation of the tagging may be necessary.  For example, a span of
text may be marked in the transcription of the primary source as a
single deletion but it may be desirable to represent just a few words
from this source as individual deletions within the context of a
critical apparatus drawing together readings from this and several other
witnesses.  In this case, the tagging of the span of words as one
deletion may need to be decomposed into a series of one-word deletions
for encoding within the apparatus.  If it is important to record
the fact that all were deleted by the same act, the markup may use
the <gi>join</gi> element or the <att>next</att> and <att>prev</att>
attributes defined by chapter <ptr target="#SA"/>.</p></div>

<div><head>Module for Critical Apparatus</head>
<p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following
components:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DTC" ident="textcrit">
<altIdent type="FPI">Text Criticism</altIdent>
<desc>Critical Apparatus</desc>
<desc xml:lang="fr">Apparat critique</desc>
<desc xml:lang="zh-TW">學術編輯註解</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Apparato critico</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Critical Apparatus</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">校勘モジュール</desc></moduleSpec>

The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>
<specGrp>










&variantEncoding;















&model.rdgPart;















&att.rdgPart;















&att.textCritical;





<specGrpRef target="#DTCAPEN"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCAPLR"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCAPSU"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCAPWD"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCSCWL"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCAPLW"/>
<specGrpRef target="#DTCFW"/>
</specGrp></div>

</div>
