<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!--
Copyright TEI Consortium. 
Dual-licensed under CC-by and BSD2 licences 
See the file COPYING.txt for details.
$Date$
$Id$
-->
<div xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" type="div1" xml:id="TS" n="11">
<head>Transcriptions of Speech</head>

<p>The module described in this chapter is intended for use with a
wide variety of transcribed spoken material.  It should be stressed,
however, that the present proposals are not intended to support
unmodified every variety of research undertaken upon spoken material
now or in the future; some discourse analysts, some phonologists, and
doubtless others may wish to extend the scheme presented here to
express more precisely the set of distinctions they wish to draw in
their transcriptions.  Speech regarded as a purely acoustic phenomenon
may well require different methods from those outlined here, as may
speech regarded solely as a process of social interaction.
</p>
<p>This chapter begins with a discussion of some of the problems
commonly encountered in transcribing spoken language (section <ptr target="#TSOV"/>).  Section <ptr target="#HD32"/> documents some
additional TEI Header elements which may be used to document the
recording or other source from which transcribed text is taken.
Section <ptr target="#TSBA"/> describes the basic structural elements
provided by this module.  Finally, section <ptr target="#TSSA"/> of this
chapter reviews further problems specific to the encoding of spoken
language, demonstrating how mechanisms and elements discussed
elsewhere in these Guidelines may be applied to them.</p>


<div type="div2" xml:id="TSOV"><head>General Considerations and Overview</head>
<p>There is great variation in the ways different researchers have
chosen to represent speech using the written medium.<note place="bottom">For a
discussion of several of these see <ptr type="cit" target="#TS-BIBL-1"/>; <ptr type="cit" target="#TS-BIBL-2"/>; and
<ptr type="cit" target="#TS-BIBL-3"/>.</note> This
reflects the special difficulties which apply to the encoding or <term rend="noindex">transcription</term> of speech.  Speech varies according to
a large number of dimensions, many of which have no counterpart in
writing (for example, tempo, loudness, pitch, etc.).  The audibility of
speech recorded in natural communication situations is often less than
perfect, affecting the accuracy of the transcription.  Spoken material
may be transcribed in the course of linguistic, acoustic,
anthropological, psychological, ethnographic, journalistic, or many
other types of research.  Even in the same field, the interests and
theoretical perspectives of different transcribers may lead them to
prefer different levels of detail in the transcript and different styles
of visual display.  The production and comprehension of speech are
intimately bound up with the situation in which speech occurs, far more
so than is the case for written texts.  A speech transcript must
therefore include some contextual features; determining which are
relevant is not always simple.  Moreover, the ethical problems in
recording and making public what was produced in a private setting and
intended for a limited audience are more frequently encountered in
dealing with spoken texts than with written ones.
 </p>
<p>Speech also poses difficult structural problems.  Unlike a written
text, a speech event takes place in time.  Its beginning and end may be
hard to determine and its internal composition difficult to define.
Most researchers agree that the utterances or <term>turns</term> of
individual speakers form an important structural component in most kinds
of speech, but these are rarely as well-behaved (in the structural
sense) as paragraphs or other analogous units in written texts:
speakers frequently interrupt each other, use gestures as well as words,
leave remarks unfinished and so on.  Speech itself, though it may be
represented as words, frequently contains items such as vocalized pauses
which, although only semi-lexical, have immense importance in the
analysis of spoken text.  Even non-vocal elements such as gestures may
be regarded as forming a component of spoken text for some analytic
purposes.
Below the level of the individual utterance, speech may be segmented
into units defined by phonological, prosodic, or syntactic phenomena;
no clear agreement exists, however, even as to appropriate names for
such segments.
 </p>

<p>Spoken texts transcribed according to the guidelines presented here
are organized as follows.  The overall structure of a TEI spoken text
is identical to that of any other TEI text: the <gi>TEI</gi> element
for a spoken text contains a <gi>teiHeader</gi> element, followed by a
<gi>text</gi> element.  Even texts primarily composed of transcribed
speech may also include conventional front and back matter, and may
even be organized into divisions like printed texts. </p>
<p>We may say, therefore, that these Guidelines regard transcribed
speech as being composed of arbitrary high-level units called <term rend="noindex">texts</term>.<index><term>texts</term><index><term>as
organizing unit for spoken material</term></index></index> A spoken
<gi>text</gi> might typically be a conversation between a small number
of people, a lecture, a broadcast TV item, or a similar event.  Each
such unit has associated with it a <gi>teiHeader</gi> providing
detailed contextual information such as the source of the transcript,
the identity of the participants, whether the speech is scripted or
spontaneous, the physical and social setting in which the discourse
takes place and a range of other aspects.  Details of the header
in general are provided in  chapter <ptr target="#HD"/>; the
particular elements it provides for use with spoken texts are
described below (<ptr target="#HD32"/>). Details concerning
additional elements which may be used for the documentation of participant and
contextual information are given in  <ptr target="#CCAH"/>.
 </p>

<p>Defining the bounds of a spoken text is frequently a matter of
arbitrary convention or convenience.  In public or semi-public contexts,
a text may be regarded as synonymous with, for example, a <term rend="noindex">lecture</term>, a <term rend="noindex">broadcast item</term>,
a <term rend="noindex">meeting</term>, etc.  In informal or private
contexts, a text may be simply a conversation involving a specific group
of participants.  Alternatively, researchers may elect to define spoken
texts solely in terms of their duration in time or length in words.  By
default, these Guidelines assume of a text only that:
<list type="simple">
<item>it is internally cohesive,</item>
<item>it is describable by a single header, and</item>
<item>it represents a single stretch of time with no significant
discontinuities.</item></list>
Deviation from these assumptions may be specified (for example, the
<att>org</att> attribute on the <gi>text</gi> element may take the value
<val>compos</val> to specify that the components of the
text are discrete) but is not recommended.
 </p>

<p>Within a <gi>text</gi> it may be necessary to identify subdivisions
of various kinds, if only for convenience of handling.  The neutral
<gi>div</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#DSDIV"/> is
recommended for this purpose.  It may be found useful also for
representing subdivisions relating to discourse structure, speech act
theory, transactional analysis, etc., provided only that these divisions
are hierarchically well-behaved.  Where they are not, as is often the
case, the mechanisms discussed in chapters <ptr target="#SA"/> and
<ptr target="#NH"/> may be used.
 </p>

<p>A spoken text may contain any of the following components:
<list type="simple">
<item>utterances</item>
<item>pauses</item>
<item>vocalized but non-lexical phenomena such as coughs</item>
<item>kinesic (non-verbal, non-lexical) phenomena such as gestures</item>
<item>entirely non-linguistic incidents occurring during and possibly
influencing the course of speech</item>
<item>writing, regarded as a special class of incident in that it can
be transcribed, for example captions or overheads displayed during
a lecture</item>
<item>shifts or changes in vocal quality</item></list>
 </p>
<p>Elements to represent all of these features of spoken language are
discussed in section <ptr target="#TSBA"/> below.
 </p>
<p>An utterance (tagged <gi>u</gi>) may contain lexical items
interspersed with pauses and non-lexical vocal sounds; during an
utterance, non-linguistic incidents may occur and written materials may be
presented.  The <gi>u</gi> element can thus contain any of the other
elements listed, interspersed with a transcription of the lexical items
of the utterance; the other elements may all appear between utterances
or next to each other, but except for <gi>writing</gi> they do not
contain any other elements nor any data.
 </p>

<p>A spoken text itself may be without substructure, that is, it may
consist simply of units such as utterances or pauses, not grouped
together in any way, or it may be subdivided. If the notion of what
constitutes a <soCalled>text</soCalled> in spoken discourse is
inevitably rather an arbitrary one, the notion of formal subdivisions
within such a <soCalled>text</soCalled> may appear even more debatable.
Nevertheless, such divisions may be useful for such types of discourse
as debates, broadcasts, etc., where structural subdivisions can easily
be identified, or more generally wherever it is desired to aggregate
utterances or other parts of a transcript into units smaller than a
complete <soCalled>text</soCalled>.  Examples might include
<q>conversations</q> or <q>discourse fragments</q>, or more narrowly,
<q>that part of the conversation where topic x was discussed</q>,
provided only that the set of all such divisions is coextensive with
the text.
 </p>
<p>Each such division of a spoken text should be represented by the
numbered or unnumbered <gi>div</gi> elements defined in chapter <ptr target="#DS"/>.  For some detailed kinds of analysis a hierarchy of
such divisions may be found useful; nested <gi>div</gi> elements may
be used for this purpose, as in the following example showing how a
collection made up of transcribed <soCalled>sound bites</soCalled>
taken from speeches given by a politician on different occasions
might be encoded.  Each extract is regarded as a distinct
<gi>div</gi>, nested within a single composite <gi>div</gi> as
follows: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><div type="soundbites" subtype="conservative" org="composite">
   <div sample="medial">
   </div>
   <div sample="medial">
   </div>
   <div sample="initial">
   </div>
</div></egXML>
 </p>
<p>As a member of the class <ident type="class">att.declaring</ident>, the
<gi>div</gi> element may also carry a <att>decls</att> attribute, for
use where the divisions of a text do not all share the same set of the
contextual declarations specified in the TEI header.  (See further
section <ptr target="#CCAS"/>).
</p> 

</div>

<div type="div3" xml:id="HD32"><head>Documenting the Source of Transcribed Speech</head>
<p>Where a computer file is derived from a spoken text rather than a
written one, it will usually be desirable to record additional
information about the recording or broadcast which constitutes its
source. Several additional elements are provided for this purpose
within the source description component of the TEI Header:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="scriptStmt"/>
  <specDesc key="recordingStmt"/>
  <specDesc key="recording" atts="type"/>
</specList>
As a member of the <ident type="class">att.duration</ident> class,
the <gi>recording</gi> element inherits the  following attribute:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.duration.w3c" atts="dur"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>Note that detailed information about the participants or setting of
an interview or other transcript of spoken language should be recorded
in the appropriate division of the profile description, discussed in
chapter <ptr target="#CC"/>, rather than as part of the source
description.  The source description is used to hold information only
about the source from which the transcribed speech was taken, for
example, any script being read and any technical details of how the
recording was  produced.  If the source was a previously-created
transcript, it should be treated in the same way as any other source
text.
 </p>
<p>The <gi>scriptStmt</gi> element should be used where it is known that
one or more of the participants in a spoken text is speaking from a
previously prepared script.  The script itself should be documented in
the same way as any other written text, using one of the three citation
tags mentioned above.  Utterances or groups of utterances may be linked
to the script concerned by means of the <att>decls</att> attribute,
described in section <ptr target="#CCAS"/>.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><sourceDesc>
  <scriptStmt xml:id="CNN12">
    <bibl>
      <author>CNN Network News</author>
      <title>News headlines</title>
      <date when="1991-06-12">12 Jun 91</date>
    </bibl>
  </scriptStmt>
</sourceDesc></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>recordingStmt</gi> is used to group together information
relating to the recordings from which the spoken text was transcribed.
The element may contain either a prose description or, more helpfully,
one or more <gi>recording</gi> elements, each corresponding with a
particular recording.  The linkage between utterances or groups of
utterances and the relevant recording statement is made by means of the
<att>decls</att> attribute, described in section <ptr target="#CCAS"/>.
 </p>
<p>The <gi>recording</gi> element should be used to provide a
description of how and by whom a recording was made.  This information
may be provided in the form of a prose description, within which such items as statements of
responsibility, names, places, and dates may be identified using the
appropriate phrase-level tags.  Alternatively, a selection of elements
from the <ident type="class">model.recordingPart</ident> class may be
provided. This element class makes available the following elements:
<specList>
  <specDesc key="date"/>
  <specDesc key="time"/>
  <specDesc key="respStmt"/>
  <specDesc key="equipment"/>
  <specDesc key="broadcast"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>Specialized
collections may wish to add further sub-elements to these major
components.  These elements should be used only for
information relating to the recording process itself; information about
the setting or participants (for example) is recorded elsewhere:  see
sections <ptr target="#CCAHSE"/> and <ptr target="#CCAHPA"/><!-- below-->.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><recordingStmt>
<recording type="video">
  <p>U-matic recording made by college audio-visual department staff, 
    available as PAL-standard VHS transfer or sound-only cassette</p>
</recording></recordingStmt></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><recordingStmt>
<recording type="audio" dur="P30M">
  <respStmt>
     <resp>Location recording by</resp>
     <name>Sound Services Ltd.</name>
  </respStmt>
  <equipment>
     <p>Multiple close microphones mixed down to stereo Digital
     Audio Tape, standard play, 44.1 KHz sampling frequency</p>
  </equipment>
  <date>12 Jan 1987</date>
</recording>
</recordingStmt></egXML>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><recordingStmt>
<recording type="audio" dur="P15M" xml:id="rec-3001">
<date>14 Feb 2001</date>
</recording>
<recording type="audio" dur="P15M" xml:id="rec-3002">
<date>17 Feb 2001</date>
</recording>
<recording type="audio" dur="P15M" xml:id="rec-3003">
<date>22 Feb 2001</date>
</recording>
</recordingStmt>
</egXML></p>
<p>When a recording has been made from a public broadcast, details of
the broadcast itself should be supplied within the <gi>recording</gi>
element, as a nested <gi>broadcast</gi> element.  A broadcast is closely
analogous to a publication and the <gi>broadcast</gi> element should
therefore contain one or the other of the bibliographic citation
elements <gi>bibl</gi>, <gi>biblStruct</gi>, or <gi>biblFull</gi>.  The
broadcasting agency responsible for a broadcast is regarded as its
author, while other participants (for example interviewers,
interviewees, script writers, directors, producers, etc.) should be specified using the
<gi>respStmt</gi> or <gi>editor</gi> element with an appropriate
<gi>resp</gi> (see further section <ptr target="#COBI"/>).
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><recording type="audio" dur="P10M">
  <equipment><p>Recorded from FM Radio to digital tape</p></equipment>
  <broadcast>
    <bibl>
      <title>Interview on foreign policy</title>     <author>BBC Radio 5</author>
      <respStmt><resp>interviewer</resp><name>Robin Day</name></respStmt>
      <respStmt><resp>interviewee</resp><name>Margaret Thatcher</name></respStmt>
      <series><title>The World Tonight</title></series>
      <note>First broadcast on <date when="1989-11-27">27 Nov 1989</date></note>
    </bibl>
  </broadcast>
</recording></egXML></p>
<p>When a broadcast contains several distinct recordings (for example a
compilation), additional <gi>recording</gi> elements may be further
nested within the <gi>broadcast</gi> element.
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><recording dur="P100M">
   <broadcast>
      <recording>
      </recording>
   </broadcast>
</recording></egXML>
<!-- need a real example here -->
	<!-- damn straight.  -msm     -->
 </p>

<specGrp xml:id="D2231" n="Script statement and recording statement">
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/scriptStmt.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/recordingStmt.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/recording.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/equipment.xml"/>
<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/broadcast.xml"/>
</specGrp>
</div>

<div type="div2" xml:id="TSBA"><head>Elements Unique to Spoken Texts</head>
<p>The following elements characterize spoken texts, transcribed
according to these Guidelines:
<specList><specDesc key="u"/><specDesc key="pause"/><specDesc key="vocal"/><specDesc key="kinesic"/><specDesc key="incident"/><specDesc key="writing"/><specDesc key="shift"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>The <gi>u</gi> element may appear directly within a spoken text,
and may contain any of the others; the others may also appear directly
(for example, a <gi>vocal</gi> may appear between two utterances) but cannot
contain a <gi>u</gi> element. In terms of the basic TEI model,
therefore, we regard the <gi>u</gi> element as analogous to a
paragraph, and the others as analogous to <soCalled>phrase</soCalled>
elements, but with the important difference that they can exist either
as siblings or as children of utterances. The class <ident type="class">model.divPart.spoken</ident> provides the <gi>u</gi>
element; the class <ident type="class">model.global.spoken</ident>
provides the six other elements listed above.</p>

<p>As  members of the <ident type="class">att.ascribed</ident> class,
all of these elements  share the following attribute:
<specList><specDesc key="att.ascribed" atts="who"/></specList>
As  members of the <ident type="class">att.typed</ident>, <ident type="class">att.timed</ident> and <ident type="class">att.duration</ident> classes,
all of these elements except <gi>shift</gi> share the following attribute:
<specList>
<specDesc key="att.typed" atts="type subtype"/>
<specDesc key="att.timed" atts="start end"/>
<specDesc key="att.duration.w3c" atts="dur"/>
</specList>
</p>
<p>Each of these elements is further discussed and specified in
sections <ptr target="#TSBAUT"/>  to <ptr target="#TSBAWR"/>.
 </p>
<p>We can show the relationship between four of these constituents of
speech using the features <mentioned>eventive</mentioned>, <mentioned>communicative</mentioned>, <mentioned>anthropophonic</mentioned> (for sounds produced by the human
vocal apparatus), and <mentioned>lexical</mentioned>:
<table>
<row role="label"><cell> </cell><cell>eventive</cell><cell>communicative</cell><cell>anthropophonic</cell><cell>lexical</cell></row>
<row><cell>incident</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row>
<row><cell>kinesic</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>-</cell><cell>-</cell></row>
<row><cell>vocal</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>-</cell></row>
<row><cell>utterance</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>+</cell><cell>+</cell></row>
</table>
The differences are not always clear-cut.  Among <term rend="noindex">incidents</term> might be included actions like slamming
the door, which can certainly be communicative.  <term rend="noindex">Vocals</term> include coughing and sneezing, which
are<index><term>vocal events</term><index><term>in
transcription of speech</term></index></index> usually
involuntary noises.  Equally, the distinction between utterances and
vocals is not always clear, although for many analytic purposes it
will be convenient to regard them as distinct.  Individual scholars
may differ in the way borderlines are drawn and should declare their
definitions in the <gi>editorialDecl</gi> element of the header (see
<ptr target="#HD53"/>).
 </p>
<p>The following short extract exemplifies several of these elements. It
is recoded from a text originally transcribed in the CHILDES
format.<note place="bottom">The original is a conversation between two children and
their parents, recorded in 1987, and discussed in
<ptr type="cit" target="#TS-BIBL-4"/></note>
Each utterance is encoded using a <gi>u</gi> element (see section <ptr target="#TSBAUT"/>). The speakers are defined using the
<gi>listPerson</gi> element discussed in <ptr target="#NDPERSE"/> and each is
given a unique identifier also used to identify their speech. Pauses marked by the transcriber are indicated
using the <gi>pause</gi> element (see section <ptr target="#TSBAPA"/>).
Non-verbal vocal effects such as the child's meowing are indicated
either with orthographic transcriptions or with the <gi>vocal</gi>
element, and entirely non-linguistic but significant incidents such as
the sound of the toy cat are represented by the <gi>incident</gi>
elements (see section <ptr target="#TSBAVO"/>).
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TSBA-eg-19"><u who="#mar">you
never <pause/> take this cat for show and tell
<pause/> meow meow</u>
<u who="#ros">yeah well I dont want to</u>
<incident><desc>toy cat has bell in tail which continues to make a tinkling sound</desc></incident>
<vocal who="#mar"><desc>meows</desc></vocal>
<u who="#ros">because it is so old</u>
<u who="#mar">how <choice><orig>bout</orig><reg>about</reg></choice>
  <emph>your</emph> cat <pause/>yours is  <emph>new</emph>
  <kinesic><desc>shows Father the cat</desc></kinesic> </u>
<u trans="pause" who="#fat">thats <pause/> darling</u>
<u who="#mar"><seg>no <emph>mine</emph> isnt old</seg>
<seg>mine is just um a little dirty</seg></u>
<!-- ... -->
<listPerson>
<person xml:id="mar"><!-- ... --></person>
<person xml:id="ros"><!-- ... --></person>
<person xml:id="fat"><!-- ... --></person>
</listPerson></egXML>
<!-- from MacWhinney 88, 87, cited by SJ --></p>
<p>This example also uses some elements common to all TEI texts,
notably the <gi>reg</gi> tag for editorial regularization. Unusually
stressed syllables have been encoded with the <gi>emph</gi>
element. The <gi>seg</gi> element has also been used to segment the
last utterance. Further discussion of all of such options is provided
in section <ptr target="#TSSA"/>.
 </p>
<p>Contextual information is of particular importance in spoken texts,
and should be provided by the TEI header of a text. In general, all of
the information in a header is understood to be relevant to the whole
of the associated text. The element <gi>u</gi> as a member of the
<ident type="class">att.declaring</ident> class, may however specify a
different context by means of the <att>decls</att> attribute (see
further section <ptr target="#CCAS"/>).
 </p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSBAUT"><head>Utterances</head>
<p>Each distinct <term>utterance</term> in a spoken text is represented
by a <gi>u</gi> element, described as follows:
<specList><specDesc key="u" atts="trans"/>
</specList>
 </p>
<p>Use of the <att>who</att> attribute to associate the utterance with a
particular speaker is recommended but not required. Its use implies as
a further requirement that all speakers be identified by a
<gi>person</gi> or <gi>personGrp</gi> element in the TEI
header (see section <ptr target="#CCAHPA"/>), but it may also point to another 
external source of information about the speaker. Where utterances or
other parts of the transcription cannot be
attributed with confidence to any particular participant or group of
participants, the encoder may choose to create <gi>personGrp</gi> elements
with <att>xml:id</att> attributes such as <val>various</val> or <val>unknown</val>,
and perhaps give the root <gi>listPerson</gi> element an <att>xml:id</att> value of
<val>all</val>, then point to those as appropriate using <att>who</att>.</p>

<p>The <att>trans</att> attribute is provided as a means of
characterizing the transition from one utterance to the next at a
simpler level of detail than that provided by the temporal alignment
mechanism discussed in section <ptr target="#SASY"/>.  The value specified
applies to the transition from the preceding utterance into the
utterance bearing the attribute.  For example:<note place="bottom">For
the most part, the examples in this chapter use no sentence punctuation
except to mark the rising intonation often found in interrogative
statements; for further discussion, see section <ptr target="#TSREG"/>.</note>
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u xml:id="ts_a1" who="#a">Have you heard the</u>
<u xml:id="ts_b1" trans="latching" who="#b">the election results? yes</u>
<u xml:id="ts_a2" trans="pause" who="#a">it's a disaster</u>
<u xml:id="ts_b2" trans="overlap" who="#b">it's a miracle</u></egXML>
In this example, utterance <val>ts_b1</val> latches on to utterance
<val>ts_a1</val>, while there is a marked pause between
<val>ts_b1</val> and <val>ts_a2</val>. <val>ts_b2</val> and
<val>ts_a2</val> overlap, but by an unspecified amount. For ways of
providing a more precise indication of the degree of overlap, see
section <ptr target="#TSSAPA"/>.
 </p>
<p>An utterance may contain either running text, or text within which
other basic structural elements are nested.  Where such nesting occurs,
the <att>who</att> attribute is considered to be inherited for the
elements <gi>pause</gi>, <gi>vocal</gi>, <gi>shift</gi> and
<gi>kinesic</gi>; that is, a pause or shift (etc.) within an utterance
is regarded as being produced by that speaker only, while a pause
between utterances applies to all speakers.
 </p>
<p>Occasionally, an utterance may seem to contain other utterances,
for example where one speaker interrupts himself,  or 
when another speaker produces a <soCalled>back-channel</soCalled>
while they are still speaking.  The present version of these
Guidelines does not support nesting of one <gi>u</gi> element within
another. The transcriber must therefore decide whether such
interruptions constitute a change of utterance, or whether other
elements may be used. In the case of self-interruption, the
<gi>shift</gi> element may be used to show that the speaker has
changed the quality of their speech:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#a">Listen to this <shift new="reading"/>The government is
confident, he said, that the current economic problems will be
completely overcome by June<shift/> what nonsense</u></egXML> 
Alternatively the <gi>incident</gi> element described in section <ptr target="#TSBAVO"/> might be used, without transcribing the read material: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#a">Listen to this
<incident><desc>reads aloud from newspaper</desc></incident> what
nonsense</u></egXML> 
</p>
<p>Often, back-channelling is only semi-lexicalized and may therefore be
represented using the <gi>vocal</gi> element:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#a">So what could I have done <vocal who="#b"><desc>tut-tutting</desc></vocal> about it anyway?</u></egXML>
Where this is not possible, it is simplest to regard the back-channel
as a distinct utterance.</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSBAPA"><head>Pausing</head>
<p>Speakers differ very much in their rhythm and in particular in the
amount of time they leave between words. The following element is
provided to mark occasions where the transcriber judges that
speech has been paused, irrespective of the actual amount of silence:
<specList><specDesc key="pause"/></specList>
A pause contained by an utterance applies to the speaker of that
utterance.  A pause between utterances applies to all speakers.  The
<att>type</att> attribute may be used to categorize the pause, for
example as short, medium, or long; alternatively the attribute
<att>dur</att> may be used to indicate its length more exactly, as in
the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TSBAPA-eg-24"><u>Okay <pause dur="PT2M"/>U-m<pause dur="PT75S"/>the scene opens up
<pause dur="PT50S"/> with <pause dur="PT20S"/> um <pause dur="PT145S"/> you see
a tree okay?</u></egXML>
<!-- example recoded from Chafe  -->
If detailed synchronization of pausing with other vocal phenomena is
required, the alignment mechanism defined at section <ptr target="#SASY"/>
and discussed informally below should be used.  Note that the
<att>trans</att> attribute mentioned in the previous section may also be
used to characterize the degree of pausing between (but not within)
utterances.
 </p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSBAVO"><head>Vocal, Kinesic, Incident</head>
<p>The presence of
non-transcribed semi-lexical or non-lexical phenomena either between or
within utterances may be indicated with the following three elements.
<specList><specDesc key="vocal"/><specDesc key="kinesic"/><specDesc key="incident"/></specList>
 </p>
<p>The <att>who</att> attribute should be used to specify the person or
group responsible for a <gi>vocal</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>, or <gi>incident</gi> which is contained
within an utterance, if this differs from that of the enclosing
utterance.  The attribute must be supplied for a <gi>vocal</gi>, <gi>kinesic</gi>, or <gi>incident</gi>
which is not contained within an utterance.
 </p>
<p>The <att>iterated</att> attribute may be used to indicate that the
vocal, kinesic, or incident is repeated, for example <val>laughter</val> as opposed to <val>laugh</val>.
These should both be distinguished from <val>laughing</val>,
where what is being encoded is a shift in voice quality.  For this last
case, the <gi>shift</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#TSSASH"/> should be used.
 </p>
<p>A child <gi>desc</gi> element may be used to supply a conventional
representation for the phenomenon, for example:
<list type="gloss"><label>non-lexical </label>
<item>burp, click, cough, exhale, giggle, gulp,
    inhale, laugh, sneeze, sniff, snort, sob, swallow, throat, yawn
    </item><label>semi-lexical </label>
<item>ah, aha, aw, eh, ehm, er, erm, hmm, huh,
    mm, mmhm, oh, ooh, oops, phew, tsk, uh, uh-huh, uh-uh, um, urgh,
    yup</item></list>
Researchers may prefer to regard some semi-lexical phenomena as
<soCalled>words</soCalled> within the bounds of the <gi>u</gi> element.
See further the discussion at section <ptr target="#TSREG"/> below.  As
for all basic categories, the definition should be made clear in the
<gi>encodingDesc</gi> element of the TEI header.
 </p>
<p>Some typical examples follow:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TSSASE-eg-20"><u who="#jan">This is just delicious</u>
<incident><desc>telephone rings</desc></incident>
<u who="#ann">I'll get it</u>
<u who="#tom">I used to <vocal><desc>cough</desc></vocal> smoke a lot</u>
<u who="#bob"><vocal><desc>sniffs</desc></vocal>He thinks he's tough</u>
<vocal who="#ann"><desc>snorts</desc></vocal>
<!-- ... -->
<listPerson>
<person xml:id="ann"><!-- ... --></person>
<person xml:id="bob"><!-- ... --></person>
<person xml:id="jan"><!-- ... --></person>
<person xml:id="kim"><!-- ... --></person>
<person xml:id="tom"><!-- ... --></person>
</listPerson>

</egXML>
Note that Ann's snorting could equally well be encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#ann">
   <vocal><desc>snorts</desc></vocal>
</u></egXML>
 </p>
<p>The extent to which encoding of incidents or kinesics is included in a
transcription will depend entirely on the purpose for which the
transcription was made.  As elsewhere, this will depend on the
particular research agenda and the extent to which their presence is
felt to be significant for the interpretation of spoken interactions.
 </p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSBAWR"><head>Writing</head>
<p>Written text may also be encountered when speech is transcribed, for
example in a television broadcast or cinema performance, or where one
participant shows written text to another.  The <gi>writing</gi> element
may be used to distinguish such written elements from the spoken text in
which they are embedded.
<specList><specDesc key="writing" atts="gradual"/><specDesc key="att.source"/></specList>
<!-- example needed -->
For example, if speaker A in the breakfast table conversation in section <ptr target="#TSBAUT"/>
 above had simply shown the newspaper passage to her
interlocutor instead of reading it, the interaction might have been
encoded as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#a">look at this</u>
<writing who="#a" type="newspaper" gradual="false">
Government claims economic problems 
<soCalled>over by June</soCalled></writing> <u who="#a">what nonsense!</u></egXML>
 </p>
<p>If the source of the writing being displayed is known,
bibliographic information
about it may be stored in a <gi>listBibl</gi> within the
<gi>sourceDesc</gi> element of the TEI Header, and then pointed to
using the <att>source</att> attribute. For example, in the following
imaginary example, a lecturer displays two different versions of the same
passage of text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<sourceDesc>
<!-- ...-->
<bibl xml:id="FOL1">Shakespeare First Folio text</bibl>
<bibl xml:id="FOL2">Shakespeare Second Folio text</bibl>
<!-- ...-->
</sourceDesc>
<!-- ...-->
<u>.... now compare the punctuation of lines 12 and 14 in these two
versions of page 42...
<writing source="#FOL1">....</writing>
<writing source="#FOL2">....</writing>
</u>
</egXML></p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSBATI"><head>Temporal Information</head>
<p>As noted above, utterances, vocals, pauses, kinesics, incidents,
and writing elements all inherit attributes providing information
about their position in time from the classes <ident type="class">att.timed</ident> and <ident type="class">att.duration</ident>. These attributes can be used to
link parts of the transcription very exactly with points on a
timeline, or simply to indicate their duration.  Note that if
<att>start</att> and <att>end</att> point to <gi>when</gi> elements
whose temporal distance from each other is specified in a timeline,
then <att>dur</att> is ignored.
 </p>
<p>The <gi>anchor</gi> element (see <ptr target="#SACS"/>) may be used as
an alternative means of aligning the start and end of timed elements,
and is required when the temporal alignment involves points within an
element.
 </p>
<p>For further discussion of temporal alignment and synchronization
see  <ptr target="#TSSAPA"/> below.</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSSASH"><head>Shifts</head>
<p>A common requirement in transcribing spoken language is to mark
positions at which a variety of prosodic features change.  Many
paralinguistic features (pitch, prominence, loudness, etc.) characterize
stretches of speech which are not co-extensive with utterances or any of
the other units discussed so far.  One simple method of encoding such
units is simply to mark their boundaries.  An empty element called
<gi>shift</gi> is provided for this purpose.
<specList><specDesc key="shift" atts="feature new"/></specList>
A <gi>shift</gi> element may appear within an utterance or a segment to
mark a significant change in the particular feature defined by its
attributes, which is then understood to apply to all subsequent
utterances for the same speaker, unless changed by a new shift for the
same feature in the same speaker.  Intervening utterances by other
speakers do not normally carry the same feature.
For example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u><shift feature="loud" new="f"/>Elizabeth</u>
<u>Yes</u>
<u><shift feature="loud" new="normal"/>Come and try this <pause/>
     <shift feature="loud" new="ff"/>come on</u></egXML>
In this example, the word <mentioned>Elizabeth</mentioned> is spoken loudly, the
words <mentioned>Yes</mentioned> and <mentioned>Come and try this</mentioned> with
normal volume, and the words <mentioned>come on</mentioned> very loudly.
 </p>
<p>The values proposed here for the <att>feature</att> attribute are
based on those used by the Survey of English Usage (see further
<ref>Boase 1990</ref>); this list may be revised or supplemented using
the methods outlined in section <ptr target="#MD"/>. </p>
<p>The <att>new</att> attribute specifies the new state of the feature
following the shift.  If no value is specified, it is implied that the
feature concerned ceases to be remarkable at this point:  the special
value <val>normal</val> may be specified to have the same
effect.</p>
<p>A list of suggested values for each of the features proposed follows:
<list type="simple">
<item>tempo
<list type="gloss">
<label>a    </label>
<item>allegro (fast)</item>
<label>aa  </label>
<item>very fast</item><label>acc  </label>
<item>accelerando (getting faster)</item><label>l    </label>
<item>lento (slow)</item><label>ll   </label>
<item>very slow</item><label>rall </label>
<item>rallentando (getting slower)</item></list></item>
<item>loud (for loudness):
<list type="gloss"><label>f     </label>
<item>forte (loud)</item><label>ff    </label>
<item>very loud</item><label>cresc </label>
<item>crescendo (getting louder)</item><label>p     </label>
<item>piano (soft)</item><label>pp    </label>
<item>very soft</item><label>dimin </label>
<item>diminuendo (getting softer)</item></list></item>
<item>pitch (for pitch range):
<list type="gloss"><label>high  </label>
<item>high pitch-range</item><label>low   </label>
<item>low pitch-range</item><label>wide  </label>
<item>wide pitch-range</item><label>narrow</label>
<item>narrow pitch-range</item><label>asc   </label>
<item>ascending</item><label>desc  </label>
<item>descending</item><label>monot </label>
<item>monotonous</item><label>scand </label>
<item>scandent, each succeeding syllable higher than
                   the last, generally ending in a falling tone</item></list></item>
<item>tension:
<list type="gloss"><label>sl  </label>
<item>slurred</item><label>lax </label>
<item>lax, a little slurred</item><label>ten </label>
<item>tense</item><label>pr  </label>
<item>very precise</item><label>st  </label>
<item>staccato, every stressed syllable being doubly
                 stressed</item><label>leg </label>
<item>legato, every syllable receiving more or less equal
                 stress</item></list></item>
<item>rhythm:
<list type="gloss"><label>rh   </label>
<item>beatable rhythm</item><label>arrh </label>
<item>arrhythmic, particularly halting</item><label>spr  </label>
<item>spiky rising, with markedly higher unstressed
                  syllables</item><label>spf  </label>
<item>spiky falling, with markedly lower unstressed
                  syllables</item><label>glr  </label>
<item>glissando rising, like spiky rising but the
                  unstressed syllables, usually several, also rise
                  in pitch relative to each other</item><label>glf  </label>
<item>glissando falling, like spiky falling but with the
                  unstressed syllables also falling in pitch relative
                  to each other</item></list></item>
<item>voice (for voice quality):
<list type="gloss"><label>whisp   </label>
<item>whisper</item><label>breath  </label>
<item>breathy</item><label>husk    </label>
<item>husky</item><label>creak   </label>
<item>creaky</item><label>fals    </label>
<item>falsetto</item><label>reson   </label>
<item>resonant</item><label>giggle </label>
<item>unvoiced laugh or giggle</item><label>laugh  </label>
<item>voiced laugh</item><label>trem   </label>
<item>tremulous</item><label>sob    </label>
<item>sobbing</item><label>yawn   </label>
<item>yawning</item><label>sigh   </label>
<item> sighing</item></list></item></list>
 </p>
<p>A full definition of the sense of the values provided for each
feature should be provided in the encoding description section of the
text header (see section <ptr target="#HD5"/>).
 </p>
<specGrp xml:id="DTSCOMP" n="Components of Transcribed Speech">











<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/u.xml"/>















<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/pause.xml"/>















<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/vocal.xml"/>















<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/kinesic.xml"/>














<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/incident.xml"/>















<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/writing.xml"/>















<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/shift.xml"/>






</specGrp>
</div>
</div>
<div type="div2" xml:id="TSSA"><head>Elements Defined Elsewhere</head>
<p>This section describes the following features characteristic of
spoken texts for which elements are defined elsewhere in these
Guidelines:
<list type="simple">
<item>segmentation below the utterance level</item>
<item>synchronization and overlap</item>
<item>regularization of orthography</item></list> The elements
discussed here are not provided by the module for spoken texts.  Some
of them are included in the core module and others are contained in
the modules for linking and for analysis respectively.  The selection
of modules and their combination to define a TEI schema is discussed
in section <ptr target="#STIN"/>.


<!-- I still think it's completely bonkers not to define timeline here. LB --></p>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSSASE"><head>Segmentation</head>
<p>For some analytic purposes it may be desirable to subdivide the
divisions of a spoken text into units smaller than the individual
utterance or turn.  Segmentation may be performed for a number of
different purposes and in terms of a variety of speech phenomena.
Common examples include units defined both prosodically (by intonation,
pausing, etc.) and syntactically (clauses, phrases, etc.)  The term
<term>macrosyntagm</term> has been used by a number of researchers to
define units peculiar to speech transcripts.<note place="bottom">The term was
apparently first proposed by <ptr type="cit" target="#TS-BIBL-7"/>,
where it is defined as follows: <q>A text can be analysed as a sequence
of segments which are internally connected by a network of syntactic
relations and externally delimited by the absence of such relations with
respect to neighbouring segments. Such a segment is a syntactic unit
called a macrosyntagm</q> (trans. S. Johansson).</note></p>
<p>These Guidelines propose that such analyses be performed in terms of
neutrally-named <term>segments</term>, represented by the <gi>seg</gi>
element, which is discussed more fully in section <ptr target="#SASE"/>.
This element may take a <att>type</att> attribute to specify the kind of
segmentation applicable to a particular segment, if more than one is
possible in a text.  A full definition of the segmentation scheme or
schemes used should be provided in the <gi>segmentation</gi> element of
the <gi>editorialDecl</gi> element in the TEI header (see <ptr target="#HD53"/>).</p>
<p>In the first example below, an utterance has been segmented according
to a notion of syntactic completeness not necessarily marked by the
speech, although in this case a pause has been recorded between the two
sentence-like units.  In the second, the segments are defined
prosodically (an acute accent 
has been used to mark the position immediately following the syllable
bearing the primary accent or stress), and may be thought of as
<soCalled>tone units</soCalled>.
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TSSASE-eg-37"><u>
   <seg>we went to the pub yesterday</seg>
   <pause/>
   <seg>there was no one there</seg>
</u>
<u>
   <seg>although its an old ide´a</seg>
   <seg>it hasnt been on the mar´ket very long</seg>
</u></egXML>
<!-- examples from J Payne NERC Report -->
In either case, the <gi>segmentation</gi> element in the header of the
text should specify the principles adopted to define the segments marked
in this way.</p>
<p>When utterances are segmented end-to-end in the same way as the
s-units in written texts, the <gi>s</gi> element discussed in chapter <ptr target="#AI"/>
 may be used, either as an alternative or in addition to
the more general purpose <gi>seg</gi> element.  The <gi>s</gi> element
is available without formality in all texts, but does not allow segments
to nest within each other.
</p>
<p>Where segments of different kinds are to be distinguished within the
same stretch of speech, the <att>type</att> attribute may be used, as in
the following example:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="true" xmlns:ext="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI"><u who="#T1">
<seg type="C">I think </seg>
<seg type="C">this chap was writing </seg>
<seg type="C">and he <del type="repeated">said hello</del> said </seg>
<seg type="M">hello </seg>
<seg type="C">and he said </seg>
<seg type="C">I'm going to a gate
            at twenty past seven </seg>
<seg type="C">he said </seg>
<seg type="M">ok </seg>
<seg type="M">right away </seg>
<seg type="C">and so <gap extent="1 syll"/> on they went </seg>
<seg type="C">and they were <gap extent="3 sylls"/>
            writing there </seg>
</u></egXML>
<!-- <note>Reference needed!</note>                           -->
In this example, recoded from a corpus of language-impaired speech
prepared by Fletcher and Garman, the speaker's utterance has been fully
segmented into clausal (<code>type="C"</code>) 
or minor (<code>type="M"</code>) units.</p> 

<p>For some features, it may be 
more appropriate or convenient to introduce a new element in a custom namespace:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" valid="false" xmlns:ext="http://www.example.org/ns/nonTEI"><u who="#T1">
<!-- ... --> 
<seg type="C">and he said </seg>
<seg type="C">I'm going to a 
<ext:paraphasia>gate</ext:paraphasia>
at twenty past seven </seg> 
<!-- ... --> 
</u></egXML>

Here, <gi scheme="imaginary">ext:paraphasia</gi> has been used to define a particular
characteristic of this corpus for which no element exists in the TEI scheme.
See further chapter <ptr target="#MD"/> for a discussion of the way in
which this kind of user-defined extension of the TEI scheme may be
performed and chapter <ptr target="#ST"/> for the mechanisms on which it
depends.</p>
<p>This example also uses the core elements <gi>gap</gi> and
<gi>del</gi> to mark editorial decisions concerning matter completely
omitted from the transcript (because of inaudibility), and words which
have been transcribed but which the transcriber wishes to exclude from
the segment because they are repeated, respectively.  See
section <ptr target="#COED"/> for a discussion of these and related
elements.</p>
<p>It is often the case that the desired segmentation does not respect
utterance boundaries; for example, syntactic units may cross utterance
boundaries.  For a detailed discussion of this problem, and the various
methods proposed by these Guidelines for handling it, see chapter
<ptr target="#NH"/>. Methods discussed there include these:
<list type="simple">
<item><soCalled>milestone</soCalled> tags may be used;
the special-purpose <gi>shift</gi> tag discussed
in section <ptr target="#TSSASH"/> is an extension of this method</item>
<item>where several discontinuous segments are to be grouped
together to form a syntactic unit (e.g. a phrasal verb with interposed
complement), the <gi>join</gi> element may be used</item>
</list></p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSSAPA"><head>Synchronization and Overlap</head>
<p>A major difference between spoken and written texts is the importance
of the temporal dimension to the former.  As a very simple example,
consider the following, first as it might be represented in a
playscript:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> Jane: Have you read Vanity Fair?
Stig: Yes
Lou: (nods vigorously)</egXML>
To encode this, we first define the participants:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><listPerson>
<person xml:id="stig"> <!-- ... --> </person>
<person xml:id="lou"> <!-- ... --> </person>
<person xml:id="jane"> <!-- ... --> </person>
</listPerson></egXML>
Let us assume that Stig and Lou respond to Jane's question before she
has finished asking it—a fairly normal situation in spontaneous
speech.  The simplest way of representing this <term>overlap</term>
would be to use the <att>trans</att> attribute previously discussed:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#jane">have you read Vanity Fair</u>
<u trans="overlap" who="#stig">yes</u>
</egXML>
However, this does not allow us to indicate either the extent to which
Stig's utterance is overlapped, nor does it show that there are in
fact three things which are synchronous:  the end of Jane's utterance,
Stig's whole utterance, and Lou's kinesic.  To overcome these problems,
more sophisticated techniques, employing the mechanisms for pointing and
alignment discussed in detail in section <ptr target="#SASY"/>, are needed.
If the module for linking has been enabled (as described in
section <ptr target="#TSSASE"/> above), one way to represent the simple
example above would be as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u xml:id="utt1" who="#jane">have you read Vanity <anchor synch="#utt2 #k1" xml:id="a1"/> Fair</u>
<u xml:id="utt2" who="#stig">yes</u>
<kinesic xml:id="k1" who="#lou" iterated="true"><desc>nods head vertically</desc></kinesic></egXML></p>
<p>For a full discussion of this and related mechanisms, section <ptr target="#SASYMP"/> should be consulted. The rest of the present
section, which should be read in conjunction with that more detailed
discussion, presents a number of ways in which these mechanisms may be
applied to the specific problem of representing temporal alignment,
synchrony, or overlap in transcribing spoken texts.</p>
<p>In the simple example above, the first utterance (that with
identifier <val>utt1</val>) contains an <gi>anchor</gi> element, the function of
which is simply to mark a point within it. The <att>synch</att>
attribute associated with this anchor point specifies the identifiers of
the other two elements which are to be synchronized with it:
specifically, the second utterance (<val>utt2</val>) and the kinesic (k1). Note that
one of these elements has content and the other is empty.</p>
<p>This example demonstrates only a way of indicating a point within one
utterance at which it can be synchronized with another utterance and a
kinesic. For more complex kinds of alignment, involving possibly
multiple synchronization points, an additional element is provided,
known as a <gi>timeline</gi>. This consists of a series of
<gi>when</gi> elements, each representing a point in time, and bearing
attributes which indicate its exact temporal position relative to other
elements in the same timeline, in addition to the sequencing implied by
its position within it.</p>
<p>For example:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><timeline unit="s" origin="#TS-P1">
   <when xml:id="TS-P1" absolute="12:20:01+01:00"/>
   <when xml:id="TS-P2" interval="4.5" since="#TS-P1"/>
   <when xml:id="TS-P6"/>
   <when xml:id="TS-P3" interval="1.5" since="#TS-P6"/>
</timeline></egXML>
This timeline represents four points in time, named TS-P1, TS-P2, TS-P6, and TS-P3
(as with all attributes named <att>xml:id</att> in the TEI scheme, the
names must be unique within the document but have no other
significance).  TS-P1 is located absolutely, at 12:20:01:01 BST.  TS-P2 is 4.5
seconds later than TS-P2 (i.e. at 12:20:46).  TS-P6 is
at some unspecified time later than TS-P2 and previous to TS-P3 (this is
implied by its position within the timeline, as no attribute values have
been specified for it).  The fourth point, TS-P3, is 1.5 seconds 
later than TS-P6.</p>
<p>One or more such timelines may be specified within a spoken text, to
suit the encoder's convenience.  If more than one is supplied, the
<att>origin</att> attribute may be used on each to specify which other
<gi>timeline</gi> element it follows.  The <att>unit</att> attribute
indicates the units used for timings given on <gi>when</gi> elements
contained by the alignment map.  Alternatively, to avoid the need to
specify times explicitly, the <att>interval</att> attribute may be used
to indicate that all the <gi>when</gi> elements in a time line are a
fixed distance apart.</p>
<p>Three methods are available for aligning points or elements within a
spoken text with the points in time defined by the <gi>timeline</gi>:
<list type="simple">
<item>The elements to be synchronized may specify the identifier
of a <gi>when</gi> element as the value of one of the <att>start</att>,
<att>end</att>, or <att>synch</att> attributes</item>
<item>The <gi>when</gi>
element may specify the identifiers of all the elements to be
synchronized with it using the <att>synch</att> attribute</item>
<item>A
free-standing <gi>link</gi> element may be used to associate the
<gi>when</gi> element and the elements synchronized with it by
specifying their identifiers as values for its <att>target</att>
attribute.</item></list></p>
<p>For example, using the timeline given above: <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u xml:id="TS-U1" start="#TS-P2" end="#TS-P3">This is my <anchor synch="#TS-P6" xml:id="TS-P6A"/> turn</u></egXML> The start of utterance
<val>TS-U1</val> is aligned with <val>TS-P2</val> and its end with
<val>TS-P3</val>.  The transition between the words
<mentioned>my</mentioned> and <mentioned>turn</mentioned> occurs at
point <val>TS-P6A</val>, which is synchronous with point
<val>TS-P6</val> on the timeline.</p>
<p>The synchronization represented by the preceding examples could
equally well be represented as follows:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><timeline origin="#ts-p1" unit="s">
  <when xml:id="ts-p1" absolute="12:20:01+01:00"/>
  <when synch="#ts-u1" xml:id="ts-p2" interval="4.5" since="#ts-p1"/>
  <when synch="#ts-x1" xml:id="ts-p6"/>
  <when synch="#ts-u1" xml:id="ts-p3" interval="1.5" since="#ts-p6"/>
</timeline>
<u xml:id="ts-u1">This is my <anchor xml:id="ts-x1"/> turn</u></egXML>
Here, the whole of the object with identifier <val>ts-u1</val> (the
utterance) has been aligned with two different points,
<val>ts-p2</val> and <val>ts-p3</val>.  This is interpreted to mean
that the utterance spans at least those two points.</p>
<p>Finally, a <gi>linkGrp</gi> may be used as an alternative to the
<att>synch</att> attribute:
<egXML xml:lang="und" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><timeline origin="#TS-p1" unit="s">
  <when xml:id="TS-p1" absolute="12:20:01"/>
  <when xml:id="TS-p2" interval="4.5" since="#TS-p1"/>
  <when xml:id="TS-p6"/>
  <when xml:id="TS-p3" interval="1.5" since="#TS-p6"/>
</timeline>
<u xml:id="TS-u1">
  <anchor xml:id="TS-u1start"/>
  This is my <anchor xml:id="TS-x1"/> turn
  <anchor xml:id="TS-u1end"/>
</u>
<linkGrp type="synchronous">
  <link target="#TS-u1start #TS-p1"/>
  <link target="#TS-u1end #TS-p2"/>
  <link target="#TS-x1 #TS-p6"/>
</linkGrp></egXML></p>
<p>As a further example of the three possibilities, consider the
following dialogue, represented first as it might appear in a
conventional playscript:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TSSASE-eg-20">Tom: I used to smoke - -
Bob: (interrupting) You used to smoke?
Tom: (at the same time) a lot more than this.  But I never
     inhaled the smoke</egXML>
<!-- Atkinson and Heritage (1984) ix-xvi -->
A commonly used convention might be to transcribe such a passage as
follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> (1) I used to smoke [ a lot more than this ]
(2)&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;[ you used to smoke ]
(1) but I never inhaled the smoke</egXML>
Such conventions have the drawback that they are hard to generalize or
to extend beyond the very simple case presented here.  Their reliance on
the accidentals of physical layout may also make them difficult to
transport and to process computationally.  These Guidelines recommend
the following mechanisms to encode this.</p>
<p>Where the whole of one or another utterance is to be synchronized,
the <att>start</att> and <att>end</att> attributes may be used:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#tom">I used to smoke <anchor xml:id="TS-p10"/> a lot more than this
<anchor xml:id="TS-p20"/>but I never inhaled the smoke</u>
<u start="#TS-p10" end="#TS-p20" who="#bob">You used to smoke</u></egXML>
Note that the second utterance above could equally well be encoded as
follows with exactly the same effect:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u who="#bob"><anchor synch="#TS-p10"/>You used to smoke<anchor synch="#TS-p20"/></u></egXML></p>
<p>If synchronization with specific timing information is required, a
<gi>timeline</gi> must be included:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><timeline origin="#TS-t01" unit="s">
  <when xml:id="TS-t01" absolute="15:33:01Z"/>
  <when xml:id="TS-t02" interval="2.5" since="#TS-t01"/>
</timeline>
<u who="#tom">I used to smoke
   <anchor synch="#TS-t01"/>a lot more than this
   <anchor synch="#TS-t02"/>but I never inhaled the smoke</u>
<u who="#bob">       
   <anchor synch="#TS-t01"/>You used to smoke<anchor synch="#TS-t02"/></u></egXML></p>
<p>As above, since the whole of Bob's utterance is to be aligned, the
<att>start</att> and <att>end</att> attributes may be used as an
alternative to the second pair of <gi>anchor</gi> elements:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u start="#TS-t01" end="#TS-t02" who="#bob">You used to smoke</u></egXML></p>
<p>An alternative approach is to mark the synchronization by pointing
from the <gi>timeline</gi> to the text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><timeline origin="#TS-T01">
   <when synch="#TS-nm1 #bob-u2" xml:id="TS-T01"/>
   <when synch="#TS-nm2 #bob-u2" xml:id="TS-T02"/>
</timeline>
<u who="#tom">I used to smoke
   <anchor xml:id="TS-nm1"/>a lot more than this
   <anchor xml:id="TS-nm2"/>but I never inhaled the smoke</u>
<u xml:id="bob-u2" who="#bob">You used to smoke</u></egXML>
To avoid deciding whether to point from the timeline to the text or vice
versa, a <gi>linkGrp</gi> may be used:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><body>
  <timeline origin="#T001">
     <when xml:id="T001"/>
     <when xml:id="T002"/>
  </timeline>
  <u who="#tom">I used to smoke
     <anchor xml:id="NM01"/>a lot more than this
     <anchor xml:id="NM02"/>but I never inhaled the smoke</u>
  <u xml:id="bob-U2" who="#bob">You used to smoke</u>
  <linkGrp type="synchronize">
     <link target="#T001 #NM01 #bob-U2"/>
     <link target="#T002 #NM02 #bob-U2"/>
  </linkGrp>
</body></egXML></p>
<p>Note that in each case, although Bob's utterance follows Tom's
sequentially in the text, it is aligned temporally with its middle,
without any need to disrupt the normal syntax of the text.</p>
<p>As a final example, consider the following exchange, first as it
might be represented using a musical-score-like notation, in which
points of synchronization are represented by vertical alignment of the
text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"> Stig : This is |my&#160;&#160;|turn
Jane :&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;|Balderdash
Lou&#160; :&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;|No, |it's mine</egXML>
All three speakers are simultaneous at the words <mentioned>my</mentioned>,
<mentioned>Balderdash</mentioned>, and <mentioned>No</mentioned>; speakers Stig and Lou are
simultaneous at the words <mentioned>turn</mentioned> and <mentioned>it's</mentioned>.
This could be encoded as follows, using pointers from the alignment map
into the text:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><timeline origin="#TSp1">
   <when synch="#TSa1 #TSb1 #TSc1" xml:id="TSp1"/>
   <when synch="#TSa2 #TSc2" xml:id="TSp2"/>
</timeline>
<!-- ... -->
<u who="#stig">this is <anchor xml:id="TSa1"/> my <anchor xml:id="TSa2"/> turn</u>
<u who="#jane" xml:id="TSb1">balderdash</u>
<u who="#lou" xml:id="TSc1"> no <anchor xml:id="TSc2"/> it's mine</u>
</egXML></p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSREG"><head>Regularization of Word Forms</head>
<p>When speech is transcribed using ordinary orthographic notation, as
is customary, some compromise must be made between the sounds produced
and conventional orthography.  Particularly when dealing with informal,
dialectal, or other varieties of language, the transcriber will
frequently have to decide whether a particular sound is to be treated as
a distinct vocabulary item or not.  For example, while in a given
project <mentioned>kinda</mentioned> may not be worth distinguishing as a
vocabulary item from <mentioned>kind of</mentioned>, <mentioned>isn't</mentioned> may
clearly be worth distinguishing from <mentioned>is not</mentioned>; for some
purposes, the regional variant <mentioned>isnae</mentioned> might also be worth
distinguishing in the same way.</p>
<p>One rule of thumb might be to allow such variation only where a
generally accepted orthographic form exists, for example, in published
dictionaries of the language register being encoded; this has the
disadvantage that such dictionaries may not exist.  Another is to
maintain a controlled (but extensible) set of normalized forms for all
such words; this has the advantage of enforcing some degree of
consistency among different transcribers.  Occasionally, as for example
when transcribing abbreviations or acronyms, it may be felt necessary to
depart from conventional spelling to distinguish between cases where the
abbreviation is spelled out letter by letter (e.g.  <mentioned>B B C</mentioned>
or <mentioned>V A T</mentioned>) and where it is pronounced as a single word
(<mentioned>VAT</mentioned> or <mentioned>RADA</mentioned>).  Similar considerations
might apply to pronunciation of foreign words
(e.g. <mentioned>Monsewer</mentioned> vs. <mentioned>Monsieur</mentioned>).</p>
<p>In general, use of punctuation, capitalization, etc., in spoken
transcripts should be carefully controlled.  It is important to
distinguish the transcriber's intuition as to what the punctuation
should be from the marking of prosodic features such as pausing,
intonation, etc.</p>
<p>Whatever practice is adopted, it is essential that it be clearly and
fully documented in the editorial declarations section of the header.
It may also be found helpful to include normalized forms of
non-conventional spellings within the text, using the elements for
simple editorial changes described in section <ptr target="#COED"/> (see
further section <ptr target="#TSTPSM"/>).</p></div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSTPPR"><head>Prosody</head>
<p>In the absence of conventional punctuation, the marking of prosodic
features assumes paramount importance, since these structure and
organize the spoken message.  Indeed, such prosodic features as points
of primary or secondary stress may be represented by specialized
punctuation marks, or other characters such as those provided by the
Unicode Spacing Modifier Letters block.  Pauses have already been dealt with in section
<ptr target="#TSBAPA"/>; while tone units (or intonational phrases)
can be indicated by the segmentation tag discussed in section
<ptr target="#TSSASE"/>. The <gi>shift</gi> element discussed in section <ptr target="#TSSASH"/> 
may also be used to encode some prosodic features, for example where all
that is required is the ability to record shifts in voice quality.</p>

<p>In a more detailed phonological transcript, it is common practice
to include a number of conventional signs to mark prosodic features of
the surrounding or (more usually) preceding speech. Such signs may be
used to record, for example, particular intonation patterns,
truncation, vowel quality (long or short) etc. These signs may be
preserved in a transcript either by using conventional punctuation or
by marking their presence by <gi>g</gi> 
elements. Where a transcript
includes many phonetic or phonemic aspects, it will generally be
more convenient to use the appropriate Unicode characters (see
further chapters <ptr target="#CH"/> and <ptr target="#WD"/>). For
representation of phonemic information, the use of the International
Phonetic Alphabet, which can be represented in Unicode characters, is
recommended.</p>
<p>In the following example, special characters have been defined as
follows within the <gi>encodingDesc</gi> of the TEI header
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><charDecl>
  <char xml:id="lf"><desc>low fall intonation</desc></char>
  <char xml:id="lr"><desc>low rise intonation</desc></char>
  <char xml:id="fr"><desc>fall rise intonation</desc></char>
  <char xml:id="rf"><desc>rise fall intonation</desc></char>
  <char xml:id="long"><desc>lengthened syllable</desc></char>
  <char xml:id="short"><desc>shortened syllable</desc></char>
</charDecl>
</egXML>
These declarations might additionally provide information about
how the characters concerned should be rendered,  their equivalent
IPA form, etc. In the transcript itself references to them can then
be included as follows:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" corresp="#TSTPPR-eg-58"><div n="Lod E-03" type="exchange">
   <note>C is with a friend</note>
   <u who="#cwn">
      <unclear>Excuse me<g ref="#lf"/></unclear> <pause/> You dont have some
      aesthetic<g ref="#short"/> <pause/> <unclear>specially on early</unclear>
      aesthetics terminology <g ref="#lr"/></u>
   <u who="#aj">
      No<g ref="#lf"/> <pause/>No<g ref="#lf"/> <gap extent="2 beats"/> I'm
      afraid<g ref="#lf"/></u>
   <u trans="latching" who="#cwn">
      No<g ref="#lr"/> <unclear>Well</unclear> thanks<g ref="#lr"/> <pause/> Oh<g ref="#short"/>
      <unclear>you couldnt<g ref="#short"/> can we</unclear> kind of<g ref="#long"/>
      <pause/>I mean ask you to order it for us<g ref="#long"/><g ref="#fr"/></u>
   <u trans="latching" who="#aj">
      Yes<g ref="#fr"/> if you know the title<g ref="#lf"/> Yeah<g ref="#lf"/></u>
   <u who="#cwn"> 
      <gap extent="4 beats"/> </u>
   <u who="#aj">
      Yes thats fine. <unclear>just as soon as it comes in we'll send
      you a postcard<g ref="#lf"/></unclear> </u>
<listPerson>
<person xml:id="cwn"><p>Customer WN</p></person>
<person xml:id="aj"><p>Assistant K</p></person>
</listPerson>
</div></egXML>
<!-- Recoded from Gavioli and Mansfield: The PIXI Corpora     -->
	<!-- (Bologna, 1990, CLUEB), p74                              --></p>
<p>This example, which is taken from a corpus of bookshop service
encounters, <!--(<ref target="#TS-BIBL-8">Gavioli and Mansfield 1990</ref>)-->
also demonstrates the use of the <gi>unclear</gi> and <gi>gap</gi>
elements discussed in section <ptr target="#COED"/>.  Where words are so
unclear that only their extent can be recorded, the empty <gi>gap</gi>
element may be used; where the encoder can identify the words but wishes
to record a degree of uncertainty about their accuracy, the
<gi>unclear</gi> element may be used. More flexible and detailed
methods of indicating uncertainty are discussed in chapter <ptr target="#CE"/>.</p>


<p>For more detailed work, involving a detailed phonological transcript
including representation of stress and pitch patterns, it is probably
best to maintain the prosodic description in parallel with the
conventional written transcript, rather than attempt to embed detailed
prosodic information within it.  The two parallel streams may be aligned
with each other and with other streams, for example an acoustic
encoding, using the general alignment mechanisms discussed in section
<ptr target="#TSSASH"/>.</p>


</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSTPSM"><head>Speech Management</head>
<p>Phenomena of <term>speech management</term> include disfluencies such
as filled and unfilled pauses, interrupted or repeated words,
corrections, and reformulations as well as interactional devices asking
for or providing feedback.  Depending on the importance attached to such
features, transcribers may choose to adopt conventionalized
representations for them (as discussed in section <ptr target="#TSREG"/>
above), or to transcribe them using IPA or some other transcription
system.  To simplify analysis of the lexical features of a speech
transcript, it may be felt useful to <soCalled>tidy away</soCalled> many
of these disfluencies.  Where this policy has been adopted, these
Guidelines recommend the use of the tags for simple editorial
intervention discussed in section <ptr target="#COED"/>, to make explicit
the extent of regularization or normalization performed by the
transcriber.</p>
<p>For example, false starts, repetition, and truncated words might all
be included within a transcript, but marked as editorially deleted, in
the following way:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u><del type="truncation">s</del>see
<del type="repetition">you you</del> you know
<del type="falseStart">it's</del> he's crazy</u></egXML></p>
<p>As previously noted, the <gi>gap</gi> element may be used to mark
points within a transcript where words have been omitted, for example
because they are inaudible, as in the following example in which 5 seconds of
speech is drowned out by an external event:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><gap reason="passing-truck" quantity="5" unit="s"/></egXML></p>
<p>The <gi>unclear</gi> element may be used to mark words which have
been included although the transcriber is unsure of their accuracy:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples"><u>...and then <unclear reason="passing-truck">marbled queen</unclear></u></egXML></p>
<p>Where a transcriber is believed to have incorrectly identified a
word, the elements <gi>corr</gi> or <gi>sic</gi> embedded within a
<gi>choice</gi> element may be used to indicate
both the original and a corrected form of it:
<egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<choice><corr>SCSI</corr><sic>skuzzy</sic></choice>
</egXML>
These elements are further discussed in section <ptr target="#COEDCOR"/>.
</p>
<p>Finally phenomena such as <term>code-switching</term>, where a
speaker switches from one language to another, may easily be
represented in a transcript by using the <gi>foreign</gi> element
provided by the core tagset:
<egXML xml:lang="mul" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
<u who="#P1">I proposed that <foreign xml:lang="de"> wir können 
<pause dur="PT1S"/> vielleicht </foreign> go to warsaw 
and <emph>vienna</emph> </u>
</egXML>
<!-- example from Stefan Majewski on TEI-L 2007-10-05 -->

</p>
</div>
<div type="div3" xml:id="TSTPAC"><head>Analytic Coding</head>
<p>The recommendations made here only concern the establishment of a
basic text. Where a more sophisticated analysis is needed, more
sophisticated methods of markup will also be appropriate, for example,
using stand-off markup to indicate multiple segmentation of the
stream of discourse, or complex alignment of several segments within it.
Where additional annotations (sometimes called
<soCalled>codes</soCalled> or <soCalled>tags</soCalled>) are used to
represent such features as linguistic word class (noun, verb, etc.),
type of speech act (imperative, concessive, etc.), or information status
(theme/rheme, given/new, active/semi-active/new), etc., a selection from
the general purpose analytic tools discussed in chapters <ptr target="#SA"/>, <ptr target="#AI"/>, and <ptr target="#FS"/> may be used to
advantage.
</p>
</div>
</div>

<div><head>Module for Transcribed Speech</head>


<p>The module described in this chapter makes available the following components:
<moduleSpec xml:id="DTS" ident="spoken">
<altIdent type="FPI">Transcribed Speech</altIdent>
<desc>Transcribed Speech</desc>
<desc xml:lang="fr">Transcriptions de la parole</desc>
<desc xml:lang="zh-TW">轉錄的言詞</desc>
<desc xml:lang="it">Trascrizione del parlato</desc><desc xml:lang="pt">Transcrição do discurso</desc><desc xml:lang="ja">発話モジュール</desc></moduleSpec>
The selection and combination of modules to form a TEI schema is described in
<ptr target="#STIN"/>.
</p>
<specGrp>











<include xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2003/XInclude" href="../../Specs/model.divPart.spoken.xml"/>




 
<specGrpRef target="#DTSCOMP"/>
</specGrp>



</div></div>
