<?oxygen RNGSchema="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="xml"?>
<TEI xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" xmlns:svg="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
    xmlns:math="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
    <teiHeader>
        <fileDesc>
            <titleStmt>
                <title>Guidelines for notatedMusic</title>
                <respStmt>
                    <resp>Author</resp>
                    <name>Raffaele Viglianti</name>
                </respStmt>
            </titleStmt>
            <publicationStmt>
                <authority>TEI Special Interest Group in Music</authority>
                <availability>
                    <p><hi>Copyright 2010 TEI Consortium.</hi></p>
                    <p>This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it under the
                        terms of the GNU General Public License as published by the Free Software
                        Foundation; either version 2 of the License, or (at your option) any later
                        version.</p>
                    <p>This material is distributed in the hope that it will be useful, but
                            <emph>without any warranty</emph>; without even the implied warranty of
                            <emph>merchantability</emph> or <emph>fitness for a particular
                            purpose.</emph> See the GNU General Public License for more details.</p>
                    <p>A copy of the GNU General Public License is stored on the TEI web site along
                        with this file; you can also contact the Free Software Foundation, Inc., 59
                        Temple Place, Suite 330, Boston, MA 02111-1307, USA, for a copy.</p>

                    <p>Copyright (c) 2010 by the Music Encoding Initiative (MEI) Council.</p>

                    <p>Licensed under the Educational Community License, Version 2.0 (the
                        "License"); you may not use this file except in compliance with the License.
                        You may obtain a copy of the License at
                        http://www.osedu.org/licenses/ECL-2.0.</p>

                    <p>Unless required by applicable law or agreed to in writing, software
                        distributed under the License is distributed on an "AS IS" BASIS, WITHOUT
                        WARRANTIES OR CONDITIONS OF ANY KIND, either express or implied. See the
                        License for the specific language governing permissions and limitations
                        under the License.</p>

                    <p>This is a derivative work based on earlier versions of the schema copyright
                        (c) 2001-2006 Perry Roland and the Rector and Visitors of the University of
                        Virginia; licensed under the Educational Community License version 1.0.</p>
                </availability>
            </publicationStmt>
            <sourceDesc>
                <p>Adapted from: <ref target="http://www.tei-c.org/SIG/Music/ODD/tei_mei.xml"
                    >TEI with Music Notation ODD</ref></p>
            </sourceDesc>
        </fileDesc>
    </teiHeader>
    <text>
        <body>
            <div>
                <head>Notated music in written text</head>

                <p>Music, like many other art forms, is often mentioned, discussed and described in
                    writings of various kinds. This applies to both historical and contemporary
                    documents, even though the way of notating music has changed considerably in
                    western history. In most cases, music notation enters the text flow in a way
                    similar to figures, images or graphs. On other occasions, elements of music
                    notation are treated as inline characters in running text.</p>

                <p><ref target="#notatedMusic">notatedMusic</ref>provides a way of
                    signalling the presence of music notation in text, but defer to other
                    representations to describe the music notation itself, which is not covered by
                    the TEI guidelines. In fact, several commercial, academic and standard bodies
                    have developed digital representations of music notation and, given the topic's
                    complexity, these representations often focus on different aspects and adopt
                    different methodologies. Therefore, <ref target="#notatedMusic"
                        >notatedMusic</ref> only define a container element to encode the occurrence
                    of music notation and allow linking to the data format preferred by the
                    encoder.</p>

                <p>The following elements can be used or encoding music notation in text:</p>

                <list rend="specList">
                    <item>
                        <label><gi>notatedMusic</gi></label> groups elements representing or
                        containing music notation.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label><gi>ptr</gi></label> can be used to indicate the location of a
                        representation of the music notation.
                        <list type="specDesc">
                            <item><label>@mimeType</label> supplies the MIME type of the data
                            format, when available.</item>
                            </list>
                    </item>
                    <item>
                        <label><gi>desc</gi></label> can be used to give a prose description of the
                        notated music.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label><gi>graphic</gi></label> can be used to indicate the location of a
                        graphical representation of the music notation.</item>
                    <item>
                        <label><gi>binaryObject</gi></label> provides encoded binary data
                        representing a graphical representation of the music notation or other
                        object (i.e., audio).</item>
                </list>

                <p>The <ref target="#notatedMusic">notatedMusic</ref> element may contain a
                    textual description and pointers to various representations of the music
                    notation in different media. An external representation of the notated music is
                    specified using the <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-ptr.html"
                        >ptr</ref> element, whose @target attribute provides its
                    electronically-accessible location.
                    The attribute @mimeType supplies the MIME type of the data format when
                        available.
                    For example:</p>

                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.xml"/>
</notatedMusic></egXML>

                <p>A textual description of the notation can be provided within the element <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-desc.html"
                        >desc</ref>, or it is possible to give it a <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-label.html"
                        >label</ref>. For example:</p>

                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.xml"/>
  <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39</desc>
</notatedMusic></egXML>

                <p>It is possible to link to any kind of music notation data format.
                    However, when a
                    MIME type is not available, it is
                    recommended to at least specify the format in the description. For example:</p>

                <p>MIME type available</p>
                    
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><notatedMusic>
                    <ptr target="bar1.xml" mimeType="application/vnd.recordare.musicxml"/>
                    <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39. Encoded in MusicXML</desc>
                    </notatedMusic></egXML>
                    
                    <p>MIME type not available</p>

                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.ly"/>
  <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39. Encoded in Lilypond</desc>
</notatedMusic></egXML>

                <p>Application format</p>
                    
                    <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><notatedMusic>
                    <ptr target="bar1.mscz" mimeType="application/x-musescore"/>
                    <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39. MuseScore Notation Software format.</desc>
                    </notatedMusic></egXML>

                <p>It is possible to specify the location of digital objects representing the
                    notated music in other media such as images or audio-visual files. The encoder's
                    interpretation of the correspondence between the notated music and these digital
                    objects is not encoded explicitly. We recommend the use of graphic and
                    binaryObject mainly as a fallback mechanism when the notated music format is not
                    displayable by the application using the encoding. The alignment of encoded
                    notated music, images carrying the notation, and audio files is a complex matter
                    for which we refer the reader to other formats and specifications such as <ref
                        target="http://www.interactivemusicnetwork.org/mpeg-ahg/"
                    >MPEG-SMR</ref>.</p>

                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><notatedMusic>
  <ptr target="bar1.xml"/>
  <graphic url="bar1.jpg"/>
  <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39</desc>
                </notatedMusic></egXML>


                <p>In modern printing, music notation positioned between blocks of text for
                    illustrative purposes is usually referred to as a "figure" or "example". In this
                    cases, we recommend the inclusion of <ref target="#notatedMusicODD"
                        >notatedMusic</ref> in <ref
                        target="http://www.tei-c.org/release/doc/tei-p5-doc/en/html/ref-figure.html"
                        >figure</ref> in order to encode possible captions and headers. For
                    example:</p>

                <figure>
                    <figDesc>Example from: <bibl>
                            <author>Prout, E.</author> (<date when="1899">1899</date>). <title>The
                                orchestra.</title>
                        </bibl></figDesc>
                    <graphic url="prout-ex1.jpg"/>
                </figure>

                <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples" xml:space="preserve"><div n="67">
   <p>
      We now give some examples, from the works of the great masters, 
      of some of the most frequently used bowings.
   </p>
							
   <figure>
      <head><label>Ex. 3</label>SCHUBERT: Symphony in B minor.</head>
	  <notatedMusic>
         <ptr ref="example_schubert.xml"/>
      </notatedMusic>
   </figure>
</div></egXML>


            </div>
        </body>

        <back>
            <div xml:id="notatedMusicODD">
                <head>ODD definition</head>
                <schemaSpec ident="tei_notatedmusic" docLang="en" xml:lang="en" targetLang="en" start="TEI TEICorpus">
         <moduleRef key="tei"/>                              <!-- required -->
         <moduleRef key="core"/>                             <!-- required -->
         <moduleRef key="analysis"/>
         <moduleRef key="certainty"/>
         <moduleRef key="corpus"/>
         <moduleRef key="dictionaries"/>
         <moduleRef key="drama"/>
         <moduleRef key="figures"/>
         <moduleRef key="gaiji"/>
         <moduleRef key="header"/>                           <!-- required -->
         <moduleRef key="iso-fs"/>
         <moduleRef key="linking"/>
         <moduleRef key="msdescription"/>
         <moduleRef key="namesdates"/>
         <moduleRef key="nets"/>
         <moduleRef key="spoken"/>
         <moduleRef key="textcrit"/>
         <moduleRef key="textstructure"/>                    <!-- required -->
         <moduleRef key="transcr"/>
         <moduleRef key="verse"/>

         <moduleRef key="tagdocs"/>

<!-- added elementSpec for notatedMusic -->

                    <elementSpec xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" module="figures"
                        ident="notatedMusic" mode="add">
                        <equiv/>
			<gloss>notated music</gloss>
                        <desc>encodes the presence of music notation in a text.</desc>
                        <classes>
                            <memberOf key="model.global"/>
                            <memberOf key="att.placement"/>
                            <memberOf key="att.typed"/>
                            <memberOf key="att.global"/>
                        </classes>
                        <content>
                            <zeroOrMore xmlns="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0">
                                <choice>
                                    <ref name="model.labelLike"/>
                                    <ref name="model.ptrLike"/>
                                    <ref name="graphic"/>
                                    <ref name="binaryObject"/>
                                </choice>
                            </zeroOrMore>
                        </content>
                        <exemplum xml:lang="en">
                            <egXML xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/Examples">
                                <notatedMusic>
                                    <ptr target="bar1.xml"/>
                                    <graphic url="bar1.jpg"/>
                                    <desc>First bar of Chopin's Scherzo No.3 Op.39</desc>
                                </notatedMusic>
                            </egXML>
                        </exemplum>
                        <remarks>
			 <p>It is possible to describe the content of the notation using elements from 
			the model.labelLike class and it is possible to point to an external representation 
			using elements from model.ptrLike.  It is possible to specify the location of digital objects
                                representing the notated music in other media such as images or
                                audio-visual files. The encoder's interpretation of the
                                correspondence between the notated music and these digital objects
                                is not encoded explicitly. We recommend the use of graphic and
                                binaryObject mainly as a fallback mechanism when the notated music
                                format is not displayable by the application using the encoding. The
                                alignment of encoded notated music, images carrying the notation,
                                and audio files is a complex matter for which we refer the encoder
                                to other formats and specifications such as MPEG-SMR.</p>
                        </remarks>
                    </elementSpec>
                </schemaSpec>
            </div>
        </back>

    </text>
</TEI>
